<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../src/vmachine.xsl"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI [

<!ENTITY ff "<!-- ff ligature, representing capital modern day capital F, here represented as 'ff' -->ff">

]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mads.pp.56">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>A Dialogue Between Two Sisters, Virgins Bewailing Their Solitary Life</title>
                 <title type="sub">Poem 56</title>
                <respStmt><resp>Created by</resp>
                    <persName>Leah Knight</persName>
                    <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoded by</resp>
                    <persName>Katherine Poland</persName>
                    <persName>Matthew Taylor</persName>
			              <persName>Betsy Chou</persName>
                    <persName>Emily Andrey</persName>
                    <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
                </respStmt>
		            <respStmt>
                     <resp>IT-project consultation by</resp>
                     <persName>Josh Honn</persName>
                 </respStmt>
                <sponsor>
                    <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
                    <orgName>Brock University</orgName>
                    <orgName>University of Leeds</orgName>
                </sponsor>
                <principal>
                    <persName/>
                </principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1"/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription, transformations, and notes</resp>
                    <persName>Leah Knight</persName>
                    <orgName>Brock University</orgName>
                    <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>
                    <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent/>
            <publicationStmt>
                <ab/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl>
                    <msDesc>
                        <msIdentifier>
                            <repository>See witness list.</repository>
                        </msIdentifier>
                    </msDesc>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <p>Transcriptions are encoded in TEI(P5)-conformant XML.</p>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p>Apparent errors are preserved and editorial corrections provided using SIC
                        and CORR tags, but only where the editor conjectures that the original
                        scribe or compositor would have recognized the instance as an error. For
                        example, what according to modern usage is incorrect subject/verb agreement
                        might have been deemed acceptable to a seventeenth-century scribe or
                        compositor. All such instances are treated instead using the ORIG and REG
                        tags. (See below.) </p>
                    <p>Corrections and annotations made within the scope of the original document
                        either by its original authors, owners, and/or transcribers are noted using
                        ADD tags. These annotations and may be further explained within NOTE tags, as
                        added by the editors of this digital edition, for display within the
                        apparatus.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p>Original spellings, abbreviations, and orthography are preserved. Where in
                        the manuscripts a character’s status as majuscule or minuscule is ambiguous,
                        the editor has silently chosen one or the other based on context and
                        judgment (i.e., does not register such ambiguity in either the markup or the
                        notes).</p>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p>Original quotation marks, if any, are preserved.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p>Original hyphenation is preserved.</p>
                </hyphenation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <charDecl>
                <!-- Ligature combinations for which there are currently no corresponding Unicode codepoints. -->
                <glyph xml:id="ffllig">
                    <glyphName>Handwritten 'ff' ligature, used in handwriting to represent modern
                        F</glyphName>
                </glyph>
            </charDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="DDC22">
                    <bibl>
                        <title>Dewey Decimal Classification</title>
                        <edition/>
                        <publisher/>
                        <pubPlace/>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en-GB">British English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <!-- dewey decimal system class code 821: English Poetry -->
                <classCode scheme="DDC22">821</classCode>
                <keywords>
                    <term>lamentation</term>
                    <term>confinement</term>
                    <term>pathetic fallacy</term>
                    <term>dialogue</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
         <graphic url="./document_images/7610_157.jpg" xml:id="f7610_157"/>
         <graphic url="./document_images/7610_158.jpg" xml:id="f7610_158"/>
         <graphic url="./document_images/7610_159.jpg" xml:id="f7610_159"/>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div>
                <listWit>
                    <witness xml:id="ft">Transcription of manuscript: By <persName xml:id="lknight">Leah Knight</persName> and <persName xml:id="wwall">Wendy Wall</persName>.</witness>
                    <witness xml:id="ee">Elemental edition: By <persName>Leah Knight</persName> and <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>.</witness>
                    <witness xml:id="ae">Amplified edition: By <persName>Sarah C. E. Ross</persName>.</witness>
                </listWit>
            </div>
        </front>

        <body>
            <app>
                <rdg wit="#ft"><pb ed="#ft" facs="#f7610_157" n="77r"/></rdg>
                <rdg wit="#ee"><pb ed="#ee" facs="#f7610_157"/></rdg>
                <rdg wit="#ae"><pb ed="#ae" facs="#f7610_157"/></rdg>
            </app>

            <head>
                <app type="title">
                    <rdg wit="#ft"><fw facs="#f7610_069" type="pageNum" place="margin-topright">149</fw>A Dialogue between two Sisters Virgins
                        bewailing their Solitary life. P: P:. &ff;: P: .</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1"><seg>A Dialogue Between Two Sisters, Virgins Bewailing Their Solitary Life<note type="critical">The title is followed by two sets of initials, “P. P.”, presumably for Pulter’s daughter, Penelope Pulter (1633–55), and “F. P.”, another daughter named in the poem as Anne Pulter (1635–60).</note></seg>
                    </rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1"><seg>A Dialogue Between Two Sisters, Virgins, Bewailing their Solitary Life, P.P., A.P.<note type="critical">MS = P.P., F.P. The “F” seems to be an error, as the two speakers are clearly identified in the poem as Penelope and Anne. These are poetic versions of Pulter’s two daughters Penelope (1633–55) and Anne (1635–66). For other poems addressed to her daughters, see <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="2">The Invitation into the Country</ref> and <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="38">To My Dear Jane, Margaret, and Penelope Pulter, they Being at London, I at Broadfield</ref>.</note></seg></rdg>
                </app>
                <app type="editorialnote">
                    <rdg wit="#ft"><note type="editorialnote">In these transcriptions we preserve as many details of the original material, textual, and graphic properties of Hester Pulter’s manuscript verse as we have found practical. Whenever possible, for instance, original spelling, punctuation, capitalization, lineation, insertions, deletions, alterations, spacing between words and lines, and indentation are all maintained; abbreviations and brevigraphs are not expanded; and superscript and subscript representations are retained. <ref target="//pulterproject.northwestern.edu/about-project-conventions.html#top" type="new-window-url">See full conventions for the transcriptions here.</ref></note></rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">
                      <note type="editorialnote">
                        The aim of the elemental edition is to make the poems accessible to the largest variety of readers,
                        which involves modernizing spelling and punctuation as well as adding basic glosses. Spelling and
                        punctuation reflect current standard American usage; punctuation highlights syntax which might
                        otherwise be obscure. Outmoded but still familiar word forms (“thou,” “‘tis,” “hold’st”) are not
                        modernized, and we do not modernize grammar when the sense remains legible. After a brief headnote
                        aimed at offering a “way in” to the poem’s unique qualities and connections with other verse by
                        Pulter or her contemporaries, the edition features a minimum of notes and interpretative framing to
                        allow more immediate engagement with the poem. Glosses clarify synonyms or showcase various
                        possible meanings in Pulter’s time. Other notes identify named people and places or clarify obscure
                        material. We rely (without citation) primarily on the Oxford English Dictionary (OED), the Oxford
                        Reference database, and the King James Version (KJV) of the Bible. When we rely on Alice Eardley’s
                        edition of Pulter’s work, we cite her text generally (“Eardley”); other sources are cited in full. The
                        result is an edition we consider a springboard for further work on Pulter’s poetry. <ref target="//pulterproject.northwestern.edu/about-project-conventions.html#elemental-edition" type="new-window-url">See full conventions for this edition here.</ref>
                      </note>
                    </rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1"><note type="editorialnote">
                    <p>My priority in editing these poems has been to modernise, and to achieve interpretative and visual clarity, in order to make the poems as accessible as possible to as wide a modern audience as is possible. Spelling is modernised, as is punctuation. Modernising the latter, in particular, often involves a significant act of editorial interpretation, but in my view this is one of the most productive areas of editorial intervention, particularly for a manuscript text such as Pulter’s where the punctuation is erratic compared to modern usage (and, indeed, compared to early modern printed texts).<seg>1<note type="critical">1. See <bibl>Alice Eardley, “‘I haue not time to point yr booke … which I desire you yourselfe to doe’: Editing the Form of Early Modern Manuscript Verse”, in <title rend="italic">The Work of Form: Poetics and Materiality in Early Modern Culture</title>, ed. Ben Burton and Elizabeth Scott-Baumann (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2014), pp. 162–178.</bibl></note></seg></p>
                  </note></rdg>
                </app>
            <app type="headnote">
                <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1"><note type="headnote">Uncharacteristically, Pulter here chooses to write a pastoral dialogue in which two of her daughters express their sorrows in relation to the natural world. Penelope and Anne seek solace for their laments by immersing themselves in a landscape that also appears to be mourning. The source of the speakers’ sadness is unclear: it seems to derive from their awareness of life’s mortality and decay; their frustrated desire to be in heaven; and their awareness of the world’s general imperfections. Because they see the environment through the lens of classical mythology, however, they do not find comfort; instead the particular flowers and birds signal tragic mythological stories of injury, rape, loss, and death. The daughters’ complaints are also intensified by their inability to produce song while surrounded by a natural world that effortlessly emotes sympathetic sorrow. On realizing that they are mortals unable to release their souls into other bodies or to eternal life, they stoically turn to the comfort of a family community cemented by shared sorrow. The poem poignantly ends with them resolving to ease the isolation of their mother Hester. Out of the six poems in the collection in which Pulter specifically mentions her daughters (<ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="2">The Invitation into the Country, 1647</ref>, <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="10">Upon the Death of my Dear and Lovely Daughter, Jane Pulter</ref>, <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="11">Tell Me No More [On the Same]</ref>, <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="38">To My Dear Jane, Margaret, and Penelope Pulter, They Being at London, I at Broadfield</ref>, and <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="68">Come, My Dear Children (Emblem 2)</ref>), this is the only verse in which her daughters are portrayed as artistic creators.</note></rdg>
                <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1"><note type="headnote"><p>This poem brings together in intriguing ways two poetic modes or forms common in seventeenth-century poetry: the complaint and the dialogue poem. The mode of complaint can be broadly understood as the “woe is me” posture and the rhetorical exposition of emotion deriving from it; typically, complaint is an open-ended expression of woe, in which the grief-stricken speaker expands in an exorbitant way on their lamentable circumstances. Complaint is pervasive in seventeenth-century literature, with foundational examples such as <bibl><author>Shakespeare</author>’s <title rend="italic">A Lover’s Complaint</title></bibl> and <bibl>Spenser’s volume of <title rend="italic">Complaints</title> (<date>1591</date>)</bibl> influencing a plethora of amatory, religious, and political applications. For definitions and influential discussions of complaint, see <bibl>John Kerrigan, <title rend="italic">Motives of Woe: Shakespeare and "Female Complaint": A Critical Anthology</title> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1991)</bibl>; <bibl>Katharine Craik, “Spenser’s ‘Complaints’ and the New Poet”, <title rend="italic">Huntington Library Quarterly</title>, 64 (2001): 63–79</bibl>; <bibl>Rosalind Smith, Michelle O’Callaghan, and Sarah C. E. Ross, “Complaint”, in Catherine Bates (ed.), <title rend="italic">A Companion to Renaissance Poetry</title> (Oxford: Wiley-Blackwell, 2018), pp. 339–52</bibl>.</p>
                    <p>Complaint is often female-voiced, and Pulter’s poem bears multiple markers of the mode. Here, the two speaking virgins occupy a landscape that reflects or shares their woe; they help “poor Philomel”, the nightingale, a common poetic figure for sorrow, to sing a lamenting song; and their sad songs are sung “in vain” (“Then let us cease in vain to make our moan”, line 53). While the reason for the sisters’ woe is not explicitly identified, the poem is a broad complaint against the times, the “base world” offering only “wants and losses” (lines 50, 12). Pulter’s wider body of work suggests a political context for this: the poem’s complaint elements can be usefully read alongside <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="2">The Invitation into the Country</ref>, <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="4">The Complaint of Thames, 1647</ref>; <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="38">To My Dear Jane, Margaret, and Penelope Pulter, they Being at London, I at Broadfield</ref>, and several other of Pulter’s poems that construe Broadfield as a landscape of loss and loneliness.</p>
                    <p>At the same time as the poem is a clear example of complaint, its title and form mark it as a dialogue poem, another mode with a “dizzying array of precedents” in the early modern period. (For dialogue poetry, see <bibl>W. Scott Howard, "Milton’s ‘Hence’: Dialogue and the Shape of History in ‘L’Allegro’ and ‘Il Penseroso’, in <title rend="italic">Printed Voices: The Renaissance Culture of Dialogue, ed. Dorothea Heitsch and Jean-François Vallée</title> (Toronto: University of Toronto Press, 2004), pp. 157–74</bibl>). Pastoral dialogues are the clearest precedent here, in the broad tradition of <bibl><author>Spenser’s</author> <title rend="italic">The Shepheard’s Calendar</title></bibl>, and the poem reflects the proximity of pastoral and complaint that can also be seen in Spenser’s work (see Craik, “Spenser’s ‘Complaints’ and the New Poet”). Spenser is a likely influence on Pulter’s poetry, with commonalities also evident between “The Complaint of Thames, 1647” (Poem 4) and <bibl><title rend="italic">The Ruines of Time</title></bibl>, which was published in <bibl><title rend="italic">Complaints</title> (<date>1591</date>)</bibl>. The Spenserian text closest to “A Dialogue Between Two Sisters” is another poem published in the same volume, <bibl><title rend="italic">The Tears of the Muses</title></bibl>.</p>
                    <p>Pulter’s placement of complaint in a dialogue between two sisters is, however, divergent from dominant traditions. Female complainers are most frequently heard in dialogue with a framing male narrator, whose understanding of the complainer’s (or complainers’) plight is limited, and who is unable to offer any consolation. Kerrigan has reflected productively on the “compulsive dialectic” of framed female-voiced complaint, with a “sense of distortion” and an “interpretative instability” emerging between the woman’s grief and the masculine framing narrator’s incomprehension (p. 12). Pulter’s dialogue, in contrast, is between two female speakers who share and understand each other’s grief, sympathising with each other. Their woes are shared not only with each other, but with all aspects of the landscape around them: “For all things here which do in order rise, / Methinks in woe with us do sympathise” (lines 13–14). And at the end of the poem, the sisters turn to their mother (the implied author of the dialogue poem), promising to go and mitigate her sorrowful loneliness. In its dynamic of female woes shared, the poem can be compared to “The Complaint of Thames, 1647” (Poem 4), in which the woeful Thames outlines her sorrows to the implicitly female framing speaker of the poem. Beyond Pulter’s oeuvre, another female-authored, female-voiced complaint in dialogue is Anne Bradstreet’s <bibl><title rend="italic">A Dialog ue Between Old England and New</title></bibl>.</p>
                </note></rdg>
            </app>
            </head>
            
            <app>
              <rdg wit="#ft"><milestone unit="poem-section" rend="stanza-whitespace"/> </rdg>
				      <rdg wit="#ee"><milestone unit="poem-section" rend="stanza-whitespace"/> </rdg>
				      <rdg wit="#ae"><milestone unit="poem-section" rend="stanza-whitespace"/> </rdg>
			      </app>
      			<app>
      				<rdg wit="#ft"><milestone unit="poem-section" n="Young Anne" rend="left-gutter"/></rdg>
      				<rdg wit="#ee"><milestone unit="poem-section" n="Young Anne" rend="left-gutter"/></rdg>
      				<rdg wit="#ae"><milestone unit="poem-section" n="Young Anne" rend="left-gutter"/></rdg>
      			</app>
          
              <l n="1">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Come my deare Sister Sit with mee a while</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Come, my dear sister, sit with me awhile</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Come, my dear sister, sit with me a while,</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="2">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">That wee both Time and Sorrow may beguile</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">That we both time and sorrow may <seg>beguile<note type="gloss">cheat, entertain</note></seg>.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">That we both Time and Sorrow may beguile;</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="3">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">In this Sweet Shade by this cleer Purling Spring</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">In this sweet shade, by this clear <seg>purling<note type="gloss">rippling, murmuring</note></seg> spring,</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">In this sweet shade, by this clear, purling spring,</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="4">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Wee’l Sit and help poor Philomele to Sing</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">We’ll sit and help poor <seg>Philomel<note type="critical"> in mythology, Tereus rapes Philomela and cuts out her tongue; after she takes revenge, she is turned into a nightingale, a bird known for its beautiful song.</note></seg> to sing;</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">We’ll sit and help poor <seg>Philomel<note type="critical">the nightingale. In Greek mythology, Philomela is raped by Tereus, who cuts out her tongue so she is unable to tell anyone what has happened to her; however, she reveals her story in an embroidered tapestry and is metamorphosed into the nightingale. On account of the myth, the nightingale’s song has a long poetic association with sorrow and melancholy; for example, see Milton, “Il Penseroso”, lines 56–64. (In fact, in nature, the female bird is silent and only the male sings.)</note></seg> to sing,</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="5">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">And to Compleat the Conſort and the Quire</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">And to complete the <seg>consort<note type="gloss">harmony</note></seg> and the choir,</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">And to complete the <seg>consort<note type="gloss">a company of musicians making music together (<bibl><title rend="italic">OED</title> n.2 4</bibl>); here, instrumental musicians to complement the vocal “choir”</note></seg> and the choir,</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="6">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">I would I had my Viol you your Lyre</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">I would I had <seg>my viol, you your lyre<note type="gloss">stringed musical instruments</note></seg>.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">I would I had my <seg>viol, you your lyre<note type="gloss">stringed instruments, the viol played with a bow and the lyre plucked like a harp</note></seg>.</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
          
            <app>          
				      <rdg wit="#ft"><milestone unit="poem-section" rend="stanza-whitespace"/> </rdg>
              <rdg wit="#ee"><milestone unit="poem-section" rend="stanza-whitespace"/> </rdg>
				      <rdg wit="#ae"><milestone unit="poem-section" rend="stanza-whitespace"/> </rdg>
			      </app>
      			<app>
      				<rdg wit="#ft"><milestone unit="poem-section" n="Elder Pen" rend="left-gutter"/></rdg>
      				<rdg wit="#ee"><milestone unit="poem-section" n="Elder Pen" rend="left-gutter"/></rdg>
      				<rdg wit="#ae"><milestone unit="poem-section" n="Elder Pen" rend="left-gutter"/></rdg>
      			</app>

          
              <l n="7">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Aye mee my Sister Time on Restles wheels</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Ay me, my sister! Time on restless wheels</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Ay me, my sister, Time on restless wheels</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="8">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Doth ever turn <seg><del>with</del><note type="physical">imperfectly erased</note></seg> With wings upon his Heels</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Doth ever turn with wings upon his heels,</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Doth ever turn with wings upon his heels,</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="9">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">&ff;ast as the Sand that Huddles through his Glaſs</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Fast as the sand that huddles through his <seg>glass<note type="gloss">hourglass</note></seg>;</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Fast as the sand that <seg>huddles<note type="gloss">hurries (<bibl><title rend="italic">OED</title> 4b</bibl>)</note></seg> through his <seg>glass<note type="gloss">hourglass</note></seg>,</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="10">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Regardles of our Tears hee on doth Paſs</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Regardless of our tears, he on doth pass.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Regardless of our tears, he on doth pass;</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="11">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Yet in the Shade of this Sad Sycomore</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Yet in the shade of this sad <seg>sycamore<note type="gloss">tree associated with sorrow</note></seg></rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Yet in the shade of this sad sycamore</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="12">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Wee’l Sit our wants and Loſſes to deplore</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">We’ll sit, our wants and losses to <seg>deplore<note type="gloss">lament</note></seg>;</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">We’ll sit, our wants and losses to <seg>deplore<note type="gloss">bewail, lament</note></seg>,</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="13">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">&ff;or all things here which doe in order Rise</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">For all things here which do <seg>in order<note type="gloss">in the natural order</note></seg> rise,</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">For all things here which do in <seg>order<note type="critical">natural order (<bibl><title rend="italic">OED</title> 11c</bibl>), perhaps with a sense of a fraternity or sorority, a society (<bibl><title rend="italic">OED</title> 8c</bibl>)</note></seg> rise,</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="14">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Mee thinks in woe with us doe Sympathiſe</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Methinks in woe with us do sympathize.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Methinks in woe with us do sympathise.</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="15">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Theſe Cypris like our hopes doe leſſer grow</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">These <seg>cypress<note type="critical">cypresses; trees associated with death and mourning; once cut, they were thought to stop growing; here the speaker sees this lack of growth as a shrinking</note></seg>, like our hopes, do lesser grow;</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">These <seg>cypress<note type="critical">a tree traditionally associated with death and mourning (<bibl><title rend="italic">OED</title> 1c</bibl>)</note></seg>, like our hopes, do lesser grow;</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="16">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">This Bubling &ff;ount like our Sad eyes doe fllow</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">This bubbling fount, like our sad eyes, does flow,</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">This bubbling fount like our sad eyes does flow,</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="17">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">And though it doth a greater murmering keep</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">And though it doth a greater murmuring keep,</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">And though it doth a greater murmuring keep,</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="18">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Yet wee may teach this living Spring to weep</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Yet we may <seg>teach this living spring to weep<note type="critical">They could teach the fount to flow more because their weeping exceeds even its output.</note></seg>.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Yet we may teach this living spring to weep;</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <app>
                <rdg wit="#ft"><fw type="catch" place="bottom">these</fw></rdg>
            </app>
              <app>
                <rdg wit="#ft"><pb ed="#ft" facs="#f7610_158" n="77v"/></rdg>
                <rdg wit="#ee"><pb ed="#ee" facs="#f7610_158"/></rdg>
                <rdg wit="#ae"><pb ed="#ae" facs="#f7610_158"/></rdg>
              </app>
            <l n="19">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Theſe Primroſes like us neglected &ff;ade</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">These primroses, like us, neglected fade,</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">These primroses, like us, neglected fade,</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="20">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">And Violets Sit weeping in the Shade</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">And violets sit weeping in the shade.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">And violets sit weeping in the shade;</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="21">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">With us Sad Hiacinthus Sighs out Aye</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">With us sad <seg>Hyacinthus<note type="critical">mythological lover of Apollo (god of the sun); Zephrus, the wind god, kills him in a jealous rage and he is turned into a flower; according to Ovid, Apollo wrote lines about his grief, which Phoebus (the sun) imprinted on the flower’s petals (“ay”). See John Gerard, <bibl><title rend="italic">Herbal</title> (London, 1633), 193–4.</bibl></note></seg> sighs out, “ay!”</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">With us, sad <seg>Hyacinthus<note type="critical">the hyacinth. In Greek mythology, a young man loved by both Apollo and Zephyrus; he is killed by Zephyrus in a jealous rage, and turns into the flower.</note></seg> sighs out “ay”,</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="22">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">And lovly Aramantha doth display</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">And lovely <seg>Amarantha<note type="critical">flower thought never to fade; symbol of immortality sometimes placed on gravestones</note></seg> doth display</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">And lovely <seg>Amarantha<note type="gloss">the amaranth, an imaginary flower reputed never to fade</note></seg> doth display</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="23">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Her bevties here to noe admireing eye</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Her beauties here to no admiring eye.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Her beauties here to no admiring eye;</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="24">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Just Soe obliviated wee live and die</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Just so, <seg>obliviated<note type="gloss">made to be forgotten</note></seg>, we live and die;</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Just so <seg>obliviated<note type="gloss">forgotten, committed to oblivion</note></seg> we live and die.</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="25">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">And for your Viol and my Theorbo Lute</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">And for your viol and my <seg>theorbo lute<note type="gloss">variety of lute with two sets of tuning pegs and a larger neck</note></seg>,</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">And for your viol and my <seg>theorbo lute<note type="gloss">a large lute with two sets of tuning pegs and an extended neck, enabling additional bass strings</note></seg>,</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="26">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">They <seg>both Unſtrung<note type="physical">words crowded slightly; “U” in unstrung originally a minuscule, corrected to majuscule</note></seg> upon the Wall hang Mute</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">They both, unstrung, upon the wall hang mute,</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">They both unstrung, upon the wall, hang mute,</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="27">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">And in a uniſon will Scarcely move</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">And in a unison will scarcely move,</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">And in a unison will scarcely move,</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="28">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">They’r Soe unuſed Ay mee to Strains of Love</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">They’re so unused (ay me) to strains of love.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">They’re so unused, ay me, to strains of love.</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="29">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">With Philomele wee may lament too Late</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">With Philomel we may lament too late</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">With <seg>Philomel<note type="critical">see note to line 4</note></seg> we may lament too late</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="30">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Our most disastrous and too differing &ff;ate</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Our most disastrous, and <seg>too differing, fate<note type="critical">both the speaker and Philomela are pained by obstacles in expressing their woes (given that the sisters’ instruments are “unstrung”), though Philomela’s fate is much more tragic.</note></seg>.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Our most disastrous, and too differing, fate.</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="31">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Oh my Sad Heart would wee might paſs <w lemma="our"><abbr>o:<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></abbr></w> Howers</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">O my sad heart, would we might pass our hours</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">O, my sad heart, would we might pass our hours</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="32">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">As innocently <seg>contented<note type="physical">“ed” is written over imperfectly erased “ly”</note></seg> as theſe &ff;lowers</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">As innocently contented as these flowers,</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">As innocently contented as these flowers</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="33">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Who Shew their bevties to admireing eyes</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Who show their beauties to admiring eyes,</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Who show their beauties to admiring eyes,</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="34">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Then breathing Aromatick Odours dies</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Then <seg>breathing<note type="gloss">exhaling</note></seg> aromatic odors, dies.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Then breathing aromatic odours <seg>dies<note type="critical">i.e. die. Verb agreement in Pulter’s verse is not strict; this instance has not been modernised, in order to preserve the rhyme.</note></seg>.</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="35">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Come my dear Nan in this Sad Shade wee’l lye</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Come, my dear <seg>Nan<note type="gloss">nickname for Anne</note></seg>, in this sad shade we’ll lie,</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Come, my dear <seg>Nan<note type="gloss">a common pet-name for “Anne”</note></seg>, in this sad shade we’ll lie,</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="36">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">And like them Sweetly liue and Sweetly Die</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">And, like them, sweetly live and sweetly die.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">And like them sweetly live and sweetly die.</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="37">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Adonis blood the Enymonie up Rears</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1"><seg>Adonis’ blood the anemone uprears<note type="critical">young hunter beloved by Venus; after he is killed by a boar, she uses his blood to transform him into a colorful flower (the anemone).</note></seg>.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1"><seg>Adonis’ blood the anemone uprears:<note type="critical">In Greek mythology, Adonis is the young and beautiful man loved by Aphrodite. After he is killed by a wild boar, her tears mingle with his blood to transform him into a brightly-coloured flower, the anemone.</note></seg></rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="38">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Who knowes? Such vertue may <seg><add place="below">\</add><add place="above">bee \</add><note type="physical">in different hand from main scribe</note></seg> in <w lemma="our"><abbr>o:<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></abbr></w> tears</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Who knows? Such virtue may be in our tears:</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Who knows, such virtue may <seg>be<note type="critical">The word “be” has been inserted above the line, as a correction in the hand that I take to be Pulter’s own (see Ross (2000), pp. 150–171 and 252–4).</note></seg> in our tears;</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="39">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">These <seg>vi’lets<note type="physical">“i” written over other letter, perhaps “e”</note></seg>, Primroſe, Payles <w lemma="which"><abbr>w:<hi rend="superscript">ch</hi></abbr></w> apears</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">These violets, primrose, <seg>pales<note type="gloss">florets</note></seg> which appears,</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">These vi’lets, primrose, <seg>pales<note type="critical">apparently a type of flower, like others listed in the line. For an approximate meaning, see <bibl><title rend="italic">OED</title> n.1.III.7a</bibl>: The ray (outer florets) of a typical flower of the family Asteraceae (Compositae).</note></seg> which <seg>appears<note> i.e. appear. Verb agreement in Pulter’s verse is not strict; this instance has not been modernised, in order to preserve the rhyme.</note></seg>,</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="40">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Perhaps their number Springs from Virgins tears</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Perhaps their number springs from virgins’ tears.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Perhaps their number <seg>springs from virgins’ tears<note type="critical">See note to line 37. For a similar idea, see <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="61">The Weeping Wish</ref>: “Oh that my tears that fall down to the earth / Might give some noble, unknown flower birth” (lines 9–10).</note></seg>.</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <app><rdg wit="#ft"><fw type="catch" place="bottom">O</fw></rdg></app>
              <app>
                <rdg wit="#ft"><pb ed="#ft" facs="#f7610_159" n="78r"/></rdg>
                <rdg wit="#ee"><pb ed="#ee" facs="#f7610_159"/></rdg>
                <rdg wit="#ae"><pb ed="#ae" facs="#f7610_159"/></rdg>
              </app>

            <l n="41">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">O mee I would I might this very hower</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">O me, I would I might this very hour</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">O me, I would I might this very hour</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="42">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Sigh my Sad Soul into this July &ff;lower</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Sigh my sad soul into this <seg>gillyflower<note type="gloss">carnation</note></seg>.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Sigh my sad soul into this <seg>July flower<note type="gloss">gillyflower</note></seg>;</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="43">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Trust mee I <add place="below">^</add><add place="above">gladly</add> would <seg>trancmigerate<note type="physical">“i” appears written over earlier “e”</note></seg></rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Trust me, I gladly would <seg>transmigrate<note type="gloss"> to move to another place; movement of the soul into another body after death; here, to die</note></seg>,</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Trust me, I gladly would <seg>transmigerate<note type="gloss">i.e. transmigrate, the action of the soul passing, after death, into another body (<bibl><title rend="italic">OED</title> 2a</bibl>)</note></seg>,</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="44">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">That <seg>my<note type="physical">“m” written over imperfectly erased “I”</note></seg> aflicted life might haue a date</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">That my afflicted life might have a <seg>date<note type="gloss">limit, end</note></seg>.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">That my afflicted life might <seg>have a date<note type="critical">probably in the sense of <bibl><title rend="italic">OED</title> n.2 5</bibl>: have a limit, an end-point</note></seg>,</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="45">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">But wee (he las) in Sad obſcurity</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">But we (alas) in sad obscurity</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">But we, alas, in sad obscurity</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="46">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Must hopeles live, and Soe I doubt I must die</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Must hopeless live, and so, I <seg>doubt<note type="gloss">fear</note></seg>, must die.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Must hopeless live and so, I doubt, must die.</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="47">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Oh that a recluſe life had bin my &ff;ate</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">O that a recluse life had been my fate,</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">O, that a <seg>rècluse life<note type="gloss">a life of seclusion, withdrawal from society</note></seg> had been my fate,</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="48">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">To take our viſits at a Curteous grate</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">To take our visits at a <seg>courteous grate<note type="gloss">place of confinement named for metal bars that nevertheless permit communication (and so are “courteous”)</note></seg>.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">To take our visits at a <seg>courteous grate<note type="gloss">metal bars (a grate) through which a conversation is taken, as were common at houses of religious seclusion</note></seg>.</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
          
            <app>
				      <rdg wit="#ft"><milestone unit="poem-section" rend="stanza-whitespace"/> </rdg>
              <rdg wit="#ee"><milestone unit="poem-section" rend="stanza-whitespace"/> </rdg>
				      <rdg wit="#ae"><milestone unit="poem-section" rend="stanza-whitespace"/> </rdg>
              
			      </app>
      			<app>
      				<rdg wit="#ft"><milestone unit="poem-section" n="Ann." rend="left-gutter"/></rdg>
      				<rdg wit="#ee"><milestone unit="poem-section" n="Anne" rend="left-gutter"/></rdg>
      				<rdg wit="#ae"><milestone unit="poem-section" n="Anne" rend="left-gutter"/></rdg>
      			</app>

            <l n="49">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Stay my Dear Sister I have noe mind to die</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Stay, my dear sister, I have no mind to die;</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Stay, my dear sister, I have no mind to die;</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="50">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">A little more of this baſe World Ile trie</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">A little more of this base world I’ll <seg>try<note type="gloss">test</note></seg>;</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">A little more of this base world I’ll try,</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="51">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">And if whats future proue like what is <seg>past<note type="physical">part of “s” in darker ink, possibly over earlier “r”</note></seg></rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">And if what’s future <seg>prove<note type="gloss">prove to be</note></seg> like what is past,</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">And if what’s future prove like what is past,</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="52">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">I’le patient bee, I can but die at last</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">I’ll patient be; I can but die at last.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">I’ll patient be, I can but die at last.</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="53">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Then let us ceaſe in vain to make our <seg>moane<note type="physical">“e” is fainter, perhaps imperfectly erased</note></seg></rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Then let us cease in vain to make our moan,</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Then let us cease in vain to make our moan,</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="54">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">And go to our Sad Mother Shee’s <seg>alone.<note type="physical">A tilde-shaped line follows the poem; the remaining third of the page and the reverse are blank.</note></seg></rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">And go to our sad mother; she’s alone.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">And go to our sad mother; she’s alone.</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
          
            <app>
                <rdg type="milestone" wit="#ft">
                    <milestone unit="poem" rend="tilda-line"/>
                </rdg>
            </app>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
