<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../src/vmachine.xsl"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI [

<!ENTITY ff "<!-- ff ligature, representing capital modern day capital F, here represented as 'ff' -->ff">

]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mads.pp.63">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Dear God, From Thy High Throne Look Down</title>
                <title type="sub">Poem 63</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>authored by</resp>
                    <persName>Hester Pulter</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcription, transformations, and notes by</resp>
                    <persName>Leah Knight</persName>
                    <orgName>Brock University</orgName>
                    <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>
                    <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoded by</resp>
                    <persName>Katie Poland</persName>
                    <persName>Matthew Taylor</persName>
                    <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>
                    <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
                    <orgName>Brock University</orgName>
                    <orgName>University of Leeds</orgName>
                </sponsor>
                <!--
                <funder>
                    <orgName></orgName>
                    <orgName></orgName>
                </funder>
                -->
                <principal>
                    <persName/>
                </principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1"/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription, transformations, and notes</resp>
                    <persName>Leah Knight</persName>
                    <orgName>Brock University</orgName>
                    <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>
                    <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent/>
            <publicationStmt>
                <ab/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl>
                    <msDesc>
                        <msIdentifier>
                            <repository>See witness list.</repository>
                        </msIdentifier>
                    </msDesc>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <p>Transcriptions are encoded in TEI(P5)-conformant XML.</p>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p>Apparent errors are preserved and editorial corrections provided using SIC
                        and CORR tags, but only where the editor conjectures that the original
                        scribe or compositor would have recognized the instance as an error. For
                        example, what according to modern usage is incorrect subject/verb agreement
                        might have been deemed acceptable to a seventeenth-century scribe or
                        compositor. All such instances are treated instead using the ORIG and REG
                        tags. (See below.) </p>
                    <p>Corrections and annotations made within the scope of the original document
                        either by its original authors, owners, and/or transcribers are noted using
                        ADD tags. These annotations and may be further explained within NOTE tags, as
                        added by the editors of this digital edition, for display within the
                        apparatus.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p>Original spellings, abbreviations, and orthography are preserved. Where in
                        the manuscripts a character’s status as majuscule or minuscule is ambiguous,
                        the editor has silently chosen one or the other based on context and
                        judgment (i.e., does not register such ambiguity in either the markup or the
                        notes).</p>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p>Original quotation marks, if any, are preserved.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p>Original hyphenation is preserved.</p>
                </hyphenation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <charDecl>
                <!-- Ligature combinations for which there are currently no corresponding Unicode codepoints. -->
                <glyph xml:id="ffllig">
                    <glyphName>Handwritten 'ff' ligature, used in handwriting to represent modern
                        F</glyphName>
                </glyph>
            </charDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="DDC22">
                    <bibl>
                        <title>Dewey Decimal Classification</title>
                        <edition/>
                        <publisher/>
                        <pubPlace/>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en-GB">British English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <!-- dewey decimal system class code 821: English Poetry -->
                <classCode scheme="DDC22">821</classCode>
                <keywords>
                    <term>prayer</term>
                    <term>suffering</term>
                    <term>transformation</term>
                    <term>faith</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic url="./document_images/7610_175.jpg" xml:id="f7610_175"/>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div>
                <listWit>
                    <witness xml:id="ft">Transcription of manuscript: By <persName xml:id="lknight">Leah Knight</persName> and <persName xml:id="wwall">Wendy Wall</persName>.</witness>
                    <witness xml:id="ee">Elemental edition: By <persName>Leah Knight</persName> and <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>.</witness>
                    <witness xml:id="ae">Amplified edition: By <persName>Victoria E. Burke</persName>.</witness>
                </listWit>
            </div>
        </front>

        <body>
            <app>
                <rdg wit="#ft"><pb ed="#ft" facs="#f7610_175" n="86r"/></rdg>
                <rdg wit="#ee"><pb ed="#ee" facs="#f7610_175"/></rdg>
                <rdg wit="#ae"><pb ed="#ae" facs="#f7610_175"/></rdg>
            </app>
            <head>
              <app type="title">
                <rdg wit="#ft"><!-- [Untitled] --></rdg>
                <rdg wit="#ee">Dear God, From Thy High Throne Look Down</rdg>
                <rdg wit="#ae">Dear God from thy high Throne look down</rdg>
              </app>
              <app type="editorialnote">
                <rdg wit="#ft"><note type="editorialnote">In these transcriptions we preserve as many details of the original material, textual, and graphic properties of Hester Pulter’s manuscript verse as we have found practical. Whenever possible, for instance, original spelling, punctuation, capitalization, lineation, insertions, deletions, alterations, spacing between words and lines, and indentation are all maintained; abbreviations and brevigraphs are not expanded; and superscript and subscript representations are retained. <ref target="//pulterproject.northwestern.edu/about-project-conventions.html#top" type="new-window-url">See full conventions for the transcriptions here.</ref></note></rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#ee"><note type="editorialnote">The aim of the elemental edition to make the poems accessible to the largest variety of readers, which involves modernizing spelling and punctuation as well as adding basic glosses. Spelling and punctuation reflect current standard American usage; punctuation highlights syntax which might otherwise be obscure. Outmoded but still familiar word forms (“thou,” “‘tis,” “hold’st”) are not modernized, and we do not modernize grammar when the sense remains legible. After a brief headnote aimed at offering a “way in” to the poem’s unique qualities and connections with other verse by Pulter or her contemporaries, the edition features a minimum of notes and interpretative framing to allow more immediate engagement with the poem. Glosses clarify synonyms or showcase various possible meanings in Pulter’s time. Other notes identify named people and places or clarify obscure material. We rely (without citation) primarily on the Oxford English Dictionary (OED), the Oxford Reference database, and the King James Version (KJV) of the Bible. When we rely on Alice Eardley’s edition of Pulter’s work, we cite her text generally (“Eardley”); other sources are cited in full. The result is an edition we consider a springboard for further work on Pulter’s poetry. <ref target="//pulterproject.northwestern.edu/about-project-conventions.html#elemental-edition" type="new-window-url">See full conventions for this edition here.</ref></note></rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#ae"><note type="editorialnote">This is a diplomatic transcription in which original spelling, punctuation, and spacing between lines are retained. This poem is one of five poems written near the end of the poetry section of the manuscript in a different hand from the main scribe’s. That scribe makes no use in this poem of any abbreviations or scribal signs and so a pure, diplomatic transcription, in which every original feature of the manuscript is replicated, can be done without leading to any alienation for the modern reader, who may find these features cryptic. These notes point out parallels I see with other writers, and particularly women writers, with the aims of placing Pulter in dialogue with ideas explored by other women around this time, and of tracing a kind of female poetic lineage or alternate canon.</note></rdg>
              </app>
              <app type="headnote">
                <rdg wit="#ee"><note type="headnote">The taut lines and short stanzas here epitomize the tension in the speaker’s plea to God, which is not simply for God to end but to “crown” her sufferings on earth, perhaps in recognition of what the speaker proceeds to demonstrate: her fervent faith in his mercy and justice, despite her unremitting experience of grief, tears, and sighs. That earthly experience is contrasted with an anticipated dissolution of her corporeal being, one which is (as is typical in Pulter’s poems) not imagined as a loss but as a reconfiguration of particles, or a rewriting of divine poetic “figures.” With this metaphorical term for metaphor, as in subsequent lines, the speaker quietly likens herself and God as writers, each composing a book which features her: “poor wretched me, each part, / E’en all my soul, my thoughts, my heart.” She is confident God reads her aright in either his own records or her verse, wherein her love is made “plain.” The poem’s condensed form contrasts vividly with the expansive plenitude of multiple worlds toward which its vision tends.</note></rdg>
                <rdg wit="#ae"><note type="headnote">This lyric skilfully links discourses of religion, alchemy, and natural philosophy (or science), and demonstrates their congruence for this mid-seventeenth-century writer. Formally this poem is written in nine three-line stanzas, featuring two lines of rhyming tetrameter followed by a line of dimeter that rhymes with the dimeter lines in the following two stanzas. This exact stanzaic structure does not appear to be used elsewhere in Pulter’s poetry, though <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="24">How Long Shall My Dejected Soul</ref> and <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="29">My Soul’s Sole Desire</ref> are similar.</note></rdg>
                </app>
            </head>
            <l n="1">
              <app>
                <rdg wit="#ft"><seg>Dear God<note type="physical">This poem is in a different hand from the main scribe, and is on paper that was tipped into the manuscript after binding.</note></seg> from thy high Throne look down</rdg>
                <rdg wit="#ee"><seg>Dear<note type="physical">This poem is not in the hand of the main scribe nor in the hand we identify as probably Pulter's.</note></seg> God, from Thy high throne look down,</rdg>
                <rdg wit="#ae">Dear God from thy high Throne look down</rdg>
              </app>
            </l>
            <l n="2">
              <app>
                <rdg wit="#ft">And lett my ſuff’rings haue their Crown</rdg>
                <rdg wit="#ee">And let my suff’rings have their <seg>crown<note type="critical">Pertinent examples include the mock royal crown made of thorns put on Jesus’s head before his crucifixion and those, symbolizing victory, conceived in Christianity as being conferred on any soul received in heaven, or the reward or glory represented by it; also the consummation or pinnacle of something.</note></seg>:</rdg>
                <rdg wit="#ae">And <seg>lett my suff’rings haue their Crown<note type="gloss">The sense of lines 1-2 is that she wishes God would notice her suffering and reward or sanctify it.</note></seg></rdg>
              </app>
            </l>
            <l n="3" rend="tab-6">
              <app>
                <rdg wit="#ft">I thee Implore</rdg>
                <rdg wit="#ee">I Thee implore.</rdg>
                <rdg wit="#ae">I thee Implore</rdg>
              </app>
            </l>
            <app>
                <rdg wit="#ee"><milestone unit="poem-section" rend="stanza-whitespace"/></rdg>
            </app>
            <l n="4">
              <app>
                  <rdg wit="#ft">Tho’ greif calcine my Flesh to Duſt</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#ee">Though grief <seg>calcine<note type="gloss">burn to ash or dust; purify or refined by consuming the grosser part</note></seg> my flesh to <seg>dust<note type="critical">physical being; primal elements; see Genesis 2:7: “And the Lord God formed man [of] the dust of the ground, and breathed into his nostrils the breath of life; and man became a living soul.”</note></seg></rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#ae">Tho’ greif <seg>calcine<note type="gloss">burn to ashes or purify, often used as an alchemical term</note></seg> my Flesh to Dust</rdg>
              </app>
          </l>
            <l n="5">
              <app>
                  <rdg wit="#ft">Yett in thy Mercy still I Trust</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#ee">Yet in Thy mercy still I trust</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#ae">Yett in thy Mercy still I Trust</rdg>
              </app>
          </l>
            <l n="6" rend="tab-6">
              <app>
                  <rdg wit="#ft">and thee Adore</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#ee">And Thee adore.</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#ae">and thee Adore</rdg>
              </app>
          </l>
            <app>
              <rdg wit="#ee"><milestone unit="poem-section" rend="stanza-whitespace"/></rdg>
            </app>
            <l n="7">
              <app>
                <rdg wit="#ft">Should I to Tears diſsolved be</rdg>
                <rdg wit="#ee">Should I to tears dissolvéd be</rdg>
                <rdg wit="#ae">Should I to Tears <seg>dissolved<note type="critical">Pulter uses images of dissolution in many of her poems, and the specific image of being dissolved into tears at least five other times in her verse (see <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="13">Upon the Imprisonment of his Sacred Majesty</ref>, <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="17">The Circle [1]</ref>, <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="32">Aletheia’s Pearl</ref>, <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="35">The Pismire</ref>, and <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="87">The Hunted Hart (Emblem 22)</ref>). Several of her poems depict her earthly body dissolving, dispersing, or being reduced to dust, while her spirit travels to heaven.</note></seg> be</rdg>
              </app>
          </l>
            <l n="8">
              <app>
                  <rdg wit="#ft">Yett will I Still depend on thee</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#ee">Yet will I still <seg>depend<note type="gloss">rely upon; await</note></seg> on Thee</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#ae">Yett will I Still depend on thee</rdg>
              </app>
          </l>
            <l n="9" rend="tab-6">
              <app>
                  <rdg wit="#ft">for Evermore</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#ee">Forevermore.</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#ae">for Evermore</rdg>
              </app>
          </l>
            <app>
              <rdg wit="#ee"><milestone unit="poem-section" rend="stanza-whitespace"/></rdg>
            </app>

            <l n="10">
              <app>
                  <rdg wit="#ft">Or ſhould I ſigh away to Air</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#ee">Or should I sigh away to air,</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#ae">Or should I sigh away to Air</rdg>
              </app>
          </l>
            <l n="11">
              <app>
                <rdg wit="#ft">Tho Rarify’d, I’d not Despair</rdg>
                <rdg wit="#ee">Though <seg>rarefied<note type="gloss">dissipated, purified</note></seg>, I’d not despair</rdg>
                <rdg wit="#ae">Tho <seg>Rarify’d<note type="gloss">thinner and less dense, but also purified</note></seg>, I’d not Despair</rdg>
              </app>
          </l>
            <l n="12" rend="tab-6">
              <app>
                  <rdg wit="#ft">but in thee trust</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#ee">But in Thee trust.</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#ae">but in thee trust</rdg>
              </app>
            </l>
            <app>
              <rdg wit="#ee"><milestone unit="poem-section" rend="stanza-whitespace"/></rdg>
            </app>

            <l n="13">
              <app>
                <rdg wit="#ft">Tho’ I to Atomſ am disperſ’d,</rdg>
                <rdg wit="#ee">Though I to <seg>atoms<note type="gloss">indivisible particles</note></seg> am dispersed,</rdg>
                <rdg wit="#ae">Tho’ I to <seg>Atoms<note type="critical">Atoms are indivisible particles from which matter is composed. As David Norbrook and Reid Barbour explain in their introduction to Lucy Hutchinson’s translation of Lucretius’s <title rend="italic">De rerum natura</title>, by the 1650s many English natural philosophers were engaging with Epicurean theories such as atomism and were reconciling them with Christianity (<title rend="italic">The Works of Lucy Hutchinson</title>, volume 1, Oxford University Press, 2011, pp. xxix-xxxiii).</note></seg> am dispers’d,</rdg>
              </app>
          </l>
            <l n="14">
              <app>
                  <rdg wit="#ft">I in their dances am unverſ’d,</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#ee">I in their dances am <seg>unversed<note type="gloss">inexperienced; not in verse</note></seg>,</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#ae">I in their <seg>dances<note type="critical">Other early modern writers characterized the movement of atoms as “dancing.” For example, in <title rend="italic">The darkness of atheisme expelled by the light of nature, or, The existence of a deity, and his creation and government of the world demonstrated from reason and the light of nature only</title> (1683), Henry Care articulates with horror the claims of atheists: “The Beauty and Harmony of the world they’l tell you, is only caused by the curious motion of Dancing Atoms, or the apt, yet fortuitous concurrence of Actives with Passives” (sig. B2v). Lucy Hutchinson, in her polemical manuscript dedication to her translation of Lucretius, which Norbrook and Barbour explain takes the stance of a reformed sinner, writes, “All these, and all the other poore deluded instructors of the Gentiles, are guilty of no lesse Impiety, ignorance &amp; folly then this Lunatick [i.e., Lucretius], who not able to diue into the true Originall &amp; Cause of Beings &amp; Accidents, admires them who devizd this Casuall, Irrationall dance of Attomes” (<title rend="italic">The Works of Lucy Hutchinson</title>, volume 1, pp. 7-9). But for Margaret Cavendish (many of whose poems in <title rend="italic">Poems and fancies</title> [1653] treat atoms), the dance of atoms is a more orderly phenomenon: see “A World made by Atomes” and “Motion directs, while Atomes dance” in <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="#ctxs">Margaret Cavendish’s Dancing Atoms</ref> in the Curations for this poem.</note></seg> am <seg>unvers’d<note type="gloss">untutored</note></seg>,</rdg>
              </app>
          </l>
            <l n="15" rend="tab-6">
              <app>
                <rdg wit="#ft">Yett Shall no Dust</rdg>
                <rdg wit="#ee">Yet shall no dust</rdg>
                <rdg wit="#ae">Yett Shall no Dust</rdg>
              </app>
            </l>
            <app>
              <rdg wit="#ee"><milestone unit="poem-section" rend="stanza-whitespace"/></rdg>
            </app>

            <l n="16">
              <app>
                  <rdg wit="#ft">of my old Carcaſe E’re be lost</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#ee">Of my old carcass e’er be lost</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#ae">of my old Carcase E’re be lost</rdg>
              </app>
          </l>
            <l n="17">
              <app>
                  <rdg wit="#ft">tho’ in a thousand Figures tost</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#ee">Though in a thousand <seg>figures<note type="gloss">shapes; appearances; embodiments; representations; horoscopes; movement of a dance; form of expression</note></seg> tossed,</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#ae">tho’ in a thousand <seg>Figures<note type="critical">shapes, movements, or configurations. The terminology of “figures” is often used in relation to atomistic movement at this time. For example, Robert Boyle in <title rend="italic">Certain physiological essays and other tracts written at distant times, and on several occasions</title> (1669) writes, “And because, <persName rend="italic">Pyrophilus</persName>, in the Reasons and Explications I offer of Natural Effects, I have not for the most part an immediate recourse to the Magnitude, Figure, and Motion of Atoms, or of the least Particles of Bodies, I hold it not unfit to give You here some account of this Practice” (p. 20). For a playfully gendered perspective, in which she claims that if a male motion had not persuaded female atoms to be his bawds (or procurers of prostitutes) in order to create a variety of young female forms or figures to delight him then they would have stayed unchanged in one shape, see Cavendish’s “Motion makes Atomes a Bawd for Figure” in <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="#ctxs">Margaret Cavendish’s female figures</ref> in the Curations for this poem.</note></seg> tost,</rdg>
              </app>
          </l>
            <l n="18" rend="tab-6">
              <app>
                  <rdg wit="#ft">for thou art Just.</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#ee">For Thou art just.</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#ae">for thou art Just.</rdg>
              </app>
          </l>
            <app>
              <rdg wit="#ee"><milestone unit="poem-section" rend="stanza-whitespace"/></rdg>
            </app>

            <l n="19">
              <app>
                <rdg wit="#ft">What Mortal can or dares to look</rdg>
                <rdg wit="#ee">What mortal can or dares to look</rdg>
                <rdg wit="#ae">What Mortal can or dares to look</rdg>
              </app>
          </l>
            <l n="20">
              <app>
                <rdg wit="#ft">Into thy Gloriouſ Bleſsed Book,</rdg>
                <rdg wit="#ee">Into Thy glorious <seg>blessed book<note type="critial">God’s register of those destined to enter heaven; see Revelation 20:12-15: “And I saw the dead, small and great, stand before God; … another book was opened, which is the book of life: and the dead were judged out of those things which were written in the books, according to their works. … And whosoever was not found written in the book of life was cast into the lake of fire.”</note></seg>?</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#ae">Into thy <seg>Glorious Blessed Book<note type="critical">The book of life into which God has written who will be saved and who damned (Revelation 20:12-15). The terms “unversed” (l. 14), “figures” (l. 17), and God’s “book” (l. 20) may all be puns on writing. The depiction of the speaker as unversed in the ways of atoms and tossed into a thousand figures may capture the impossibility of representing unfathomable truths as a “mortal” (l. 19). God, on the other hand, can read the book of life wherein each part of the speaker is “written” (l. 21).</note></seg>,</rdg>
              </app>
            </l>
            <l n="21" rend="tab-6">
                <app>
                  <rdg wit="#ft">Where written be</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#ee">Where written be</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#ae">Where written be</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <app>
              <rdg wit="#ee"><milestone unit="poem-section" rend="stanza-whitespace"/></rdg>
            </app>

            <l n="22">
              <app>
                  <rdg wit="#ft">of mee, poor wretched mee, each part</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#ee">Of me, poor wretched me, each part,</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#ae">of mee, poor wretched mee, each part</rdg>
              </app>
          </l>
            <l n="23">
              <app>
                <rdg wit="#ft">E’en all my ſoul my thoughts My Heart.</rdg>
                <rdg wit="#ee">E’en all my soul, my thoughts, my heart.</rdg>
                <rdg wit="#ae">E’en all my soul my thoughts My Heart.</rdg>
              </app>
            </l>
            <l n="24" rend="tab-6">
              <app>
                <rdg wit="#ft">Thou plain may’st ſee.</rdg>
                <rdg wit="#ee">Thou plain may’st see</rdg>
                <rdg wit="#ae">Thou plain may’st <seg>see.<note type="critical">This stanza on God’s knowing each part of her recalls Mary Sidney’s version of Psalm 139 which begins, “O lord in mee, there lieth nought / but to thy search revealed lies / for when I sitt / thou markest it / no lesse thou notest when I rise / yea closest Closett of my thought / hath open windows to thine eyes” (<title rend="italic">Isabella Whitney, Mary Sidney and Aemilia Lanyer: Renaissance Women Poets</title>, edited by Danielle Clarke, Penguin, 2000, p. 176, ll. 1-7).</note></seg></rdg>
              </app>
            </l>
            <app>
              <rdg wit="#ee"><milestone unit="poem-section" rend="stanza-whitespace"/></rdg>
            </app>

            <l n="25">
              <app>
                <rdg wit="#ft">that I my Gracious God do love</rdg>
                <rdg wit="#ee">That I my gracious God do love</rdg>
                <rdg wit="#ae">that I my Gracious God do love</rdg>
              </app>
            </l>
            <l n="26">
              <app>
                <rdg wit="#ft">A thouſand thouſsand worlds above,</rdg>
                <rdg wit="#ee">A thousand, thousand worlds above</rdg>
                <rdg wit="#ae">A thousand thoussand worlds above,</rdg>
              </app>
            </l>
            <l n="27" rend="tab-6">
              <app>
                <rdg wit="#ft">and still praiſe thee.</rdg>
                <rdg wit="#ee">And <seg>still<note type="gloss">always</note></seg> praise Thee.</rdg>
                <rdg wit="#ae">and still <seg>praise<note type="critical">The journey in this poem from the speaker imploring God (l. 3) to praising him recalls Anne Locke’s paraphrase of Psalm 51 in her “A Meditation of a Penitent Sinner.” In sonnet 17 Locke’s speaker asks God to “make me pray, and grant when I have prayed. / Lord loose my lips, I may express my moan, / And finding grace with open mouth I may / Thy mercies praise, and holy name display” (l. 11-14; <title rend="italic">The Broadview Anthology of Sixteenth-Century Poetry and Prose</title>, edited by Marie H. Loughlin, Sandra Bell, and Patricia Brace, Broadview, 2012, p. 218). Pulter’s speaker does not share Locke’s Calvinist anguish about his or her wretchedness without God’s grace. Pulter trusts in God’s mercy (l.5) and knows that he is “Just” (l. 18) in protecting every atom of her being, while Locke begs God for mercy and imagines his justice taking the form of severe punishment for the speaker’s unworthiness.</note></seg> thee.</rdg>
              </app>
            </l>
            <app>
              <rdg type="milestone" wit="ft"><seg><milestone unit="poem" rend="straight-ascendline"/><note type="physical">reverse of page blank</note></seg></rdg>
            </app>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
