<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../src/vmachine.xsl"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI [

<!ENTITY ff "<!-- ff ligature, representing capital modern day capital F, here represented as 'ff' -->ff">

]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mads.pp.51">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Made When I Was Not Well</title>
                 <title type="sub">Poem 51</title>
                <respStmt><resp>Created by</resp>
                    <persName>Leah Knight</persName>
                    <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoded by</resp>
                    <persName>Katherine Poland</persName>
                    <persName>Matthew Taylor</persName>
			              <persName>Betsy Chou</persName>
                    <persName>Emily Andrey</persName>
                    <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
                </respStmt>
		            <respStmt>
                     <resp>IT-project consultation by</resp>
                     <persName>Josh Honn</persName>
                 </respStmt>
                <sponsor>
                    <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
                    <orgName>Brock University</orgName>
                    <orgName>University of Leeds</orgName>
                </sponsor>
                <principal>
                    <persName/>
                </principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1"/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription, transformations, and notes</resp>
                    <persName>Leah Knight</persName>
                    <orgName>Brock University</orgName>
                    <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>
                    <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent/>
            <publicationStmt>
                <ab/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl>
                    <msDesc>
                        <msIdentifier>
                            <repository>See witness list.</repository>
                        </msIdentifier>
                    </msDesc>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <p>Transcriptions are encoded in TEI(P5)-conformant XML.</p>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p>Apparent errors are preserved and editorial corrections provided using SIC
                        and CORR tags, but only where the editor conjectures that the original
                        scribe or compositor would have recognized the instance as an error. For
                        example, what according to modern usage is incorrect subject/verb agreement
                        might have been deemed acceptable to a seventeenth-century scribe or
                        compositor. All such instances are treated instead using the ORIG and REG
                        tags. (See below.) </p>
                    <p>Corrections and annotations made within the scope of the original document
                        either by its original authors, owners, and/or transcribers are noted using
                        ADD tags. These annotations and may be further explained within NOTE tags, as
                        added by the editors of this digital edition, for display within the
                        apparatus.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p>Original spellings, abbreviations, and orthography are preserved. Where in
                        the manuscripts a character’s status as majuscule or minuscule is ambiguous,
                        the editor has silently chosen one or the other based on context and
                        judgment (i.e., does not register such ambiguity in either the markup or the
                        notes).</p>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p>Original quotation marks, if any, are preserved.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p>Original hyphenation is preserved.</p>
                </hyphenation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <charDecl>
                <!-- Ligature combinations for which there are currently no corresponding Unicode codepoints. -->
                <glyph xml:id="ffllig">
                    <glyphName>Handwritten 'ff' ligature, used in handwriting to represent modern
                        F</glyphName>
                </glyph>
            </charDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="DDC22">
                    <bibl>
                        <title>Dewey Decimal Classification</title>
                        <edition/>
                        <publisher/>
                        <pubPlace/>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en-GB">British English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <!-- dewey decimal system class code 821: English Poetry -->
                <classCode scheme="DDC22">821</classCode>
              <!--<keywords>-->
                     <!--<term>illness</term>-->
                     <!--<term>death</term>-->
                     <!--<term>blazon</term>-->
        	    <!--</keywords>-->
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic url="./document_images/7610_150.jpg" xml:id="f7610_150"/>
        <graphic url="./document_images/7610_151.jpg" xml:id="f7610_151"/>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div>
                <listWit>
                    <witness xml:id="ft">Transcription of manuscript: By <persName xml:id="lknight">Leah Knight</persName> and <persName xml:id="wwall">Wendy Wall</persName>.</witness>
                    <witness xml:id="ee">Elemental edition: By <persName>Leah Knight</persName> and <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>.</witness>
                    <witness xml:id="ae">Amplified edition: By <persName>Frances E. Dolan</persName>.</witness>
                </listWit>
            </div>
        </front>

        <body>
            <app>
                <rdg wit="#ft"><pb ed="#ft" facs="f7610_150" n="73v"/></rdg>
                <rdg wit="#ee"><pb ed="#ee" facs="f7610_150"/></rdg>
                <rdg wit="#ae"><pb ed="#ae" facs="f7610_150"/></rdg>
            </app>


            <head>
                <app type="title">
                    <rdg wit="#ft"><fw facs="#f7610_150" type="pageNum" place="margin-topright">142</fw>Made when I was not well. <seg>April 20. 1655.<note type="physical">The date is written in a different hand from the main scribe.</note></seg></rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee"><seg>Made When I Was Not Well<note type="physical">Following the title, in a different hand from that of the main scribe and from the hand we identify as probably Pulter’s: “April 20. 1655”</note></seg></rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>Made When I Was Not Well<note type="critical">The title seems to locate the poem in a particular moment. When the speaker was unwell, this is how she saw herself; perhaps her perspective changed when she recovered. The date April 20, 1655 has been added in the manuscript next to the poem’s title, linking the poem to a particular moment of illness when Pulter was fifty.</note></seg></rdg>
                </app>
                <app type="editorialnote">
                    <rdg wit="#ft"><note type="editorialnote">In these transcriptions we preserve as many details of the original material, textual, and graphic properties of Hester Pulter’s manuscript verse as we have found practical. Whenever possible, for instance, original spelling, punctuation, capitalization, lineation, insertions, deletions, alterations, spacing between words and lines, and indentation are all maintained; abbreviations and brevigraphs are not expanded; and superscript and subscript representations are retained. <ref target="//pulterproject.northwestern.edu/about-project-conventions.html#top" type="new-window-url">See full conventions for the transcriptions here.</ref></note></rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee"><note type="editorialnote">The aim of the elemental edition to make the poems accessible to the largest variety of readers, which involves modernizing spelling and punctuation as well as adding basic glosses. Spelling and punctuation reflect current standard American usage; punctuation highlights syntax which might otherwise be obscure. Outmoded but still familiar word forms (“thou,” “‘tis,” “hold’st”) are not modernized, and we do not modernize grammar when the sense remains legible. After a brief headnote aimed at offering a “way in” to the poem’s unique qualities and connections with other verse by Pulter or her contemporaries, the edition features a minimum of notes and interpretative framing to allow more immediate engagement with the poem. Glosses clarify synonyms or showcase various possible meanings in Pulter’s time. Other notes identify named people and places or clarify obscure material. We rely (without citation) primarily on the Oxford English Dictionary (OED), the Oxford Reference database, and the King James Version (KJV) of the Bible. When we rely on Alice Eardley’s edition of Pulter’s work, we cite her text generally (“Eardley”); other sources are cited in full. The result is an edition we consider a springboard for further work on Pulter’s poetry. <ref target="//pulterproject.northwestern.edu/about-project-conventions.html#elemental-edition" type="new-window-url">See full conventions for this edition here.</ref></note></rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae"><note type="editorialnote">My “amplified” editions seek to make the poems as accessible as possible by modernizing spelling and punctuation and providing only brief definitions for words, while discursive notes and the materials I gather for the “curations” section place Pulter’s poems into conversations. As I build the curations for a given poem—provisional and quirky as they are—I keep returning to the poem, re-reading, rethinking, and adding layers to the notes. I hope to show that Pulter was intellectually and politically embedded rather than isolated, taking up issues, genres, and tropes that also interested her contemporaries and that sometimes accrue unpredictable salience in later periods. Rather than focusing only on possible sources or influences, I cast a wide net both within the seventeenth century and outside it, trying to catch cultural materials Pulter might have engaged, some she excludes or ignores, and even some she probably could never have imagined. Curations don’t precede the poems nor are they implied by the poems—as if the poem gathers them to itself (although it can sometimes feel that way) or hales them forth. Instead, as a curator I weave the poem into a web of relations, seeking to open out rather than close down interpretive possibilities. This extends to including extracts that are long enough that readers might find things therein that I do not anticipate. I also look for a multi-vectored traffic among Pulter’s poetry and the other materials. What might the materials I’ve gathered help readers see in the poems—or notice is not there? But also, how do the poems bring fresh perspectives into the conversations into which I draw them? The more one reads the poems as participants in wider ranging conversations, the more fascinatingly twisty Pulter appears. Often, I don’t grasp how she upends or comes at conventions aslant until I have mucked about composting my “curations.”</note></rdg>
                </app>
            <app type="headnote">
                <rdg wit="#ee"><note type="headnote">Today we talk about medically-assisted death. Here, the speaker imagines a poetically—or rhetorically—assisted death, as she urges the departure of her soul from her body. In her sickness, she asks why her soul won’t just go and let her die. This poem suggests the soul’s attachment to the body’s “prison” is itself unholy; and as though to quicken the dissolution and decay that she desires, the speaker dissects her body and mind. Her self-blazon, however, swerves between aversion and nostalgia, “mourning” her lost youth in many of the same terms as Pulter uses in grieving her daughter Jane in <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="11">Tell Me No More [On the Same]</ref>. In a striking revision of one of the most common poetic conventions of love poetry, the speaker inventories her body parts—hair, lips, skin, breasts—and overlays a realistic aging body over the usual idealized comparisons. The poem’s repeated oscillation between glimpses of a beautiful golden age and the ruined present seem almost like a series of practice swings, pendulously building momentum for the soul’s anticipated onward movement, “away.”</note></rdg>
                <rdg wit="#ae"><note type="headnote">
                  <p>The title of this poem suggests that it will be a reflection on mortality prompted by illness, similar to those by poets including Donne and Herbert (see <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="#ctxs">Illness and Poetry</ref>). To a certain extent it is. But Pulter’s poem differs from other reflections from the sickroom in two ways: 1) the speaker’s gaze dwells on her own body, past and present, struggling to shift the focus to the future, to the death and resurrection that she is supposed to desire and that animate other Pulter poems (such as <ref target="/" corresp="18" type="pp-poem-ref">The Desire</ref>); and 2) the speaker never directly addresses God. The poem is self-contained, a conversation between speaker and soul about the body. What Pulter produces here is a diptych self-portrait, braiding together a blazon of her beauties when young with an anti-blazon frankly assessing her body now, ravaged by illness, age, and grief. (On the blazon, see <ref target="https://pulterproject.northwestern.edu/#hester-pulter-and-english-blazon" type="new-window-url">Hester Pulter and the Blazon in Early Modern England</ref> in “Explorations”). The two pictures are not simply set side by side. Throughout, the speaker tempers the assertion that this body is a ruined prison she should be eager to abandon with puzzled ruminations on her attachment to it regardless. What’s curious here is that the poem suggests that it is the soul, so often depicted as imprisoned in the body and released by death, that mourns over the ruined body and wants to stay in it. The speaker keeps urging the soul to look at this body and thereby get over being attached to it; the tone verges on hectoring: “see’st thou these eyes?” (line 3). The poem begins and ends with questions to the soul: why does it mourn the decaying flesh? Why does it want to stay in the world? The sharp observation driving the poem suggests one reason: an attachment to the specifics of the body, now as well as then.</p>
                  <p>Particular hostility focused on women’s aging bodies in the early modern period. An old woman often appeared in allegories of vanity, looking into or out of a mirror (see <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="#ctxs">Aging Women</ref>). John Gaule warns that “every old woman with a wrinkled face, a furrowed brow, a hairy lip, a gobber [buck] tooth, a squint eye, a squeaking voice, or a scolding tongue … is not only suspected, but pronounced for a witch” <bibl>(John Gaule, <title rend="italic">Select Cases of Conscience Touching Witches and Witchcraft</title> [London, 1646], 5)</bibl>. While today it is often said that aging women are culturally invisible, Pulter insists on seeing the aging female body and pointing out its features to the soul—and to the reader. The speaker regrets what she sees, but never looks away.</p></note></rdg>
            </app>
            </head>
            <l n="1">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">My Soul why do’st thou Such a mourning make</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">My soul, why dost thou such a mourning make,</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">My soul, why dost thou such a mourning make</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="2">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">This Loathſom ruind Priſon to forſake</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">This loathsome ruined prison to forsake?</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">This loathsome ruined <seg>prison to forsake<note type="critical">It was conventional to describe the body as the soul’s prison, usually so as to promote death as a release. Richard Allestree, for example, reminds readers that the friends they mourn for are no longer “confined to this prison of the body, but gone to dwell in the region of spirits; they are no longer exposed to these stormy seas, but are gladly arrived at their safe harbor” <bibl>(<title rend="italic">The Whole Duty of Mourning and the Great Concern of Preparing Ourselves for Death</title> [London, 1695], p. 154)</bibl>. Pulter knows this logic, repeats it often in her poetry, and struggles to reconcile it with her attachment to lost persons and, here, to her own flesh and the memory of its lost youth. If it is the soul that is imprisoned in the body, then it is particularly interesting that the speaker has to work to detach the soul from the body, interrogating the soul as to why it loves and clings to its prison. In the poem, “I” and “me” (lines 23, 26) reside with the decaying flesh and not the soul.</note></seg>?</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="3">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">See’st thou these eyes (’tis thou that givest them Sight</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">Seest thou these eyes? (’Tis thou that gives them sight,</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">See’st thou these eyes? ’Tis thou that givest them sight,</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="4">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Or they would quickly Set in endles Night)</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">Or they would quickly set in endless night.)</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">Or they would quickly set in endless night.</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="5">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">What Splendent Spritelynes in youth they had</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">What <seg>splendent<note type="gloss">brightly shining</note></seg> sprightliness in youth they had!</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">What <seg>splendent<note type="gloss">shining</note></seg> sprightliness in youth they had!</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="6">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Now weeping makes them Dim and Dull &amp; Sad</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">Now weeping makes them dim and dull and sad.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">Now weeping makes them dim, and dull, and sad.</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="7">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">These Locks did Curle and were a Golden brown</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">These locks did curl, and were a golden brown;</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">These locks did curl and were a golden brown;</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="8">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Now thin and <seg>Lank<note type="physical">possible comma after
                    </note></seg> like Silver Threads hang down</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">Now thin and lank like silver threads hang down.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">Now thin and lank, like silver threads, hang down.</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="9">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">My lovly count’nance had a pleaſing grace</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">My lovely <seg>count’nance<note type="gloss">face</note></seg> had a pleasing grace;</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">My lovely <seg>count’nance<note type="gloss">face, facial expression</note></seg> had a pleasing grace;</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="10">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Now Erra Paters or A Sibbils &ff;ace</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">Now, <seg>Erra Pater’s<note type="critical">This is the assumed name for the author of a popular handbook of prognostication; Francis Beaumont refers to “a face as olde as Erra Pater” in <bibl><title rend="italic">The scornful ladie</title> (London, 1616), sig. G4v.</bibl></note></seg> or a <seg>sibyl’s<note type="gloss">classical prophetess</note></seg> face.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">Now <seg>Erra Pater’s<note type="critical">Popular books of prognostication and almanacs were attributed to Erra Pater, “a Jew, born in Jewry,” throughout the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries. These texts were so ubiquitous and popular that the name came to describe the books themselves; an almanac might be called an “erra pater” or, since these predictions were considered unreliable or erring, an “errans pater.” Erra Pater was often described as old, as in the broadside “Erra Pater’s Prophesy or Frost Fair 1683,” or depicted with a lined face (see <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="#ctxs">Erra Pater and the Sibyl</ref>). In Beaumont and Fletcher’s popular play <title rend="italic">The Scornful Lady</title> (1616), Elder Loveless describes the aged servant, Abigail, as “Thou with a face as old as Erra Pater, such a prognosticating nose: thou thing that ten years since has left to be a woman, outworn the expectation of a bawd, and thy dry bones can reach at nothing now, but gords or ninepins [dice]” (4.1).</note></seg> or a <seg>sibyl’s <note type="critical">Sibyls were female prophets in ancient Greece and Rome. Although they were mortals, they were often depicted as preternaturally old. According to Ovid’s <title rend="italic">Metamorphoses</title>, Phoebus, trying to gain the Cumaean sibyl’s virginity, offered her extended life, but when she refused him, he did not include lasting youth in the bargain. When the sibyl encounters Aeneas in Ovid’s tale, she is 700 years old and decrepit; she imagines that her body will gradually wither until nothing is left but her prophetic voice (see <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="#ctxs">Erra Pater and the Sibyl</ref>). Pulter chooses prophets as her images of the aged face, perhaps linking age and wisdom, but she also chooses prophets whose ability to foresee the future many of her contemporaries held in doubt.</note></seg> face.</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="11">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">My lips were Cherryes Roſey <seg>were<note type="physical">possible erasure of former end of word, replaced with “re”</note></seg> my Cheeks</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">My lips were cherries, rosy were my cheeks;</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">My lips were cherries, rosy were my cheeks,</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="12">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">But thoſe that now for Blood or Bevty Seek</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">But those that now for blood or beauty seek</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">But <seg>those that now for blood or beauty seek<note type="critical">That is, those who seek color in her lips and cheeks. In lines 15 and 18, the speaker emphasizes that she associates her youthful beauty with the whiteness of her skin.</note></seg></rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="13">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Will find them Spoyled by time <seg>and<note type="physical">“d”
                        appears crowded between surrounding words</note></seg> adverſs fate</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">Will find them spoiled by Time and adverse Fate,</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">Will find them spoiled by time and adverse fate,</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="14">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Whoſe cruelty doth give to all A date</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">Whose cruelty doth give to all a <seg>date<note type="gloss">bring to an end</note></seg>.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">Whose cruelty doth give to all a <seg>date<note type="gloss">limit</note></seg>.</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="15">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">My Skin was once as white as new fallen Snow</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">My skin was once as white as new fallen snow;</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">My skin was once as white as new-fallen snow,</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="16">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Through Azure veins vimillion Blood did flow</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">Through <seg>azure<note type="gloss">blue</note></seg> veins <seg>vermillion<note type="gloss">bright red</note></seg> blood did flow.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">Through <seg>azure<note type="gloss">bright blue</note></seg> veins, <seg>vermilion<note type="gloss">scarlet</note></seg> blood did flow.</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="17">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Then were my Swelling <seg>Breasts<note type="physical">first “s”
                        written over other letter</note></seg> y<hi rend="superscript">e
                        </hi> Bed of Love</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">Then were my swelling breasts the bed of love,</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>Then were my swelling breasts the bed of love<note type="critical">A skeletal timeline of Pulter’s life would focus on what we might call reproductive events: she married at age 13 and gave birth to at least 15 children between the ages of 19 and 48 (the last two years before this poem). Yet this striking evocation of her body as a source of pleasure is unusual in the poetry. The description of her breasts does not specify for whom they served as the bed of love. Pulter may refer to a husband or lover; Pulter’s husband Arthur is almost invisible in these poems, especially compared to her children. She might also remember nursing her children here.</note></seg>,</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="18">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">As Smoth as Soft as White as Swan or Dove</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">As smooth, as soft, as white as swan or dove;</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">As smooth, as soft, as white, as swan or dove.</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="19">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">As Lillyes &ff;adeing Shrink to Shun the Light</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">As lilies fading shrink to shun the light,</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">As lilies fading shrink to shun the light,</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="20">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">So Are my withred Brests Shut out of Sight</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">So are my withered breasts shut out of sight;</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">So are my withered breasts shut out of sight;</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="21">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Times tiranny they &ff;eel and Sorrows Spite</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">Time’s tyranny they feel, and Sorrow’s spite.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">Time’s tyranny they feel and sorrow’s spite.</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <app>
              <rdg wit="#ft"><pb ed="#ft" facs="f7610_151" n="74r"/></rdg>
              <rdg wit="#ee"><pb ed="#ee" facs="f7610_151"/></rdg>
              <rdg wit="#ae"><pb ed="#ae" facs="f7610_151"/></rdg>
            </app>
          <l n="22">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">My Sportive wit and Mirth is now laid by</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">My <seg>sportive<note type="gloss">light, lively</note></seg> wit and mirth is now laid by;</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">My <seg>sportive<note type="gloss">playful</note></seg> wit and mirth is now laid by;</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="23">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">None is more mopeing now and dul then I</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">None is more moping now, and dull, than I.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">None is more moping now, and dull, than I.</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="24">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">My joyes to Heaven with my Dear Pen did &ff;ly</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">My joys to heaven with my dear <seg>Pen<note type="critical">Pulter’s daughter, Penelope, died in 1655, age 22 (Eardley).</note></seg> did fly.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">My joys to heaven with my dear <seg>Pen<note type="critical">Pulter’s daughter Penelope died in 1655 at age 22 (Eardley). Pulter may have suffered her own illness and written this poem that same year. One might hear the homonym between the nickname “Pen” and the pen as a writing implement, linking Pulter’s procreative and creative activities.</note></seg> did fly.</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="25">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Then why my soul? art thou Soe fond to Stay</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">Then why, my soul, art thou so fond to stay,</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">Then why, my soul, art thou so fond to stay,</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="26">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Seeing all thats Lovly in mee doth decay</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">Seeing all that’s lovely in me doth decay?</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">Seeing all that’s lovely in me doth decay?</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="27">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">&ff;or Shame pack up thy vertues and a way.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">For shame! Pack up thy virtues, and away.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">For shame pack up thy virtues and away.</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <app>
              <rdg type="milestone" wit="#ft">
                   <milestone unit="poem" rend="curled line with cross atop at right"/>
                   </rdg>
            </app>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
