<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../src/vmachine.xsl"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
  schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI [

  <!ENTITY ff "<!-- ff ligature, representing capital modern day capital F, here represented as 'ff' -->ff">

  ]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mads.pp.33">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The Welcome [2]</title>
        <title type="sub">Poem #33</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Created by</resp>
          <persName>Leah Knight</persName>
          <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoded by</resp>
          <persName>Katherine Poland</persName>
          <persName>Matthew Taylor</persName>
          <persName>Betsy Chou</persName>
          <persName>Emily Andrey</persName>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>IT-project consultation by</resp>
          <persName>Josh Honn</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
          <orgName>Brock University</orgName>
          <orgName>University of Leeds</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <principal>
          <persName/>
        </principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="1"/>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription, transformations, and notes</resp>
          <persName>Leah Knight</persName>
          <orgName>Brock University</orgName>
          <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
        </respStmt>
      </editionStmt>
      <extent/>
      <publicationStmt>
        <ab/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listBibl>
          <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
              <repository>See witness list.</repository>
            </msIdentifier>
          </msDesc>
        </listBibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p/>
      </projectDesc>
      <p>Transcriptions are encoded in TEI(P5)-conformant XML.</p>
      <samplingDecl>
        <p/>
      </samplingDecl>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction>
          <p>Apparent errors are preserved and editorial corrections provided using SIC and CORR tags, but only where the editor conjectures that the original scribe or compositor would have recognized the instance as an error. For example, what according to modern usage is incorrect subject/verb agreement might have been deemed acceptable to a seventeenth-century scribe or compositor. All such instances are treated instead using the ORIG and REG tags. (See below.)</p>
          <p>Corrections and annotations made within the scope of the original document either by its original authors, owners, and/or transcribers are noted using ADD tags. These annotations and may be futher explained within NOTE tags, as added by the editors of this digital edition, for display within the apparatus.</p>
        </correction>
        <normalization>
          <p>Original spellings, abbreviations, and orthography are preserved. Where in the manuscripts a character's status as majuscule or miniscule is ambiguous, the editor has silently chosen one or the other based on context and judgment (i.e., does not register such ambiguity in either the markup or the notes).</p>
        </normalization>
        <quotation>
          <p>Original quotation marks, if any, are preserved.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation>
          <p>Original hyphenation is preserved.</p>
        </hyphenation>
      </editorialDecl>
      <charDecl>
        <!-- Ligature combinations for which there are currently no corresponding Unicode codepoints. -->
        <glyph xml:id="ffllig">
          <glyphName>Handwritten 'ff' ligature, used in handwriting to represent modern F</glyphName>
        </glyph>
      </charDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="DDC22">
          <bibl>
            <title>Dewey Decimal Classification</title>
            <edition/>
            <publisher/>
            <pubPlace/>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-GB">British English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <!-- dewey decimal system class code 821: English Poetry -->
        <classCode scheme="DDC22">821</classCode>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
    <!-- List of all images associated with this document -->
    <graphic url="./document_images/7610_106.jpg" xml:id="f7610_106"/>
  </facsimile>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="ft">Transcription of manuscript: By <persName xml:id="lknight">Leah Knight</persName> and <persName xml:id="wwall">Wendy Wall</persName>.</witness>
          <witness xml:id="ee">Elemental edition: By <persName>Leah Knight</persName> and <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>.</witness>
          <witness xml:id="ae">Amplified edition: By <persName>Andrea Crow</persName>.</witness>
        </listWit>
      </div>
    </front>

    <body>

      <app>
        <rdg wit="#ft">
          <pb ed="#ft" facs="#f7610_106" n="51v"/>
        </rdg>
        <rdg wit="#ee">
          <pb ed="#ee" facs="#f7610_106"/>
        </rdg>
        <rdg wit="#ae">
          <pb ed="#ae" facs="#f7610_106"/>
        </rdg>
      </app>

      <head>
        <app type="title">
          <rdg wit="#ft"><fw facs="#f7610_069" type="pageNum" place="margin-topright">PG#</fw>The Welcome [2]</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">The Welcome [2]</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>The Welcome [2]<note type="critical">The poem’s title invokes the popular early modern genre of hospitality poetry, such as the country house poem or the invitation poem. As is often the case in Pulter’s poetry, she plays with this genre by substituting a reflection on her isolation in place of the community typically at the center of these poems. On Pulter’s engagement with the pose of isolation popular in Royalist poetry during the Interregnum, as well as the political networks in which her position as the lady of a country estate likely would have involved her, see Karen Britland, “Conspiring with ‘friends’: Hester Pulter’s Poetry and the Stanley Family at Cumberlow Green,” <title rend="italic">The Review of English Studies</title> 609, no. 292 (November 2018): 832-54.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
        <app type="editorialnote">
          <rdg wit="#ft">
            <note type="editorialnote">In these transcriptions we preserve as many details of the original material, textual, and graphic properties of Hester Pulter’s manuscript verse as we have found practical. Whenever possible, for instance, original spelling, punctuation, capitalization, lineation, insertions, deletions, alterations, spacing between words and lines, and indentation are all maintained; abbreviations and brevigraphs are not expanded; and superscript and subscript representations are retained. <ref target="http://pulterproject.northwestern.edu/about-project-conventions.html#top" type="new-window-url">See full conventions for the transcriptions here.</ref></note>
          </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">
            <note type="editorialnote">The aim of the elemental edition is to make the poems accessible to the largest variety of readers, which involves modernizing spelling and punctuation as well as adding basic glosses. Spelling and punctuation reflect current standard American usage; punctuation highlights syntax which might otherwise be obscure. Outmoded but still familiar word forms (“thou,” “‘tis,” “hold’st”) are not modernized, and we do not modernize grammar when the sense remains legible. After a brief headnote aimed at offering a “way in” to the poem’s unique qualities and connections with other verse by Pulter or her contemporaries, the edition features a minimum of notes and interpretative framing to allow more immediate engagement with the poem. Glosses clarify synonyms or showcase various possible meanings in Pulter’s time. Other notes identify named people and places or clarify obscure material. We rely (without citation) primarily on the Oxford English Dictionary (OED), the Oxford Reference database, and the King James Version (KJV) of the Bible. When we rely on Alice Eardley’s edition of Pulter’s work, we cite her text generally (“Eardley”); other sources are cited in full. The result is an edition we consider a springboard for further work on Pulter’s poetry. <ref target="http://pulterproject.northwestern.edu/about-project-conventions.html#elemental-edition" type="new-window-url">See full conventions for this edition here.</ref></note></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">
            <note type="editorialnote">My editions aim to make Pulter’s poetry accessible in two ways. First, I facilitate basic legibility through modernizing spelling and punctuation according to standard American usage and through glossing unfamiliar words, points of intertexuality, and relevant historical contexts. Second, I want to help readers perceive Pulter’s nuanced approach to form and image, both within individual poems and in the extended patterns and ideas that take shape over the course of the manuscript. With this in mind, I have incorporated interpretive readings of the poems into my notes to provide insight into how Pulter’s poetics work and to spur readers to participate in the value-adding work of bringing Pulter’s writing the attentive level of interpretation it deserves.</note>
          </rdg>
        </app>
        <app type="headnote">
          <rdg wit="#ee">
            <note type="headnote">Death is hailed as an old friend in this, the second of two poems so named. Both warmly address this usually-feared figure in casual diction which suggests the speaker’s utter comfort with her own mortality. An easy, homey analogy of dying with going to bed, however, soon collides with the more complex cosmology that is typical of much of Pulter’s verse. The result lets the speaker’s sense of humor (which depicts her posthumously taking a nap in oblivion) join with a serious vision of a more lasting, longed-for transformation of her being.</note>
          </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">
            <note type="headnote">The apparent simplicity of the short couplets and images of childhood that make up this brief poem are in tension with a persistent metrical irregularity that suggests resistant discomfort underlying the speaker’s overt claims to view death as a welcome, temporary rest.<seg>1<note type="critical">On Pulter desiring death, see Frances E. Dolan, <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="/poems/ae/the-desire/#desiring-death">Desiring Death</ref> (Curation for <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="18">The Desire</ref>) and <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="/poems/ae/to-aurora-3/#more-ruminations-on-death-and-resurrection">More Ruminations on Death and Resurrection</ref> (Curation for <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="34">To Aurora [3]</ref>), Elizabeth Scott-Baumann, <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="/poems/ae/the-hope/#dear-death">Dear Death</ref> (Curation for <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="65">The Hope</ref>), and Helen Smith, <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="/poems/ae/made-when-i-was-sick-1647/#the-good-death">The Good Death</ref> (Curation for <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="31">Made When I Was Sick, 1647</ref>) in <title rend="italic">The Pulter Project: Poet in the Making</title>, edited by Leah Knight and Wendy Wall (2018).</note></seg> Pulter’s rhyme scheme and inventive use of rhetorical devices realizes in poetic form how death can at once be a definitive end (echoed in her consistently endstopped couplets) and a transformation that brings something new into being out of earlier material (echoed in the inventive forms of repetition in her use of homoioteleuton [the repetition of word endings]  and antanaclasis [repeating a word but changing its meaning]). Like the earlier poem, <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="19">The Welcome [1]</ref>, the poem approaches Pulter’s constant theme of her impending mortality from the persona of a hospitable hostess, a role not unlike that which Pulter would have played in her estate at Broadfield. The mood of this poem shifts rapidly in a short space, from domestic scenes of going to bed, to elemental dissolution in the alchemical urn, and finally to the apocalypse.</note>
          </rdg>
        </app>
      </head>

      <l n="1">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Death come and welcome, thour’t my Ancient friend,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Death, come, and welcome; thou art my ancient friend;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>Death, come<note type="critical">The spondee (a metrical foot consisting of two stressed syllables) that opens this poem is one of a handful of pointed metrical irregularities in what is otherwise fairly regular iambic pentameter. In this case, Pulter’s spondee both sonically underscores the somberness of her invocation of death, and amplifies the surprising shift in the remainder of the line from a funereal mood to one of sociability and hospitality.</note></seg>, <seg>and welcome<note type="critical">Pulter’s use here of homoioteleuton (i.e. the repetition of word endings) is the first of a number of rhetorical devices she deploys in this poem that play with forms of repetition. See also the notes on the end rhymes in lines 5-6 and 7-8. Taken together, these devices perform a transformation of the words of the poem that is analogous to death as envisioned by Pulter: not as a rupture but as a remaking of one’s substance into a new form.</note></seg>; thou art my ancient friend,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="2">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Of all my Suffrings, thou <seg>wilt<note type="physical">“lt” appears written over earlier letters, possibly “th”</note></seg> make an end.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Of all my suff’rings, thou wilt make an end.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Of all my suff’rings, thou wilt make an <seg>end<note type="critical"> Each of the five couplets that make up this poem are endstopped, a formal device that mimics the tension Pulter explores between the power of death to, on the one hand, “make an end” in the dissolution of the body into “dust” and “first principles,” and, on the other hand, the continuation of the soul’s story after death, in the “everlasting Story” in which the soul participates in the afterlife.</note></seg>.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="3">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Young Children crie, or grumble at the best,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Young children cry, or grumble at the best,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Young children cry, or grumble at the best,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="4">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">To goe to Bed I know it is my Rest.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">To go to bed; I know it is my rest.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">To go to bed; I know it is my rest.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="5">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Therefore as cheerfully Il’e lay mee Down</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Therefore as cheerfully I’ll lay me down</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>Therefore as cheerfully<note type="critical">The two dactyls (a metrical foot consisting of one stressed syllable followed by two unstressed syllables) that begin this line connote a tension working against the easy acceptance of death the speaker articulates. At the same time, the irregular meter here may convey the singsong “cheerful” tone the line describes. These two implications together suggest that this attempt to evoke cheer in the face of death is uncomfortable and artificial.</note></seg> I’ll lay me down</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="6">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">In Dust, as in the daintiest Bed of Down.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">In <seg>dust<note type="gloss">the disintegrated particles of the physical body; also its primal elements; see Genesis 2:7: “And the Lord God formed man [of] the dust of the ground, and breathed into his nostrils the breath of life; and man became a living soul.”</note></seg> as in the <seg>daintiest<note type="critical">To preserve the meter, the word must be pronounced in two syllables (i.e., “daint” and “yest”).</note></seg> bed of down,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">In dust as in the daintiest bed of <seg>down<note type="critical">Pulter’s use of antanaclasis—the repetition of a pair of homographs in two different senses, which is emphasized in the manuscript by the capitalization of both instances of the word “down”—is another example of her engagement in this poem with various forms of repetition as a means of meditating on how death at once transforms and preserves. In this case, the transformation she poetically enacts is not to the word as it is written, as in the first line, but rather to its meaning. In comparing laying herself “down” to die to a soft bed of “down,” Pulter further develops the poem’s central conceit of reframing death as gentle, familiar, and welcome.</note></seg>.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="7">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Where I to my first Principles must turn,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Where I to my <seg>first principles<note type="gloss">original, basic elements; formative constituent parts</note></seg> must turn,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Where I to my <seg>first principles<note type="gloss">The fundamental particles that make up the speaker’s body. The dissolution of the body into its originary elements is one of Pulter’s most common images. See <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="1">The Eclipse</ref>, <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="6">Universal Dissolution</ref>, <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="41">The Invocation of the Elements</ref>, et al.</note></seg> must turn,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="8">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">And take a nap in Black Oblivions Urn.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">And take a nap in black oblivion’s urn</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">And <seg>take a nap in black oblivion’s urn<note type="gloss">Cf. <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="16">Universal Dissolution</ref>: “So man to his first principles must turn / And take a nap in black Oblivion’s urn” (ln. 15-16). The image, recurrent in Pulter’s poetry, is of the alchemist’s urn in which substances are reduced to their elemental forms and transformed into new substances. See also <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="">The Revolution</ref>, <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="">The Circle [1]</ref>, <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="">The Circle [2]</ref>, <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="">The Circle [3]</ref>, and <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="">The Circle [4]</ref>, et al.</note></seg>.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="9">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Untill the Sun of Life ariſe in Glory,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Until the <seg>sun of life<note type="gloss">an allusion, built into the pun, with the second coming of Christ as the <hi rend="italic">son</hi> of God</note></seg> arise in glory—</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Until <seg>the sun of life<note type="critical">Pulter’s phrase most explicitly refers to Christ’s return. However, given Pulter’s repeated comparison of Charles I to a sun god, the idea of the restoration of the English monarchy is also evoked here.</note></seg> arise in glory—</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="10">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">And then begins my everlasting Story.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">And then begins my everlasting <seg>story<note type="gloss">life</note></seg>.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">And then begins my everlasting <seg>story<note type="critical">Pulter frequently rhymes “glory” with “story.” However, the placement of this feminine rhyme (a polysyllabic rhyme in which the final syllable is unstressed) at the end of this poem calls attention to its irregularity, which metrically mimics the speaker’s urgent pushing forward to this desired future.</note></seg>.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
