<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../src/vmachine.xsl"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI [

<!ENTITY ff "<!-- ff ligature, representing capital modern day capital F, here represented as 'ff' -->ff">

]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mads.pp.13">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Upon the Imprisonment of His Sacred Majesty</title>
                <title type="sub">Poem 13</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Created by</resp>
                    <persName>Leah Knight</persName>
                    <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoded by</resp>
                    <persName>Matthew Taylor</persName>
                    <persName>Betsy Chou</persName>
                    <persName>Katherine E. Poland</persName>
                    <persName>Emily Andrey</persName>
                    <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Website designed by</resp>
                    <persName>Sergei Kalugin</persName>
                    <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>IT-project consultation by</resp>
                    <persName>Josh Honn</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>
                    <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
                    <orgName>Brock University</orgName>
                    <orgName>University of Leeds</orgName>
                </sponsor>
                <principal>
                    <persName/>
                </principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1"/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription, transformations, and notes</resp>
                    <persName>Leah Knight</persName>
                    <orgName>Brock University</orgName>
                    <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>
                    <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent/>
            <publicationStmt>
                <ab/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl>
                    <msDesc>
                        <msIdentifier>
                            <repository>See witness list.</repository>
                        </msIdentifier>
                    </msDesc>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <p>Transcriptions are encoded in TEI(P5)-conformant XML.</p>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p>Apparent errors are preserved and editorial corrections provided using SIC
                        and CORR tags, but only where the editor conjectures that the original
                        scribe or compositor would have recognized the instance as an error. For
                        example, what according to modern usage is incorrect subject/verb agreement
                        might have been deemed acceptable to a seventeenth-century scribe or
                        compositor. All such instances are treated instead using the ORIG and REG
                        tags. (See below.) </p>
                    <p>Corrections and annotations made within the scope of the original document
                        either by its original authors, owners, and/or transcribers are noted using
                        ADD tags. These annotations and may be further explained within NOTE tags, as
                        added by the editors of this digital edition, for display within the
                        apparatus.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p>Original spellings, abbreviations, and orthography are preserved. Where in
                        the manuscripts a character’s status as majuscule or minuscule is ambiguous,
                        the editor has silently chosen one or the other based on context and
                        judgment (i.e., does not register such ambiguity in either the markup or the
                        notes).</p>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p>Original quotation marks, if any, are preserved.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p>Original hyphenation is preserved.</p>
                </hyphenation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <charDecl>
                <!-- Ligature combinations for which there are currently no corresponding Unicode codepoints. -->
                <glyph xml:id="ffllig">
                    <glyphName>Handwritten 'ff' ligature, used in handwriting to represent modern
                        F</glyphName>
                </glyph>
            </charDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="DDC22">
                    <bibl>
                        <title>Dewey Decimal Classification</title>
                        <edition/>
                        <publisher/>
                        <pubPlace/>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en-GB">British English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <!-- dewey decimal system class code 821: English Poetry -->
                <classCode scheme="DDC22">821</classCode>
                <keywords>
                    <term>royalism</term>
                    <term>lamentation</term>
                    <term>revenge</term>
                    <term>civil war</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic url="./document_images/7610_069.jpg" xml:id="f7610_069"/>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div>
                <listWit>
                    <witness xml:id="ft">Transcription of manuscript: By <persName xml:id="lknight">Leah Knight</persName> and <persName xml:id="wwall">Wendy Wall</persName>.</witness>
                    <witness xml:id="ee">Elemental Edition: By <persName>Leah Knight</persName> and <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>.</witness>
                    <witness xml:id="ae">Amplified Edition: By <persName>Ruth Connolly</persName>.</witness>
                </listWit>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <app>
                <rdg wit="#ft"><pb ed="#ft" facs="#f7610_069" n="33r"/></rdg>
                <rdg wit="#ee"><pb ed="#ee" facs="#f7610_069"/></rdg>
                <rdg wit="#ae"><pb ed="#ae" facs="#f7610_069"/></rdg>
            </app>
            <head>
                <app type="title">
                    <rdg wit="#ft">
                        <fw facs="#f7610_069" type="pageNum" place="margin-topright"
                            >61</fw><title>Upon the impriſonment of his Sacred Majestie that
                            unparalel’d Prince King Charles the <w lemma="first"
                            >&ff;irst</w>.</title>
                    </rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">Upon the Imprisonment of his Sacred Majesty, That Unparalleled
                        Prince, King <seg>Charles the First<note type="critical">Charles was King of England (1625–1649) during the civil war,
                            and was jailed, in 1647, by the opposition Parliament.</note></seg>
                    </rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">Upon the <seg>Imprisonment<note type="gloss">See Headnote. After his surrender to the Scots in April 1646, Charles was more or less continually in the custody of either the Scottish Army or the English Parliament until his execution in 1649.</note></seg> of his <seg>Sacred Majesty<note type="gloss">Loyalist portrayals of Charles portrayed the King in quasi-divine terms particularly from 1646 onwards; at the Restoration in 1660 Parliament declared him a martyr and added him to the calendar of Anglican saints.</note></seg> That Unparalleled Prince King <seg>Charles the First<note type="critical">Distinguishing Charles from his son, Charles II. This suggests the title is post-Restoration though to Royalists such as Pulter, Charles II became King in 1649.</note></seg>
                    </rdg>
                </app>
                <app type="editorialnote">
                    <rdg wit="#ft"><note type="editorialnote">In these transcriptions we preserve as many details of
                        the original material, textual, and graphic properties of Hester Pulter’s manuscript verse
                        as we have found practical. Whenever possible, for instance, original spelling, punctuation,
                        capitalization, lineation, insertions, deletions, alterations, spacing between words and lines,
                        and indentation are all maintained; abbreviations and brevigraphs are not expanded; and
                        superscript and subscript representations are retained.
                        <ref target="http://pulterproject.northwestern.edu/about-project-conventions.html#top" type="new-window-url">See full
                            conventions for the transcriptions here.</ref></note></rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee"><note type="editorialnote">
                        The aim of the Elemental Edition to make the poems accessible to the largest variety of readers,
                        which involves modernizing spelling and punctuation as well as adding basic glosses. Spelling and
                        punctuation reflect current standard American usage; punctuation highlights syntax which might
                        otherwise be obscure. Outmoded but still familiar word forms (“thou,” “‘tis,” “hold’st”) are not
                        modernized, and we do not modernize grammar when the sense remains legible. After a brief headnote
                        aimed at offering a “way in” to the poem’s unique qualities and connections with other verse by
                        Pulter or her contemporaries, the edition features a minimum of notes and interpretative framing to
                        allow more immediate engagement with the poem. Glosses clarify synonyms or showcase various
                        possible meanings in Pulter’s time. Other notes identify named people and places or clarify obscure
                        material. We rely (without citation) primarily on the Oxford English Dictionary (OED), the Oxford
                        Reference database, and the King James Version (KJV) of the Bible. When we rely on Alice Eardley’s
                        edition of Pulter’s work, we cite her text generally (“Eardley”); other sources are cited in full. The
                        result is an edition we consider a springboard for further work on Pulter’s poetry.
                        <ref target="http://pulterproject.northwestern.edu/about-project-conventions.html#elemental-edition" type="new-window-url">See full conventions
                            for this edition here.</ref></note>
                    </rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae"><note type="editorialnote">
                        The spelling and capitalisation of the original manuscript has been modernised. I have retained the original full stop at the conclusion of the final line and added no other punctuation in order to emphasise the poem’s use of enjambment as an effect. The original’s contractions of ‘-ed’ have been retained.
                    </note>
                    </rdg>
                </app>
                <app type="headnote">
                    <rdg wit="#ee">
                        <note type="headnote">This bloodthirsty portrayal of the war-time captivity of Charles I (apparently written before his assassination) faintly echoes the elegiac refrain of “Tell me no more” from Poem 11, here in the form of a repeated injunction to an unspecified addressee to “ask … no more” why the speaker laments: which should, she implies, be perfectly obvious. The context for these similar refrains could hardly differ more: instead of grieving her daughter’s untimely passing (as in <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="11">Tell Me No More [On the Same]</ref>), the speaker invokes the goddess of vengeance to bring hellish torment upon the king’s and kingdom’s captors and usurpers (who are portrayed as hypocritical, grasping, impious, and corrupt). The speaker also prays—apparently still with Nemesis as her deity of choice—for the king’s “Job-like” resurrection, an apt model for a king the speaker sees as “Sacred.” The meter is unusual for Pulter, with triplets of iambic pentameter replacing her more usual couplets, as though the enormity of the subject calls out for a form that exceeds the norm. Pulter only uses the same meter in <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="16">The Revolution</ref> and <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="55">Must I thus ever interdicted be</ref>, while Poem 66 offers a variation.</note>
                    </rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">
                        <note type="headnote">
                            <p>This political lyric responds to a crisis in Royalist representations of Charles I. In particular, it participates in the collective reshaping of the king’s image made necessary by military failure. In late April 1646 Charles I had slipped quietly, and in disguise, out of his wartime capital of Oxford and surrendered his person to the Scottish army at Southwell, near Newark, after a succession of defeats had ended the Royalist war effort. This act of personal surrender, greeted with confusion and puzzlement by Royalists, ended the first phase of the English Civil War. The English parliament and their former Scottish allies rapidly moved into negotiation with Charles, seeking his agreement for a new settlement of Church and State. Charles’ attempts to play off internal disagreements and rival proposals from either side foundered and in December 1646, exasperated by Charles’ cavilling, the Scots struck a deal with the English Parliament. The agreement saw the Scottish army withdraw from England and hand over Charles in return for payment of their pay arrears. This agreement, wrote Samuel Gardiner, the nineteenth-century historian of the Civil Wars, “was the transaction Royalist partisans were soon to qualify as the dispatch of a Judas who sold his Lord for money” (III.188). Even opponents were shocked: John Milton, in <hi rend="italic">Eikonoklastes</hi> (1649), commented that “the Scots in England should sell thir King […] and for a price so much above that, which the covetousness of Judas was contented with to sell <hi rend="it">our Saviour</hi>, is so foule an infamy and dishonour cast upon them, as befitts none to vindicate but themselves” (VI.394). This depiction of the agreement proved vital when these partisans embarked on their controversial but highly successful transformation of the defeated monarch into a figure of Christ-like suffering.</p>
                            <p>Pulter’s poem draws on this comparison and other significant tropes to participate in this Royalist effort to rehabilitate Charles. Pulter’s poem alludes directly to the monarch having been “bought and sold” and if this is a topical reference, this poem may date to early 1647 (see note on date below). At this point, Charles had accepted the English Parliament’s invitation to journey south towards London, and was being met, according to one newsbook, with popular welcome, the crowds anticipating a political reconciliation between King and Parliament and an end to the burdens of war. Pulter’s poem does not participate in this mood of optimism. Rather, she composes a furious denunciation of the perfidy of both the Scots and the English, and frames the king in sacral and suffering terms as a “Job-like saint” (line 13).</p>
                            <p>Pulter’s confident framing of the monarch’s morally unimpeachable position offers a counterpoint to the more uncertain accounts by Royalist poets such as John Cleveland and Henry Vaughan, both of whom struggled to account for the King’s decision to surrender to the bitterly loathed Scots (see Loxley, <title rend="italic">Royalism and Poetry</title>, pp. 138–147; Wilcher, <title rend="italic">Writing of English Royalism</title>, pp. 246–249; Potter, <title rend="italic">Secret Rites</title>, pp. 62–64). It may well be that Pulter also wrote poems in this vein and that she had copied out only those poems that sustained her manuscript’s carefully crafted presentation of tenacious and outraged loyalism.  The tone of Pulter’s poem is markedly different from these poems and its affective force is channelled through the introduction of Nemesis in line 4. This allusion is carefully chosen. Broadly identified as the goddess of vengeance, Nemesis specifically symbolises indignation at wrong-doers who rejoice in their actions and her role is to punish their outrageous presumption. (See the Curation <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="#ctxs">Nemesis</ref> for this poem.) Nemesis exercises her vengeance when wrongdoers are at the height of their apparent success, as indeed Parliament appeared to be, having secured the person of the king and seemingly concluded the war in victory.</p>
                            <p>Contemporary characterisations of Nemesis acknowledged that whilst her actions are inevitable, the timing of them is uncertain. Pulter’s poem manages the waiting period by resorting to a patient endurance of wrongdoing in imitation, the poem implies, of Charles himself. Her allusion to Job is as carefully selected as Nemesis. The Book of Job, an Old Testament account of a faithful but afflicted servant of God, articulates its protagonist’s confusion, suffering, and uncertainty. The analogy with Job, oppressed but ultimately assured in his faith and innocence, enabled Pulter and other loyalist writers to fashion a portrait of Charles that elided any complex questions of the king’s political failings. Pulter’s selections of Nemesis and Job frame Charles’ opponents unambiguously as the ungodly hypocrites who afflict God’s servants. Together such representations of the monarch and his opponents would culminate in <title rend="italic">Eikon Basilike</title> (1649), a book issued in the king’s name on the day of his execution (see Skerpan Wheeler, 1999). Its portrayal of a monarch martyred for his conscience, a depiction anticipated here by Pulter, proved extraordinarily successful and enduring (but see Potter, 1999).</p>
                            <emph rend="h3">Style</emph>
                            <p>The poem is written in triplets of iambic pentameter and composed as an apostrophe to an unknown interlocutor. Pulter preferred the couplet and wrote in triplets less often. Only five of her lyrics, <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="16">The Revolution</ref>, <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="18">The Desire</ref>, <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="20">Dear God, Turn Not Thy Face Away</ref>, <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="55">Must I Thus Ever Interdicted Be?</ref> and <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="66">Made When My Spirits Were Sunk Very Low</ref> are composed primarily in triplets, though she does occasionally use triplets in her other poems typically to unite a thought or reinforce a conclusion (e.g. <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="51">Made When I Was Not Well</ref> 19–28 or <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="52">The Wish</ref>.3–8). The form is reserved by her for devotional verse so whilst this poem has an explicitly political context, the choice of form strengthens a sense that it is also intended to have a strong devotional dimension.</p>
                            <p>Pulter’s use of triplets in religious poetry is influenced by George Herbert, whose poetry serves as an important formal model for the development of her verse portrayal of Charles as a figure of Christ-like suffering. Pulter is one of a number of Royalist writers who find inspiration in Herbert for this purpose. Two analogues to Pulter’s poem draw directly on “The Sacrifice,” a poem Herbert composed using stanzas of iambic pentameter triplets and a refrain. “The Sacrifice,” written in Christ’s voice, builds on a medieval lyric tradition called the “Complaint of Christ” monologues (Wilcox, p. 94). An anonymous poem entitled “His Majesties Complaint to his Subjects” (see Gottlieb, 1991; Potter, p. 174) uses the same form and is clearly loosely modelled on “The Sacrifice.” The “Complaint,” a copy of which was bought by the London bookseller George Thomason in June 1647, echoes Pulter’s language of a monarch exchanged for money: “I have been truckt for, bought and sold, yet I/Am King (though prisoner) pray tell me why/I am removed now from Holdenby?” (ll. 57–59). “The Sacrifice” also served as a model for another poem in pentameter triplets written in the King’s voice, “Verses said to be composed by His Majestie upon his first imprisonment in the Isle of Wight” which portrays the monarch as a martyr-in-waiting (Gottlieb, p. 218; Potter, 174). Pulter’s poem clearly sits within this Herbert-influenced tradition but she innovates the convention by omitting the refrain, instead creating the required sense of dialogue and complaint through a series of deft borrowings from the Caroline court lyric “Aske me no more.”</p>
                            <p>“Aske me no more,” which Scott Nixon has convincingly argued is probably by William Strode, was printed in Thomas Carew’s <title rend="italic">Poems</title> (1640) but circulated widely in manuscript both as a song and poem. The poem was set to music by William Lawes, one of the King’s personal musicians (see BL Add MS 31432, fol. 11, reproduced in Bickford-Jorgens, ed. <title rend="italic">English Song, 1600–1675</title>, vol. 2). The allusion to this poem in her opening line makes a plangent return to the culture of poetry and music associated with Charles’ pre-war court, repurposing verses closely associated with the monarch and his servants as lines of protest and lament (for Pulter’s poetic networks, see Britland, “Conspiring with ‘Friends’”). Nixon notes that “Aske me no more” “commences with an imperative, responds to a question, constructs an argument, and attempts to persuade its addressee” (Nixon, p. 113). [See also the Curation to Poem 11 entitled <ref type="pp-curation-ref" target="/poems/ae/tell-me-no-more-on-the-same/#poems-in-conversation">Poems in Conversation</ref>]. Pulter gives this structure a judicial emphasis, outlining the charges against the King’s enemies before demanding their punishment. The speaker takes the first three stanzas to outline her grievance, and uses “then” to begin each of the final three stanzas, uniting the second half of the poem in a series of linked imperatives: “Then seeing they … /Let”; “Then let”; “Then aske.” The poem is largely unpunctuated and its use of enjambment mimics a speech delivered without pause and an imagined vengeance descending unchecked from the heavens.</p>
                            <p>Its anger distinguishes this poem from the “sympathetic collectivity” that Sarah Ross finds in her analysis of Pulter’s pastoral complaint poems, where animated and feminised fluvial landscapes replicate and repeat the speaker’s woe (Ross, 183–202 (192)). The choice of Nemesis as the responsive female figure amplifies the poem’s anger, creating the expectation of future satisfaction for indignant loyalists. Yet the whole poem finally turns on instances of knowledge unspoken or unknown: the speaker’s request that their imagined interlocutor ask “no more” for answers; the uncertainty of precisely when the unrighteous will be punished; the perplexity of a monarch afflicted without cause. This crisis facing Royalism is diagnosed by the conclusion’s presentation of the speaker as simultaneously “dissolv’d” and “resolv’d,” unswayed in belief yet devastated by the disastrous turns that the wars had taken.</p>
                            <emph rend="h3">Date</emph>
                            <p>The dating of this poem poses an interesting challenge with some implications for how we interpret Pulter’s war poetry. If it is composed around the time of the events it describes, it anticipates some key Royalist strategies for representing the monarch after his military defeat. However, it may have been originally composed at any point up to this, and it is unknown whether it was revised at any point before its copying into Pulter’s manuscript. Nonetheless, exploring the dating in more detail is important to order to position Pulter’s poem not only part of her own <hi rend="italic">oeuvre</hi> but also within the larger Royalist “war of the pen” which was conducted with renewed force and vigour after the cessation of armed hostilities. Such participation complicates a vision of Pulter as an isolated figure. Positioning this poem in a precise political moment suggests that far from being cut off from events Pulter had access to a constant supply of news and London newsprint and was constructing herself as an active combatant in the Royalist struggle to control the narrative of Charles’s defeat. As the note on context records, Pulter’s depiction of Charles as a proto-martyr was a mainstay of Royalist representations of Charles by 1648 and Pulter’s allusion to Parliament’s payments may be intended to develop the parallel Royalists had begun to draw between the suffering of Christ and the treatment of the King.</p>
                            <p>If Pulter’s references to the King are topical ones the earliest likely date for the composition of this poem is early 1647. The title’s mention of “imprisonment” means it postdates Charles’ surrender to the Scottish army in May 1646, but line 8’s reference to buying and selling the king may narrow the date further. The English Parliament made a financial agreement with their Scottish allies in December 1646, a deal that included the handover of the person of Charles. Payments were made on December 16, 1646 (Gardiner, <title rend="italic">Civil War</title>, III.180), January 30, 1647 and February 3, 1647. <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="4">The Complaint of Thames</ref> specifically mentions Holdenby (or Holmby) House in Northamptonshire, some 55 miles from Pulter’s home in Cottered, where the king arrived, a <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> prisoner of Parliament, on 16 February 1647. The absence of any mention of Holdenby in this poem’s title might suggest a date of composition after December 16 and prior to news of the King’s arrival reaching Cottered. Given how close Holmby was to Cottered, it is likely that Pulter did not have to rely on printed information for news of the King’s arrival but Charles’ agreement to Parliament’s proposals to travel there was in print in London by 26 January (Thomason / E.372[8]). If Pulter was inspired by the King’s anticipated arrival to compose this poem, this makes the earliest likely date of composition to be sometime between mid-January and mid-February 1647, offering the intriguing possibility that the poem performs an act of vengeful lamentation on behalf of a monarch who was now imprisoned close to Pulter’s own home.</p>
                            <emph rend="h4">Primary Sources</emph>
                            <p rend="secondary">Charles I and others. <title rend="italic">Eikon Basilike</title>. Ed. Jim Daems and Holly Faith Nelson. Peterborough, Ont.: Broadview, 2007.; <title rend="italic">The English Poems of George Herbert</title>. Ed. Helen Wilcox. Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 2007.; <title rend="italic">English Song, 1600–1675</title>, vol. 2. Ed. Elise Bickford-Jorgens. New York: Garland, 1986.; <title rend="italic">Lady Hester Pulter: Poems, Emblems, and The Unfortunate Florinda</title>. Ed. Alice Eardley. Toronto: Iter Inc. and the Centre for Reformation and Renaissance Studies. 2014.; <title rend="italic">The Complete Works of John Milton, Vol. VI: Vernacular Writings and Republican Writings</title>. Ed. N. H. Keeble and Nick McDowell. Oxford: Oxford UP, 2013.</p>
                            <emph rend="h4">Secondary Sources</emph>
                            <p rend="secondary">Britland, Karen. “Conspiring with ‘friends’: Hester Pulter’s Poetry and the Stanley Family and Cumberlow Green.” <title rend="italic">Review of English Studies</title>, NS, 69.292 (2018): 832–854.; Cust, Richard. <title rend="italic">Charles I: A Political Life</title>. London: Pearson Longmann, 2007.; Gardiner, Samuel. <title rend="italic">History of the Great Civil War</title>. 4 vols. London: Longmann, 1901–05.; Gottlieb, Sidney. “A Royalist Rewriting of George Herbert: ‘His Majesties Complaint to his Subjects’ (1647).” <title rend="italic">Modern Philology</title> 89.2 (1991), 211–224.; Loxley, James. <title rend="italic">Royalism and Poetry in the English Civil Wars: The Drawn Sword</title>. Basingstoke: Macmillan, 1997.; Nixon, Scott. “‘Aske me no more’ and the Manuscript Verse Miscellany.” <title rend="italic">English Literary Renaissance</title>, 29.1 (1999): 97–103.; Potter, Lois. <title rend="italic">Secret Rites and Secret Writing: Royalist Literature 1641–1660</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1989.; Potter, Lois. “The Royal Martyr in the Restoration: National Grief and National Sin”. The Royal Image: Representations of Charles I. Ed. Thomas N. Corns. Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1999, 240–262.; Ross, Sarah C.E. “Complaint’s Echoes.” <title rend="italic">Early Modern Women’s Complaint: Gender, Form and Politics</title>. Ed. Sarah C.E. Ross and Ros Smith. London: Palgrave Macmillan, 2020, 183–202.; Skerpan Wheeler, Elizabeth. “Eikon Basilike and the Rhetoric of Self-Representation.” <title rend="italic">The Royal Image: Representations of Charles I</title>. Ed. Thomas N. Corns. Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1999, 122–140.; Wilcher, Robert. <title rend="italic">The Writing of Royalism, 1628–1660</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 2001.</p>
                        </note>
                    </rdg>
                </app>
            </head>
            <lg type="stanza" n="1">
                <l n="1">
                    <app>
                        <rdg wit="#ft">Why I Sit Sighing here aſk mee noe more</rdg>
                        <rdg wit="#ee">Why I sit sighing here, ask me no more;</rdg>
                        <rdg wit="#ae">Why I sit sighing here ask me no more</rdg>
                    </app>
                </l>
                <l n="2">
                    <app>
                        <rdg wit="#ft">My Sacred Soveraigns thraldom I deplore</rdg>
                        <rdg wit="#ee">My sacred sovereign’s thralldom I deplore.</rdg>
                        <rdg wit="#ae">My sacred Sovereign’s thraldom I deplore</rdg>
                    </app>
                </l>
                <l n="3">
                    <app>
                        <rdg wit="#ft">Just Nemeſis (whom they pretend to Adore)</rdg>
                        <rdg wit="#ee">Just <seg>Nemesis<note type="gloss">Greek goddess of revenge</note></seg> (whom they pretend to adore),</rdg>
                        <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>Just Nemesis<note type="gloss">See Headnote and the Curation <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="#ctxs">Nemesis</ref> for the association of Nemesis, goddess of vengeance, with justice.</note></seg> <seg>(<note type="gloss">The use of brackets here is part of the poem’s original punctuation. Ben Jonson describes its function as enclosing a complete thought within a not yet completed sentence (Jonson, <title rend="italic">English Grammar</title> (1641), sig. 2L2r).</note></seg>whom <seg>they<note type="gloss">Probably intending both the English and Scottish Parliaments who allied together against Charles.</note></seg> pretend to adore)</rdg>
                    </app>
                </l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza" n="2">
                <l n="4">
                    <app>
                        <rdg wit="#ft">Put on thy Sable blood-beſprinkled Gown</rdg>
                        <rdg wit="#ee">Put on thy sable blood-besprinkled gown,</rdg>
                        <rdg wit="#ae">Put on thy <seg>sable<note type="gloss">because of her association with darkness. Hesiod, in his account of the origins of the gods in <title rend="italic">Theogony</title> claimed that “Deadly Night gave birth to Nemesis (Indignation) too” (211).</note></seg> <seg>blood-besprinkled<note>Nemesis demanded blood; in Heywood’s <title rend="italic">Golden Age</title> (1611), Saturn proclaims of his intended victims ”Have I not their blouds / Already quaft to angry Nemesis?” (sig F1r).</note></seg> gown</rdg>
                    </app>
                </l>
                <l n="5">
                    <app>
                        <rdg wit="#ft">And thy or’eflowing Venge<add place="above">a</add>nce
                            thunder Down</rdg>
                        <rdg wit="#ee">And thy o’erflowing vengeance thunder down</rdg>
                        <rdg wit="#ae">And thy o’reflowing <seg>vengeance<note type="gloss"> See headnote and the Curation <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="#ctxs">Nemesis</ref> for Nemesis as goddess of revenge.</note></seg> thunder down</rdg>
                    </app>
                </l>
                <l n="6">
                    <app>
                        <rdg wit="#ft">On theſe Uſurpers of our Caeſars Crown</rdg>
                        <rdg wit="#ee">On these usurpers of our <seg>Caesar’s<note type="critical">Roman emperor, figurative frequently for Charles I</note></seg> crown.</rdg>
                        <rdg wit="#ae">On these <seg>usurpers<note type="critical">those who “seize or arrogate supreme power or authority without right or just cause” (<title rend="italic">OED</title>, n1, a). From early in the 1640s Charles interpreted many of his opponents’ actions as part of a concerted popular challenge to monarchical authority (Cust, <title rend="italic">Charles I</title>, p. 295), and the belief that opportunism and ambition, rather than principle or honour, drove their enemies became an entrenched Royalist view.</note></seg> of our <seg>Caesar<note type="gloss">a common poetic honorific for a monarch, nodding to the rulers of Ancient Rome, though perhaps there is a glancing allusion to the assassination of Julius Caesar (d. 44 BCE) by those who wished to restore a Roman republic.</note></seg>’s crown</rdg>
                    </app>
                </l>
            </lg>
            <app>
                <rdg type="milestone" wit="ft">
                    <milestone unit="stanza" rend="short-horlines-left-right"/>
                </rdg>
            </app>
            <lg type="stanza" n="3">
                <l n="7">
                    <app>
                        <rdg wit="#ft"><seg>They have his Sacred Perſon now in hold<note type="physical">short horizontal lines above first and last words in line; less space above this line than between other stanzas</note></seg></rdg>
                        <rdg wit="#ee">They have his sacred person now in hold;</rdg>
                        <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>They<note type="critical">Depending on the date of the poem either the Scottish army or the forces under the authority of the English parliament though Pulter’s choice of pronoun deliberately does not distinguish between Charles’ enemies.</note></seg> have his sacred person now <seg>in hold<note type="gloss">See Headnote Date.</note></seg></rdg>
                    </app>
                </l>
                <l n="8">
                    <app>
                        <rdg wit="#ft">They haue their King, and Countrey, bought &amp; Sould</rdg>
                        <rdg wit="#ee">They have their king, and country, bought and sold,</rdg>
                        <rdg wit="#ae">They have their king and country <seg>bought and sold<note type="gloss">for the details of the payments between the English and Scottish Parliaments see Headnote Date.</note></seg></rdg>
                    </app>
                </l>
                <l n="9">
                    <app>
                        <rdg wit="#ft">And hope of Glory, all for Curſed Gold</rdg>
                        <rdg wit="#ee">And hope of glory, all for curséd gold.</rdg>
                        <rdg wit="#ae">And hope of <seg>glory<note type="gloss">eternal life; by their actions they have lost all chance of reaching Heaven. </note></seg>, all for <seg>cursed gold<note type="critical">Eardley, <title rend="italic">Poems</title>, notes the allusion to Judas’ payment for betraying Christ, citing Matthew, 26:14–16. Charles or his co-authors wrote in <title rend="italic">Eikon Basilike</title>: “if I am sold by them, I am only sorry they should do it; and that my price should be so much above my Saviour’s” (p. 166).</note></seg></rdg>
                    </app>
                </l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza" n="4">
                <l n="10">
                    <app>
                        <rdg wit="#ft">Then Seeing they Eternity thus Sleight</rdg>
                        <rdg wit="#ee">Then, seeing they Eternity thus slight,</rdg>
                        <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>Then<note type="critical">Marking a shift in the poem’s argument towards judgement.</note></seg> seeing they <seg>eternity<note type="gloss">the promise to the god-fearing of eternal life in Heaven</note></seg> thus <seg>slight<note type="gloss">“treat with indifferent or disrespect” (<title rend="italic">OED</title>, v., 3a); these usurpers have little regard for the safety of their immortal souls</note></seg></rdg>
                    </app>
                </l>
                <l n="11">
                    <app>
                        <rdg wit="#ft">Let Acherons fierce Ishew them afright</rdg>
                        <rdg wit="#ee">Let <seg>Acheron’s<note type="critical">In Greek myth,
                                    Acheron is a river in Hades; the personification here may suggest
                                    identification with Hades, god of the underworld.</note></seg> fierce issue them affright</rdg>
                        <rdg wit="#ae">Let <seg>Acharon<note type="gloss">In Ancient Greek belief, a body of water on whose banks dead souls gather for transportation to the underworld of Hades, here used by metonymy for all of Hades.</note></seg>’s fierce <seg>issue<note type="gloss">children, offspring; specifically the Eumenides or Erinyes, the three goddesses of vengeance and retribution, known to the Romans as the Furies, who dwelled in the underworld. Ovid, <title rend="italic">Metamorphoses</title>. 4. 451–52 calls them “sisters born of Night, divinities deadly and implacable.”</note></seg> them affright</rdg>
                    </app>
                </l>
                <l n="12">
                    <app>
                        <rdg wit="#ft">Till endles horrour doth their Souls benight</rdg>
                        <rdg wit="#ee">Till endless horror doth their souls benight.</rdg>
                        <rdg wit="#ae">Till <seg>endless horror<note type="gloss">Virgil describes the Furies’ punishment of wrongdoers in Aeneid, 6.557–58: “From it [the Furies’ prison] are heard groans, the sound of the savage lash, the clank of iron and the dragging of chains.”</note></seg> doth their souls <seg>benight<note type="gloss">enclose in darkness (<title rend="italic">OED</title>, v., 2a)</note></seg></rdg>
                    </app>
                </l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza" n="5">
                <l n="13">
                    <app>
                        <rdg wit="#ft">Then let our Job like Saint riſe from <w lemma="the"
                                        ><abbr>y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi></abbr></w>
                            Ground</rdg>
                        <rdg wit="#ee">Then let our <seg>Job-like<note type="critical">Job is a biblical
                                    figure renowned for extraordinary patience in the face of extreme
                                    difficulties.</note></seg> saint rise from the ground,</rdg>
                        <rdg wit="#ae">Then let our <seg>Job-like<note type="gloss">See Headnote and the Curation <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="#ctxs">Job</ref> for Royalist comparisons of Charles to the Biblical figure of Job</note></seg> <seg>saint<note type="gloss">one who is especially holy. The term was heavily contested in this period: “saint” was a term commonly used by more radical and usually non-Anglican Protestant congregations to describe their members. Such congregations tended to ally themselves with Parliament. Its use was also strongly associated with Presbyterianism, the version of Protestantism widely practised in Scotland, and which Charles refused to impose in England. Pulter’s description of Charles as “our saint” reclaims the term and positions the defeated Charles as a proto-martyr for his faith.</note></seg> rise <seg>from the ground<note type="gloss">Alluding to Job’s actions when afflicted with misfortune: “Then Job arose, and rent his mantle, and shaved his head, and fell down upon the ground, and worshipped” (Job, 1.20).</note></seg></rdg>
                    </app>
                </l>
                <l n="14">
                    <app>
                        <rdg wit="#ft"><w lemma="for">&ff;or</w> Piety and Patience Soe
                            renow’nd</rdg>
                        <rdg wit="#ee">For piety and patience so renowned,</rdg>
                        <rdg wit="#ae">For piety and patience so renown’d</rdg>
                    </app>
                </l>
                <l n="15">
                    <app>
                        <rdg wit="#ft">That for the <seg>beſt<note type="physical">“ſ” written over
                                    earlier letter, possibly “t”</note></seg> of kings hee may be
                            Crownd</rdg>
                        <rdg wit="#ee">That for the best of kings he may be crowned.</rdg>
                        <rdg wit="#ae">That for the best of kings he may be crown’d</rdg>
                    </app>
                </l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza" n="6">
                <l n="16">
                    <app>
                        <rdg wit="#ft">Then aſk noe more why I’m in tears diſſolv’d</rdg>
                        <rdg wit="#ee">Then ask no more why I’m in tears dissolved,</rdg>
                        <rdg wit="#ae">Then ask no more why I’m in tears dissolv’d</rdg>
                    </app>
                </l>
                <l n="17">
                    <app>
                        <rdg wit="#ft">Whilst our good king with <add place="below">\</add><seg><add
                                    place="above">ſorrow\</add><note type="physical">written in hand H2</note></seg> is involv’d</rdg>
                        <rdg wit="#ee">Whilst our good king with sorrow is <seg>involved<note
                                    type="gloss">entangled, enveloped</note></seg>:</rdg>
                        <rdg wit="#ae">Whilst our good king with sorrow is <seg>involv’d<note type="gloss">enveloped (<title rend="italic">OED</title>, v., 4)</note></seg></rdg>
                    </app>
                </l>
                <l n="18">
                    <app>
                        <rdg wit="#ft">To pray and weep for him I am <seg>resolvd<note type="physical">after poem ends at bottom of page, reverse is blank</note></seg>.</rdg>
                        <rdg wit="#ee">To pray and weep for him I am <seg>resolved<note
                                    type="critical">convinced; melted; dissolved; brought to a clear
                                    conclusion</note></seg>.</rdg>
                        <rdg wit="#ae">To pray and weep for him I am resolv’d.</rdg>
                    </app>
                </l>
            </lg>

            <app>
                <rdg type="milestone" wit="#ft">
                    <milestone unit="poem" rend="curline-right"/>
                </rdg>
            </app>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
