<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../src/vmachine.xsl"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI [

<!ENTITY ff "<!-- ff ligature, representing capital modern day capital F, here represented as 'ff' -->ff">

]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mads.pp.34">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>To Aurora [3]</title>
                 <title type="sub">Poem #34</title>
                <respStmt><resp>Created by</resp>
                    <persName>Leah Knight</persName>
                    <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoded by</resp>
                    <persName>Katherine Poland</persName>
                    <persName>Matthew Taylor</persName>
			<persName>Betsy Chou</persName>
                        <persName>Emily Andrey</persName>
                    <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
                </respStmt>
		<respStmt>
                     <resp>IT-project consultation by</resp>
                     <persName>Josh Honn</persName>
                 </respStmt>
                <sponsor>
                    <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
                    <orgName>Brock University</orgName>
                    <orgName>University of Leeds</orgName>
                </sponsor>
                <principal>
                    <persName/>
                </principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1"/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription, transformations, and notes</resp>
                    <persName>Leah Knight</persName>
                    <orgName>Brock University</orgName>
                    <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>
                    <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent/>
            <publicationStmt>
                <ab/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl>
                    <msDesc>
                        <msIdentifier>
                            <repository>See witness list.</repository>
                        </msIdentifier>
                    </msDesc>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <p>Transcriptions are encoded in TEI(P5)-conformant XML.</p>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p>Apparent errors are preserved and editorial corrections provided using SIC
                        and CORR tags, but only where the editor conjectures that the original
                        scribe or compositor would have recognized the instance as an error. For
                        example, what according to modern usage is incorrect subject/verb agreement
                        might have been deemed acceptable to a seventeenth-century scribe or
                        compositor. All such instances are treated instead using the ORIG and REG
                        tags. (See below.) </p>
                    <p>Corrections and annotations made within the scope of the original document
                        either by its original authors, owners, and/or transcribers are noted using
                        ADD tags. These annotations and may be further explained within NOTE tags, as
                        added by the editors of this digital edition, for display within the
                        apparatus.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p>Original spellings, abbreviations, and orthography are preserved. Where in
                        the manuscripts a character's status as majuscule or minuscule is ambiguous,
                        the editor has silently chosen one or the other based on context and
                        judgment (i.e., does not register such ambiguity in either the markup or the
                        notes).</p>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p>Original quotation marks, if any, are preserved.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p>Original hyphenation is preserved.</p>
                </hyphenation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <charDecl>
                <!-- Ligature combinations for which there are currently no corresponding Unicode codepoints. -->
                <glyph xml:id="ffllig">
                    <glyphName>Handwritten 'ff' ligature, used in handwriting to represent modern
                        F</glyphName>
                </glyph>
            </charDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="DDC22">
                    <bibl>
                        <title>Dewey Decimal Classification</title>
                        <edition/>
                        <publisher/>
                        <pubPlace/>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en-GB">British English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <!-- dewey decimal system class code 821: English Poetry -->
                <classCode scheme="DDC22">821</classCode>
		<keywords>
                     <term>goddesses</term>
                     <term>Aurora</term>
                     <term>light</term>
                     <term>death</term>
		             <term>afterlife</term>
        	</keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic url="./document_images/7610_107.jpg" xml:id="f7610_107"/>
        <graphic url="./document_images/7610_108.jpg" xml:id="f7610_108"/>
        <graphic url="./document_images/7610_109.jpg" xml:id="f7610_109"/>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div>
                <listWit>
                    <witness xml:id="ft">Transcription of manuscript: Transcribed and annotated by <persName xml:id="lknight">Leah Knight</persName> and <persName xml:id="wwall">Wendy Wall</persName>. See transcription conventions.</witness>
                    <witness xml:id="ee">Elemental edition: Edited by <persName>Leah Knight</persName> and <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>. See editorial guidelines for this edition.</witness>
                    <witness xml:id="ae">Amplified edition: Edited by <persName>Frances E. Dolan</persName>.</witness>
                </listWit>
            </div>
        </front>

        <body>
            <app>
                <rdg wit="#ft"><pb ed="#ft" facs="#f7610_107" n="52r"/></rdg>
                <rdg wit="#ee"><pb ed="#ee" facs="#f7610_107" n=""/></rdg>
                <rdg wit="#ae"><pb ed="#ae" facs="#f7610_107" n=""/></rdg>
            </app>
            <head>
                <app type="title">
                    <rdg wit="#ft"><fw facs="#f7610_107" type="pageNum" place="margin-topright">99</fw>To Aurora [3]</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">To Aurora [3]</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">To Aurora [3]</rdg>
                </app>
                <app type="editorialnote">
                    <rdg wit="#ft"><note type="editorialnote">In these transcriptions we preserve as many details of
                        the original material, textual, and graphic properties of Hester Pulter’s manuscript verse
                        as we have found practical. Whenever possible, for instance, original spelling, punctuation,
                        capitalization, lineation, insertions, deletions, alterations, spacing between words and lines,
                        and indentation are all maintained; abbreviations and brevigraphs are not expanded; and
                        superscript and subscript representations are retained.
                        <ref target="http://pulterproject.northwestern.edu/about-project-conventions.html#top" type="new-window-url">See full conventions for the transcriptions here.</ref></note></rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">
                      <note type="editorialnote">
                        The aim of the elemental edition is to make the poems accessible to the largest variety of readers,
                        which involves modernizing spelling and punctuation as well as adding basic glosses. Spelling and
                        punctuation reflect current standard American usage; punctuation highlights syntax which might
                        otherwise be obscure. Outmoded but still familiar word forms (“thou,” “‘tis,” “hold’st”) are not
                        modernized, and we do not modernize grammar when the sense remains legible. After a brief headnote
                        aimed at offering a “way in” to the poem’s unique qualities and connections with other verse by
                        Pulter or her contemporaries, the edition features a minimum of notes and interpretative framing to
                        allow more immediate engagement with the poem. Glosses clarify synonyms or showcase various
                        possible meanings in Pulter’s time. Other notes identify named people and places or clarify obscure
                        material. We rely (without citation) primarily on the Oxford English Dictionary (<title rend="italic">OED</title>), the Oxford Reference database, and the King James Version (KJV) of the Bible. When we rely on Alice Eardley’s edition of Pulter’s work, we cite her text generally (“Eardley”); other sources are cited in full. The result is an edition we consider a springboard for further work on Pulter’s poetry. <ref target="http://pulterproject.northwestern.edu/about-project-conventions.html#elemental-edition" type="new-window-url">See full conventions for this edition here.</ref>
                      </note>
                    </rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae"><note type="editorialnote">My “amplified” editions seek to make the
                        poems as accessible as possible by modernizing spelling and punctuation and
                        providing only brief definitions for words, while discursive notes and the
                        materials I gather for the “curations” section place Pulter’s poems into
                        conversations. As I build the curations for a given poem—provisional and quirky
                        as they are—I keep returning to the poem, re-reading, rethinking, and adding
                        layers to the notes. I hope to show that Pulter was intellectually and
                        politically embedded rather than isolated, taking up issues, genres, and tropes
                        that also interested her contemporaries and that sometimes accrue unpredictable
                        salience in later periods. Rather than focusing only on possible sources or
                        influences, I cast a wide net both within the seventeenth century and outside
                        it, trying to catch cultural materials Pulter might have engaged, some she
                        excludes or ignores, and even some she probably could never have imagined.
                        Curations don’t precede the poems nor are they implied by the poems—as if the
                        poem gathers them to itself (although it can sometimes feel that way) or hales
                        them forth. Instead, as a curator I weave the poem into a web of relations,
                        seeking to open out rather than close down interpretive possibilities. This
                        extends to including extracts that are long enough that readers might find
                        things therein that I do not anticipate. I also look for a multi-vectored
                        traffic among Pulter’s poetry and the other materials. What might the materials
                        I’ve gathered help readers see in the poems—or notice is not there? But also,
                        how do the poems bring fresh perspectives into the conversations into which I
                        draw them? The more one reads the poems as participants in wider ranging
                        conversations, the more fascinatingly twisty Pulter appears. Often, I don’t
                        grasp how she upends or comes at conventions aslant until I have mucked about
                        composting my “curations.”</note></rdg>
                </app>
            <app type="headnote">
                <rdg wit="#ee">
                  <note type="headnote">This poem is one of many in which Pulter meditates on the dawn. She uses the occasion of the sunrise to reprimand her soul for not being willing to shake off corporeality, suffer death, and be resurrected (along with the “sleeping” body). Playing off of the aubade tradition, the speaker does not sadly bid farewell to a lover, but instead seeks the ultimate moment of what she sees as a heavenly suppression of the flaws of mortal life; the moment of drinking Christ’s redemptive blood (the communion) supersedes the classical Lethe, the river of forgetfulness that one crosses to get to the underworld.</note>
                </rdg>
                <rdg wit="#ae">
                  <note type="headnote">
                    One of Pulter’s four Aurora poems, this one begins
                    with the classical allusion it shares with the other poems, celebrating the dawn in
                    song (a lyric genre called an aubade), and then dramatically shifts gears and
                    genres, first into natural history and then from the observation of busy insects to
                    wrenching spiritual self-castigation. In the course of the poem, the speaker admits
                    to neglecting god’s laws, failing to fulfill his will, forgetting what really
                    matters, wasting time, fruitless grief, folly and lust, bad dreams, and horrid
                    frights. This is a speaker who admits (even wallows in) doubt but builds to the hope
                    of a spiritual clean slate.
                  </note>
                </rdg>
            </app>
            </head>

            <l n="1">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Why? doth Pale Phœbe thus her bevty Shrowd.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">Why doth pale <seg>Phoebe<note type="gloss">moon goddess</note></seg> thus her beauty shroud?</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">Why doth pale <seg>Phoebe<note type="gloss">moon personified as a goddess</note></seg> thus her beauty shroud?</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="2">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Why? is her &ff;ace inveloped in a Clowd.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">Why is her face enveloped in a cloud?</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">Why is her face enveloped in a cloud?</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="3">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">It’s cauſe her borrowed Lusters in the Wain?</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee"><seg>Is’t<note type="physical">“It’s“ in manuscript</note></seg> ’cause her borrowed luster’s in the wane,</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">Is’t ’cause her borrowed luster’s in the wane?</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="4">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Or cauſe Auroras Purple Curtain’s drawn.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">Or ’cause <seg>Aurora’s<note type="gloss">goddess of the dawn</note></seg> purple curtain’s drawn?</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">Or ’cause <seg>Aurora’s<note type="gloss">dawn personified as a goddess</note></seg> purple curtain’s drawn?</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="5">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">T’is Soe, look how Shee bluſhing doth ariſe;</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">’Tis so: look how she, blushing, doth arise,</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">’Tis so: <seg>look<note type="critical">The four questions in the
                        opening lines draw the reader’s attention to the appearance of the personified
                        moon and dawning sun. Then the instruction to “look” in line 5 begins a kind of
                        pan shot that draws the mind’s eye to the horizon where the sun rises, before
                        zooming in on “these flowers.” Directing the reader’s attention to these
                        particular flowers (line 8) and then “these” bees the speaker walks amongst
                        (in line 11), a rhetorical pointing called deixis, the poem tightens and
                        intensifies the focus as it also shifts from the conventional to the quirkily
                        personal.</note></seg> how she blushing doth arise,</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="6">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Chaſeing Sad Darknes with her Orient eyes.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">Chasing sad darkness with her <seg>orient<note type="critical">associated with the part of the heavens in which the sun and celestial objects appear to rise; eastern</note></seg> eyes;</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">Chasing sad darkness with her <seg>orient<note type="gloss">facing east or the rising sun</note></seg> eyes.</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="7">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">And being Attended with the flying howres;</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">And being attended with the flying <seg>Hours<note type="gloss">Horae, goddesses of the seasons</note></seg>,</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">And being attended with the <seg>flying hours<note type="critical">The flying hours may be either the swift passage of time or the Hours or Horae, three sister goddesses who presided over the changing seasons.</note></seg>,</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="8">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Shee shakes her Dewey Curles upon these &ff;lowers.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">She shakes her dewy curls upon these flowers,</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">She shakes her dewy curls upon these flowers,</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="9">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">&ff;illing with Honey Dew, each Gold inamlild Cup;</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">Filling with <seg>honeydew<note type="gloss">This sugar-rich liquid—excreted by insects, plant galls, and fungi on the leaves of plants—was formerly thought to originate from the sky in a manner similar to dew.</note></seg> each gold-enamelled cup,</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">Filling with honeydew each gold enameled cup,</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="10">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Whence Bees (their Necter) And <seg>Ambrotia<note type="physical">“b”
                        appears corrected from “p”</note></seg> Sup.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">Whence bees their nectar and <seg>ambrosia<note type="gloss">food of
                        the gods</note></seg> sup.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">Whence bees their nectar and <seg>ambrosia<note type="gloss">Ambrosia
                        was the sweet food of the gods. The word was also used to describe the pollen
                        bees collected.</note></seg> sup.</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="11">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Thus doe theſe Virgins Spend the Toylſom Day;</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">Thus do these <seg>virgins<note type="critical">bees, regularly seen
                        as virginal and innocent, with associations to the Virgin Mary, largely based on
                        the idea that they reproduced asexually. See <bibl>Claire Preston,
                            <title rend="italics">Thomas Browne and the Writing of Science</title>, 77-78.
                        </bibl></note></seg> spend the toilsome day,</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">Thus, do these virgins spend the toilsome day,</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="12">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">And as I Solely Walk Sting my delay.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">And, as I <seg>solely<note type="gloss">solitarily</note></seg> walk, sting my delay.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">And as I <seg>solely<note type="gloss">alone</note></seg> walk <seg> sting my delay.<note type="critical">The virgins seem to be the bees who “sting”
                            the speaker’s “delay,” both stinging her as she loiters or procrastinates
                            and distressing her by offering their “toilsome” industry as a contrast to
                            her indolence. Their stinging virginity is both aggressive and penetrative.
                            In the seventeenth century, there was some confusion about the gender and
                            sexuality of bees. For instance, it was still widely assumed that a king
                            rather than a queen presided over the hive (see <bibl>Jeffrey Merrick,
                                “Royal Bees: The Gender Politics of the Beehive in Early Modern Europe,”
                                <title rend="italic">Studies in Eighteenth-Century Culture</title>, ed. J.
                                Yolton 18 [1988]: 7-37</bibl>). One text that did recognize a queen bee,
                            <bibl>Charles Butler's <title rend="italic">The Feminine Monarchy, or the
                                History of Bees</title>(Oxford, 1609)</bibl>, describes both virgin wax and
                            virgin honey but does not call bees themselves virgins. But a Catholic
                            celebration of the Virgin Mary describes her as hastening “like a busy bee”
                            (<bibl>Henry Hawkins, <title rend="italic">Partheneia Sacra</title> [Rouen, 1633],
                                p. 78</bibl>). The reference to stinging virgins may also reach back to
                            include Phoebe and Aurora, the bashful, blushing goddesses who nonetheless
                            get on with the business of dawn and so, like the insects, reproach the
                            speaker with their industry.</note></seg></rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="13">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Thus (Ô my god) each Smale deſpiſed inſect;</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">Thus (O, my God), each small, despised insect</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">Thus (O my god) each small despised insect,</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="14">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Buz in <seg><del>our</del><add place="above">my</add>
                        <note type="physical">the main editing hand has written “my” directly above
                            “<del>our</del>”</note></seg> ears, that I thy Laws neglect;</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee"><seg>Buzz in my ears, that I Thy laws neglect.<note type="critical">
                        two possible meanings: 1) the insects bother (“buzz”) the speaker because
                        (“that”) she is not obedient to God; or 2) the insects murmur (an alternate
                        meaning of “buzz”) that she is disobedient.
                    </note></seg></rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">Buzz in my ears, that I thy laws neglect.</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="15">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">In doeing what they’r made for, every fly</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">In doing what they’re made for, every fly</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">In doing what they’re made for, every fly</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="16">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">&ff;ulfuls thy will, (woes mee) Soe doe not I.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">Fulfills Thy will; (woe’s me) so do not I.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">Fulfills thy will. Woe’s me: so do not I.</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="17">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">I was Created to Set forth thy Praiſe,</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">I was created to set forth Thy praise,</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">I was created to set forth thy praise;</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="18">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Yet like a wretch I fool away my Dayes;</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">Yet, like a wretch, I fool away my days</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">Yet like a wretch I fool away my days</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="19">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">In fruitleſs grief, or moyling in the earth:</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">In fruitless grief, or <seg>moiling in the earth<note type="gloss">
                        making oneself wet and muddy; wallowing in the mire; trudging; being anxious
                    </note></seg>,</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">In fruitless grief, or <seg>moiling<note type="critical">working and
                        wallowing; Moil is a verb Pulter also uses in <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="35">The Pismire</ref> to
                        describe the dirty work of earthly life, work that requires one to wallow in the
                        dust and dirt the soul aspires to shake off, becoming dirty and defiled in the
                        process. This includes not just direct engagements with dirt, such as
                        agricultural labor or cleaning, but all labor that embeds us in earthly life.
                    </note></seg> in the earth,</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="20">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">&ff;orgetting my poor Souls Celestiall Birth.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">Forgetting my poor soul’s celestial birth.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">Forgetting my poor soul’s celestial birth.</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <app>
                <rdg wit="#ft"><fw type="catch" place="bottom">I</fw></rdg>
            </app>
            <app>
                <rdg wit="#ft">
                    <pb ed="#ft" facs="#f7610_108" n="52v"/>
                </rdg>
                <rdg wit="#ee">
                    <pb ed="#ee" facs="#f7610_108"/>
                </rdg>
                <rdg wit="#ae">
                    <pb ed="#ae" facs="#f7610_108"/>
                </rdg>
            </app>
            <l n="21">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">I know I have a Spark of Heavenly fier</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">I know I have a spark of heavenly fire</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">I know I have a spark of heavenly fire</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="22">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Within my Breast, elce what moves this deſire</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">Within my breast; else what moves this desire?</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">Within my breast—else what moves <seg>this desire<note type="critical">“This desire” appears to be the desire to respect rather than neglect God’s laws and to escape the body, its folly and lust. At one level, then, it is a desire not to desire earthly pleasures but instead to transcend them. See also Pulter’s poem <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="18">The Desire</ref>.</note></seg>?—</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="23">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">But ô my Soule’s Soe clog’d with &ff;lesh &amp; bones,</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">But O, my soul’s so clogged with flesh and bones</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">But O! My soul’s so clogged with flesh and bones,</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="24">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">I Heaven can Reach with nought but Sighs &amp; Gron’s,</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">I heaven can reach with nought but sighs and groans.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">I heaven can reach with naught but sighs and groans.</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="25">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">My Slavish Soul, Shake of this Dirt &amp; Dust,</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">My slavish soul, shake off this dirt and dust,</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">My slavish soul, shake off this dirt and dust,</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="26">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Put of thy folly, and worſ then folley, Lust.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">Put off thy folly, and worse than folly, lust,</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">Put off thy folly and—worse than folly—<seg>lust<note type="critical">This confession of lust is striking, especially given the social pressures on women to be and seem chaste. While male poets often confess or boast of lust, most female poets do not. The confession of lust adds another layer to the possible meanings of “this desire,” a desire that must be distinguished from other, more bodily desires.</note></seg>;</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="27">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">And through all the Clowds and Skie make way,</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">And through all the clouds and sky make way;</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">And through all the clouds and sky make way.</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="28">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">There there is Light out Shines <seg>Meridian<note type="physical">
                        “e” was probably originally written as a “u”</note></seg> Day.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">There, there is light outshines <seg>meridian<note type="gloss">noon
                    </note></seg> day.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>There, there<note type="critical">In this poem, Pulter twice
                        doubles adverbs (“There, there” [line 28]; “Whither, whither” [line 31]), moving
                        from an assertion of where the focus should be (“there”) to the question that
                        drives the poem:  given that the desired destination is clear, why does the
                        speaker keep flying off in other directions?</note></seg>, is light outshines
                    <seg>meridian<note type="gloss">noon-time or mid-day</note></seg> day.</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="29">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Nay that inviſible and Glorious Light,</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">Nay, that invisible and glorious light</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">Nay, that invisible and glorious <seg>light<note type="critical">The
                        oxymoron of the “invisible light” of heaven (the “there” which is never named)
                        mirrors Milton’s description of the “darkness visible” in hell. I’m grateful to
                        Leah Knight for pointing this out, as well as the fact that Pulter uses the
                        phrase “invisible light” in two other poems, <ref corresp="30" type="pp-poem-ref">The Center</ref> and <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="31">Made
                        When I Was Sick</ref>.</note></seg>,</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="30">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Outshines the Sun, more then <w lemma="the"><abbr>y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi></abbr></w> Sun doth Night.
                    </rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">Outshines the sun more than the sun doth night.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">Outshines the sun, more than the sun doth night.</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="31">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Ay mee! O <seg>whither<note type="physical">“the” in darker ink
                    </note></seg> whither <seg>do’ſt<note type="physical">“s“ written over another letter
                    </note></seg> <seg>thou<note type="physical">“u” written over a “y” with descender
                        imperfectly erased</note></seg> &ff;ly,</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">Ay me! O <seg>whither<note type="gloss">where</note></seg>, whither dost thou fly?</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>Ay me! O whither, whither dost thou fly?<note type="critical">
                        The relationship between “me” and “thou” starting in this line is a bit
                        confusing. “Thou” refers back to “my slavish soul” in line 8.  “My body” must
                        die (and be interred in “thy faithful urn”) in order for “my spirit” and “my
                        enfranchised soul” to be released. But “thou” might also include the reader, as
                        the speaker hails both the reluctant part of him or herself and the reader: “hey
                        you! You have to die before you reach ‘that invisible and glorious light.’” The
                        verb “fly” here both remembers the earlier discussion of flies, linking them
                        unsettlingly to the soul, and castigates the soul for flitting about when it
                        should focus instead on rising (line 44). The soul might justly complain that
                        the advice it gets in this poem is confusing: “Don’t fly, rise.”</note></seg>
                    </rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="32">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Before <seg>thou<note type="physical">“u” crowded into space before
                        next word</note></seg> canst injoy this, thou must Die.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">Before thou canst enjoy <seg>this<note type="gloss">this light</note>
                    </seg>, thou must die.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">Before thou canst enjoy <seg>this<note type="gloss">i.e., “that
                        invisible and glorious light”</note></seg>, thou must die.</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="33">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Repentant tears and dust, must clear thy Sight</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">Repentant tears and dust must clear thy sight</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>Repentant tears and dust must clear thy sight<note type="critical">This line captures the paradox that dust will clear one’s sight and cleanse one’s soul. Central to Pulter’s theology, dust is the primordial material from which humans emerge and to which they must return (Ecclesiastes 3.20); mortals must shake off the dirt and dust of their mortality in death. But this line also suggests that dust is cleansing. This may be another example of how Pulter conjoins observation of nature and theological reflection. Birds clean themselves with dust. We might even see a Pulter/poultry identification here. For example, <bibl>Adam Shewring’s <title rend="italic">The Plain-Dealing Poulterer: Or, A Poulterer’s Shop Opened</title> (London, 1695)</bibl>, reminds readers that to condition their feathers and eliminate lice and other pests, birds need to bathe themselves “in sand, ashes, or such like” (sig. B6).</note></seg></rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="34">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Ere thou canst look on that Refulgent Light;</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee"><seg>Ere<note type="gloss">before</note></seg>  thou canst look on that <seg>refulgent<note type="gloss">brilliant, glorious
                        </note></seg> light.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">Ere thou canst look on that <seg>refulgent<note type="gloss">radiant
                    </note></seg> light.</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="35">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">To Sleep in Grave, contented thou must bee,</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">To sleep <seg>in grave<note type="gloss">entombed</note></seg>, contented thou must be;</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">To sleep in grave, contented thou must be;</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="36">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Thy buſie &ff;ancie too, must Sleep with thee.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">Thy busy <seg>fancy<note type="gloss">imagination</note></seg>, too, must sleep with thee.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">Thy busy <seg>fancy<note type="gloss">imagination</note></seg>, too,
                        <seg>must sleep with thee<note type="critical">The speaker here reminds him or
                            herself and the reader that death will not only stop the body but the mind
                            or imagination. This line marks a pause in the poem to emphasize just what
                            death means. It’s not just that the body will dissolve to dust. The “busy
                            fancy” responsible for anxiety, procrastination, bad dreams, and poetry will
                            also fall still.</note></seg>.</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="37">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Yet though my Body into dust doth turn,</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">Yet though my body into dust doth turn,</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">Yet though my body into dust doth turn,</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="38">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">An honest Grave will bee thy &ff;aith full <seg>Urn
                        <note type="physical">written over indecipherable word, last letter with
                            ascender and first letter possibly capital “T” or “G”</note></seg>.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">An honest grave will be thy faithful urn;</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">An honest grave will be thy faithful urn.</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="39">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">But my enfranchiſed Soul to heaven Shall goe,</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">But my <seg>enfranchised<note type="gloss">freed, privileged</note>
                    </seg> soul to heaven shall go.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">But my <seg>enfranchised<note type="critical">“Enfranchised” means
                        here set free from subjection or confinement. Pulter also uses this term in <ref corresp="58" type="pp-poem-ref">For
                        I No Liberty Expect to See</ref>, in which the speaker imagines s/he will
                        achieve liberty only when “dispersed” into atoms but complicates that by
                        describing this dispersed state as being “enfranchised, free as my verse”
                        (line 3). This suggests that poetry provides an earthly preview of what liberty
                        would feel like. “Enfranchise” can also mean “admit to municipal and political
                        privileges” (<title rend="italic">OED</title>), connected in recent usage with being granted the right to
                        vote. Pulter’s use of the term here participates in a larger pattern of
                        associating freedom not with politics but with death (and, perhaps, with
                        poetry). In <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="57">Why Must I Thus Forever Be Confined</ref>, for example, she
                        writes: “I no liberty expect to have / Until I find my freedom in my grave”
                        (lines 78-79).</note></seg> soul to heaven shall go;</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="40">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">My Dust the while Shall Sweetly Sleep below,</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">My dust, <seg>the while<note type="gloss">meanwhile</note></seg>, shall sweetly sleep below.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">My dust the <seg>while<note type="gloss">meanwhile</note></seg> shall sweetly sleep below.</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="41">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">&ff;ree Shall I bee from Dreams, and Horrid &ff;rights,</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">Free shall I be from dreams and horrid frights;</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">Free shall I be from dreams, and horrid frights.</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="42">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">O welcom, o thrice Welcome, Such a Night.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">O welcome, O thrice welcome, such a night.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">O welcome, O thrice welcome, <seg>such a night<note type="critical">
                        “Such a night”—the night of death’s sleep that clothes the body in “an honest
                        grave”—seems distinct from the night described in the poem’s opening lines,
                        simultaneously lyrical and quotidian. Yet the dawn that launches the poem also
                        provides the imagery of curtains, shrouds, and enveloping, a covering that is
                        protective but will also be swept aside with dawn or resurrection.</note></seg>.
                    </rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <app>
                <rdg wit="#ft"><fw type="catch" place="bottom">but</fw></rdg>
            </app>
            <app>
                <rdg wit="#ft">
                    <pb ed="#ft" facs="#f7610_109" n="53r"/>
                </rdg>
                <rdg wit="#ee">
                    <pb ed="#ee" facs="#f7610_109"/>
                </rdg>
                <rdg wit="#ae">
                    <pb ed="#ae" facs="#f7610_109"/>
                </rdg>
            </app>
            <l n="43">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">But at that Grand, and Dread, yet Blest Aſſise,</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">But at that grand and <seg>dread<note type="gloss">dreadful</note>
                    </seg>, yet blessed <seg>assize<note type="gloss">trial; decree; judgment, with hint
                        of the Christian Last Judgment</note></seg>,</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">But at that grand and <seg>dread<note type="gloss">feared</note></seg>
                        yet blessed <seg>assize<note type="critical">trial; Assize courts heard
                            prosecutions of felonies including murder, punishable by death. Judges from
                            Westminster in London visited provincial towns twice a year, bringing “the
                            strength and influence of the central courts” with them, to try criminal or
                            crown indictments (See <bibl>Cynthia B. Herrup, <title rend="italic">The Common
                                Peace: Participation and the Criminal Law in Seventeenth-Century England
                            </title> [Cambridge University Press, 1987], pp. 42-43</bibl>). The second
                            coming of the resurrected Jesus was often described as a trial at which he
                            would divide the saved from the damned (Matthew 25:31-36). This was called
                            Judgment Day or the Last Judgment. Pulter’s reference to the assize here
                            grounds this widely used legal analogy in the specifics of early modern
                            English legal procedure, which included jury participation.  Her specificity
                            raises a question: who would stand as the jury at a “blessed assize”?</note>
                        </seg>,</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="44">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">The Trump Shall sound, and then the Dead shall riſe</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee"><seg>The trump shall sound and then the dead shall rise<note type="critical"> in the book of Revelation in the bible, the trumpet (“trump”) sounds at the Last Judgment, as souls rejoin their bodies and ascend to heaven.</note></seg>.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>The trump shall sound, and then the dead shall rise.<note type="critical">Just as divine judgment might be understood by analogy to legal procedures, those legal procedures, in Pulter’s England, were intertwined with the church. At the beginning of each semi-annual meeting of an Assize court, a sermon was preached; usually, it was later published. A sermon preached at the Assize held in Hertford (near where Pulter lived) in 1653 invites listeners to “consider the day of judgment” and links the concepts of a final “trump” with judgment as Pulter does here: “The sound of the last trump may well cause a retreat, and call us off from an eager pursuit of the flesh and world (Eccles. 11.9).” See “Curations.”</note></seg>
                    </rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="45">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Then Shall I bee United with my Spirit,</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">Then shall I be united with my spirit,</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">Then shall I be united with my spirit,</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="46">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Where wee eternall Glory Shall inherit.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">Where we eternal glory shall inherit.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">Where we <seg>eternal glory<note type="critical">Once I have achieved
                        glory, who will care how I have spent my life? The final assize or judgment will
                        be an evaluation of each person’s “frail and mortal story.” But after that, these
                        lines claim, the details won’t matter anymore. Once I shine in glory, no one will
                        ask the questions that have motivated and occupied this long poem.</note></seg>
                        shall inherit.</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="47">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Then who dares aſke, when as I Shine in Glory;</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">Then, who dares ask, <seg>whenas<note type="gloss">when</note></seg> I shine in glory,</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">Then who dares ask, whenas I shine in glory,</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="48">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">How I have Spent my frail and Mortal Story?</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">How I have spent my frail and mortal <seg>story<note type="gloss">life
                    </note></seg>?</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">How I have spent my frail and mortal <seg>story<note type="gloss">
                        history or life</note></seg>?</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="49">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">When wee have Drunk not Leath but Christs pure blood</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee"><seg>When we have drunk not Lethe, but Christ’s pure blood<note type="critical">Lethe is a river in Hades that produces forgetfulness; in Christian ritual, communion, or the Eucharist, involves drinking wine that represents the blood of Christ.</note></seg>,</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">When we have drunk not <seg>Lethe<note type="critical"> In Greek
                        mythology, Lethe was a river in Hades; drinking its water was said to produce
                        forgetfulness. Pulter here contrasts and links drinking this water of oblivion
                        with drinking Christ’s blood in the Eucharist, usually associated with
                        commemoration rather than forgetfulness. At the Last Supper, the gospels tell us,
                        Christ “took bread, and gave thanks, and broke it, and gave it” to his disciples,
                        “saying, ‘This is my body which is given for you, this do in remembrance of me'.”
                        After the supper he said, “This cup is the New Testament in my blood, which is
                        shed for you” (Luke 19-20). While Christ’s blood is then the opposite of the
                        Lethe’s water, prompting memory rather than oblivion, Pulter assigns it a certain
                        reassuring ability to erase bad memories. The poem has moved from the “nectar
                        and ambrosia” the bees “sup” in line 10 to the eucharistic drinking of “Christ’s
                        blood” here in line 49.</note></seg> but Christ’s pure blood,</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="50">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">All Shall fogotten bee but what is good.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">All shall forgotten be but what is good;</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">All shall forgotten be but what is good.</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="51">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">All Shall bee known that will increaſe our Joy;</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">All shall be known that will increase our joy;</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">All shall be known that will increase our joy;</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="52">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Nothing remembred that will Cauſe annoy.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">Nothing remembered that will cause annoy.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>Nothing remembered that will cause annoy<note type="critical">This line is parallel to the emphasis on “obliviating” or consigning to forgetfulness—scrubbing the memory—in Pulter’s poem <ref corresp="18" type="pp-poem-ref">The Desire</ref>.</note></seg>.</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <app>
                <rdg type="milestone" wit="#ft">
                    <milestone unit="poem" rend="straight-horline"/>
                </rdg>
            </app>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
