<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../src/vmachine.xsl"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
  schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI [

  <!ENTITY ff "<!-- ff ligature, representing capital modern day capital F, here represented as 'ff' -->ff">

  ]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mads.pp.41">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
          <title>The Invocation of the Elements, The Longest Night in the Year, 1655</title>
        <title type="sub">Poem #41</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Created by</resp>
          <persName>Leah Knight</persName>
          <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoded by</resp>
          <persName>Katherine Poland</persName>
          <persName>Matthew Taylor</persName>
          <persName>Betsy Chou</persName>
          <persName>Emily Andrey</persName>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>IT-project consultation by</resp>
          <persName>Josh Honn</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
          <orgName>Brock University</orgName>
          <orgName>University of Leeds</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <principal>
          <persName/>
        </principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="1"/>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription, transformations, and notes</resp>
          <persName>Leah Knight</persName>
          <orgName>Brock University</orgName>
          <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
        </respStmt>
      </editionStmt>
      <extent/>
      <publicationStmt>
        <ab/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listBibl>
          <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
              <repository>See witness list.</repository>
            </msIdentifier>
          </msDesc>
        </listBibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p/>
      </projectDesc>
      <p>Transcriptions are encoded in TEI(P5)-conformant XML.</p>
      <samplingDecl>
        <p/>
      </samplingDecl>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction>
          <p>Apparent errors are preserved and editorial corrections provided using SIC and CORR tags, but only where the editor conjectures that the original scribe or compositor would have recognized the instance as an error. For example, what according to modern usage is incorrect subject/verb agreement might have been deemed acceptable to a seventeenth-century scribe or compositor. All such instances are treated instead using the ORIG and REG tags. (See below.)</p>
          <p>Corrections and annotations made within the scope of the original document either by its original authors, owners, and/or transcribers are noted using ADD tags. These annotations and may be futher explained within NOTE tags, as added by the editors of this digital edition, for display within the apparatus.</p>
        </correction>
        <normalization>
          <p>Original spellings, abbreviations, and orthography are preserved. Where in the manuscripts a character’s status as majuscule or miniscule is ambiguous, the editor has silently chosen one or the other based on context and judgment (i.e., does not register such ambiguity in either the markup or the notes).</p>
        </normalization>
        <quotation>
          <p>Original quotation marks, if any, are preserved.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation>
          <p>Original hyphenation is preserved.</p>
        </hyphenation>
      </editorialDecl>
      <charDecl>
        <!-- Ligature combinations for which there are currently no corresponding Unicode codepoints. -->
        <glyph xml:id="ffllig">
          <glyphName>Handwritten 'ff' ligature, used in handwriting to represent modern F</glyphName>
        </glyph>
      </charDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="DDC22">
          <bibl>
            <title>Dewey Decimal Classification</title>
            <edition/>
            <publisher/>
            <pubPlace/>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-GB">British English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <!-- dewey decimal system class code 821: English Poetry -->
        <classCode scheme="DDC22">821</classCode>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
    <!-- List of all images associated with this document -->
      <graphic url="./document_images/7610_122.jpg" xml:id="f7610_122"/>
      <graphic url="./document_images/7610_123.jpg" xml:id="f7610_123"/>
      <graphic url="./document_images/7610_124.jpg" xml:id="f7610_124"/>
      <graphic url="./document_images/7610_125.jpg" xml:id="f7610_125"/>
      <graphic url="./document_images/7610_126.jpg" xml:id="f7610_126"/>
  </facsimile>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="ft">Transcription of manuscript: By <persName xml:id="lknight">Leah Knight</persName> and <persName xml:id="wwall">Wendy Wall</persName>.</witness>
          <witness xml:id="ee">Elemental edition: By <persName>Leah Knight</persName> and <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>.</witness>
          <witness xml:id="ae">Amplified edition: By <persName>Whitney Sperrazza</persName>.</witness>
        </listWit>
      </div>
    </front>

    <body>
      <app>
        <rdg wit="#ft"><pb ed="#ft" facs="#f7610_122" n="59v"/></rdg>
        <rdg wit="#ee"><pb ed="#ee" facs="#f7610_122"/></rdg>
        <rdg wit="#ae"><pb ed="#ae" facs="#f7610_122"/></rdg>
      </app>
      <head>
        <app type="title">
            <rdg wit="#ft"><fw facs="#f7610_069" type="pageNum" place="margin-topright">PG#</fw>The invocation of the Elements the longest Night in the Year 1655</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">The Invocation of the <seg>Elements<note type="gloss">fundamental components of the physical world; in ancient philosophy, as in this poem, earth, fire, water, and air</note></seg>, The Longest Night in the Year, 1655</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">The Invocation of the Elements the <seg>Longest Night<note type="critical">Pulter includes a specific time stamp in several of her poems’ titles, such as <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="4">The Complaint of Thames, 1647</ref> and <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="45">This Was Written in 1648, When I Lay in, With my Son John</ref>. In this title, Pulter is hyper-specific, noting both year and date of composition. The “longest night” refers to the winter solstice (or midwinter), always mid-December for the Earth’s Northern Hemisphere. Pulter’s specificity here urges us to think about how the poem’s title offers important framing for its content—a meditation on the relationship among darkness, despair, and death. As we’ll see, the poet pleads for death by water, air, fire, and earth as the poem progresses. But even as this time stamp consequently seems the perfect framing for such a poem, the poem’s central themes are also undermined by this title. The winter solstice is a turning point, part of a yearly cycle. The longest night immediately gives way to the gradual lengthening of daylight and nature’s spring awakening. The poem’s title, then, raises some important questions for reading: Within the poem’s prominent themes of darkness, despair, and death, do we glimpse hope? Are there any signs of light in this seemingly dark poem?</note></seg> in the Year 1655</rdg>
        </app>
        <app type="editorialnote">
          <rdg wit="#ft">
            <note type="editorialnote">In these transcriptions we preserve as many details of the original material, textual, and graphic properties of Hester Pulter’s manuscript verse as we have found practical. Whenever possible, for instance, original spelling, punctuation, capitalization, lineation, insertions, deletions, alterations, spacing between words and lines, and indentation are all maintained; abbreviations and brevigraphs are not expanded; and superscript and subscript representations are retained. <ref target="//pulterproject.northwestern.edu/about-project-conventions.html#top" type="new-window-url">See full conventions for the transcriptions here.</ref></note>
          </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">
            <note type="editorialnote">The aim of the elemental edition is to make the poems accessible to the largest variety of readers, which involves modernizing spelling and punctuation as well as adding basic glosses. Spelling and punctuation reflect current standard American usage; punctuation highlights syntax which might otherwise be obscure. Outmoded but still familiar word forms (“thou,” “‘tis,” “hold’st”) are not modernized, and we do not modernize grammar when the sense remains legible. After a brief headnote aimed at offering a “way in” to the poem’s unique qualities and connections with other verse by Pulter or her contemporaries, the edition features a minimum of notes and interpretative framing to allow more immediate engagement with the poem. Glosses clarify synonyms or showcase various possible meanings in Pulter’s time. Other notes identify named people and places or clarify obscure material. We rely (without citation) primarily on the Oxford English Dictionary (OED), the Oxford Reference database, and the King James Version (KJV) of the Bible. When we rely on Alice Eardley’s edition of Pulter’s work, we cite her text generally (“Eardley”); other sources are cited in full. The result is an edition we consider a springboard for further work on Pulter’s poetry. <ref target="//pulterproject.northwestern.edu/about-project-conventions.html#elemental-edition" type="new-window-url">See full conventions for this edition here.</ref></note></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">
              <note type="editorialnote"><p>In my editions of Pulter’s poems, I prioritize accessibility and use my annotations to prompt further exploration. To make the poems accessible to the widest possible audience, I have modernized spelling, punctuation, and capitalization according to American English standards. My editions aim to demonstrate the complexity of Pulter’s thinking, while opening space for the reader’s own analysis and interpretation. I recognize editing as a political act and aim to be as transparent as possible about how I frame Pulter’s poems for the reader. My lengthy annotations are an attempt to reveal my thought processes and make clear the ideological networks that inform my readings.</p>
                <p>As an important corollary to Pulter’s conceptual work, I also attend to the material expression of her manuscript object. Her manuscript pages reveal a glimpse of her thinking and writing processes, and I briefly note Pulter’s revisions to the poems in order to foreground her poetic craft. The manuscript features variants and revisions that invite multiple interpretations, and I encourage readers to refer to the manuscript images as they engage with Pulter’s writing. I offer some intertextual references to other early modern texts, but am most interested in drawing out how Pulter’s poems speak to each other as she reflects on clusters of ideas.</p></note>
          </rdg>
        </app>
        <app type="headnote">
          <rdg wit="#ee">
              <note type="headnote">Inscribed beneath the title of this poem is not just a year, as in several other Pulter poems, but a precise indication of the date of composition: the winter solstice, the darkest day of any year. Pulter’s general preoccupation with astronomical observation is thus reflected here, as is her larger concern with—and, often, morbid fixation on—the darkness of the night sky and her corresponding emotional state. This night, though, the speaker invites guests to a wonderful feast: darkness seems, at first, at bay. But we soon realize that the main course she plans to serve is her own body, carved into its constitutive elements of water, air, fire and earth. Those elements are also, paradoxically, her invitees, along with her soul, whose impatience to die motivates the occasion and the poem. Like any good host, the speaker serves up pleasing dishes and chatty flattery at the same time, in a sequence of dramatic monologues implied in her instructions to “ask no more” and “say no more” formulations (echoing Poems 11 and 13). While initially cordial, the speaker’s table-talk at times edges toward indecorous demands to be liquified, vaporized, chilled, and consumed into the earth, increasingly signalling the urgency with which she seeks her death; her sadness at that of her “lovely children”—<hi rend="italic">seven</hi>, horribly, by this date—rationalizes her insistence on returning to her own “mother,” the Earth addressed here.</note>
          </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">
              <note type="headnote"><p>What is an elegy and how do we know when we’re reading one? The standard definition of an elegy is a lament for the dead, stemming from the Greek word <foreign rend="italic">elegos</foreign>, or “song of mourning.” Pulter’s “Invocation of the Elements” does not explicitly call attention to itself as an elegy; in fact, it reads much more like a philosophical investigation. Like many of Pulter’s poems, it grapples with a range of themes surrounding mortality: nature, cosmology, redemption, and the relationship between body and soul. The poem opens with the poet pleading for death as her soul “rowl[s]” in darkness. The poet then invokes and addresses each of the four elements in turn—water, air, fire, and earth—as she explores the different ways her body and soul could be consumed.</p>
                  <p>But by line 8, when the poet references her “sad heart,” we glimpse the grief and despair that pervade this poem. Pulter invokes the elements and pleads for death as an antidote to the overwhelming trauma of losing seven children—“seven lovely buds” that have been “drawn dry” (line 21). That trauma and Pulter’s resulting grief drive the poem, which consequently explores how grief can inform and be informed by natural philosophy (a precursor to our modern understanding of science and its various fields of inquiry). Simultaneously lamentation for the dead and philosophical investigation, this poem offers an unusual example of an early modern elegy and a particularly complex aesthetic-scientific object.</p>
                <p>In this edition of the poem, I explore several interrelated questions. First, how does Pulter both describe and perform grief throughout the poem? In other words, how does she invite the reader, through language and form, to <hi rend="italic">feel</hi> her grief over her children’s deaths? This performance of grief extends to the manuscript’s material features. The ample blank spaces between the poem’s stanzas invite us to consider what roles absence and silence can play in poetic representations of grief. Pulter’s manuscript includes more explicit elegies (<ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="10">Upon the Death of my Dear and Lovely Daughter, Jane Pulter</ref>), and other poems that function more like “Invocation of the Elements”—we might call them elegy-hybrids (see, for instance, <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="7">On those Two Unparalleled Friends, Sir George Lisle and Sir Charles Lucas, Who Were Shot to Death at Colchester</ref>). How does “Invocation of the Elements”  work alongside those others and invite us to extend our understanding of what an elegy is and the kind of work it does? As Frances E. Dolan notes about Pulter’s poem on Lisle and Lucas, “this poem is an anguished lament, but about what exactly?” (see Curation, <ref type="pp-curation-ref" target="//pulterproject.northwestern.edu/poems/ee/on-those-two-unparalleled-friends-sir-george-lisle-and-sir-charles-lucas-who-were-shot-to-death-at-colchester/#commemorating-the-dead">Commemorating the Dead</ref>).</p>
                <p>Second, my annotations consider the poem’s intersecting “modes of knowing”—Valerie Traub’s useful phrase for the methods by which things come to be known.<seg>1<note type="gloss">Traub, “The Nature of Norms in Early Modern England: Anatomy, Cartography, <hi rend="italic">King Lear</hi>,” <title rend="italic">South Central Review</title> 26:1/2 (2009): 42-81.</note></seg> In this poem, Pulter draws on many different modes of knowing that we would now separate into discrete fields, or disciplines: philosophy (“For what is death but cold and night, / Life being only heat and light?”); chemistry (“I into tears am rarified”); and physiology (“Then will my heart forget to beat / And trepidate within my breast”). The poem is also deeply informed by Pulter’s experience as a mother. How are these different modes of knowing displayed and how do they interact throughout the poem? How does this poem’s network of knowledges continue to enhance our understanding of Pulter as both poet and thinker?</p>
                  <p>The poem’s central conceit—the four elements—provides an important example of how different modes of knowing converge. The elements had philosophical, medical, and spiritual resonances in the early modern period, and we see all of these at work in Pulter’s poem. Inherited from Greek philosophy, early moderns used the four elements to explain nature and the different kinds of matter that exist in nature. Medically, the four elements were linked to the humoral theory of the body. Through the seventeenth-century, the dominant physiological theory was that the human body is made up of fluids. The essential fluids, or humors, corresponded to the four elements and to four distinct stages of life: blood (warm/moist physical qualities linked to air and infancy); yellow bile (warm/dry physical qualities linked to fire and youth); black bile (cold/dry physical qualities linked to earth and adulthood); and phlegm (cold/moist physical qualities linked to water and old age). Spiritually (or, perhaps, cosmologically), the four elements were also an important part of the microcosm-macrocosm understanding of the world—a way to explain humanity’s place in the universe. As Pulter interacts with each element in turn, where and how do we see these different modes of knowing intersect?</p></note>
          </rdg>
        </app>
      </head>

      <l n="1">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Have Patience my aflicted Soul,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Have patience, my afflicted soul:</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Have patience, my afflicted soul;</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="2">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Thou Shalt not Long in Darknes Rowl.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Thou shalt not long in darkness <seg>roll<note type="gloss">revolve; proceed; wander; be enveloped</note></seg>.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Thou shalt not long in darkness <seg>rowl<note type="critical">Editors often modernize “rowl” to “roll,” as Leah Knight and Wendy Wall do in their Elemental Edition of the poem. The modernization illuminates several useful connotations for Pulter’s word choice: “roll” can mean revolve, proceed, wander, or be enveloped. Maintaining Pulter’s original spelling, though, reminds us of the term’s important etymological (and aural) connections to the verb “ravel,” particularly its early spellings “rauel” and “rawil.” “Ravel,” in this context, means “to entangle; to confuse, perplex; to render incoherent or muddled” (“ravel, v.1,” <title rend="italic">OED Online</title>). The feelings of confusion and incoherence evoked by this word are important for some of the later formal features I’ll track in this long poem.</note></seg>.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="3">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">I will the Elements implore,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">I will the elements implore;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">I will the <seg>Elements<note type="critical"><p>Pulter capitalizes "Elements" in this opening stanza as she invokes, or summons, the elements for assistance. The capitalization signals the importance of these entities for Pulter, and resonates with early modern understandings of the elements as particularly powerful forces. The four elements—water, air, fire, and earth—were a frequent topic of Renaissance poetry and natural philosophy. See, for instance, John Donne’s “The Dissolution,” which similarly uses the elements to reflect on loss and grief. Another useful comparison is Anne Bradstreet’s “The Four Elements.” Like Pulter, Bradstreet deals with each of the four elements in turn, but imagines the elements competing with each other to determine which is most important to human life. At the time Pulter was writing, the four elements were a familiar part of philosophical and scientific debates about the existence and creation of matter, central to the period’s renewed interest in atomism, for example.</p><p>The term “elements” might also be defined more simply as “the constituent parts of a whole.” This definition is particularly useful in thinking about the structure of Pulter’s poem—four stanzas (four “elements”) that each constitute one part of an aesthetic whole. In early modern religious contexts, “elements” could also refer to the “bread and wine used in the Sacrament of the Eucharist” (“element, n.,” <title rend="italic">OED Online</title>), which directly relates to the poem’s central conceit: death as the “last, best feast” (line 5).</p></note></seg> implore.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="4">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Then Shall I Need to beg noe More,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Then shall I need to beg no more</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Then shall I need to beg no more</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="5">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">To come unto my last best feast,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">To come unto my last, best feast:</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">to come unto <seg>my last, best feast<note type="critical">Here in the last line of the opening stanza, Pulter introduces the poem’s central conceit: death as the “last, best feast.” The poet is not doing the eating but rather “beg[s]” to be eaten—consumed by death. The poet then invites each of the four elements to be a “guest” at the feast (line 6) and she describes the different ways her body could be consumed by each element.</note></seg>.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ee">
              <milestone unit="poem-section" rend="stanza-whitespace"/>
            </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">
            <milestone unit="poem-section" rend="stanza-whitespace"/>
          </rdg>
        </app>
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft"><milestone unit="poem-section" n="Water" rend="left-gutter"/></rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee"><milestone unit="poem-section" n="Water" rend="left-gutter"/></rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae"><milestone unit="poem-section" n="Water" rend="left-gutter"/></rdg>
        </app>
      <l n="6">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft"><seg>The<note type="physical">in left margin: “Water”</note></seg> Lymped Lady’es my <seg>first<note type="physical">“r” appears written over earlier letter, possibly “e”</note></seg> guest,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">The <seg>limpid<note type="gloss">transparent</note></seg> lady’s my first guest;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">The <seg>limpid<note type="gloss">clear or pure, most often used in relation to fluids</note></seg> lady’s my first guest.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="7">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Cool Cristall Water take thy part,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Cool crystal Water, take <seg>thy part<note type="critical">This refers to water’s serving of the speaker’s “feast,” which is a figure for her body.</note></seg>:</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Cool crystal Water, take thy part:</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="8">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">&ff;irst that which Circles my Sad Heart.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">First, that which circles my sad heart;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">First, <seg>that which circles my sad heart<note type="critical">Pulter refers here to a common theory espoused in both medical and theological texts of the period: the <foreign rend="italic">pericardium</foreign>—the membrane enclosing the heart—was understood to be a thin sac of water. In Thomas Gibson’s <title rend="italic">The Anatomy of Humane Bodies Epitomized</title>, a lengthy compendium of anatomical knowledge published in several editions throughout the late-seventeenth and early-eighteenth centuries, Gibson helps his reader understand the fluid inside the pericardium by citing John 19.34: “This is that liquor that is supposed to have flown from the side of our Saviour when the soldier pierced it with a spear, for saith the Text (John 19.34.) <hi rend="italic">There came forth blood and water</hi>” (<bibl>London, 1682, Text Creation Partnership digital edition, <title rend="italic">Early English Books Online</title>, p. 233</bibl>). In Lewis Bayly’s <title rend="italic">The Practice of Piety</title>, a hugely popular devotional manual (over 70 editions published by 1821), Bayly references the same story about “blood and water” flowing from Christ’s pierced side, and includes an explanatory marginal note that strikes a distinctly anatomical tone: “There is about man’s heart a skin called <hi rend="italic">Pericardium</hi> containing water which cools and moistens the heart, lest it should be scorched with continual motion. This skin once pierced, man cannot live” (London, 1695, Text Creation Partnership digital edition, <title rend="italic">Early English Books Online</title>, p. 459).</note></seg>.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="9">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Or if my Tears will Satisfie,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Or, if my tears will satisfy,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Or, if my tears will satisfy,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="10">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">To tears Il’e quickly Rariefie,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">To tears I’ll quickly <seg>rarefy<note type="gloss">dissipate</note></seg>.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">To tears I’ll quickly <seg>rarefy<note type="critical">In early modern connotations, “rarefy” most frequently meant “to make thin” or “to make less dense in texture” (“rarefy, v.,” <title rend="italic">OED Online</title>). Pulter draws on that meaning here as she contemplates how her body might be transformed into tears—the transformation of a solid into a liquid. Pulter explores similar kinds of material transformations in other poems, such as <ref  type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="16">The Revolution</ref>, where she considers how her “tears” might “rarefy / to air” (lines 28-29).</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="11">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Number them not, <seg><del>but</del><note type="physical">struck-through with multiple horizontal lines</note></seg> count <seg><del>each</del><note type="physical">struck-through with multiple horizontal lines</note></seg> Sand or Star,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Number them not; count sand or star—</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Number them <seg>not. Count<note type="critical">The poem’s first of many medial caesuras—a break or pause in the metrical line that splits the line into two equal parts (in this case, four syllables on either side). Given Pulter’s striking, repeated use of the medial caesura in this stanza (lines 11, 15, 17, 18, 22, and 23), we might consider how her use of this formal feature compares to her contemporary poets. John Donne often uses medial caesuras in his devotional poems: “Thou hast made me, and shall thy work decay? / Repair me now, for now mine end doth haste” (“Thou hast made me,” lines 1-2). Mary Sidney, Countess of Pembroke offers another useful comparison because her psalm translations were such an important model for early modern poets like Pulter writing at the intersection of devotion and politics. In a psalm about God’s omniscience, Pembroke uses medial caesura to emphasize God’s knowledge of the poet’s movements: “if forth I march, thou goest before; / if back I turn, thou com’st behind” (Psalm 139, lines 15-16).</note></seg> sand or <seg>star—<note type="critical">Pulter revised this line in the manuscript. The original line reads: “Number them not, but count each sand or star.” The revised line emphasizes the medial caesura, adding to the midline stops and starts throughout this stanza (see my note on “not. Count”). And the edit from “each sand” to “sand” is crucial for the questions about quantification Pulter raises in these lines. “Each sand” opens the possibility for counting (a collection of grains of sand that can “each” be counted), but “sand” (like “star”) seems an abstraction, a move away from the thing as countable material and a move toward the thing as uncountable idea.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="12">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">You’l Sooner Number them by farr,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">You’ll sooner number them by far.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">You’ll <seg>sooner number them by far<note type="critical">We find this theme of excessive weeping in many of Pulter’s poems, such as <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="61">The Weeping Wish</ref> and <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="14">On the Horrid Murder Of that Incomparable Prince</ref>. In this poem, weeping is not confined, as we might expect, to the “Water” stanza. Pulter revisits this theme again in the “Air” stanza: “my grief o’erflows / I into tears am rarified” (lines 42-43).</note></seg>.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="13">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Oh that they had bin Shed for Sin,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">O, that they had been shed for sin,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1"><seg>Oh<note type="critical">Pulter uses “oh” many times throughout this poem—five times in this stanza alone. Even though she is directly addressing each of the elements, she uses “oh” as an exclamation rather than direct address (or apostrophe), often during moments when she seems overwhelmed by grief. Given the term’s frequent use in apostrophe, though, we might wonder: is this word doing double work throughout the poem?</note></seg> <seg>that they had been shed for sin<note type="critical">With this conditional construction, Pulter draws on a commonplace connection between grief and repentance (she’ll do this again later when she pairs “sin and sorrow” in line 77). If I were weeping in repentance for my sins, the poet reflects, then my tears would be valuable (“in heaven … bottled” [line 14]). Instead, the poet’s tears are shed in grief over the loss of her seven children, first referenced in line 21. This brief nod to repentance, though, raises a useful question about how Pulter links her status as mother to her devotional explorations throughout the manuscript: what kind of relationship does Pulter construct here between the possibility of spiritual redemption and the experience of maternal grief? For more on the connection between grief and repentance, particularly in women’s writing, see Elizabeth Hodgson’s <title rend="italic">Grief and Women Writers in the English Renaissance</title> (2015), especially pages 8-9.</note></seg>,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="14">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Then they in <seg>heaven<note type="physical">“a” written over other letter</note></seg> had botle’d bin,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Then they in Heaven had bottled been!</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Then they in heaven had bottled been.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="15">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Why were they Shed? O aſk not why,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Why were they shed? O, ask not why;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Why were they shed? <seg>Oh ask not why<note type="critical">This and the next eight lines read as a dialogue between the poet and Water. The poet imagines Water asking about the reason for her grief (“why were they [her tears] shed?”). In response, the poet resists repeating the traumatic experiences of her children’s deaths (“If I repeat my woes, I die / a double death” [16-17]). The poet’s responses to Water recall one of Pulter’s poems on her daughter Jane’s death, <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="11">Tell Me No More</ref>. In both poems Pulter contemplates poety’s role in articulating grief. Rather than give her reader the details of her children’s deaths, how can she use poetry to mark their absence and her grief? The repetition of “tell me no more” in the poem on Jane’s death is here reprised in the repetition of the exclamatory “Oh”; the echoed phrasing “Oh ask not why” (line 15), “Oh ask no more” (line 17), and “O say no more” (line 42); and the pattern “I die / a <hi rend="italic">n</hi> death” (lines 16-17; 22-23).</note></seg>.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="16">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">If I repeat my woes, I dye</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">If I repeat my woes, I die</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">If I repeat my woes, <seg>I die<note type="critical">Pulter uses enjambment—the continuation of a sentence or clause through a line break—to emphasize the language of death and dying. “I die” lingers at the end of line 16. Grammatically, the sentence is complete, but Pulter adds the extra weight of “double death” in the next line. How does the formal feature of enjambment contribute to Pulter’s poetic representation of grief throughout the rest of the poem? What effect does it have on the reader, particularly if the poem is read aloud?</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="17">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">A dubble Death, O ask noe more,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">A double death; O, ask no more;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">A double death. Oh ask no more,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="18">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Let mee alone, my loſs deplore.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Let me alone my loss deplore.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Let me alone my loss <seg>deplore<note type="gloss">weep for, grieve over, lament</note></seg>.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="19">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">&ff;air Nymph thoust <seg>oft<note type="physical">“t” possibly added later</note></seg> Quencht thirst in mee</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Fair nymph, <seg>thou’st<note type="gloss">thou hast</note></seg> oft quenched thirst in me:	</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Fair nymph, thou’st oft quenched thirst in me.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="20">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Retaliate and drink up mee</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Retaliate and drink up me!</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Retaliate and drink up me.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">
                <pb ed="#ft" facs="#f7610_123" n="60r"/>
            </rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">
                <pb ed="#ee" facs="#f7610_123"/>
            </rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">
                <pb ed="#ae" facs="#f7610_123"/>
            </rdg>
        </app>
      <l n="21">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Seaven Lovly Buds thou hast drawn dry,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1"><seg>Seven lovely buds thou hast drawn dry:<note type="gloss">The “buds” stand for seven of Pulter’s children who died.</note></seg></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Seven lovely buds thou hast drawn dry.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="22">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Oh Spare the Rest, or elce I dye,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">O, spare the rest, or else I die</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Oh spare the rest, or else I die</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="23">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">A treble Death, O heare mee Speake,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">A treble death. O hear me speak!</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">A <seg>treble<note type="gloss">triple</note></seg> death. Oh hear me speak!</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="24">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Let not my heart Soe often breake</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Let not my heart so often break,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Let not my heart so often break</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="25">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">But Let Death Strike mee once for all,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">But let Death strike me once for all;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">But let death strike me once for all—</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="26">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">A little blow will make mee &ff;all.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">A little blow will make me fall.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">A little blow will make me fall.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="27">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Thou didst a whole World once involve</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1"><seg>Thou didst a whole world once involve;<note type="gloss">allusion to the biblical flood; see Genesis 7.</note></seg></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Thou didst a whole world once <seg>involve<note type="gloss">Pulter ends her address to Water with a biblical reference to the Old Testament flood, narrated in the Book of Genesis, chapter 7. “Involve” here means “to envelop or enfold.” As water enveloped the world during the flood, the poet pleads for Water to engulf her. “Involve” is a particularly rich term throughout the manuscript, often connected to the “dissolution” of the poet’s body (here: “involve” in line 27 rhymes with “dissolve” in line 28). For more on this term in Pulter’s poetry, see <bibl>Liza Blake, “Hester Pulter’s Particle Physics and the Poetics of Involution,” <title rend="italic">Journal for Early Modern Cultural Studies</title> 20.2 (2020): 71-98</bibl>.</note></seg>.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="28">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Then let mee into thee diſsolve</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Then let me into thee dissolve!</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Then let me into thee <seg>dissolve<note type="critical"> In this context, “dissolve” has some particularly grisly connotations: “to destroy the physical integrity; to disintegrate, decompose” and “to melt or reduce into a liquid condition” (“dissolve, v.,” <title rend="italic">OED Online</title>). Given the highly physical experience of death Pulter evokes in this line, we might consider: how does Pulter’s engagement with death in this poem compare to her representation of death in other poems—<ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="65">The Hope</ref> or <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="25">The Circle [3]</ref>, for example?</note></seg>.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">
                <lb ed="#ft"/>
            </rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">
                <milestone unit="poem-section" rend="stanza-whitespace"/>
            </rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">
               <milestone unit="poem-section" rend="stanza-whitespace"/>
            </rdg>
        </app>
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft"><milestone unit="poem-section" n="Ayr" rend="left-gutter"/></rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee"><milestone unit="poem-section" n="Air" rend="left-gutter"/></rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae"><milestone unit="poem-section" n="Air" rend="left-gutter"/></rdg>
        </app>
      <l n="29">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft"><seg>Sweet<note type="physical">in left margin: “Ayr”</note></seg> Ayr, Refreſher of Mankind,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Sweet Air, refresher of mankind,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Sweet Air, refresher of mankind,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="30">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Let mee at last thy &ff;avour &ff;ind,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Let me at last thy <seg>flavor<note type="gloss">possibly figurative, as in the “fragrance” of renown; esteem, reputation; or, as in “savor,” delight, or pleasing quality</note></seg> find:</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Let me at last thy favor find.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="31">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Doe but exhast a little vapour,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Do but <seg>exhaust<note type="gloss">drain; suck up</note></seg> a little vapor,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Do but <seg>exhaust<note type="gloss">to draw out or expend</note></seg> <seg>a little vapor<note type="critical">This line again emphasizes the fragility of the poet’s corporeal form, recalling the end of the “Water” stanza, where the poet notes, “a little blow will make me fall” (26). “Vapor” is an especially important word choice because it suggests a steamy or moist emission as water transforms into air. In John Swan’s <title rend="italic">Speculum Mundi</title>, a popular seventeenth-century encyclopedia, he links “vapors” to “clouds”: an “exhalation cold and moist, drawn from the earth out of wet or watery places” (<bibl>Cambridge, 1635, Text Creation Partnership digital edition, <title rend="italic">Early English Books Online</title>, p. 143</bibl>). When Pulter was writing, “vapor” was also a word used in relation to scent. Fragrances were still understood to be emitted as smoke or vapor, which connects to Pulter’s description of the garden in this stanza and her reference to odor as “sweet breath” (lines 36-41).</note></seg>,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="32">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Thoul’t quickly blow out my lifs tapour,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1"><seg>Thou’lt<note type="gloss">Thou wilt</note></seg> quickly blow out my life’s taper.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Thou’lt quickly blow out my life’s <seg>taper<note type="gloss">candlewick, or another word for a wax candle used in devotional or penitential contexts</note></seg>.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="33">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">T’will bee my last request <seg>to<note type="physical">appears written over imperfectly erased “of”</note></seg> thee</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">’Twill be my last request to thee;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">’Twill be my last request to thee;</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="34">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Thourt free to all, bee Soe to mee,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Thou’rt free to all–be so to me!</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Thou’rt free to all, be so to me.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="35">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">I oft have made thee Such a feast</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">I oft have made thee such a feast</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1"><seg>I oft have made thee such a feast<note type="critical">Another kind of “feast” in the poem—this time a feast of smells and odors—that recalls the “last, best feast” of the opening stanza. The poet goes on to describe briefly the “sweet breath” of her garden’s “blossoms” (lines 38-41), but then cuts herself off, overwhelmed again by grief. Pulter uses garden references and metaphors to do interesting work throughout the manuscript. See, for instance, <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="2">Invitation to the Country</ref>, which, as Liza Blake shows us in her Amplified Edition, construes the garden as both an instrument of political agency and a space of political retreat. Or we could look at <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="118">The Snail, The Tulip, and The Bee</ref>, which imagines the garden as a female separatist community. Finally, we might wonder how the manuscript’s most explicit garden poem (<ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="12">The Garden, or The Contention of Flowers</ref>) both informs and is informed by these other representations.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="36">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">That all the Odours, of the east</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">That all the odors of the east</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">That all the odors of the East</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="37">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Could not with their Sweet Breath compare,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Could not with their sweet breath compare,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Could not with their sweet breath compare,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="38">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Bloſſoms Soe Lovly Young and Rare,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Blossoms so lovely, young, and rare:</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Blossoms so lovely, young, and rare:</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">
                <fw type="catch" place="bottom">the</fw>
            </rdg>
        </app>
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">
                <pb ed="#ft" facs="#f7610_124" n="60v"/>
            </rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">
                <pb ed="#ee" facs="#f7610_124"/>
            </rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">
                <pb ed="#ae" facs="#f7610_124"/>
            </rdg>
        </app>
      <l n="39">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">The Woodbine, er’e Aurora doth Ariſe,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">The woodbine, <seg>ere<note type="gloss">before</note></seg> <seg>Aurora<note type="gloss">goddess of dawn</note></seg> doth arise,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">The <seg>woodbine<note type="gloss">honeysuckle flowering plant (<foreign rend="italic">lonicera periclymenum</foreign>), which releases fragrance at night</note></seg>, ere Aurora doth arise,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="40">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">The July &ff;lower before the Shadow &ff;lyes,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">The <seg>gillyflower<note type="gloss">carnation</note></seg> before the shadow flies,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">The <seg>July-flower<note type="gloss">Pulter’s preferred term for “gillyflower,” a common name for several varieties of flowering plants, many of which are heavily scented, including the wallflower (<foreign rend="italic">Erysimum</foreign> genus) and the stock (<foreign rend="italic">Matthiola</foreign> genus).</note></seg> before the shadow flies,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="41">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">The dewey Vi’let <seg>or<del>e</del><note type="physical">final “e” erased</note></seg> the halfe blown Roſe</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">The dewy violet, or the <seg>half-blown<note type="gloss">half-blossomed</note></seg> rose.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">The dewy <seg>violet<note type="gloss">The violet (<foreign rend="italic">Violacea</foreign> family) was especially noted for its fragrance in early modern contexts. In <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="12">The Garden</ref>, the violet flower boasts that it “perfume[s] the air with fair Aurora” (line 282). For an excellent account of the violet’s use in perfumes and herbal recipes, see Colleen Kennedy’s post, “Smelling ‘Violet’ in Renaissance Works,” on <title rend="italic"><ref target="//recipes.hypotheses.org/1904" type="new-window-url">The Recipes Project</ref></title>.</note></seg>, or the <seg>half-blown rose<note type="critical">Half-bloomed or half-blossomed. Another flower praised for its scent in early modern contexts, the rose was also a primary example of the ephemerality of youth and beauty, here a reminder of Pulter’s children (“seven lovely buds” [line 21]) and the catalyst for her eruption of grief in the subsequent line. For more on the rose’s scent and the political ramifications of its ephemerality, see Holly Dugan’s chapter on roses, rosewater, and English courts in <title rend="italic">The Ephemeral History of Perfume: Scent and Sense in Early Modern England</title> (2011).</note></seg>—</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="42">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Oh Say noe More–my grief or’e &ff;lowes</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">O say no more! My grief o’erflows;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">O say no more! My grief o’erflows.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="43">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">I into teares am Rarified,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">I into tears am <seg>rarefied<note type="gloss">dissipated</note></seg>,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1"><seg>I into tears am rarified<note type="gloss">This line directly echoes language from the “Water” stanza and reinforces the poem’s attention to material transformations (see my notes at lines 10 and 31). For another exploration of grief in relation to the material transformation of water and air, see the “sad circle” of sighs and tears in <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="17">The Circle [1]</ref>.</note></seg>,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="44">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">And thou thy part will bee denied</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1"><seg>And thou thy part will be denied.<note type="gloss">The speaker implies she will dissolve wholly into watery tears, and thus deny Air any “part” in the feast of her body.</note></seg></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">And thou thy part will be denied.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="45">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Oh take this Sigh then for thy part,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">O take this sigh, then, for thy part,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1"><seg>Oh take this sigh<note type="critical">The “sigh” is Air’s “part,” but Air is denied the rest of the poet’s body, which is again consumed by water (“tears”). Sighs are a constant theme in Pulter’s poetry, signalled in the title pages for the manuscript’s poems and emblems: “Poems Breathed Forth by the Noble Hadassas” and “The Sighs of a Sad Soul Emblematically Breathed Forth by the Noble Hadassah.” But these last two lines of the “Air” stanza show us that the sigh is not just of thematic interest to Pulter; rather, these lines start with a literal exhalation of air—<hi rend="italic">oh</hi>. Throughout the poem, but especially here, “oh” is both sigh and breath, a formal marker and performance of feeling.</note></seg>, then, for thy part,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="46">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">&ff;or Such another breaks my <seg>Heart<note type="physical">remaining half-page blank</note></seg>.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">For such another breaks my heart.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">For such another breaks my <seg>heart<note type="critical">In the manuscript this stanza is followed by a large blank space that fills the rest of the page before the “Fire” stanza begins on the facing leaf. Are we meant to imagine that the poet’s feeling sigh in line 45 (both sigh and breath; both written “oh” and aural exhalation) gives way to a moment of silence? How does this material feature of the manuscript—the blank page space—enhance the poetic work of the “sigh” at the stanza’s end?</note></seg>.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">
                <pb ed="#ft" facs="#f7610_125" n="61r"/>
            </rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">
                <pb ed="#ee" facs="#f7610_125"/>
            </rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">
                <pb ed="#ae" facs="#f7610_125"/>
            </rdg>
        </app>
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ee">
                <milestone unit="poem-section" rend="stanza-whitespace"/>
            </rdg>
             <rdg wit="#ae">
                <milestone unit="poem-section" rend="stanza-whitespace"/>
            </rdg>
        </app>
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft"><milestone unit="poem-section" n="ffier" rend="left-gutter"/></rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee"><milestone unit="poem-section" n="Fire" rend="left-gutter"/></rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae"><milestone unit="poem-section" n="Fire" rend="left-gutter"/></rdg>
        </app>
      <l n="47">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft"><seg>Most<note type="physical">in left margin: “&ff;ier”</note></seg> Noble and Illustrious &ff;ier</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Most noble and illustrious fire,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Most noble and illustrious fire,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="48">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Whom (though I know not) I admire</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Whom (though I know not) I admire:</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Whom (though I know not) I admire,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="49">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">If Such an <seg>Ellement<note type="physical">first minuscule “e” appears corrected from earlier “i”</note></seg> there bee</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">If such an element there be,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1"><seg>If<note type="critical">Pulter begins this stanza emphasizing her unfamiliarity with fire—"whom (though I know not) I admire” (line 48)—so this invitation to the “last, best feast,” more than the others, is a “strange petition” (line 50). The “if” is significant, an exploratory tool that introduces the rhetoric of scientific inquiry into Pulter’s poem. Fire’s status as an element was increasingly contested in seventeenth-century natural philosophy. John Donne succinctly cites the debate in his “Anatomy of the World”: “and new philosophy calls all in doubt; / the element of fire is quite put out” (lines 205-206). For more on the use of “if” and the rhetoric of scientific hypothesis in early modern texts, see Chapter 3 of <bibl>Jonathan P. Lamb’s <title rend="italic">Shakespeare in the Marketplace of Words</title> (Cambridge University Press, 2017)</bibl>.</note></seg> such an Element there be,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="50">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">My Strange <seg>petition<note type="physical">second “t” may correct other letter, perhaps “c”</note></seg> is to thee</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">My strange petition is to thee.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">My strange petition is to thee.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="51">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Oh hearken to my last deſire</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">O hearken to my last desire</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">O hearken to my last desire</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="52">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">And help my Sad Soul to expire</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">And help my sad soul to expire!</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">And help my sad soul to expire.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="53">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Contract thy vigour hold thy heat</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Contract thy vigor, hold thy heat:</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1"><seg>Contract<note type="gloss">to draw in, condense</note></seg> thy vigor, hold thy heat,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="54">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Then will my heart forget to beat</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Then will my heart forget to beat</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Then will <seg>my heart forget to beat<note type="critical">Pulter’s emphasis on the heart as the body’s life-giving center recalls her lines in the “Water” stanza about the pericardium (see my note at line 8). These lines can seem a bit opaque: how will fire “hold[ing] its heat” result in the poet’s heart stopping? In William Harvey’s foundational work on the circulatory system (1628)—the first detailed account of how blood circulates through the body—Harvey associated heat with the motion of blood: “the blood, therefore, required to have motion, and indeed such a motion that it should return again to the heart … for we see motion generating and keeping up heat and spirits under all circumstances.” Harvey’s explanation helps us understand Pulter’s line: by holding its heat and, thereby, denying heat to the poet’s body, fire would cause the poet’s blood to stop circulating. See <bibl><title rend="italic">Anatomical Exercise on the Motion of the Heart</title>, Chapter XV, page 69, cited from <title rend="italic">The Works of William Harvey</title>, trans. Robert Willis, University of Pennsylvania Press, 1989.</bibl></note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="55">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">And trepidate within my Breast</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">And <seg>trepidate<note type="gloss">tremble</note></seg> within my breast.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">And <seg>trepidate<note type="gloss">to tremble with fear</note></seg> within my breast.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="56">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">O then how Sweet will bee my rest</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">O, then, how sweet will be my rest;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">O then how sweet will be <seg>my rest<note type="critical">Here Pulter draws on the familiar trope of sleep as a kind of death. Shakespeare’s <title rend="italic">Hamlet</title> includes a famous use of this analogy in Hamlet’s “to be or not to be” soliloquy: “to die, to sleep; to sleep, perchance to dream” (Act 3, Scene 1). Pulter threads this trope through the remainder of this stanza with references to “sweet slumber,” “sad dreams,” and “blessed night.” For an entire poem centered on this trope, see <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="47">Why Art Thou Sad at the Approach of Night</ref>.</note></seg>;</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="57">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">What a Sweet Slumber Shall I take</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">What a sweet slumber shall I take</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">What a sweet slumber shall I take</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="58">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">When my Sad Dreams doe mee forſake</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">When my sad dreams do me forsake</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">When my sad dreams do me forsake</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="59">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">And ceaſe my aflicted Soul t’afright</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">And cease my afflicted soul t’affright!</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">And cease my afflicted soul t’afright.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="60">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Welcome Oh welcome that blesst Night</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Welcome, O welcome, that blessed night.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1"><seg>Welcome, O welcome, that blessed night<note type="critical">By repeating this line verbatim three lines later, Pulter uses her characteristic doubling to underscore the poet’s desire for death. The enveloped lines between the repetition convey an almost effortless death: the poet will exhale a “short breath” and her “structure” will “fall” to “dust.” Death is not only “welcome,” but easy.</note></seg>.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="61">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Then doe but my Short Breath Exhale</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Then do but my short breath <seg>exhale<note type="gloss">draw up</note></seg>,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Then do but my short breath exhale,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="62">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">My Structure Straight to dust will fall</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">My structure straight to <seg>dust<note type="critical">finely disintegrated matter, or original formative physical materials; for the latter, see Genesis 2:7: “And the Lord God formed man [of] the dust of the ground, and breathed into his nostrils the breath of life; and man became a living soul.”</note></seg> will fall.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">My structure straight to dust will fall.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="63">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Welcome Oh welcome that blest Night</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Welcome, O welcome, that blessed night,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Welcome, O welcome, that blessed night,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="64">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Which Ushers in Eternall Light</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Which ushers in eternal light!</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Which ushers in eternal light.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="65">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">&ff;or what is Death but Cold and Night</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">For what is death but cold and night,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1"><seg>For what is death but cold and night<note type="critical">Pulter’s definition of death as “cold and night” turns us back to the poem’s title where she records its composition on the “longest night in the year.” We might also think about how this question about the definition of death and life connect to Pulter’s use of “if” at the stanza’s opening. The Fire stanza, more than any of the others, seems truly an exploration, first marked by the conditional “if,” then by Pulter’s reflection on the relationship between blood and heat, and finally here by the interrogative mode at the stanza’s end.</note></seg>,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="66">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Life beeing onely Heat and Light</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Life being only heat and light?</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Life being only heat and light?</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="67">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Then all my Heat to thee Il’e give</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Then all my heat to thee I’ll give,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Then all my heat to thee I’ll give,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="68">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">And though I Die in thee I Live</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">And though I die, in thee I live.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">And though I die, in thee I live.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">
                <pb ed="#ft" facs="#f7610_126" n="61v"/>
            </rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">
                <pb ed="#ee" facs="#f7610_126"/>
            </rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">
                <pb ed="#ae" facs="#f7610_126"/>
            </rdg>
        </app>
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ee">
              <milestone unit="poem-section" rend="stanza-whitespace"/>            
            </rdg>
             <rdg wit="#ae">
               <milestone unit="poem-section" rend="stanza-whitespace"/>            
             </rdg>
        </app>
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft"><milestone unit="poem-section" n="Dust, or Earth" rend="left-gutter"/></rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee"><milestone unit="poem-section" n="Dust, or Earth" rend="left-gutter"/></rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae"><milestone unit="poem-section" n="Dust, or Earth" rend="left-gutter"/></rdg>
        </app>
      <l n="69">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft"><seg>Dear<note type="physical">in left margin: “Dust, or Earth”; latter two words in different hand from main scribe; first third of page blank</note></seg> Dust from thee I drew my Birth</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Dear Dust, from thee I drew my birth:</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Dear <seg>Dust<note type="gloss">“Dust” is one of Pulter’s frequent preoccupations throughout the manuscript and she often uses this term to refer to the element of Earth. For some other poems that consider “dust,” see <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="63">Dear God, From Thy High Throne Look Down</ref> and <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="65">The Hope</ref>.</note></seg>, from thee I drew my birth.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="70">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Then come, and t’is but Earth to Earth</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Then come, and ’tis but <seg>earth to earth<note type="critical">a common period phrase alluding to the body’s disintegration at death; see the <title rend="italic">Book of Common Prayer</title> burial service (London, 1549), Ee 4v: “earth to earth, ashes to ashes, dust to dust.”</note></seg>.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Then come, and ‘tis but <seg>Earth to Earth<note type="critical"><p>This stanza’s opening lines introduce the concept of life as a circle, succinctly captured by the phrase “Earth to Earth.” The life/death cycle provides important framing for the stanza’s maternal themes. Even though Pulter draws on her status as mother throughout the rest of the poem, in this stanza she explicitly identifies herself as “mother” (line 72) for the first time and uses that identification as leverage to petition Mother Earth.</p><p>An important context underlying Pulter’s themes in this stanza is the very real fear of death that accompanied childbirth in early modern England. Giving birth was a dangerous process and maternal and infant mortality rates were high. How does the connection between death and motherhood function in this stanza compared to, for instance, <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="45">This Was Written in 1648, When I Lay in, With my Son John</ref>? For more on Pulter’s status as mother and how she contemplates her mortality through her motherhood, see <bibl>Amanda Zoch, “Rewriting the Lying-In: Hester Pulter, Katherine Philips, and the Felt Mortality of Pregnancy,” <title rend="italic">Early Modern Women</title> 15.1 (2020): 3-25</bibl>, and <ref type="pp-curation-ref" target="//pulterproject.northwestern.edu/poems/ee/this-was-written-in-1648-when-i-lay-in-with-my-son-john/#lying-in">Lying-In</ref> in the Curations for Poem 45.</p></note></seg>.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="71">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">My lovly Children thou hast taken</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">My lovely children thou hast taken:</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">My lovely children thou hast taken.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="72">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Shall their Sad Mother bee forſaken</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Shall their sad mother be forsaken?</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Shall their sad mother be forsaken?</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="73">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Aye mee thou took’st them<add place="below">^</add><add place="above">young&amp;</add> faire</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Ay me, thou took’st them young and fair,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Aye me, <seg>thou took’st them young and fair<note type="critical">Revised in the manuscript. The original line reads, “Aye me, thou took’st them faire.” It seems that Pulter’s insertion of “young and” is a practical formal revision to ensure the line fits metrically with the next line. But we might also ask, does this revision do conceptual work too, as we saw in Pulter’s revision to line 11?</note></seg>,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="74">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">And leav’st mee here with Hoarie Haire</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">And leav’st me here with <seg>hoary<note type="gloss">grey or white</note></seg> hair.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">And leav’st me here with <seg>hoary<note type="gloss">grey, white with age</note></seg> hair.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="75">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">They Lovly faire with Snowey Skin</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">They lovely fair, with snowy skin,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">They, <seg>lovely fair with snowy skin<note type="critical">Pulter’s language here echoes her elegies on Jane Pulter’s death, <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="10">Upon the Death of my Dear and Lovely Daughter, Jane Pulter</ref> and <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="11">Tell Me No More [On the Same]</ref>. In “Upon the Death,” for example, Pulter describes how “fever spot[s]” appeared on Jane’s “snowy skin.” Like this poem, both elegies depict a mother consumed with grief over the loss of her child. The echoes between this poem and Pulter’s more traditional elegies bring us back to my question in the poem’s “Headnote”: what is an elegy and how do we know when we’re reading one?</note></seg>,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="76">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Did too too Soone thy favour win</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Did too, too soon thy favor win.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Did too, too soon thy favor win.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="77">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">But I involved with Sin and Sorrow</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">But I, involved with sin and sorrow,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">But I, involved with sin and sorrow,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="78">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Sadly expect thee Night and Morrow</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Sadly expect thee night and morrow.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Sadly expect thee night and morrow.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="79">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">I ask noe Piramide nor Stately Tomb</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">I ask no pyramid nor stately tomb:</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">I ask no pyramid nor stately tomb;</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="80">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Doe but involve mee in thy Spacious Womb</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Do but <seg>involve<note type="gloss">envelop</note></seg> me in thy spacious womb.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Do but involve me in <seg>thy spacious womb<note type="critical"><p>Pulter joins many of her contemporary poets in representing Earth as a fertile mother who both gives and takes life. In John Milton’s <title rend="italic">Paradise Lost</title>, Hell’s demons “rifle[ ] the bowels of their mother Earth” (1.687) and, when Adam bites the fruit from the Tree of Knowledge, Milton describes the Earth “trembl[ing] from her entrails, as again / in pangs” (9.1000). Mary Sidney, Countess of Pembroke, also consistently draws on this metaphor in her psalm translations: “All things in brief, that life in life maintain, / From earth’s old bowels fresh and youngly grows” (Psalm 104, lines 47-48). Both Milton and Pembroke’s uses of this metaphor remind us that this is a common biblical trope, one with which Pulter would have been very familiar. In Pulter’s representation, Earth’s womb is central to the life/death cycle and the Earth’s “bowels” ultimately become the poet’s final desired resting place.</p><p>When I read this final stanza, I think about Pulter’s representation of Earth as a living, maternal organism in contrast to increasingly mechanistic representations of nature in seventeenth-century England. Within several decades of Pulter’s writing, changing attitudes toward science and the study of nature would result in widespread attempts to control, contain, and dominate the natural world. English poet Anna Laetitia Barbauld (1743-1825) confronts this shift in her 1773 poem <ref target="//romantic-circles.org/editions/contemps/barbauld/poems1773/invitation.html#p22" type="new-window-url">“The Invitation,”</ref> where she describes scientists that “pensive creep” and “hunt” nature “to her elemental forms.” For foundational ecofeminist work to read alongside Pulter’s representation, see <bibl>Carolyn Merchant, <title rend="italic">The Death of Nature: Women, Ecology and the Scientific Revolution</title> (Harper &amp; Row, 1980)</bibl>.</p></note></seg>.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="81">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">To Beg thys once dear Mother give mee leave</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">To beg this once, dear mother, give me leave:</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">To beg this once, dear mother, give me leave:</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="82">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Oh let thy Bowels yern and mee receive.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">O let thy <seg>bowels<note type="gloss">intestines or the heart or core; also pity, compassion</note></seg> yearn, and me receive.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">O let thy bowels <seg>yearn<note type="critical">The poem ends with the poet voicing her desire to be incorporated back into the earth. The Earth’s “yearn[ing]” here bookends the poet’s yearning in the poem’s opening stanza (how she “implore[s]” the Elements to attend her “last, best feast”). In early modern connotations, “yearn” could mean both “to have a strong desire or longing for” and “to be deeply moved; to feel something (as compassion, sympathy, etc.) intensely” (“yearn, v.1,” <title rend="italic">OED Online</title>). The second connotation usefully extends the elegiac work of the poem we’ve traced thus far. How does this poem function not only as elegy, but specifically as a call for collective mourning? An invitation for the poem’s readers to mourn and “yearn” alongside the poet? To continue exploring these questions, we might now turn to one of Pulter’s elegies on her daughter’s death, where the poet asks “all…parents” to “lend one tear” to contribute to her lament (<ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="10">Upon the Death of my Dear and Lovely Daughter, Jane Pulter</ref>).</note></seg> and me receive.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
