<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../src/vmachine.xsl"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
  schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI [

  <!ENTITY ff "<!-- ff ligature, representing capital modern day capital F, here represented as 'ff' -->ff">

  ]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mads.pp.14">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
          <title>On the Horrid Murder of that Incomparable Prince</title>
        <title type="sub">Poem #14</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Created by</resp>
          <persName>Leah Knight</persName>
          <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoded by</resp>
          <persName>Katherine Poland</persName>
          <persName>Matthew Taylor</persName>
          <persName>Betsy Chou</persName>
          <persName>Emily Andrey</persName>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>IT-project consultation by</resp>
          <persName>Josh Honn</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
          <orgName>Brock University</orgName>
          <orgName>University of Leeds</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <principal>
          <persName/>
        </principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="1"/>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription, transformations, and notes</resp>
          <persName>Leah Knight</persName>
          <orgName>Brock University</orgName>
          <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
        </respStmt>
      </editionStmt>
      <extent/>
      <publicationStmt>
        <ab/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listBibl>
          <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
              <repository>See witness list.</repository>
            </msIdentifier>
          </msDesc>
        </listBibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p/>
      </projectDesc>
      <p>Transcriptions are encoded in TEI(P5)-conformant XML.</p>
      <samplingDecl>
        <p/>
      </samplingDecl>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction>
          <p>Apparent errors are preserved and editorial corrections provided using SIC and CORR tags, but only where the editor conjectures that the original scribe or compositor would have recognized the instance as an error. For example, what according to modern usage is incorrect subject/verb agreement might have been deemed acceptable to a seventeenth-century scribe or compositor. All such instances are treated instead using the ORIG and REG tags. (See below.)</p>
          <p>Corrections and annotations made within the scope of the original document either by its original authors, owners, and/or transcribers are noted using ADD tags. These annotations and may be further explained within NOTE tags, as added by the editors of this digital edition, for display within the apparatus.</p>
        </correction>
        <normalization>
          <p>Original spellings, abbreviations, and orthography are preserved. Where in the manuscripts a character’s status as majuscule or minuscule is ambiguous, the editor has silently chosen one or the other based on context and judgment (i.e., does not register such ambiguity in either the markup or the notes).</p>
        </normalization>
        <quotation>
          <p>Original quotation marks, if any, are preserved.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation>
          <p>Original hyphenation is preserved.</p>
        </hyphenation>
      </editorialDecl>
      <charDecl>
        <!-- Ligature combinations for which there are currently no corresponding Unicode codepoints. -->
        <glyph xml:id="ffllig">
          <glyphName>Handwritten 'ff' ligature, used in handwriting to represent modern F</glyphName>
        </glyph>
      </charDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="DDC22">
          <bibl>
            <title>Dewey Decimal Classification</title>
            <edition/>
            <publisher/>
            <pubPlace/>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-GB">British English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <!-- dewey decimal system class code 821: English Poetry -->
        <classCode scheme="DDC22">821</classCode>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
    <!-- List of all images associated with this document -->
      <graphic url="./document_images/7610_071.jpg" xml:id="f7610_071"/>
  </facsimile>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="ft">Transcription of manuscript: By <persName xml:id="lknight">Leah Knight</persName> and <persName xml:id="wwall">Wendy Wall</persName>.</witness>
          <witness xml:id="ee">Elemental edition: By <persName>Leah Knight</persName> and <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>.</witness>
<!--          <witness xml:id="ae">Amplified edition: By <persName>AE EDITOR</persName>.</witness>-->
        </listWit>
      </div>
    </front>

    <body>
      <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft"><pb ed="#ft" facs="#f7610_071" n="34r"/></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee"><pb ed="#ee" facs="#f7610_071"/></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><pb ed="#ae" facs="#f7610_071"/></rdg>
      </app>
      <head>
        <app type="title">
            <rdg wit="#ft"><fw facs="#f7610_069" type="pageNum" place="margin-topright">PG#</fw>On the Horrid Murther of that incomparable  –
                Prince, King Charles the &ff;irst
            </rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">On the Horrid Murder of that <seg>Incomparable Prince<note type="gloss">In the manuscript, the title specifies: “King Charles the First.” In the English civil war between royalists and parliamentarians, Charles I was sentenced to death and beheaded in 1649.</note></seg>
            </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">AE TITLE</rdg>
        </app>
        <app type="editorialnote">
          <rdg wit="#ft">
            <note type="editorialnote">In these transcriptions we preserve as many details of the original material, textual, and graphic properties of Hester Pulter’s manuscript verse as we have found practical. Whenever possible, for instance, original spelling, punctuation, capitalization, lineation, insertions, deletions, alterations, spacing between words and lines, and indentation are all maintained; abbreviations and brevigraphs are not expanded; and superscript and subscript representations are retained. <ref target="//pulterproject.northwestern.edu/about-project-conventions.html#top" type="new-window-url">See full conventions for the transcriptions here.</ref></note>
          </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">
            <note type="editorialnote">The aim of the elemental edition is to make the poems accessible to the largest variety of readers, which involves modernizing spelling and punctuation as well as adding basic glosses. Spelling and punctuation reflect current standard American usage; punctuation highlights syntax which might otherwise be obscure. Outmoded but still familiar word forms (“thou,” “‘tis,” “hold’st”) are not modernized, and we do not modernize grammar when the sense remains legible. After a brief headnote aimed at offering a “way in” to the poem’s unique qualities and connections with other verse by Pulter or her contemporaries, the edition features a minimum of notes and interpretative framing to allow more immediate engagement with the poem. Glosses clarify synonyms or showcase various possible meanings in Pulter’s time. Other notes identify named people and places or clarify obscure material. We rely (without citation) primarily on the Oxford English Dictionary (OED), the Oxford Reference database, and the King James Version (KJV) of the Bible. When we rely on Alice Eardley’s edition of Pulter’s work, we cite her text generally (“Eardley”); other sources are cited in full. The result is an edition we consider a springboard for further work on Pulter’s poetry. <ref target="//pulterproject.northwestern.edu/about-project-conventions.html#elemental-edition" type="new-window-url">See full conventions for this edition here.</ref></note></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">
            <note type="editorialnote"></note>
          </rdg>
        </app>
        <app type="headnote">
          <rdg wit="#ee">
            <note type="headnote">This poem follows one <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="13">Upon the Imprisonment of his Sacred Majesty, That Unparalleled Prince, King Charles the First</ref>; it thus follows not only in the manuscript’s arrangement, but in chronology. Charles, jailed in 1647, was in 1649 beheaded by his opponents in England’s civil wars. The monstrous singularity of this event seems reflected in the volume’s preceding blank page, paired with another after the next poem, <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="15">On the Same</ref>: these two poems, in their efforts to grieve a beloved, murdered ruler, huddle together between visible, almost legible stretches of silence. Here, the speaker draws on the authority of conventional poetic claims of ineffability associated with praising monarchs. But now it is not just words that fail; now, even tears and sighs won’t serve—a devastating claim for a poet who figures much of her verse as tears and sighs. Instead, this poem insists the only fitting response to the king’s dismemberment is a kind of self-vivisection by mourners who are exhorted to weep not tears, but eyeballs, and to sigh not air, but their very souls: that is, to grieve themselves to death.</note>
          </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">
            <note type="headnote"></note>
          </rdg>
        </app>
      </head>

      <l n="1">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Let none preſume to weep, tears are to weak</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Let none presume to weep; tears are too weak</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="2">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Such an <seg>unparreld<note type="physical">“e” written over “i” (with dot still visible)</note></seg> loſs as this to Speak</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee"><seg>Such<note type="gloss">of such</note></seg> an <seg>unparall’d<note type="critical">Spelled “unparelled” (for “unparalleled”) in the manuscript, we have maintained an abbreviation for the sake of the meter.</note></seg> loss as this to speak.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="3">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Poor village Girles doe Soe expreſs their grief</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Poor village girls do so express their grief,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="4">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">And in that Sad expreſſion find relief</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">And in that sad expression find relief.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="5">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">When Such a Prince in Such a manner Dies</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">When such a <seg>prince<note type="physical">sovereign ruler</note></seg> in such a manner dies,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="6">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Let us (ay mee) noe more drop tears but eyes</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Let us (ay me!) no more drop tears, but eyes;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="7">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Nor let none dare to Sigh or Strike their breast</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Nor let none dare to sigh or strike their breast</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="8">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">To Shew a grief that Soe tranſcends the rest</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">To show a grief that so transcends the rest.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="9">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft"><seg>Plebeans<note type="physical">“b” possibly written over an existing later, perhaps a “v”</note></seg> Soe each vulgar loſs <seg>deplore<del>s</del><note type="physical">“s” erased</note></seg></rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee"><seg>Plebeians<note type="gloss">commoners</note></seg> so each vulgar loss <seg>deplore<note type="gloss">mourn</note></seg>;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="10">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Wee doo too little if wee doo noe more</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">We do too little, if we do no more.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="11">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">When Such a King in Such a manner Dies</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">When such a king in such a manner dies,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="12">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Let us suſpire our Soules, weep out <w lemma="our"><abbr>o:<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></abbr></w> eyes.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Let us <seg>suspire<note type="gloss">sigh, breathe out</note></seg> our souls, weep out our eyes.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
