<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../src/vmachine.xsl"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
  schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI [

  <!ENTITY ff "<!-- ff ligature, representing capital modern day capital F, here represented as 'ff' -->ff">

  ]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mads.pp.112">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
          <title>The Turtle and his Paramour (Emblem 47)</title>
        <title type="sub">Poem #112</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Created by</resp>
          <persName>Leah Knight</persName>
          <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoded by</resp>
          <persName>Katherine Poland</persName>
          <persName>Matthew Taylor</persName>
          <persName>Betsy Chou</persName>
          <persName>Emily Andrey</persName>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>IT-project consultation by</resp>
          <persName>Josh Honn</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
          <orgName>Brock University</orgName>
          <orgName>University of Leeds</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <principal>
          <persName/>
        </principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="1"/>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription, transformations, and notes</resp>
          <persName>Leah Knight</persName>
          <orgName>Brock University</orgName>
          <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
        </respStmt>
      </editionStmt>
      <extent/>
      <publicationStmt>
        <ab/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listBibl>
          <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
              <repository>See witness list.</repository>
            </msIdentifier>
          </msDesc>
        </listBibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p/>
      </projectDesc>
      <p>Transcriptions are encoded in TEI(P5)-conformant XML.</p>
      <samplingDecl>
        <p/>
      </samplingDecl>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction>
          <p>Apparent errors are preserved and editorial corrections provided using SIC and CORR tags, but only where the editor conjectures that the original scribe or compositor would have recognized the instance as an error. For example, what according to modern usage is incorrect subject/verb agreement might have been deemed acceptable to a seventeenth-century scribe or compositor. All such instances are treated instead using the ORIG and REG tags. (See below.)</p>
          <p>Corrections and annotations made within the scope of the original document either by its original authors, owners, and/or transcribers are noted using ADD tags. These annotations and may be further explained within NOTE tags, as added by the editors of this digital edition, for display within the apparatus.</p>
        </correction>
        <normalization>
          <p>Original spellings, abbreviations, and orthography are preserved. Where in the manuscripts a character's status as majuscule or minuscule is ambiguous, the editor has silently chosen one or the other based on context and judgment (i.e., does not register such ambiguity in either the markup or the notes).</p>
        </normalization>
        <quotation>
          <p>Original quotation marks, if any, are preserved.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation>
          <p>Original hyphenation is preserved.</p>
        </hyphenation>
      </editorialDecl>
      <charDecl>
        <!-- Ligature combinations for which there are currently no corresponding Unicode codepoints. -->
        <glyph xml:id="ffllig">
          <glyphName>Handwritten 'ff' ligature, used in handwriting to represent modern F</glyphName>
        </glyph>
      </charDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="DDC22">
          <bibl>
            <title>Dewey Decimal Classification</title>
            <edition/>
            <publisher/>
            <pubPlace/>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-GB">British English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <!-- dewey decimal system class code 821: English Poetry -->
        <classCode scheme="DDC22">821</classCode>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
    <!-- List of all images associated with this document -->
    <graphic url="./document_images/7610_251.jpg" xml:id="f7610_251"/>
  </facsimile>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="ft">Transcription of manuscript: By <persName xml:id="lknight">Leah Knight</persName> and <persName xml:id="wwall">Wendy Wall</persName>.</witness>
          <witness xml:id="ee">Elemental edition: By <persName>Leah Knight</persName> and <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>.</witness>
         <witness xml:id="ae">Amplified edition: By <persName>Emma K. Atwood</persName>.</witness>
        </listWit>
      </div>
    </front>

    <body>

      <!-- Each page break should be represented wih a block like this with the correct facs reference-->
      <app>
        <rdg wit="#ft">
          <pb ed="#ft" facs="#f7610_251" n="124r"/>
        </rdg>
        <rdg wit="#ee">
          <pb ed="#ee" facs="#f7610_251"/>
        </rdg>
        <rdg wit="#ae">
          <pb ed="#ae" facs="#f7610_251"/>
        </rdg>
      </app>

      <head>
        <app type="title">
          <rdg wit="#ft"><fw facs="#f7610_069" type="pageNum" place="margin-topright">PG#</fw>[Emblem 47]</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">The Turtle and his Paramour<lb/>(Emblem 47)</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">The Turtle and his Paramour</rdg>
        </app>
        <app type="editorialnote">
          <rdg wit="#ft">
            <note type="editorialnote">In these transcriptions we preserve as many details of the original material, textual, and graphic properties of Hester Pulter’s manuscript verse as we have found practical. Whenever possible, for instance, original spelling, punctuation, capitalization, lineation, insertions, deletions, alterations, spacing between words and lines, and indentation are all maintained; abbreviations and brevigraphs are not expanded; and superscript and subscript representations are retained. <ref target="//pulterproject.northwestern.edu/about-project-conventions.html#top" type="new-window-url">See full conventions for the transcriptions here.</ref></note>
          </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">
            <note type="editorialnote">The aim of the elemental edition is to make the poems accessible to the largest variety of readers, which involves modernizing spelling and punctuation as well as adding basic glosses. Spelling and punctuation reflect current standard American usage; punctuation highlights syntax which might otherwise be obscure. Outmoded but still familiar word forms (“thou,” “‘tis,” “hold’st”) are not modernized, and we do not modernize grammar when the sense remains legible. After a brief headnote aimed at offering a “way in” to the poem’s unique qualities and connections with other verse by Pulter or her contemporaries, the edition features a minimum of notes and interpretative framing to allow more immediate engagement with the poem. Glosses clarify synonyms or showcase various possible meanings in Pulter’s time. Other notes identify named people and places or clarify obscure material. We rely (without citation) primarily on the Oxford English Dictionary (OED), the Oxford Reference database, and the King James Version (KJV) of the Bible. When we rely on Alice Eardley’s edition of Pulter’s work, we cite her text generally (“Eardley”); other sources are cited in full. The result is an edition we consider a springboard for further work on Pulter’s poetry. <ref target="//pulterproject.northwestern.edu/about-project-conventions.html#elemental-edition" type="new-window-url">See full conventions for this edition here.</ref></note></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">
            <note type="editorialnote">I have chosen a semi-diplomatic transcription, retaining the original spelling, capitalization, and punctuation. I have retained spelling errors (e.g., E’ne as a likely cognate for E’en, itself a single-syllable elision of Even). However, I have omitted redundant superscripts and clear strikethrough corrections for ease of reading. I hope that retaining these original choices might illuminate some instances of wordplay (e.g., chaste and chased) or welcome moments of ambiguity and plural possibility into the text. My notes offer cultural and literary context and provide cross-references to Pulter’s possible sources.</note>
          </rdg>
        </app>
        <app type="headnote">
          <rdg wit="#ee">
              <note type="headnote">This poem was certainly not written for an era with heightened awareness of sexual harassment. With its moral based, as in so many of Pulter’s emblems, on a combination of zoological, mythological, and historical (or pseudo-historical) precedents, the speaker advises women seeking love to demonstrate “a virgin modesty”—which, in this case, involves playing hard to get, even in response to “desired embraces.” The female turtle at the heart of the poem is a surprisingly complex character: “as wise, as fair, as chaste, as coy,” she imagines (through the speaker’s focalization) accepting a mate as a matter of “sell[ing] her freedom,” and at once desires and fears the male’s embraces. The comparison of her to the mythological Daphne, who was not coyly seeking to increase Apollo’s desire but running from a would-be rapist, adds tension to the story of the turtle’s happy desire to get her man. While such complex motivations, especially in a turtle, are necessarily intriguing, there is also something more than slightly disconcerting in Pulter’s impassive likening of this successful courtship to a sword being stabbed through a vassal’s foot, and in her knowing invocation of a worn and wearing paradox: “love repulsed doth more increase desire.”</note>
          </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">
            <note type="headnote">
            <p>Pulter’s “The Turtle and his Paramour” is a short emblem poem that recounts a turtle’s persistent pursuit of a mate. The paramour is a largely unwilling partner, impossibly described as wise, fair, chaste, modest, fearful, reluctant and, simultaneously, coy. Conventional in many ways—in form, theme, and allusion—this poem also contends with the complex problem of early modern consent and offers direct advice to women readers at its conclusion. Pulter’s gendered subject position transforms this poem into a subversive critique of coquetry rather than a recapitulation of the familiar game of cat and mouse (or, in this case, turtle and turtle). Rather than a playful account of two amorous animals, this poem offers a pointed interrogation of Renaissance ideas about rape.</p>

            <p>Of exceptional note is Pulter’s command of form. The heroic couplets mimic the language of epic poetry, though the poem comprises only twenty-two lines. The form elevates the subject matter, casting sexual assault as a subject worthy of epic weight. Pulter deploys other formal poetic devices with skillful wit. When she breaks the regular iambic meter with anapests and dactyls, she uses sound to emphasize the slow, methodical terror of brutal immobilization (“Soe the grand Sygnior makes his vassels yield” (15)) or the frenzied speed of the turtle’s chase (“Love made him nimble fear made her make hast” (9)). In this particular line, the caesura between “nimble” and “fear” separates the two figures mid-chase as form echoes poetic function.</p>

            <p>Pulter’s emblem poems derive inspiration from natural history and from the popular genre of emblem books. Mara R. Wade defines the emblem as “one of the primary vehicles of cultural knowledge during the early modern period (ca. 1500–1750), capable of expressing highly complex ideas in compact and compelling forms.”<seg>1<note type="gloss">Wade, Mara R. <ref target="//emblematica.grainger.illinois.edu/help/what-emblem" type="new-window-url">“What is an Emblem?”</ref> Emblematica Online. 2022.</note></seg> Typically, emblems consist of both words and pictures, yet Pulter evokes pictures with her words. Emblem 47 is not her only emblem poem to feature a turtle. <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="74">The Turtle (Emblem 8)</ref> also centers on a female turtle, but there it serves as a warning of the turtle’s physical vulnerability: “But do but turn this turtle to the skies: / She sighs and sobs and discontented lies / And in this passion, bathed in tears, she dies” (5–7). <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="79">The Porcupine (Emblem 13)</ref> features a tortoise who is similarly vulnerable but whose shell protects her soul: “What if they hurt my flesh? ’Tis but my shell / That suffers; my enfranchised soul is well” (30–31). <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="85">This Poor Turtledove (Emblem 20)</ref> features a turtledove, a distinct animal with an analogous name that, like Emblem 47, emphasizes constancy, as she encourages her readers to “imitate this turtledove” (21).</p>

            <p>Emblem 47 begins with an amorous turtle burning, in Petrarchan fashion, with “Reinflamd desire.” This reference echoes other aggressive pursuers in Pulter’s work, like Rodrigo the rapist in <title rend="italic">The Unfortunate Florinda</title> who is “inflamed with the love of Florinda.”<seg>2<note type="gloss">Pulter, Hester. <title rend="italic">Poems, Emblems, and The Unfortunate Florinda</title>. Ed. Alice Eardley. Toronto: Iter, 2014, p. 283.</note></seg> Interestingly, the “Beauteous Paramore” does not catch the turtle’s eye until line 3. His desire is a precondition that exists before she appears. It is the “Geniall Universall fire” that burns in line 1—an animalistic desire to procreate, reminiscent of Shakespeare’s urging the fair youth to reproduce in the first line of his sonnet sequence (“From fairest creatures we desire increase”<seg>3<note type="gloss">Shakespeare, William. <title rend="italic">The Riverside Shakespeare, 2<add place="above">nd</add> ed.</title> Ed. G. Blakemore Evans and J. J. M. Tobin. New York: Houghton Mifflin, 1996, p. 1843.</note></seg>). This language is purposefully deceptive, though. What fronts as “genial” in the sense of a pleasant, welcoming, or kind demeanor is in fact “genial” in the sense that this pursuer is hell-bent on generation, procreation, and sex by any means necessary to achieve his goal.</p>

            <p>In her 2014 edition of Pulter’s poetry, Alice Eardley cites Holland’s translation of Pliny’s <title rend="italic">Natural History</title> as a possible source for her depiction of the turtles.<seg>4<note type="gloss">Pulter, Hester. <title rend="italic">Poems, Emblems, and The Unfortunate Florinda</title>. Ed. Alice Eardley. Toronto: Iter, 2014, p. 253 n. 443.</note></seg> Holland published his English translation in 1601 and describes tortoise copulation as follows: “The female flieth from the male, and will not abide to engender, untill such time as he pricke her behind and sticke somewhat in her taile for running away from him so fast.”<seg>5<note type="gloss">Pliny the Elder. <title rend="italic"><ref target="//penelope.uchicago.edu/holland/index.html" type="new-window-url">The Historie of the Wolrd. Commonly called, The Naturall Historie of C. Plinius Secundus.</ref></title> Trans. Philemon Holland. London, 1601, 9.10.</note></seg> This adversarial relationship between male and female tortoise is expanded in the Renaissance bestiary <title rend="italic">The history of four-footed beasts and serpents</title>. In this illustrated account, Edward Topsell expounds upon tortoise (and sea turtle) copulation, giving human characteristics and motivations to these animals in their sexual pursuit: “the male is very salacious and given to carnal copulation, but the female is not so; for when she is attempted by the male, they fight it out by the teeth, and at last the male overcometh, whereat he rejoyceth as much as one that in a hard conflict, fight, or battail, hath won a fair Woman; the reason of this unwillingnesse is, because it is exceedingly painful to the female.”<seg>6<note type="gloss">Topsell, Edward. <title rend="italic">The history of four-footed beasts and serpents.</title> London: Printed by E. Cotes for G. Sawbridge, 1607, 1608, 1658, p. 795.</note></seg> Topsell further elaborates that “the female [tortoise of the sea] resisteth the copulation with the male, until he set against her a stalk or stem of some tree or plant.”<seg>7<note type="gloss">Topsell, Edward. <title rend="italic">The history of four-footed beasts and serpents.</title> London: Printed by E. Cotes for G. Sawbridge, 1607, 1608, 1658, p. 798.</note></seg>
            <figure>
              <graphic url="/images/poems/p112-1.jpg"/>
                  <figDesc>From Edward Topsell’s <title rend="italic"><ref target="//archive.org/details/historyoffourfoo00tops/page/794/mode/2up" type="new-window-url"></ref>The history of four-footed beasts and serpents</title> (London: Printed by E. Cotes, 1658), p. 794.</figDesc>
            </figure> 
            By using the turtle for her allegory, Pulter speaks in shorthand about the salacious motivations driving  sexual pursuit, reinforcing the reluctance and legitimate fear on the part of the paramour. The Ovidian anthropomorphism of the turtle works both ways: it humanizes the turtle in order to moralize, but it also likens Renaissance men who relentlessly pursue women to mere animals.</p>

            <p>At first, the choice of a turtle seems odd for depicting a swift and aggressive chase, but this is likely due to a conflation between the turtle and the tortoise in Pulter’s sources. Aesop characterizes the tortoise as slow and steady; other Renaissance emblems associate turtles with the paradox “<foreign rend="italic">festina lente</foreign>,” depicting a turtle decorated with sails to “<hi rend="italic">make haste slowly</hi>.” 
            <figure>
              <graphic url="/images/poems/p112-2.jpg"/>
                  <figDesc>Three devices of the printer Bartolomeo Sermartelli: Courtesy Provenance Online Project and Google Books, cited in Liz Broadwell, “<ref target="//uniqueatpenn.wordpress.com/2020/09/02/turtles-all-the-way-down-woodcut-devices-of-bartolomeo-sermartelli/" type="new-window-url">Turtles All the Way Down: Woodcut Devices of Bartolomeo Sermartelli.</ref>”<title rend="italic"> Unique at Penn</title>. Kislak Center for Special Collections, Rare Books and Manuscripts. 2 September 2020.</figDesc>
            </figure> 
            Neither tortoises nor turtles are known for their speed, at least not on land. But importantly, Pulter’s turtles are both sea turtles: she spies his head “above the Waves” (7). Turtles may be slow on land, but they are fast in the water. This duality is key to the turtle’s pursuit.</p>

            <p>The turtle shows up in another common Renaissance emblem tradition, depicting an eagle carrying a turtle to a dizzying height in his talons, “<foreign rend="italic">ut lapsu graviore ruat</foreign>” or “<foreign rend="italic">ut corruat</foreign>,” so that it may fall.  
            <figure>
              <graphic url="/images/poems/p112-3.jpg"/>
                  <figDesc>Juan Francisco de Villava, <title rend="italic">Empresas espirituales y morales</title>. Baeza, Spain, 1613.</figDesc>
            </figure> 
            This emblematic appearance of the turtle can be read as a critique of “excessive ambition.”<seg>8<note type="gloss">D’Onofrio, Julia. <ref target="//www.studiolum.com/en/silva7.htm" type="new-window-url">“Sancho Panza and the Turtle.”</ref> <title rend="italic">Silva de varia lección.</title> 2005.</note></seg> The turtle will inevitably be dropped from on high, smashing its shell and making it the easier prey. Pulter uses this image in <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="96">Old Aeschylus (Emblem 31)</ref> when she recounts the legend of Old Aeschylus’ death, killed by a falling tortoise dropped by a passing eagle: “A Tow’ring Eagle let her prey fall down / In hope to break the Escallop on his Crown. / She had her wish: it broke the fatal Shell, / And struck the Poet’s Rhyming Soul to Hell” (7–10). While this particular emblematic reading is not directly pertinent to Emblem 47, it does demonstrate the multivalent resonances of the turtle in Renaissance culture. Perhaps Pulter’s turtle is similarly ambitious (and self-destructive) in his pursuit.</p>

            <p>Another puzzle derives from the Renaissance emblem tradition that depicts Venus, or Aphrodite, standing atop a turtle, or tortoise, as in Alciato’s 16<add place="above">th-</add>century emblem.<seg>9<note type="gloss">For a study of this trope, see Dougherty, Carol L. “Why Does Aphrodite Have Her Foot on That Turtle?” <title rend="italic">Arion: A Journal of the Humanities and the Classics</title> 27.3 (Winter 2020), pp. 25–48.</note></seg> 
            <figure>
              <graphic url="/images/poems/p112-4.jpg"/>
                  <figDesc>Aphrodite with foot on tortoise. Andrea Alciato, <title rend="italic">Livret des emblemes</title> (Paris 1536). By permission of University of Glasgow Library, Archives & the iconography of Special Collections.</figDesc>
            </figure>

        
            Victoria E. Burke’s Curation <ref type="pp-curation-ref" target="/poems/ee/the-porcupine-emblem-13/#early-modern-tortoises">Early Modern Tortoises</ref> cites Topsell, Alciato, and Anne Southwell and considers “the female tortoise’s association with domesticity,” as she carries her home on her back. This frame of reference makes the association with the goddess of erotic love particularly curious.<seg>10<note type="gloss">For more on this connection between Venus and early modern women, see Kaznowska, Helena. “Women Are from Venus: Addressing Female Agency with Classical Allegory.” <title rend="italic">Audience Reception in the Early Modern Period.</title> Ed. John R. Decker and Mitzi Kirkland-Ives. New York: Routledge, 2021. pp. 276–302.</note></seg> Dorothy Stephens suggests that the Venus’s association with the tortoise evokes a teasing brand of sexuality marked by “reluctant, amorous delay”: “Because a tortoise does cover ground, despite being slow, the image of Venus with her foot upon a tortoise leaves itself open to interpretation as an emblem not of immovable chastity but of sweet reluctant, amorous delay … for being slow and playing fast-and-loose are not mutually exclusive.”<seg>11<note type="gloss">Stephens, Dorothy. <title rend="italic">The Limits of Eroticism in Post-Petrarchan Narrative: Conditional Pleasure from Spenser to Marvell.</title> Cambridge, UK: Cambridge University Press, 1998, p. 200, n. 17.</note></seg> This gives credence to a reading of the female turtle as a purposefully coy paramour, playfully refusing the turtle’s advances to maintain her chaste appeal while secretly anticipating the inevitable embrace. [See Curation: <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="#ctxs">Approaches to Early Modern Chastity</ref>].</p>

            <p>But this Ovidian reading—whereby “no” means “yes” and, as Marlowe translates it, “red shame becomes white cheeks”<seg>12<note type="gloss">Ovid. <title rend="italic"><ref target="//www.proquest.com/books/ouids-elegies-three-bookes-c-m-epigrames-i-d/docview/2240871421/se-2" type="new-window-url">Ouid’s Elegies Three Bookes. by C.M. Epigrames by I.D</ref></title> [Amores. Epigrams. Epigrams]. London: 1603, Book 1, Elegy 8, line 35. </note></seg>—is further complicated by the violence of Pulter’s ensuing metaphors. The two turtles are first likened to Daphne and Apollo, an aggressive pursuit so unwelcome that Daphne prays to be transformed into a tree to escape. Unfortunately, the faster Daphne runs away, the more Apollo wants her: Daphne “seemed most lovely to his fancy in her flight.”<seg>13<note type="gloss">Ovid. <title rend="italic">Metamorphoses.</title> “Daphne and Phoebus.” Trans. Brookes More. Boston: Cornhill Publishing, 1922, 1.531–2.</note></seg> Troublingly, Pulter’s narrator similarly warns, “Love Repulst doth more increase desire,” invoking a skewed logic endemic to rape culture. [See Curation: <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="#ctxs">“Love Repulst”: Paradoxical Desire</ref>].</p>

            <p><hi rend="italic">Rape culture</hi> is a sociological concept originating with second-wave feminism in the 1970s that identifies the normalization of (male) sexual violence and the blame placed on victims of sexual assault. Peter Herman aptly notes Pulter’s evocation of a gender binary that shapes men’s and women’s expected sexual behavior in his analysis of Pulter’s romance <title rend="italic">The Unfortunate Florinda</title>: “Pulter situates the divide between the chaste and the licentious, between men as sexual predators and women as their prey.”<seg>14<note type="gloss">Herman, Peter C. “Lady Hester Pulter’s <title rend="italic">The Unfortunate Florinda</title>: Race, Religion, and the Politics of Rape.” <title rend="italic">Renaissance Quarterly</title> 63.4 (2010), p. 1226.</note></seg> Kay Stanton discusses the pressing connections between contemporary rape culture and early modern antecedents in <title rend="italic">Shakespeare/Sex: Contemporary Readings in Gender and Sexuality</title>.<seg>15<note type="gloss">Stanton, Kay. “‘For me, I am the mistress of my fate’: Lucrece, rape culture, and feminist political activism.” <title rend="italic">Shakespeare/Sex: Contemporary Readings in Gender and Sexuality.</title> Ed. Jennifer Drouin. New York: Bloomsbury Publishing, 2020, p. 26.</note></seg> In her discussion of Shakespeare’s “The Rape of Lucrece,” Stanton considers the ways women are blamed for their own rapes. “The fault,” Stanton notes, is “not on the whore side of a virgin-whore binary in a short skirt or too much makeup, as is often the accusation against women today, but rather on its virginal side.”<seg>16<note type="gloss">Stanton, Kay. “‘For me, I am the mistress of my fate’: Lucrece, rape culture, and feminist political activism.” <title rend="italic">Shakespeare/Sex: Contemporary Readings in Gender and Sexuality.</title> Ed. Jennifer Drouin. New York: Bloomsbury Publishing, 2020, p. 35.</note></seg> Superlative virtues make an attractive victim in many early modern representations, Pulter’s included. In many early modern indications of rape culture, the more chaste or virginal a woman appears, and the more she resists sexual advances, the more enticing she becomes to her attacker. As Pulter puts it in this emblem, “Oyl Thrown on to quench augments the fire” (20).</p>

            <p>Where Pulter’s turtles differ from Daphne and Apollo is not in the chase but in the catch: Daphne prays to transform her body in order to elude capture, but the female turtle is caught, a perverse “love conquers all” outcome: “Thus Love then fear did prove more Swift in Chase” (13). Cynthia E. Garrett connects such poetic rationalization of rape to the legal practice of “post facto consent”: “the medieval concept of post facto consent lends credence to the timeline built into Ovid’s legitimation of male force, in which a woman may ‘at first’ resist but will eventually yield willingly. Indeed, the notion that a woman can yield internally while resisting externally defers denial indefinitely.”<seg>17<note type="gloss">Garrett, Cynthia E. “Sexual Consent and the Art of Love in the Early Modern English Lyric.” <title rend="italic">Studies in English Literature, 1500–1900</title> 44.1 (Winter 2004), p. 41.</note></seg> Indeed, it seems the female turtle consents to the match after the fact—he is now described as “her love” as if they have come to a mutually affectionate arrangement—though the resistance is palpable: “Which forct her Yield Unto her Loves imbrace” (14). In her study <title rend="italic">Writing Rape, Writing Women in Early Modern England</title>, Jocelyn Catty explores the historical phenomenon of a “yielding rape” that casts women as both a helpless victim and a responsible agent: “although a woman is apparently not to blame for a ‘yielding-rape’, this definition [that is, the term ‘yielding rape’ itself] subtly allocates a degree of responsibility to her. However resolutely she may have clung to the ideal of chastity, however she may have resisted, if verbal threats or physical violence induce her to <hi rend="italic">yield</hi>, she is technically consenting.”<seg>18<note type="gloss">Catty, Jocelyn. <title rend="italic">Writing Rape, Writing Women in Early Modern England: Unbridled Speech.</title> New York: Palgrave Macmillan, 2011, p. 32.</note></seg> The perception of the turtle’s “imbrace” is thus open to interpretation, ambiguously consensual and menacing. [See Curation: “Forct Her Yield”: Consent and Early Modern Rape]</p>

            <p>Yielding to sexual violence could, ironically, offer early modern women a sense of agency. If they perceive the outcome as inevitable, yielding might allow them some control over the situation and a degree of preserved respectability. Pulter entertains these alternatives in <title rend="italic">The Unfortunate Florinda</title>. Florinda, “a most unparalleled lady of an electrical beauty, superlative in all virtues, especially chastity,”<seg>19<note type="gloss">Pulter, Hester. <title rend="italic">Poems, Emblems, and The Unfortunate Florinda</title>. Ed. Alice Eardley. Toronto: Iter, 2014, p. 274.</note></seg> vehemently resists her rape and publicly denounces the violation. However, Zabra chooses to yield rather than resist: “The royal Zabra, wisely considering the violence of the king’s affection, chose rather to yield upon honorable terms than to be taken by storm.”<seg>20<note type="gloss">Pulter, Hester. <title rend="italic">Poems, Emblems, and The Unfortunate Florinda</title>. Ed. Alice Eardley. Toronto: Iter, 2014, p. 273.</note></seg> Florinda’s “too, too proud” chastity attracts her rapist and exacerbates her suffering; her superlative virtues are, to her detriment, what make her so attractive a victim. Zabra’s “yielding,” like the paramour’s in Emblem 47, preserves her social standing and her sense of self.</p>

            <p>Importantly, yielding does not negate violence. The violence of the catch is only reinforced by the whiplash shift Pulter makes to a pseudo-historical reference, invoking the brutality of the Grand Seignior, Turkish sultan of the Ottoman Empire: “Soe the grand Sygnior makes his vassels yield / When through their foot his cruell spheir they feild” (15–16). This metaphor evokes an alluring orientalist fantasy, mixing “terrors, pleasures, [and] desires.”<seg>21<note type="gloss">Said, Edward. <title rend="italic">Orientalism</title>. New York: Random House, 1979, p. 63.</note></seg> While the paramour’s yielding is shaded in gray, this yielding is expressly involuntary; there is no illusion of choice. These vassals are quite literally stopped in their tracks with a spear through their foot, and like Daphne, they are rooted to the ground, unable to run. Eardley provides this commentary: “A precise reference has not been identified, but this is a reference to a Turkish emperor using his spear to force the women in his seraglio, or harem, to yield to his advance.”<seg>22<note type="gloss">Pulter, Hester. <title rend="italic">Poems, Emblems, and The Unfortunate Florinda</title>. Ed. Alice Eardley. Toronto: Iter, 2014, p. 254 n. 446.</note></seg> A possible resonance is the legend of an Ottoman footrace that would allow a condemned man to attempt to outrun his executioner.<seg>23<note type="gloss">Dash, Mike. “<ref target="//www.smithsonianmag.com/history/the-ottoman-empires-life-or-death-race-164064882/" type="new-window-url">The Ottoman Empire’s Life-or-Death Race.</ref>” <title rend="italic">Smithsonian Magazine</title> 22 March 2012.</note></seg> Such a mythology evokes the Daphne and Apollo myth, the dichotomy between speed and stillness, and the serious repercussions of the chase.</p>

            <p>Pulter ends her poem with a direct appeal—and warning—to her women readers. Pulter advises, “the Weomen of this age may see / Nothing gains love like virgin Modestie.” Coming on the heels of such violent metaphors, “love” feels like an unsavory euphemism. Call it what you will: love—unwanted attention—post facto consent—rape. If this is the reward for “virgin Modestie,” perhaps the game isn’t worth playing. As Jocelyn Catty argues in <title rend="italic">Writing Rape, Writing Women in Early Modern England</title>, “The concept of female sexual ‘coyness’, then, which at its most extreme is portrayed as a masochistic desire for violence, becomes closely connected with rape.”<seg>24<note type="gloss">Catty, Jocelyn. <title rend="italic">Writing Rape, Writing Women in Early Modern England: Unbridled Speech.</title> New York: Palgrave Macmillan, 2011, p. 97.</note></seg> In asking her women readers to witness, to “see” this outcome, Pulter critiques the social role of coy affectation from the woman’s perspective.</p>

            <p>Pulter’s advice climaxes in an ambiguously worded conclusion: “Ladyes leave your Impudence for shame / Let not the Turtle have A Chaster flame” (21–22). The imperative command, “leave your Impudence for shame,” offers a few alternative interpretations. Impudence might reference immodest behavior (OED def. 1); in her edition, Eardley glosses “impudence” as “shamelessness; immodesty.”<seg>25<note type="gloss">Pulter, Hester. <title rend="italic">Poems, Emblems, and The Unfortunate Florinda.</title> Ed. Alice Eardley. Toronto: Iter, 2014, p. 254 n. 447.</note></seg> However, read another way, it might also reference a “cool confidence” (OED def. 3), more in line with coy performance. Is Pulter suggesting that the reader should “leave your immodesty” or “leave your cool confidence”? The ambiguity hints at the nature of a sexual double standard—women must be chaste enough to avoid shame, but not so performatively chaste to draw unwanted attention. Her use of the phrase “for shame” further complicates her message. Taken simply, impudence is being traded for shame. But punctuated differently, Pulter may be scolding her women readers for their behavior: “for shame!” Pulter offers her final piece of advice in the last line: “Let not the Turtle have A Chaster flame.” Here, she reminds her readers that they would be wise not to seem <hi rend="italic">too</hi> chaste, thus avoiding a situation whereby they become the turtle’s next victim. Pulter thus advocates for chastity (as she does explicitly in <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="84">The Elephant (Emblem 19)</ref> and <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="99">Mark But Those Hogs (Emblem 34)</ref>, among others) but also warns women against seeming <hi rend="italic">too</hi> chaste, too precious, too modest so as to attract undue attention from the wrong admirers.</p>

            </note>
          </rdg>
        </app>
      </head>

      <l n="1">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft"><fw type="seqNum" place="inline">47</fw>Whenas that Geniall Univerſall &ff;ire</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee"><seg>When as<note type="gloss">Seeing as; when</note></seg> that <seg>genial<note type="gloss">of or relating to marriage or procreation; natural</note></seg> universal fire</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">When as that <seg>Geniall<note type="gloss">a possible pun relating to both marriage and procreative sex (e.g. genealogy) (OED def. 1) and a kind, jovial spirit (OED def. 5a)</note></seg> <seg>Universall<note type="gloss">The burning fire of desire comes directly from the Petrarchan sonnet tradition. See <title rend="italic">The Poetry of Petrarch</title>, Trans. David Young. New York: Farrar, Straus and Giroux, 2004.</note></seg> fire</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="2">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Had in the <seg>Turtle<del>s</del><note type="physical">vertical strike-through</note></seg> Reinflamd deſire</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Had in the turtle reinflamed desire,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Had in the Turtle Reinflamd desire</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="3">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Hee having found a Beavtious Paramore</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">He, having found a beauteous <seg>paramour<note type="gloss">object of love</note></seg>,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Hee having found a Beauteous <seg>Paramore<note type="gloss">an object of love and desire, especially associated with chivalric romance (OED def. 2a, 2c); an illicit lover or affair partner (OED def. 3)</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="4">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Her Love, and pitty, both hee doth implore</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Her love and pity both he doth implore.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Her Love, and pitty, both hee doth implore</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="5">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">But Shee as Wiſe, as &ff;aire, as Chast, as Coy</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">But she, as wise, as fair, as chaste, as coy,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">But shee as Wise, as faire, as <seg>Chast<note type="gloss">See Curation:<ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="#ctxs">Approaches to Early Modern Chastity</ref>. “Chaste” and “chased” operate as an aural pun, connecting the two major themes of the poem.</note></seg>, as <seg>Coy<note type="gloss">“displaying shyness or modesty, esp. in matters of love or sex; not receptive to romantic or sexual advances. Often with connotations of affectation, pretence, or flirtatiousness” (OED def. 2ai); “aloof, distant” (OED def. 3a)</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="6">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Was Loth to Sell her &ff;reedome for A Toy</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Was loath to sell her freedom for a <seg>toy<note type="gloss">amorous sport, dallying; amusement; trifling speech; idle fancy; thing of little value</note></seg>;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Was Loth to sell her freedome for a Toy</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="7">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">&ff;or Having Spie’d above the Waves his Head</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">For having spied, above the waves, his head,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">For Having spied above the Waves his Head</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="8">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Shee Chastly his deſir’d imbraces &ff;led</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">She chastely his desired embraces fled.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Shee Chastly his desir’d imbraces fled</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="9">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Love made him nimble &ff;ear made her make haſt</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Love made him <seg>nimble<note type="gloss">light and quick in movement; versatile; clever</note></seg>; fear made her make haste;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>Love made him nimble fear made her make hast<note type="critical">This line echoes the Daphne and Apollo chase in Ovid’s <title rend="italic">Metamorphoses</title>: “one / with hope pursued, the other fled in fear” (1.542–543).</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="10">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Soe Daphne from her lover fled as fast</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">So <seg>Daphne from her lover fled<note type="gloss">In Ovid’s <title rend="italic">Metamorphoses</title>, Daphne is a nymph committed to virginity who runs from the lustful god Apollo, who seeks to rape her; she is turned into a laurel tree by the gods in order to help her escape.</note></seg> as fast.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Soe <seg>Daphne<note type="gloss">In Ovid’s <title rend="italic">Metamorphoses</title>, Daphne has vowed virginity but Apollo relentlessly pursues her. Daphne prays for protection and is changed into a laurel tree. Apollo wears the branches of the laurel in her memory (1.452–566).</note></seg> from her lover fled as fast</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="11">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">At last his Breath did move her flowing Haire</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">At last, <seg>his breath did move her flowing hair<note type="gloss">Apollo’s breath moves Daphne’s hair when he is near enough almost to overtake her.</note></seg>;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">At last <seg>his Breath did move her flowing Haire<note type="gloss">In Ovid’s <title rend="italic">Metamorphoses</title>, Daphne can feel Apollo’s breath on her hair: “he who followed, borne on wings of love, / permitted her no rest and gained on her, / until his warm breath mingled in her hair” (1.544–546).</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="12">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">En’e Soe the Turtle did or’e Catch his &ff;aire</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">E’en so the turtle did <seg>o’ercatch<note type="gloss">overtake</note></seg> his fair.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">E’ne soe the Turtle did or’e Catch his faire</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="13">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Thus Love then &ff;ear did prove more Swift in Chaſe</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Thus love than fear did prove more swift in chase,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Thus Love <seg>then<note type="gloss">The spelling variant of “then” (sequential adverb) or “than” (comparative conjunction) makes this an ambiguous line.</note></seg> fear did prove more Swift in Chase</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="14">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Which forct her Yield Unto her Loves imbrace</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Which forced her yield unto her love’s embrace.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Which <seg>forct her Yield<note type="gloss">See Curation: <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="#ctxs">“Forct Her Yield”: Consent and Early Modern Rape</ref>.</note></seg> Unto her Loves imbrace</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="15">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Soe the grand Sygnior makes his vaſſels yield</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">So the <seg>Grand Seignior<note type="gloss">the Ottoman Sultan</note></seg> makes his <seg>vassals<note type="gloss">subordinates; servants; subjects</note></seg> yield</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Soe the <seg>grand Sygnior<note type="gloss">The Grand Seignior was the Turkish Sultan of the Ottoman Empire, a brutal and imposing figure in the English popular imagination.</note></seg> makes his <seg>vassels<note type="gloss">a feudal tenant (OED def. 1a); “a humble servant or subordinate” (OED def. 2b); “a base or abject person” (OED def. 3)</note></seg> yield</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="16">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">When through their foot his cruell <seg>Sp<del>h</del>eir<note type="physical">multiple and diagonal strike-through</note></seg> they feild</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee"><seg>When through their foot his cruel spear they feild<note type="gloss">“feild” was an early modern spelling for “feel.” The source for the claim that the Sultan threw spears at his subject’s feet is not known.</note></seg>.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">When through their foot his cruell spheir they <seg>feild<note type="gloss">a possible pun relating to both physical feeling and fealty, the obligation of a vassal to his feudal lord (OED def. 1)</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="17">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft"><seg>By<del>t</del><note type="physical">originally “But”; “t” struck-through multiple times on diagonal, then blotted; descender on “y” appears added later</note></seg> this the Weomen of this Age may See</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">By this the women of this age may see</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">By this the Weomen of this age may see</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="18">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft"><seg>Nothing’s<note type="physical">apostrophe and “s” either imperfectly erased or in light ink</note></seg> gains love like a virgin Modestie</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Nothing gains love like a virgin modesty;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Nothing gains love like virgin Modestie</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="19">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">&ff;or Love Repulst doth more increaſe deſire</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">For love repulsed doth more increase desire,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">For <seg>Love Repulst doth more increase desire<note type="gloss">See Curation: <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="#ctxs">“Love Repulst”: Paradoxical Desire</ref></note></seg>.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="20">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">As Oyl Thrown on to quench augments the fire</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">As oil thrown on to quench augments the fire.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">As Oyl Thrown on to quench augments the fire</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="21">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Then Ladyes leave your Impudence for Shame</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Then, ladies, leave your <seg>impudence<note type="gloss">immodesty, indelicacy</note></seg>, for shame;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Then Ladyes leave your <seg>Impudence<note type="gloss">“shamelessness; immodesty, indelicacy” (OED def. 1); “freedom from shamefastness; cool confidence” (OED def. 3)</note></seg> for shame</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="22">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Let not the Turtle have a Chaſter &ff;lame.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Let not the turtle have a chaster flame.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Let not the Turtle have A Chaster flame.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
        <app>
            <rdg type="milestone" wit="#ft">
                <milestone unit="poem" rend="straight-horline"/>
            </rdg>
        </app>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
