<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../src/vmachine.xsl"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
  schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI [

  <!ENTITY ff "<!-- ff ligature, representing capital modern day capital F, here represented as 'ff' -->ff">

  ]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mads.pp.23">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
          <title>To Astraea</title>
        <title type="sub">Poem #23</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Created by</resp>
          <persName>Leah Knight</persName>
          <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoded by</resp>
          <persName>Katherine Poland</persName>
          <persName>Matthew Taylor</persName>
          <persName>Betsy Chou</persName>
          <persName>Emily Andrey</persName>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>IT-project consultation by</resp>
          <persName>Josh Honn</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
          <orgName>Brock University</orgName>
          <orgName>University of Leeds</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <principal>
          <persName/>
        </principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="1"/>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription, transformations, and notes</resp>
          <persName>Leah Knight</persName>
          <orgName>Brock University</orgName>
          <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
        </respStmt>
      </editionStmt>
      <extent/>
      <publicationStmt>
        <ab/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listBibl>
          <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
              <repository>See witness list.</repository>
            </msIdentifier>
          </msDesc>
        </listBibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p/>
      </projectDesc>
      <p>Transcriptions are encoded in TEI(P5)-conformant XML.</p>
      <samplingDecl>
        <p/>
      </samplingDecl>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction>
          <p>Apparent errors are preserved and editorial corrections provided using SIC and CORR tags, but only where the editor conjectures that the original scribe or compositor would have recognized the instance as an error. For example, what according to modern usage is incorrect subject/verb agreement might have been deemed acceptable to a seventeenth-century scribe or compositor. All such instances are treated instead using the ORIG and REG tags. (See below.)</p>
          <p>Corrections and annotations made within the scope of the original document either by its original authors, owners, and/or transcribers are noted using ADD tags. These annotations and may be futher explained within NOTE tags, as added by the editors of this digital edition, for display within the apparatus.</p>
        </correction>
        <normalization>
          <p>Original spellings, abbreviations, and orthography are preserved. Where in the manuscripts a character's status as majuscule or miniscule is ambiguous, the editor has silently chosen one or the other based on context and judgment (i.e., does not register such ambiguity in either the markup or the notes).</p>
        </normalization>
        <quotation>
          <p>Original quotation marks, if any, are preserved.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation>
          <p>Original hyphenation is preserved.</p>
        </hyphenation>
      </editorialDecl>
      <charDecl>
        <!-- Ligature combinations for which there are currently no corresponding Unicode codepoints. -->
        <glyph xml:id="ffllig">
          <glyphName>Handwritten 'ff' ligature, used in handwriting to represent modern F</glyphName>
        </glyph>
      </charDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="DDC22">
          <bibl>
            <title>Dewey Decimal Classification</title>
            <edition/>
            <publisher/>
            <pubPlace/>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-GB">British English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <!-- dewey decimal system class code 821: English Poetry -->
        <classCode scheme="DDC22">821</classCode>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
    <!-- List of all images associated with this document -->
      <graphic url="./document_images/7610_086.jpg" xml:id="f7610_086"/>
  </facsimile>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="ft">Transcription of manuscript: By <persName xml:id="lknight">Leah Knight</persName> and <persName xml:id="wwall">Wendy Wall</persName>.</witness>
<!--          <witness xml:id="ee">Elemental edition: By <persName>Leah Knight</persName> and <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>.</witness>-->
<!--          <witness xml:id="ae">Amplified edition: By <persName>AE EDITOR</persName>.</witness>-->
        </listWit>
      </div>
    </front>

    <body>
      <app>
        <rdg wit="#ft">
          <pb ed="#ft" facs="#f7610_086" n="41v"/>
        </rdg>
        <rdg wit="#ee">
          <pb ed="#ee" facs="#f7610_086"/>
        </rdg>
        <rdg wit="#ae">
          <pb ed="#ae" facs="#f7610_086"/>
        </rdg>
      </app>
      <head>
        <app type="title">
            <rdg wit="#ft"><fw facs="#f7610_069" type="pageNum" place="margin-topright">PG#</fw>To Astrea</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">To <seg>Astraea<note type="gloss">the daughter of Aurora, the goddess of dawn or, here, “celestial morn” (l.1); also a classical goddess associated with justice and identified with the constellation Virgo; the last deity to leave Earth, who lived among humans in the Golden Age before fleeing the corruption of the Bronze Age</note></seg></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">AE TITLE</rdg>
        </app>
        <app type="editorialnote">
          <rdg wit="#ft">
            <note type="editorialnote">In these transcriptions we preserve as many details of the original material, textual, and graphic properties of Hester Pulter’s manuscript verse as we have found practical. Whenever possible, for instance, original spelling, punctuation, capitalization, lineation, insertions, deletions, alterations, spacing between words and lines, and indentation are all maintained; abbreviations and brevigraphs are not expanded; and superscript and subscript representations are retained. <ref target="http://pulterproject.northwestern.edu/about-project-conventions.html#top" type="new-window-url">See full conventions for the transcriptions here.</ref></note>
          </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">
            <note type="editorialnote">The aim of the elemental edition is to make the poems accessible to the largest variety of readers, which involves modernizing spelling and punctuation as well as adding basic glosses. Spelling and punctuation reflect current standard American usage; punctuation highlights syntax which might otherwise be obscure. Outmoded but still familiar word forms (“thou,” “‘tis,” “hold’st”) are not modernized, and we do not modernize grammar when the sense remains legible. After a brief headnote aimed at offering a “way in” to the poem’s unique qualities and connections with other verse by Pulter or her contemporaries, the edition features a minimum of notes and interpretative framing to allow more immediate engagement with the poem. Glosses clarify synonyms or showcase various possible meanings in Pulter’s time. Other notes identify named people and places or clarify obscure material. We rely (without citation) primarily on the Oxford English Dictionary (OED), the Oxford Reference database, and the King James Version (KJV) of the Bible. When we rely on Alice Eardley’s edition of Pulter’s work, we cite her text generally (“Eardley”); other sources are cited in full. The result is an edition we consider a springboard for further work on Pulter’s poetry. <ref target="http://pulterproject.northwestern.edu/about-project-conventions.html#elemental-edition" type="new-window-url">See full conventions for this edition here.</ref></note></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">
            <note type="editorialnote"></note>
          </rdg>
        </app>
        <app type="headnote">
          <rdg wit="#ee">
              <note type="headnote">Astraea, a classical goddess traditionally associated with justice but linked elsewhere by Pulter to truth, appears here as a beloved young girl or woman in the lap of her mother Aurora (goddess of dawn). While the speaker admires the glimmering beauty of this tableau, she also anxiously anticipates its dissolution and the departure of Astraea, perhaps as the dawn itself dissolves imperceptibly into the full blaze of day. After all, it was with the passing of earthly time through the soft light of the Golden Age into the brazen corruptions of the Bronze that Astraea first, according to legend, fled from where she ruled on earth into the skies, where the speaker now perceives her—so might she not, facing further signs of worldly “fraud,” flee yet farther off? To forestall this possibility, Pulter proposes a less spectacular but more Protestant form of political sanctuary within the temple of her own heart, where this female figure is daringly granted sole dominion—at least until Astraea and Pulter shall both, as the latter confidently anticipates, be elevated to a still greater station.</note>
          </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">
            <note type="headnote"></note>
          </rdg>
        </app>
      </head>

      <l n="1">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Thou bleſſed Birth of the Celestiall Morn</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Thou, blessed birth of the celestial morn</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="2">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Whoſe brighter Limbs noe Gem̄s needs to Adorn</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Whose brighter limbs no gems needs to adorn:</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="3">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Thou then apearest most Lovly to <w lemma="our"><abbr>o:r</abbr></w> Sight</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Thou then appear most lovely to our sight</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="4">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">When thou lyest naked in the Lap of Light</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">When thou lie naked in the lap of light.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="5">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Sweet Maid though thou art of Celestiall Birth</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Sweet maid, though thou art of celestial birth,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="6">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Leave not (ôh leave not) this our Orb of Earth</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Leave not (O leave not) this, our orb of Earth.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="7">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">If fraud Uſurps that thou canst find noe Rest</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">If fraud usurps, that thou canst find no rest,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="8">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Then take thy Lodging up in my poor breast</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Then take thy lodging up in my poor breast.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="9">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">There thou Shalt Monarchiſe and Rule alone</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">There thou shalt <seg>monarchize<note type="gloss">rule as a monarch</note></seg> and rule alone,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="10">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">None dareing to diſplace thee from thy throne</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">None daring to displace thee from thy throne</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="11">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Till Everlasting, Glory, Joy, and Love</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Till everlasting glory, joy, and love</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="12">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Shall us invite to live with them aboue.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Shall us invite to live with them above.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
        <app>
            <rdg type="milestone" wit="#ft">
                <milestone unit="poem" rend="curved-ascending"/>
            </rdg>
        </app>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
