<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../src/vmachine.xsl"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
  schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI [

  <!ENTITY ff "<!-- ff ligature, representing capital modern day capital F, here represented as 'ff' -->ff">

  ]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mads.pp.106">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
          <title>The Ostrich (Emblem 41)</title>
        <title type="sub">Poem #106</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Created by</resp>
          <persName>Leah Knight</persName>
          <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoded by</resp>
          <persName>Katherine Poland</persName>
          <persName>Matthew Taylor</persName>
          <persName>Katrina Garofalo</persName>
          <persName>Betsy Chou</persName>
          <persName>Sam Nguyen</persName>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>IT-project consultation by</resp>
          <persName>Josh Honn</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
          <orgName>Brock University</orgName>
          <orgName>University of Leeds</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <principal>
          <persName/>
        </principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="1"/>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription, transformations, and notes</resp>
          <persName>Leah Knight</persName>
          <orgName>Brock University</orgName>
          <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
        </respStmt>
      </editionStmt>
      <extent/>
      <publicationStmt>
        <ab/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listBibl>
          <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
              <repository>See witness list.</repository>
            </msIdentifier>
          </msDesc>
        </listBibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p/>
      </projectDesc>
      <p>Transcriptions are encoded in TEI(P5)-conformant XML.</p>
      <samplingDecl>
        <p/>
      </samplingDecl>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction>
          <p>Apparent errors are preserved and editorial corrections provided using SIC and CORR tags, but only where the editor conjectures that the original scribe or compositor would have recognized the instance as an error. For example, what according to modern usage is incorrect subject/verb agreement might have been deemed acceptable to a seventeenth-century scribe or compositor. All such instances are treated instead using the ORIG and REG tags. (See below.)</p>
          <p>Corrections and annotations made within the scope of the original document either by its original authors, owners, and/or transcribers are noted using ADD tags. These annotations and may be further explained within NOTE tags, as added by the editors of this digital edition, for display within the apparatus.</p>
        </correction>
        <normalization>
          <p>Original spellings, abbreviations, and orthography are preserved. Where in the manuscripts a character’s status as majuscule or minuscule is ambiguous, the editor has silently chosen one or the other based on context and judgment (i.e., does not register such ambiguity in either the markup or the notes).</p>
        </normalization>
        <quotation>
          <p>Original quotation marks, if any, are preserved.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation>
          <p>Original hyphenation is preserved.</p>
        </hyphenation>
      </editorialDecl>
      <charDecl>
        <!-- Ligature combinations for which there are currently no corresponding Unicode codepoints. -->
        <glyph xml:id="ffllig">
          <glyphName>Handwritten 'ff' ligature, used in handwriting to represent modern F</glyphName>
        </glyph>
      </charDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="DDC22">
          <bibl>
            <title>Dewey Decimal Classification</title>
            <edition/>
            <publisher/>
            <pubPlace/>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-GB">British English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <!-- dewey decimal system class code 821: English Poetry -->
        <classCode scheme="DDC22">821</classCode>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
      <graphic url="./document_images/7610_241.jpg" xml:id="f7610_241"/>
      <graphic url="./document_images/7610_242.jpg" xml:id="f7610_242"/>
  </facsimile>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="ft">Transcription of manuscript: By <persName xml:id="lknight">Leah Knight</persName> and <persName xml:id="wwall">Wendy Wall</persName>.</witness>
          <witness xml:id="ee">Elemental edition: By <persName>Leah Knight</persName> and <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>.</witness>
         <witness xml:id="ae">Amplified edition: By <persName>Claire Richie</persName>.</witness>
        </listWit>
      </div>
    </front>

    <body>

      <app>
        <rdg wit="#ft">
          <pb ed="#ft" facs="#f7610_241" n="119r"/>
        </rdg>
        <rdg wit="#ee">
          <pb ed="#ee" facs="#f7610_241"/>
        </rdg>
        <rdg wit="#ae">
          <pb ed="#ae" facs="#f7610_241"/>
        </rdg>
      </app>

      <head>
        <app type="title">
          <rdg wit="#ft"><fw facs="#f7610_069" type="pageNum" place="margin-topright">41</fw>[Emblem 41]</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">The Ostrich<lb/>(Emblem 41)</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Emblem 41</rdg>
        </app>
        <app type="editorialnote">
          <rdg wit="#ft">
            <note type="editorialnote">In these transcriptions we preserve as many details of the original material, textual, and graphic properties of Hester Pulter’s manuscript verse as we have found practical. Whenever possible, for instance, original spelling, punctuation, capitalization, lineation, insertions, deletions, alterations, spacing between words and lines, and indentation are all maintained; abbreviations and brevigraphs are not expanded; and superscript and subscript representations are retained. <ref target="//pulterproject.northwestern.edu/about-project-conventions.html#top" type="new-window-url">See full conventions for the transcriptions here.</ref></note>
          </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">
            <note type="editorialnote">The aim of the elemental edition is to make the poems accessible to the largest variety of readers, which involves modernizing spelling and punctuation as well as adding basic glosses. Spelling and punctuation reflect current standard American usage; punctuation highlights syntax which might otherwise be obscure. Outmoded but still familiar word forms (“thou,” “‘tis,” “hold’st”) are not modernized, and we do not modernize grammar when the sense remains legible. After a brief headnote aimed at offering a “way in” to the poem’s unique qualities and connections with other verse by Pulter or her contemporaries, the edition features a minimum of notes and interpretative framing to allow more immediate engagement with the poem. Glosses clarify synonyms or showcase various possible meanings in Pulter’s time. Other notes identify named people and places or clarify obscure material. We rely (without citation) primarily on the Oxford English Dictionary (OED), the Oxford Reference database, and the King James Version (KJV) of the Bible. When we rely on Alice Eardley’s edition of Pulter’s work, we cite her text generally (“Eardley”); other sources are cited in full. The result is an edition we consider a springboard for further work on Pulter’s poetry. <ref target="//pulterproject.northwestern.edu/about-project-conventions.html#elemental-edition" type="new-window-url">See full conventions for this edition here.</ref></note></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">
            <note type="editorialnote">I have utilized a semi-diplomatic transcription convention and maintained original spelling, except where the double ff has been reduced to a single f throughout. Abbreviations have been expanded and brevigraphs preserved. I have maintained original punctuation and capitalization from the manuscript so that the reader might interpret the potential significance and ambiguities of those scribal choices on their own. In any cases where the capitalization is ambiguous, I have defaulted to lowercase.. All biblical quotations are from the 1612 King James Version.</note>
          </rdg>
        </app>
        <app type="headnote">
          <rdg wit="#ee">
            <note type="headnote">The mother ostrich in this emblem is doubly vain, since her high self-regard (or vanity) coincides with her deeply inadequate parenting skills, such that “she lays and labors all in vain.” While the speaker might first play the haughty ostrich for laughs, this emblem’s primary concern connects with several deeply serious poems by Pulter on the importance of loving (or even “indulgent”) parenting. Examples of birds who exhibit better and worse mothering are woven throughout this heartfelt critique of English parents who “sell their children, ne’er to see them more”—a shocking claim that brings into the poem’s orbit the slave trade in Africa and the English subjection of the Irish. These moral and social failures provide a sharp contrast to the divine parent-child relations she posits as a model for the wisdom of her attachment to her own offspring. The speaker ends with a humble plea to God to let her be an instrument to reproduce not just children but the blessing of love.</note>
          </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">
            <note type="headnote">
              <p>Hester Pulter’s “The Ostrich” (Emblem 41) is numerically the last of what Elizabeth Kolkovich terms her indulgent parenting emblems, following <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="71">The Manucodiats (Emblem 5)</ref> and <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="76">Wisest Creatures (Emblem 10)</ref>. Beginning with an account of the ostrich, who arrogantly leaves her eggs in the sand to hatch on their own, Pulter compares this form of bad parenting to the cuckoo, subject of <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="94">The Cuckoo (Emblem 29)</ref>. For Pulter, the ostrich is far worse than a bird who leaves her eggs for another species to hatch, as abandoning her eggs to the sand to incubate is tantamount to selling her children into slavery, a brief but startling reference to contemporary practices of forced labor in the English colonies. Pulter offers an alternative animal exemplar in the stork, whose children return the care that their parents gave them when the elders age. Ending with a typical Pulterian prayer that she receive holy wisdom so that she may pass it along to her own children, Pulter crafts a scale of animal parenting to which any mother could compare herself.</p>

              <p>The ostrich has a surprisingly prominent place in Renaissance and early modern popular culture, the subject of many myths and folk legends that made it a rich source for metaphor and images. Its feathers and eggs, especially, were regarded as luxurious goods that could be found everywhere from the fashions of the nobility to church decorations. Ostriches were also thought to be able to consume and digest anything, even metals, a myth invoked by Jack Cade in William Shakespeare’s <title rend="italic">Henry VI, Part II</title>:  “I’ll make thee eat iron like an ostrich and swallow my sword like a great pin, ere thou and I part.”<seg>1<note type="gloss"><title rend="italic">The Complete Works of William Shakespeare</title> 7th ed., ed. David Bevington (New York: Pearson, 2014), 4.10.28–29.</note></seg> They were the subjects of emblems by both Geoffrey Whitney in 1586, who emphasized the hypocrisy of a bird who cannot fly, and George Wither in 1655, who used the ostrich’s plumes to warn against trusting ostentatious courtiers. Instead of following many of the popular conceptions of the ostrich, Pulter emphasizes the bird as a neglectful parent, a portrayal that can also be found in William Gouge’s parenting guide, <title rend="italic">Of Domestical Duties</title> (1622). (See <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="#ctxs">Early Modern Ostriches</ref>). Pulter relies on the biblical description of the ostrich that appears in the Book of Job (39: 13–18) for her portrayal in this poem, largely eschewing Pliny the Elder’s <title rend="italic">History of the World</title>, which first appeared in translation by Philemon Holland in 1601 and has been noted as a source in many of Pulter’s other emblems. In the biblical description and Pulter’s, the ostrich is portrayed as a vain and arrogant mother who leaves her newly laid eggs in the sand, leaving them vulnerable to being crushed by passerby. This careless act of pride betrays the ostrich’s actions as sinful. Good parents, argues Pulter, would never abandon their children as this callous bird does.</p>

              <p>Emphasizing the need to both be a loving parent and devout Christian, Pulter also invokes a political practice of exile and servitude that was deeply rooted in the English colonial endeavor as the poem turns further outward in line 20. She condemns the “base English” who would dare sell their own young into servitude. During the Interregnum, forcibly transported indentured servants and Royalist political exiles made up a significant percentage of the labor force sent to colonies in the Atlantic, including the Caribbean and the Americas. Royalist soldiers captured by Parliamentarian armies could be placed into a seven-year labor contract and transported to Jamaica or Barbados. This practice existed in tandem with an increasing trade in enslaved people from Africa, also held up as an example in this poem. Pulter condemns the neglectful ostrich mother with the same vigor that she does the Cromwellian government’s practice of sending prisoners to labor in British colonial holdings. The transport of prisoners, poor, and convicts to labor in the colonies was especially prevalent during Cromwell’s conquest of Ireland, a plight in which Pulter may have had a particular interest given her Irish connections. Her stark comparison between a neglectful parent and forced labor practices emphasizes the dire implications of parenting without a deep love for the child. For this ostrich, whose great vanity and thoughtlessness endangers her young, neglectful parenting can be equated with exiling innocents to thankless labor.</p>
            </note>
          </rdg>
        </app>
      </head>

      <l n="1">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft"><fw type="seqNum" place="inline">41</fw>The Estrich with her gallant gaudy plu<hi rend="overline">m</hi>es</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">The ostrich, with her <seg>gallant gaudy plumes<note type="gloss">gorgeous or showy (“gallant”) brilliantly fine or ornate (“gaudy”) feathers</note></seg>,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">The Estrich with her <seg>gallant gaudy plumes<note type="critical"> Describing the ostrich’s feathers as “gallant” (gorgeous or showy in appearance [<title rend="italic">OED</title> 1]) and “gaudy” (brilliantly fine or colourful, highly ornate, showy [<title rend="italic">OED</title> 3]) attaches signifiers of boasting luxury to the bird. Ostrich feathers were fashionable and expensive, appearing on headdresses and helmets of the nobility. Pulter emphasizes them as a sign of wealth and excess that the bird naturally carries, associating her with those traits. Ostrich eggs, too, were valued for their large size and pleasing shape, and they were collected as display items. See Joan Barclay Lloyd, <title rend="italic">African Animals in Renaissance Literature and Art</title> (1971).</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="2">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">In her great wit and Courage Soe Preſumes</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">In her great <seg>wit<note type="gloss">intellect</note></seg> and courage so presumes</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">In her great <seg>wit<note type="critical">understanding, intellect, reason (<title rend="italic">OED</title> 1); Pulter is utilizing sarcasm here, as will become apparent when she derides the ostrich’s lack of intellect in lines 11–12.</note></seg> and Courage soe Presumes</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="3">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">That as with wind and wing upright Shees bo’rn</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">That, <seg>as with<note type="gloss">since with</note></seg> wind and wing upright she’s borne,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">That as with wind and wing upright shees born</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="4">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">The Horſe and’s valient Rider Shee doth Scorn</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">The horse <seg>and’s<note type="gloss">and his</note></seg> valiant rider she doth scorn.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">The Horse <seg>and’s<note type="gloss">and his</note></seg> valient Rider shee doth scorn</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="5">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">But folly is Concom̃itant with Pride</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">But folly is <seg>concomitant<note type="gloss">concurrent, accompanied</note></seg> with pride,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">But folly is <seg>Concommitant<note type="gloss">going together, accompanying (<title rend="italic">OED</title> 1)</note></seg> with Pride</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="6">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">&ff;or Shee her precious Egs in Sand doth hide</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">For she her precious eggs in sand doth hide,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">For shee her precious Egs in sand doth hide</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="7">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">&ff;orgetting that the Travellor’s foot may Cruſh</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Forgetting that the traveler’s foot may crush</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Forgetting that the Travellor’s foot may Crush</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="8">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Their Tender Shell, nor doth Shee Care a Ruſh</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee"><seg>Their tender shell<note type="critical">The preceding account closely tracks the biblical book of Job 39:14–18, in which the ostrich is described as scorning the horse and rider and being negligent of her offspring: she “leaveth her eggs in the earth, … and forgetteth that the foot may crush them.”</note></seg>; nor doth she <seg>care a rush<note type="gloss">care at all</note></seg></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Their Tender shell, nor doth shee <seg>Care a Rush<note type="gloss">as for something of little or no value or importance (<title rend="italic">OED</title> P.2)</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="9">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Though Shee her young doe never See again</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Though she her young do never see again.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Though shee her young doe never see again</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="10">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">And thus Shee lays and labours all in vain</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">And thus she lays and labors all in vain,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">And thus shee lays and <seg>labours all in vain<note type="critical">Pairing “labours” with the action of egg-laying suggests both labor as childbirth and as physical or manual exertion. The ostrich lays her eggs only to leave them in the sand and never see them hatch, while her prideful actions betray a lack of godliness.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="11">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Cauſ God hath Underſtanding her deni’de</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">’Cause God hath understanding her denied.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>Caus God hath Understanding her deni’de<note type="critical">The substance of Pulter’s description of the Ostrich in lines 3–11 is drawn directly from the Bible. Job 39: 13–18 gives this account: “Gavest thou the goodly wings unto the peacocks or wings and feathers unto the ostrich? / Which leaveth her egges in the earth, and warmeth them in dust / And forgetteth that the foote may crush them, or that the wilde beast may breake them./ She is hardened against her yong ones, as though they were not hers; labour is in vaine without feare: / Because God hath deprived her of wisedom, neither hath hee imparted to her understanding. / What time she lifteth up by her selfe on high, she scorneth the horse and his rider.” Pulter uses this description to emphasize the ostrich as a careless mother, willing to leave her eggs to incubate in the sand and risk them being crushed by a passing traveler rather than sit on them herself. She has no sympathy for, nor intelligence enough to understand, the risk to her young. </note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="12">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">&ff;or Love, and Wiſdome, never will Reſide</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">For love and wisdom never will reside</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">For Love, and Wisdome, never will reside</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="13">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">With Arogance for they Are from above</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">With arrogance, for they are from above,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">With Arogance for they Are from above</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="14">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">&ff;rom God who is the &ff;ountain of all Love</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">From God, who is the fountain of all love.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">From God who is the fountain of all Love</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="15">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">The Estrich then the Cuckow is &ff;ar worſs</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">The ostrich than the cuckoo is far worse,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">The Estrich then the Cuckow is far worss</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="16">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">&ff;or Shee doth onely put her Egs to Nurſs</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">For <seg>she doth only put her eggs to nurse<note type="gloss">Many cuckoos lay their eggs in the nests of other birds, who feed (“nurse”) them.</note></seg>;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">For shee doth onely <seg>put her Egs to Nurss<note type="critical">The cuckoo was understood to lay its eggs in the nests of other birds, a practice known as brood parasitism. Pliny describes: “These lay alwaies in other birds nests, and most of all in the Stock-doves, commonly one egge and no more (which no other bird doth besides) and seldome twaine” (1601 trans. Philemon Holland, X.IX, p. 275). Pulter’s ambivalent representation of the cuckoo is consistent with <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="94">The Cuckoo (Emblem 29)</ref>.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="17">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Hard is her Meat but harder is her Heart</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee"><seg>Hard is her meat<note type="gloss">The flesh of the cuckoo is tough for humans to eat.</note></seg>, but harder is her heart,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Hard is her Meat but harder is her Heart</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="18">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">That with her new lay’d Ovums thus can part</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">That with her new laid <seg>ovums<note type="gloss">eggs</note></seg> thus can part.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">That with her new lay’d <seg>Ovums<note type="gloss">eggs. The word “ovum” is directly from Latin and predominantly appears in scientific texts in the early modern period. Pulter’s literary use is notable, if not unusual.</note></seg> thus can part</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="19">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Oh my Sad Soul this mak’s my Heart e’ne bleed</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Oh, my sad soul: this makes my heart e’en bleed!</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Oh my sad soul this mak’s my Heart e’ne bleed</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="20">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">None but baſe Engliſh and Cams curſed Seed</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">None but base English and <seg>Ham’s curséd seed<note type="gloss">In the Bible, Ham’s son Canaan is cursed by his grandfather, Noah (Genesis 9:20–27) causing his descendants to become subject to Israelites. Numerous early modern texts suggest that Ham’s dark-skinned lineage populated Africa.</note></seg></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">None but <seg>base English<note type="critical">morally low; despicable (<title rend="italic">OED</title> I.2). As the English Civil War raged and Cromwell invaded Ireland, Royalist prisoners and the poor were often shipped to the West Indies as labor. It is important to note that none of these political prisoners endured lifelong bondage in the form of slavery, but instead had finite contracts for servitude that ended usually after a period of seven years. However, much of the rhetoric surrounding this practice was of outrage that even noble English citizens were treated like common criminals or subhuman animals. A particularly scandalous case of this political trafficking was that of two Royalists, Marcellus Rivers and Oxenbridge Foyle, who were forcibly transported to Barbados in 1655. The popular pamphlet, <title rend="italic">Englands Slavery, or Barbados Merchandize</title> that related their ensuing petition to Parliament, also described the inhuman treatment the pair suffered at the hands of the planters to whom their contracts were sold. Pulter’s tone towards this practice resonates with the petition’s argument that this practice was “a thing not known amongst the cruell Turks, to sell and enslave these of their own Countrey and Religion, much lesse the Innocent” (7). Pulter makes explicit reference to the Parliamentarian practice of exiling captured Royalists to Jamaica and elsewhere in <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="115">Phalaris and the Brazen Bull (Emblem 50)</ref>, a political emblem against Cromwell. For further information on Pulter’s relationship to English colonies in the Caribbean, see Jonathan Koch’s curation for that poem, <ref type="pp-curation-ref" target="/poems/ee/phalaris-and-the-brazen-bull-emblem-50/#pulter-and-jamaica">Pulter and Jamaica</ref>. For forced labor practices in the interregnum, see Carla Gardina Pestana, <title rend="italic">The English Atlantic in an Age of Revolution, 1640–1661</title>(2004).</note></seg> and <seg>Cams cursed seed<note type="critical">In Genesis, Ham’s (also spelled Cham) son Canaan is cursed with servitude by Noah as a punishment for Ham seeing Noah naked: “And Noah awoke from his wine, and knew what his younger sonne had done unto him. / And he said, Cursed be Canaan: a servant of servants shall he be unto his brethren” (Gen. 9: 24–25). Eardley notes that this story is often conflated with a curse of blackness upon Ham’s other son, Chus. (Alice Eardley, “An Edition of Lady Hester Pulter’s Book of ‘Emblemes’”. PhD diss., University of Warwick [2008], 128).This conflated curse was also for many years used as an explanation for blackness and a justification for the enslavement of Africans, especially throughout the transatlantic slave trade. At the same time that indentured servant labor was being transported to the islands, the African slave trade to the Caribbean, especially Barbados, was also increasing. While Pulter does not explicitly equate Black Africans with the enslaved Canaan in this line, she also uses this phrase in <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="110">Aristomenes (Emblem 45)</ref> to refer to an Ethiopian biblical character. This would certainly suggest that Pulter had some associations between dark-skinned inhabitants of African nations and slavery. For more on the curse of Ham and its relationship to slavery, see David M. Goldenberg, <title rend="italic">Black and Slave: The Origins and History of the Curse of Ham</title> (2017).</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">
              <fw type="catch" place="bottom">doe</fw>
          </rdg>
        </app>
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">
              <pb ed="#ft" facs="#f7610_242" n="119v"/>
          </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">
              <pb ed="#ee" facs="#f7610_242"/>
          </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">
              <pb ed="#ae" facs="#f7610_242"/>
          </rdg>
        </app>
      <l n="21">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Doe Sell their Children ne’re to See them more</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Do <seg>sell their children, ne’er to see them more<note type="critical">Eardley suggests that this line might refer to the sale of royalist political prisoners, criminals, and Irish to the West Indies as indentured servants or slaves in the 1650s.</note></seg>!</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Doe <seg>sell their Children<note type="critical">It was often the poor and vagrant (including children) who would be selected, willingly or not, for transportation to both the North American and Caribbean colonial holdings. Henry Cromwell, Oliver Cromwell’s son and Lord Lieutenant of Ireland, at one point proposed that one thousand Irish girls and two thousand boys be transported to Jamaica to work in the colony (“Henry Cromwell,” <title rend="italic">ODNB</title>). The kidnap and transport of children as labor forces was a particular source of anxiety for the public, as stories circulated of even well-off English children being kidnapped for labor.</note></seg> ne’re to see them more</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="22">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Such Barbariſme all Christians muſt deplore</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Such barbarism all Christians must <seg>deplore<note type="gloss">lament</note></seg>.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Such Barbarisme all Christians must deplore</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="23">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Cruell’s the Eſtrich crueller their heart</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Cruel’s the ostrich: crueller their heart</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Cruell’s the Estrich crueller their heart</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="24">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">That with their dear bought Children thus can part</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">That with their <seg>dear-bought<note type="gloss">obtained at a great cost</note></seg> children thus can part,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">That with their dear bought Children <seg>thus can part<note type="critical">The repetition of the construction of this statement, beginning on line 23 and mirroring lines 17–18, creates a refrain that emphasizes the negative traits of both the ostrich and the Cromwellian government. Though the ostrich’s “hard heart” toward her young has already been emphasized, those who would willingly send children into servitude are even worse than this bad mother. </note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="25">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">When as the Stork her Young doe bear &amp; feed</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee"><seg>Whenas<note type="gloss">When; seeing that</note></seg> the stork her young do bear and feed,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">When as the stork her Young doe bear &amp; feed</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="26">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft"><seg>Which<note type="physical">“ich” appears written over earlier letters</note></seg> they Retaliate in Age and Need</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee"><seg>Which they retaliate in age and need<note type="gloss">The young storks support their parents when old. Here, “retaliate” means to repay a kindness or service.</note></seg>—</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Which they <seg>retaliate<note type="gloss">to repay a kindness or service; to reciprocate (<title rend="italic">OED</title> 2.b)</note></seg> <seg>in Age and need<note type="critical">In opposition to ostriches, storks exemplify the ideal parent-child relationship as the parents care for their young, and young storks do the same for their parents as they age. Pliny: “Storkes keepe one nest still from yeare to yeare, and never chaunge: and of this kind nature they are, that the yong will keepe and feed their parents when they be old, as they themselves were by them nourished in the beginning” (1601 trans. Philemon Holland, XXIII, p. 282).</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="27">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">By which the Noble Reader plain may See</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">By which the noble reader plain may see</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">By which the noble Reader plain may see</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="28">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">That &ff;ooliſh Creatures least indulgent bee</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">That foolish creatures least indulgent be.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>That foolish Creatures least indulgent bee<note type="critical">The mirror of this statement appears in <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="76">Wisest Creatures (Emblem 10)</ref>, “The wisest creatures most indulgent be,” placing the ostrich in opposition to the good animal parents described in that poem. See also Elizabeth Kolkovich’s Curation for Emblem 10, <ref type="pp-curation-ref" target="/poems/ee/wisest-creatures-emblem-10/#indulgent-parenting">Indulgent Parenting</ref>.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="29">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Let Parents then to theirs extend their Love</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Let parents then to <seg>theirs<note type="gloss">their offspring</note></seg> extend their love,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Let Parents then to theirs extend their Love</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="30">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Seeing Naturall affection’s from above</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Seeing natural affection’s from above.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Seeing <seg>Naturall affection’s<note type="critical">Parents extending care to their children, even if indulgent, is natural, as opposed to the unnatural mothering practices of the ostrich. Gouge’s <title rend="italic">Of Domestical Duties</title> (1622) uses this same language to shame mothers who do not care for their infants: “It is noted as a point of vnnaturalnesse in the Ostrich, to leaue her eggs in the earth, and in the dust” (507). This phrase also mimics the “naturall affection” mentioned in 2 Timothy 3:3, further emphasizing the Christian nature of familial care.  </note></seg> from above</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="31">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Then Gracious God into my Soul infuſe</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Then, gracious God, into my soul infuse</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Then Gracious God into my soul infuse</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="32">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Thy Love and Wiſdome that it may diffuſe</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Thy love and wisdom, that it may diffuse</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Thy Love and Wisdome that it may <seg>diffuse<note type="critical">Pulter here uses “diffuse” (to send forth an immaterial thing in many directions [<title rend="italic">OED</title> 1]) in a similar way as in <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="71">The Manucodiats (Emblem 5)</ref>. Lara Dodds describes in the Amplified Edition headnote that Pulter prays “that she may serve as an intermediary between the divine and her relations on earth.” Pulter mirrors that concept here, in another indulgent-parenting poem, in which she asks God to “infuse” her with his love and wisdom, so that she may share it with her children. </note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="33">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">To all my Children great as well as leſs</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">To all my children, great as well as less;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">To all my Children <seg>great as well as less<note type="gloss">older as well as younger</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="34">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Then ô my God that Love and Wiſdome bleſs.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Then, O my God, that love and wisdom bless.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Then o’ my God that Love and Wisdome bless.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <app>
        <rdg type="milestone" wit="#ft">
            <milestone unit="poem" rend="straight-horline"/>
        </rdg>
      </app>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
