<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../src/vmachine.xsl"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
  schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI [

  <!ENTITY ff "<!-- ff ligature, representing capital modern day capital F, here represented as 'ff' -->ff">

  ]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mads.pp.120">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
          <title>Somnus, Why Art Thou Still to Me Unkind?</title>
        <title type="sub">Poem #120</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Created by</resp>
          <persName>Leah Knight</persName>
          <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoded by</resp>
          <persName>Katherine Poland</persName>
          <persName>Matthew Taylor</persName>
          <persName>Betsy Chou</persName>
          <persName>Emily Andrey</persName>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>IT-project consultation by</resp>
          <persName>Josh Honn</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
          <orgName>Brock University</orgName>
          <orgName>University of Leeds</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <principal>
          <persName/>
        </principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="1"/>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription, transformations, and notes</resp>
          <persName>Leah Knight</persName>
          <orgName>Brock University</orgName>
          <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
        </respStmt>
      </editionStmt>
      <extent/>
      <publicationStmt>
        <ab/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listBibl>
          <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
              <repository>See witness list.</repository>
            </msIdentifier>
          </msDesc>
        </listBibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p/>
      </projectDesc>
      <p>Transcriptions are encoded in TEI(P5)-conformant XML.</p>
      <samplingDecl>
        <p/>
      </samplingDecl>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction>
          <p>Apparent errors are preserved and editorial corrections provided using SIC and CORR tags, but only where the editor conjectures that the original scribe or compositor would have recognized the instance as an error. For example, what according to modern usage is incorrect subject/verb agreement might have been deemed acceptable to a seventeenth-century scribe or compositor. All such instances are treated instead using the ORIG and REG tags. (See below.)</p>
          <p>Corrections and annotations made within the scope of the original document either by its original authors, owners, and/or transcribers are noted using ADD tags. These annotations and may be futher explained within NOTE tags, as added by the editors of this digital edition, for display within the apparatus.</p>
        </correction>
        <normalization>
          <p>Original spellings, abbreviations, and orthography are preserved. Where in the manuscripts a character's status as majuscule or miniscule is ambiguous, the editor has silently chosen one or the other based on context and judgment (i.e., does not register such ambiguity in either the markup or the notes).</p>
        </normalization>
        <quotation>
          <p>Original quotation marks, if any, are preserved.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation>
          <p>Original hyphenation is preserved.</p>
        </hyphenation>
      </editorialDecl>
      <charDecl>
        <!-- Ligature combinations for which there are currently no corresponding Unicode codepoints. -->
        <glyph xml:id="ffllig">
          <glyphName>Handwritten 'ff' ligature, used in handwriting to represent modern F</glyphName>
        </glyph>
      </charDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="DDC22">
          <bibl>
            <title>Dewey Decimal Classification</title>
            <edition/>
            <publisher/>
            <pubPlace/>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-GB">British English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <!-- dewey decimal system class code 821: English Poetry -->
        <classCode scheme="DDC22">821</classCode>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
    <!-- List of all images associated with this document -->
    <graphic url="./document_images/7610_265.jpg" xml:id="f7610_000"/>
    <graphic url="./document_images/7610_266.jpg" xml:id="f7610_000"/>
  </facsimile>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="ft">Transcription of manuscript: By <persName xml:id="lknight">Leah Knight</persName> and <persName xml:id="wwall">Wendy Wall</persName>.</witness>
          <witness xml:id="ee">Elemental edition: By <persName>Leah Knight</persName> and <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>.</witness>
          <witness xml:id="ae">Amplified edition: By <persName>Megan Heffernan</persName>.</witness>
        </listWit>
      </div>
    </front>

    <body>

      <app>
        <rdg wit="#ft">
          <pb ed="#ft" facs="#f7610_265" n="130a"/>
        </rdg>
        <rdg wit="#ee">
          <pb ed="#ee" facs="#f7610_265"/>
        </rdg>
        <rdg wit="#ae">
          <pb ed="#ae" facs="#f7610_265"/>
        </rdg>
      </app>

      <head>
        <app type="title">
          <rdg wit="#ft"><fw facs="#f7610_265" type="pageNum" place="margin-topright">PG#</fw>[Untitled]</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Somnus, Why Art Thou Still to Me Unkind?</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Somnus Why Art Thou Still To Me Unkind</rdg>
        </app>
        <app type="editorialnote">
          <rdg wit="#ft">
            <note type="editorialnote">In these transcriptions we preserve as many details of the original material, textual, and graphic properties of Hester Pulter’s manuscript verse as we have found practical. Whenever possible, for instance, original spelling, punctuation, capitalization, lineation, insertions, deletions, alterations, spacing between words and lines, and indentation are all maintained; abbreviations and brevigraphs are not expanded; and superscript and subscript representations are retained. <ref target="http://pulterproject.northwestern.edu/about-project-conventions.html#top" type="new-window-url">See full conventions for the transcriptions here.</ref></note>
          </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">
            <note type="editorialnote">The aim of the elemental edition is to make the poems accessible to the largest variety of readers, which involves modernizing spelling and punctuation as well as adding basic glosses. Spelling and punctuation reflect current standard American usage; punctuation highlights syntax which might otherwise be obscure. Outmoded but still familiar word forms (“thou,” “‘tis,” “hold’st”) are not modernized, and we do not modernize grammar when the sense remains legible. After a brief headnote aimed at offering a “way in” to the poem’s unique qualities and connections with other verse by Pulter or her contemporaries, the edition features a minimum of notes and interpretative framing to allow more immediate engagement with the poem. Glosses clarify synonyms or showcase various possible meanings in Pulter’s time. Other notes identify named people and places or clarify obscure material. We rely (without citation) primarily on the Oxford English Dictionary (OED), the Oxford Reference database, and the King James Version (KJV) of the Bible. When we rely on Alice Eardley’s edition of Pulter’s work, we cite her text generally (“Eardley”); other sources are cited in full. The result is an edition we consider a springboard for further work on Pulter’s poetry. <ref target="http://pulterproject.northwestern.edu/about-project-conventions.html#elemental-edition" type="new-window-url">See full conventions for this edition here.</ref></note></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">
            <note type="editorialnote">Because “Somnus Why Art Thou Still To Me Unkind” is unfinished and contains revisions, likely in Pulter’s hand, I have opted to include scored out and corrected words. To make the poem accessible for all readers, I have modernized the text by updating spelling, expanding contractions, and standardizing capitalization. The only exceptions are cases where the form or the sense of the poem would be lost by modernizing, particularly the elision of syllables to preserve meter. I have also supplied punctuation because, as was typical for seventeenth-century poetry manuscripts, Pulter’s poems contained almost no punctuation. There are both benefits and liabilities to this approach. While the introduction of punctuation improves the sense of grammatical structures for modern readers, it loses the productive ambiguities of the manuscript, where clauses might connect to each other in multiple ways. So I would invite readers to proceed by comparing the edition to the images of the manuscript and the transcription supplied by <hi rend="italic">The Pulter Project</hi>. Does an alternative to my punctuation open up different interpretive possibilities? How might the meaning of the poem change without it? </note>
          </rdg>
        </app>
        <app type="headnote">
          <rdg wit="#ee">
              <note type="headnote">This fragment of a poem, in what is probably Pulter’s hand, appears on a loose sheet in a folder associated with the bound volume in which her other poems are found. Although a complete copy might someday be found, Pulter appears not to have finished this experimental dream vision about a relatively recent event: the 1667 battle, known as the Raid on the Medway, which ended in the destruction by the Dutch navy of the fort and shipyard at Sheerness, on England’s east coast. Part of the Second Anglo-Dutch War, this was one of the worst defeats ever suffered by the British navy, which saw many warships destroyed or captured and the hasty arrangement by Charles II of an unfavorable treaty. The few extant verses of what promises an epic treatment of these events are framed by the speaker’s recurrent nightmare visions which mingle her distress with an incongruous perception of Sheerness remaining “unconquered” despite the “purple gore” that sprinkles the sea. The speaker’s horrified amazement joins that of the powerful and resplendent water gods and goddesses, mustering (too late, it must be said) as British reinforcements under Saturn’s command. Neptune, Triton, Nereus, Doris: the speaker, perched on a rock above the fray, witnesses a catalogue of mythic powerhouses whom she has imaginatively installed into current political events. What dreamy counterfactual scenario might have ensued, if the poem continued past its opening catalogue and into the martial action one might expect to follow? We will only know if the poem’s continuation one day comes to light.</note>
          </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">
            <note type="headnote"><p>Written on a loose sheet of paper, probably in Pulter’s own hand, these 41 lines recast recent politics as classical mythology.<seg>1<note type="gloss">On Hester Pulter’s hand, see <bibl>Alice Eardley’s conclusion in <title rend="italic">Hester Pulter, Poems, Emblems, and The Unfortunate Florinda</title>, ed. Alice Eardley, The Other Voice in Early Modern Europe (Iter Gateway to the Middle Ages and Renaissance, 2014), 182</bibl>, note 838.</note></seg> Possibly an unfinished narrative or epic, the poem refers to a battle in the second Anglo-Dutch war that took place in 1667 in the town of Sheerness, on the Isle of Stepney in Kent. Dutch forces captured the town, destroying fortifications, then sailed up the river Medway and part way up the Thames estuary to burn several British ships. The embarrassing defeat for the British is depicted somewhat ambiguously in “Somnus Why Art Thou Still to Me Unkind.” Narrated by an insomniac, the poem recounts a scene in which the sleepless speaker perches on a rock above Sheerness, where she witnesses the tears of the inconsolable Thames. Even though the town has been the site of one notable loss in battle, it remains “unconquered” in the war. “Unconquered Sheere” may mean something like “brave” or “valiant” Sheerness, whatever losses the town has suffered, or it may be one of the rough patches that would have been revised if this work had been completed.</p>
              <p>While “Somnus Why Art Thou Still to Me Unkind” remains unfinished, the opening recalls Pulter’s tactics elsewhere. Like <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="35">The Pismire</ref> and <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="45">This Was Written in 1648, When I Lay in, With my Son John</ref>, this poem begins with a personal distress that first manifests as bodily suffering, then goes on to liberate the speaker’s mind to wander freely in contemplation of the scene that confronts her. “Somnus” provides two seemingly related ways to understand the experience of the watchful insomniac: first, through contemporary political turmoil, and, second, through the mythological motifs that might ultimately transform or lend a cosmic significance to the British defeat. The powers of classical deities are relocated to the English coast as the “trembling bosom” of the sea summons the nautical forces of mythology: sea gods, goddesses, minor nymphs, and even helpful dolphins answer the trumpet call and begin to flow toward Sheerness. Neptune “gazes” upon the same “bloody billows” as the speaker, and we are left to suspect that it is partly her own distress that conjures this epic force.</p>
              <p>We can’t know whether Pulter is marshaling the gods to mount a counterattack against the Dutch or to join a mourning procession, but the existing portion of “Somnus Why Art Thou Still to Me Unkind” suggests that she may have been exploring a reading based on Edmund Spenser’s <title rend="italic">The Faerie Queene</title>. Early in Book 3, Britomart sits on a rocky shore, watching “a while the surges hore, / That gainst the craggy clifts did loudly rore.”<seg>2<note type="gloss"><bibl>Edmund Spenser, <title rend="italic">The Faerie Queene</title>, ed. A. C. Hamilton, Toshiyuki Suzuki, and Hiroshi Yamashita, 2nd edition, Longman Annotated Poets (New York: Routledge, 2007), 3.4.7.5-6.</bibl></note></seg> An emblem of chastity, Britomart externalizes her erotic suffering in an extended complaint about the “Huge sea of sorrow, and tempestuous griefe,” and it is possible that this scene of reading the seascape offered Pulter an allegorical text through which she could write her own political distress (3.4.8.1). The geography specific to the Sheerness battle also appears at the end of Book 4 of <title rend="italic">The Faerie Queene</title>, when the narrative thread begun in Britomart’s reading of the sea is brought to a partial resolution by the marriage of the Medway and Thames rivers. Spenser depicts a host of sea gods flowing in to celebrate:</p>
              <p>It fortun’d then, a solemne feast was there
                To all the Sea-gods and their fruitfull seede,
                In honour of the spousalls, which then were 
                Betwixt the Medway and the Thames agreed. (4.11.8.1-4)
              </p>
              <p>What follows is an epic catalog of the aquatic deities who travel across the globe, from “great Neptune with his threeforkt mace, / That rules the Seas, and makes them rise or fall” to the lesser local nymphs and even the mighty rivers of the Nile and the Amazon (4.11.11.1-2). Like Pulter’s unfinished poem, Spenser’s celebration of England’s fertile estuary overflows its boundaries and remains open-ended. Book 4, Canto 12 of <title rend="italic">The Faerie Queene</title> opens with Spenser responding to the aquatic marriage festivities with a lament for the futility of his own poetic labor: “O what an endlesse worke haue I in hand, / To count the seas abundant progeny” (4.12.1.1-2).</p>
              <p>Whether Pulter was equally stymied by the scope of her task is impossible to say, because “Somnus Why Art Thou Still to Me Unkind” is interrupted well before we learn what the gods had planned at the site of Sheerness’s carnage. This truncated scene invites us to place Pulter’s poetic fragment alongside the work of poets including Spenser and Chaucer whose ambitious plans never achieved fruition. While this Amplified Edition attends to the unfinished state of the poem by preserving revisions that offer evidence of Pulter’s writing practice, it resists offering speculations or conclusions about where those revisions might be heading. In this sense, the trailing off of “Somnus Why Art Thou Still to Me Unkind” functions, as Catherine Nicholson observes of Spenser’s unfinished <title rend="italic">Two Cantos of Mutabilitie</title>, “almost as a gloss on the strange unraveling of the work to which they belong.”<seg>3<note type="gloss"><bibl>Catherine Nicholson, <title rend="italic">Reading and Not Reading The Faerie Queene: Spenser and The Making of Literary Criticism</title> (Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press, 2020), 244.</bibl></note></seg></p>
              <p>My edition of the poem attempts to record what remains on the page in order to give a sense of one moment in an active process of poetic composition. In words that were scored out and replaced, we can watch Pulter experiment with word choice and verb tense as she transformed this contemporary episode in international politics into an allegorical and classicizing dream narrative. She twice included marginal markers signaling the entrance of named sea deities, as she does with flowers in her <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="12">The Garden, or The Contention of Flowers</ref>. The final lines of the fragment are rougher, making the relation between clauses particularly mobile, and it is difficult to determine definitively how to punctuate the passages about Doris and her rich jewels. Perhaps the best way to end this edition is with a question: in this unfinished poem, should the last line be closed with a full stop—a final period—or should it remain without any punctuation as a sign of the instant in which Pulter lifted her pen and left her work open for us to receive?</p></note>
          </rdg>
        </app>
      </head>

      <l n="1">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft"><seg>ſomnus<note type="physical">on loose sheet, in folder associated with manuscript; hand appears same as in “The Weepeinge Wishe”</note></seg> why art thou ſtill to mee unkinde?</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1"><seg>Somnus<note type="gloss">Roman god of sleep</note></seg>, why art thou still to me unkind?</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1"><seg>Somnus<note type="gloss">the god of sleep.</note></seg> why art thou still to me unkind?</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="2">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Why doe all els ſuch comfort finde</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Why do all else such comfort find</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Why do all else such comfort find</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="3">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">In thy imbrace? but I and only I</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">In thy embrace? But I, and only I,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">In thy embrace? But I and only I</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="4">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Allternately (aye mee) doe live and die</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Alternately (ay me) do <seg>live and die<note type="gloss">wake and sleep; sleep was commonly referred to as the image of death; for instance, John Donne calls rest and sleep Death’s “pictures” (“Death Be Not Proud,” l. 5).</note></seg>.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1"><seg>Alternately (ay me) do live and die<note type="critical">alternating between sleep and waking; a description of how agonizing fitful sleep can be. The speaker’s stagnant suffering is expressed sonically in the repetition of “I and only I” and then, half a line later, “ay me.” The original spelling, “aye mee,” is ambiguous. “Aye” might mean “yes,” or it might be a cry of pain now colloquially spelled “ay.”</note></seg>?</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="5">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Thy fellow Morphius too doth ſhew his ſpite</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Thy fellow <seg>Morpheus<note type="gloss">son of Somnus and Roman god of dreams</note></seg> too doth show his spite</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Thy fellow <seg>Morpheus<note type="gloss">the god of dreams, companion of Somnus</note></seg> too doth show his spite,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="6">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">When from his Horney gate <seg>[?]<note type="physical">single letter, possibly “d,” blotted on bottom half</note></seg> hee doth affright</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">When from his <seg>horny gate<note type="gloss">The gates of horn and ivory is a literary image (originally from <title rend="italic">The Odyssey</title>) distinguishing two kinds of dreams: those passing through the gate of horn are true, while those passing through the gate of ivory are deceptive. Many writers used the term “horny gate” to describe Morpheus’s dream invasions. See, for instance, <bibl><title rend="italic">Du Bartas His Divine Weeks and Works</title>, trans. Josuah Sylvester (London, 1641), p. 249.</bibl></note></seg> he doth affright</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">When from his <seg>horny <del>d</del> gate<note type="gloss">classical allusion to the gates of horn, through which only true dreams may pass; false dreams were said to pass instead through the gates of ivory.</note></seg> he doth affright</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="7">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">My troubled ſoul, as hee did t’hother night</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">My troubled soul, as he did th’other night.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">My troubled soul, as he did <seg>t’other<note type="gloss">the other</note></seg> night.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="8">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Oh <seg><del>y</del><note type="physical">blotted only on top half</note></seg> my ſad hart would itt might prove a dream</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">O my sad heart, would it might prove a dream!</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Oh <del>y</del> my sad heart, would it might prove a dream:</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="9">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">In that uncounquerd sheere wher Thameses ſtreame</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">In that <seg>unconquered Sheer, when Thames’s stream<note type="gloss">At Sheerness (on England’s eastern coast) the river Medway (mentioned in the next line) joins with the estuary of the Thames river; it is presumably called “unconquered” here in relation to the 1667 Dutch attack there in the Second Anglo-Dutch War, despite the fact that both contemporary and later accounts consider the battle there to have been a resounding defeat of the English navy.</note></seg></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">In that <seg>unconquered Sheere<note type="gloss">Sheerness, a town on the Isle of Stepney in northeast Kent where the English navy was defeated in June 1667 during an attack in the Second Anglo-Dutch War. The counterfactual “unconquered” description offers a few possible readings. Pulter may have been stopped mid-revision or she may have been thinking of the town as itself unconquered even if the navy suffered a defeat.</note></seg> where Thames’s stream,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="10">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Joyened with faire Medwaye <del>did</del>,<seg><add place="above">doth</add><note type="physical">directly over “did”</note></seg> their tribute paye</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Joined with fair Medway doth their <seg>tribute<note type="gloss">an offering paid as a duty, here also alluding to the the fact that a “tributary” is a stream flowing into a river</note></seg> pay,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Joined with fair <seg>Medway<note type="gloss">The river Medway meets the Thames at Sheerness, where Dutch fleets sailed up both rivers,  attacked land fortifications, and captured several English ships.</note></seg> <del>did</del> doth their tribute pay.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="11">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Thar on a lofty rock mee thought I laye</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">There on a lofty rock me thought I lay;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">There on a lofty rock me thought I lay,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="12">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Then on the tremblinge <seg>bo<del>o</del>ſome<note type="physical">second “o” blotted on right half</note></seg> of the deepe</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Then, on the trembling bosom of the deep,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Then on the trembling boosom of the deepe</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="13">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Huge floods of tears poore Thames did weepe</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Huge floods of tears poor Thames did weep</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Huge floods of tears poor Thames did weep</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <app>
        <rdg wit="#ae">
          <milestone unit="poem-section" n="+" rend="left-gutter"/>
        </rdg>
      </app>
      <l n="14">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft"><seg>To<note type="physical">“+” in left margin</note></seg> ſee the ſea ſprinc’led with purple gore</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1"><seg>To<note type="physical">A mark (“+”) appears in the left margin, as though to signal an insertion of a phrase which is not present in the manuscript.</note></seg> see the sea sprinkled with purple gore.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1"><seg>To<note type="gloss">marginal “+” perhaps as a sign of Pulter’s plans for revision.</note></seg> see the sea <seg>sprinkled with purple gore<note type="gloss">The Thames, the river that runs through the heart of London and out to the base of the North Sea, weeps to see the sea covered with the blood of slaughtered English sailors.</note></seg>;</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="15">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">The ſad Nereades did much deplore</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">The sad <seg>Nereides<note type="gloss">in Greek legend, the fifty daughters of Doris and Nereus; sea nymphs</note></seg> did much <seg>deplore<note type="gloss">lament</note></seg></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">The sad <seg>Nereids<note type="gloss">beautiful sea nymphs; daughters of Nereus and Doris</note></seg> did much deplore</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="16">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">This <del>change</del>, <seg><add place="above">omen</add><note type="physical">directly over “change”</note></seg> great Neptune was amazed</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">This omen. Great <seg>Neptune<note type="gloss">Roman god of water and the sea</note></seg> was amazed</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">This <del>change</del> omen; great <seg>Neptune<note type="gloss">chief sea god, the Roman counterpart of Poseidon</note></seg> was amazed</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="17">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">As hee upon those blooddy <seg>billow<note type="physical">blot immediately after may obscure final “s”</note></seg> gaz’d</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">As he upon those bloody billows gazed;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">As he upon those bloody billows gazed,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="18">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Then instantly hee <seg>bad blu<note type="physical">“bad” may have read “bid” originally, or reverse; “blu” appears written over “buw”</note></seg> Triton ſound</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Then, instantly he bid blue <seg>Triton<note type="gloss">son of Neptune, represented as a fish with a human head, who makes the ocean roar by blowing through his shell</note></seg> sound</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Then instantly he bade blue <seg>Triton<note type="gloss">Greek sea god known as the herald of the sea, the son of Poseidon</note></seg> sound</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="19">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">His wrethed Trumpe t’was hard the Oceane rownd</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">His wreathéd <seg>trump<note type="gloss">trumpet</note></seg>—’twas heard the ocean round—</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">His <seg>wreathéd trump<note type="gloss">Triton uses a conch shell as a trumpet to broadcast Neptune’s message.</note></seg>; t’was heard the ocean round,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="20">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">To ſummun each <seg><del>great</del><add place="above">ſea \</add><note type="physical">“ſea \” written directly atop “<del>great</del>”</note></seg> God, and Godes faire</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">To summon each sea god and goddess fair,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">To summon each <del>great</del> sea god and goddess fair,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="21">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">That <seg>to<note type="physical">“t” appears to correct earlier “o”</note></seg> our narrough ſeas they should repaire</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">That to our narrow seas they should <seg>repair<note type="gloss">return</note></seg>.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">That to our narrow seas they should <seg>repair<note type="gloss">Neptune is calling all the gods to the seas surrounding England.</note></seg>.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="22">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Then did they come from every ſea and strand</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Then did they come from every sea and <seg>strand<note type="gloss">shore, coast</note></seg></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Then did they come from every sea and strand</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="23">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">To heer their kinge ſaturnius dread command</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">To hear their king <seg>Saturnus’s<note type="gloss">Latin for Saturn, the Roman god associated by the Romans with the Greek god Kronos, the father of the first-generation Olympians</note></seg> dread command.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">To hear their king <seg>Saturnus’s<note type="gloss">chief Roman god and father to Neptune and the other Roman gods</note></seg> dread command.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="24">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">ſome did bestride Philanthropes broad backe</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Some did bestride <seg>Philanthrope’s<note type="gloss">The name (etymologically, “lover of humanity”) refers in classical literature to the dolphin; it is based on the animal’s alleged friendliness to people, which in some cases included allowing people to ride (“bestride”) them.</note></seg> broad back;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Some did bestride <seg>Philanthrope’s broad back<note type="gloss">A reference to the dolphin, described etymologically as the “lover of humans,” appears in classical anecdotes about the singer Arion, who was robbed and left to drown in the sea, but saved by a dolphin—or sometimes a school of dolphins—that carried him back to shore.</note></seg>.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="25">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">The <seg>Nimphes<note type="physical">final part of “h” appears added to earlier “l,” crowded between surrounding letters</note></seg> in Perley ſhells, not one <seg>thar<note type="physical">“a” appears to correct earlier “ei”</note></seg> lacks</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">The <seg>nymphs<note type="gloss">semi-divine spirits in the form of maidens inhabiting the sea, rivers, mountains, woods, trees; often portrayed in poetry as attendants on a god</note></seg> in pearly shells, not one there lacks</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">The nymphs in pearly shells, not one there lacks</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="26">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Of all great Oceanus watry traine</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Of all great <seg>Oceanus’s<note type="gloss">in Greek mythology, the son of Uranus (Heaven) and Gaia (Earth); the personification of the great river believed to encircle the world</note></seg> wat’ry <seg>train<note type="gloss">a body of attendants or followers</note></seg>,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Of all great <seg>Oceanus’s watery train<note type="gloss">the numerous river gods and sea nymphs who were the children of Oceanus, the river that circled the world.</note></seg>,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="27">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">But floteinge came upon the frothey maine</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">But floating came upon the frothy <seg>main<note type="gloss">open sea</note></seg>.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">But floating came upon the frothy main,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">
            <milestone unit="poem-section" n="Nereus 1" rend="left-gutter"/>
          </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">
            <milestone unit="poem-section" n="Nereus 1" rend="left-gutter"/>
          </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">
            <milestone unit="poem-section" n="[...] reus 1" rend="left-gutter"/>
          </rdg>
        </app>
      <l n="28">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Emperiall Nereus frist did lead the waye</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Imperial <seg>Nereus<note type="gloss">an old sea god, father of the Nereides</note></seg> first did lead the way,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1"><seg>Imperial Nereus<note type="gloss">partly visible in the digital image, presumably marking the entrance of Nereus, father of the Nereids</note></seg> first did lead the way,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="29">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Who o’ur the tumed waves bares cheeffest ſwaye</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Who o’er the <seg>tumid<note type="gloss">swelling; puffed with wind</note></seg> waves bears chiefest sway;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Who o’er the tumid waves bears chiefest sway,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="30">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Rich <seg><del>purple</del><note type="physical">twice struck-through</note></seg> orient gemms his purple robe adorninge</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Rich <seg>orient gems<note type="gloss">possibly, pearls, especially those from near India; alternatively, any jewel from or associated with the Orient, the part of the globe east of Europe; “orient” could refer to a bright red color (like sunrise in the east), to the color or lustre of the best pearls (understood to come from the East), or to anything brilliant or resplendent.</note></seg> his purple robe adorning,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Rich <del>purple</del> orient gems his purple robe adorning,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="31">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Which cast a luster like the blusheinge morninge</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Which cast a luster like the blushing morning.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Which cast a luster like the <seg>blushing morning<note type="gloss">Nereus wears an imperial purple robe decked with gems that shines like the dawn.</note></seg>.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>

        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">
                <pb ed="#ft" facs="#f7610_266" n=""/>
            </rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">
                <pb ed="#ee" facs="#f7610_266"/>
            </rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">
                <pb ed="#ae" facs="#f7610_266"/>
            </rdg>
        </app>
        
      <l n="32">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">This glistringe Charott drawn with <del>Cro</del> pranceinge fishe</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">This <seg>glist’ring<note type="gloss">for “glistering,” meaning sparkling or glittering</note></seg> chariot drawn with prancing fish,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">This <seg>glist’ring<note type="gloss">glistering, an archaic form of glittering</note></seg> chariot drawn with prancing fish,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="33">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Which would have ſatisfied prowed <seg>[<del>?</del>]<note type="physical">diagonally struck-through text, possibly “ff[<del>?</del>]”</note></seg> Phaetons wishe</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Which would have satisfied proud <seg>Phaeton’s<note type="gloss">Phaeton was the rash son of Helios, the Greek sun god, who, when riding his father’s chariot, lost control of it and almost destroyed the world by fire (had Zeus not killed Phaeton and restored order).</note></seg> wish.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Which would have satisfied proud <seg>Phaeton’s<note type="gloss">the sun god, who rode a gleaming chariot across the sky</note></seg> wish.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">
            <milestone unit="poem-section" n="Doris 2" rend="left-gutter"/>
          </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">
            <milestone unit="poem-section" n="Doris 2" rend="left-gutter"/>
          </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">
            <milestone unit="poem-section" n="Doris 2" rend="left-gutter"/>
          </rdg>
        </app>
      <l n="34">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Just by his ſide faire fruetfull Doris came</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Just by his side, fair fruitful <seg>Doris<note type="gloss">a sea goddess, wife of Nereus and mother of the Nereides</note></seg> came,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1"><seg>Just<note type="gloss">marginal note marking the entrance of Doris, wife of Nereus and mother of the numerous Nereids</note></seg> by his side fair fruitful Doris came,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="35">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Whos numeros iſsew doth inlarge her fame</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Whose numerous <seg>issue<note type="gloss">offspring</note></seg> doth enlarge her fame;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Whose numerous issue doth enlarge her fame;</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="36">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Riche Orient Perls her ſnowey neck did grace</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Rich orient pearls her snowy neck did grace;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Rich orient pearls her snowy neck did grace;</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="37">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Her ſparklinge Crowne gave luster to her face</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Her sparkling crown gave luster to her face;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Her sparkling crown gave luster to her face;</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="38">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Between her brests a rich Carbuncle ſhone</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">Between her breasts a rich <seg>carbuncle<note type="gloss">a large precious stone of a red or fiery color; a mythical jewel reputed to emit light in darkness</note></seg> shone;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">Between her breasts a rich <seg>carbuncle<note type="gloss">precious red gemstone</note></seg> shone.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="39">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">The univerce afforded not a ſtone</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">The universe afforded not a stone</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">The universe afforded not a stone</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="40">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">That equal’d itt for ſplendentie of light</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">That equalled it for <seg>splendency<note type="gloss">splendor, brilliance</note></seg> of light.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">That equaled it for <seg>splendentie<note type="gloss">Pulter’s idiosyncratic form of “splendency,” or splendor</note></seg> of light;</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="41">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Itt rul’d the rest as Cinthia doth the night</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" rend="left-gutter-1">It ruled the rest as <seg>Cynthia<note type="gloss">the personification of the moon</note></seg> doth the <seg>night<note type="gloss">The poem breaks off here and is unfinished.</note></seg></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" rend="left-gutter-1">It ruled the rest as <seg>Cynthia<note type="gloss">goddess of the moon</note></seg> doth the night</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>

    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
