<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../src/vmachine.xsl"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
  schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI [

  <!ENTITY ff "<!-- ff ligature, representing capital modern day capital F, here represented as 'ff' -->ff">

  ]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mads.pp.26">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
          <title>To Aurora [2]</title>
        <title type="sub">Poem #26</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Created by</resp>
          <persName>Leah Knight</persName>
          <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoded by</resp>
          <persName>Katherine Poland</persName>
          <persName>Matthew Taylor</persName>
          <persName>Betsy Chou</persName>
          <persName>Emily Andrey</persName>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>IT-project consultation by</resp>
          <persName>Josh Honn</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
          <orgName>Brock University</orgName>
          <orgName>University of Leeds</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <principal>
          <persName/>
        </principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="1"/>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription, transformations, and notes</resp>
          <persName>Leah Knight</persName>
          <orgName>Brock University</orgName>
          <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
        </respStmt>
      </editionStmt>
      <extent/>
      <publicationStmt>
        <ab/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listBibl>
          <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
              <repository>See witness list.</repository>
            </msIdentifier>
          </msDesc>
        </listBibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p/>
      </projectDesc>
      <p>Transcriptions are encoded in TEI(P5)-conformant XML.</p>
      <samplingDecl>
        <p/>
      </samplingDecl>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction>
          <p>Apparent errors are preserved and editorial corrections provided using SIC and CORR tags, but only where the editor conjectures that the original scribe or compositor would have recognized the instance as an error. For example, what according to modern usage is incorrect subject/verb agreement might have been deemed acceptable to a seventeenth-century scribe or compositor. All such instances are treated instead using the ORIG and REG tags. (See below.)</p>
          <p>Corrections and annotations made within the scope of the original document either by its original authors, owners, and/or transcribers are noted using ADD tags. These annotations and may be further explained within NOTE tags, as added by the editors of this digital edition, for display within the apparatus.</p>
        </correction>
        <normalization>
          <p>Original spellings, abbreviations, and orthography are preserved. Where in the manuscripts a character's status as majuscule or minuscule is ambiguous, the editor has silently chosen one or the other based on context and judgment (i.e., does not register such ambiguity in either the markup or the notes).</p>
        </normalization>
        <quotation>
          <p>Original quotation marks, if any, are preserved.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation>
          <p>Original hyphenation is preserved.</p>
        </hyphenation>
      </editorialDecl>
      <charDecl>
        <!-- Ligature combinations for which there are currently no corresponding Unicode codepoints. -->
        <glyph xml:id="ffllig">
          <glyphName>Handwritten 'ff' ligature, used in handwriting to represent modern F</glyphName>
        </glyph>
      </charDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="DDC22">
          <bibl>
            <title>Dewey Decimal Classification</title>
            <edition/>
            <publisher/>
            <pubPlace/>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-GB">British English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <!-- dewey decimal system class code 821: English Poetry -->
        <classCode scheme="DDC22">821</classCode>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
    <!-- List of all images associated with this document -->
      <graphic url="./document_images/7610_089.jpg" xml:id="f7610_089"/>
      <graphic url="./document_images/7610_090.jpg" xml:id="f7610_090"/>
  </facsimile>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="ft">Transcription of manuscript: By <persName xml:id="lknight">Leah Knight</persName> and <persName xml:id="wwall">Wendy Wall</persName>.</witness>
          <witness xml:id="ee">Elemental edition: By <persName>Leah Knight</persName> and <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>.</witness>
          <witness xml:id="ae">Amplified edition: By <persName>Victoria E. Burke</persName>.</witness>
        </listWit>
      </div>
    </front>

    <body>
      <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">
              <pb ed="#ft" facs="#f7610_089" n="43r"/>
          </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">
              <pb ed="#ee" facs="#f7610_089"/>
          </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">
              <pb ed="#ae" facs="#f7610_089"/>
          </rdg>
      </app>
      <head>
        <app type="title">
            <rdg wit="#ft"><fw facs="#f7610_069" type="pageNum" place="margin-topright">PG#</fw>To Aurora [2]</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">To Aurora [2]</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">To Aurora [2]</rdg>
        </app>
        <app type="editorialnote">
          <rdg wit="#ft">
            <note type="editorialnote">In these transcriptions we preserve as many details of the original material, textual, and graphic properties of Hester Pulter’s manuscript verse as we have found practical. Whenever possible, for instance, original spelling, punctuation, capitalization, lineation, insertions, deletions, alterations, spacing between words and lines, and indentation are all maintained; abbreviations and brevigraphs are not expanded; and superscript and subscript representations are retained. <ref target="http://pulterproject.northwestern.edu/about-project-conventions.html#top" type="new-window-url">See full conventions for the transcriptions here.</ref></note>
          </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">
            <note type="editorialnote">The aim of the elemental edition is to make the poems accessible to the largest variety of readers, which involves modernizing spelling and punctuation as well as adding basic glosses. Spelling and punctuation reflect current standard American usage; punctuation highlights syntax which might otherwise be obscure. Outmoded but still familiar word forms (“thou,” “‘tis,” “hold’st”) are not modernized, and we do not modernize grammar when the sense remains legible. After a brief headnote aimed at offering a “way in” to the poem’s unique qualities and connections with other verse by Pulter or her contemporaries, the edition features a minimum of notes and interpretative framing to allow more immediate engagement with the poem. Glosses clarify synonyms or showcase various possible meanings in Pulter’s time. Other notes identify named people and places or clarify obscure material. We rely (without citation) primarily on the Oxford English Dictionary (OED), the Oxford Reference database, and the King James Version (KJV) of the Bible. When we rely on Alice Eardley’s edition of Pulter’s work, we cite her text generally (“Eardley”); other sources are cited in full. The result is an edition we consider a springboard for further work on Pulter’s poetry. <ref target="http://pulterproject.northwestern.edu/about-project-conventions.html#elemental-edition" type="new-window-url">See full conventions for this edition here.</ref></note></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">
            <note type="editorialnote">This is a semi-diplomatic transcription in which original spelling and punctuation are retained, abbreviations (such as tildes) are expanded with added letters in italics (with the exception of “<w lemma="the"><abbr>y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi></abbr></w>” which is rendered as “the”), “ff” is modernized to “F,” superscriptions are lowered, colons indicating abbreviations are removed, and major alterations to the text (of a word or more, not individual letters) are noted in the footnotes. The retention of original spelling and punctuation has the potential to get us closer to the choices made by the poet and scribe, but some scribal details (such as abbreviations) do not seem substantive or meaning-bearing and run the risk of alienating a modern reader.</note>
          </rdg>
        </app>
        <app type="headnote">
          <rdg wit="#ee">
              <note type="headnote">Throughout her collection, Pulter repeatedly tests ways to poetically imagine and interpret the moment of sunrise, which usually has strong symbolic resonances in Christianity. But in this poem in which Pulter seeks consolation in the morning sky, she keeps her attention fully on a pagan mythological and female-populated world. The speaker commands her own eyes to take in the splendor of a personified goddess of the dawn, Aurora, who fills the beholder’s senses and enamors viewers. As she did in <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="51">Made When I Was Not Well</ref> and <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="11">Tell Me No More</ref>, Pulter creates a radical response to the poetic convention of the blazon (a catalogue of body parts filled with comparisons). Rather than a male viewer anatomizing and eroticizing a female body, Pulter dwells on a temporal moment—sunrise—which emerges in sensuous corporeal detail, complete with curling hair, blushing cheeks, clear eyes, and fair breasts. The poem soon is filled with female goddesses: the reader is to imagine Astraea, the goddess of truth or justice, “naked in the arms of Light” (her mother Aurora); and Cynthia, goddess of the moon, hides in shame at Aurora’s superior radiant beauty, as do the other stars and planets visible only at night. In the second half of the poem, the speaker declares that she would have worshipped Aurora had she lived in pagan times, and she provides an extensive list of all the female deities she would reject (she does not imagine worshipping a male god at all). The irony of the poem’s ending lies in the fact that the rituals of worship (here, burning incense) obscure her view of the deified Aurora.</note>
          </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">
            <note type="headnote">
              <p>Aurora, the Roman goddess of the dawn, was evidently an important figure in Pulter’s poetry, and in this poem she comes to represent divine “Light,” which the speaker cannot properly see until she is in heaven (ll. 12-14). This poem is the second of three poems with the same title, “To Aurora” (the others are <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="22">To Aurora [1]</ref> and <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="34">To Aurora [3]</ref>); Pulter also wrote two poems headed simply “Aurora” (<ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="3">Aurora [1]</ref> and <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="37">Aurora [2]</ref>). In this poem the speaker addresses her desolate self, requesting that she look up to see the beautiful morning while also noting that Cynthia (the moon) and all the other planets retreat in Aurora’s presence. Pulter explains that if she had lived in a pre-Christian era and worshipped pagan divinities, she might have chosen to celebrate a number of goddesses that she goes on to list (Juno, Bellona, Venus, Derceto, Cybele, Diana, Ceres, Doris, Leucothea, and Isis). Instead, she knows that she would have chosen to celebrate Aurora, to whom she would send up so many burnt offerings that the smoke would obscure the sky. It is noteworthy that she never entertains the notion of worshipping any male gods–she only mentions Jupiter, ruler of the gods, at the end of the poem in the context of imagining Aurora being sufficiently worshipped and so not needing to complain to him. Perhaps most noteworthy of all, in this and several poems that praise Aurora and other goddesses, Pulter does not explicitly refer to the male Judaeo-Christian God, or his son, Jesus Christ. For Pulter, the concept of divine light in this poem is not primarily derived from a biblical tradition which described Christ as “the true Light, which lighteth every man that cometh into the world” (John 1:9), but is instead mediated by a feminine force. Arguably, Pulter is not mocking the idol worship of classical tradition in her references to goddesses she might have revered had she lived in a different age; in this poem and elsewhere in her work, goddesses and feminized planets seem to function as a complement to traditional Christian religious iconography.</p>
              <p>While the poet ends up equating Aurora with light itself (ll. 12 and 30)–arguably a divine quality, or a version of God himself, rather than just the dawn of the day in classical tradition–her characterization of pagan gods and goddesses can have an element of fun in them. In <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="59">My Love is Fair</ref> the poet seems to mock the wooer of the poem who is convinced that his beloved surpasses a number of goddesses (for example, the speaker wonders if the cheeks of his beloved excel Aurora’s at l. 7). The speaker ends that poem by urging the lover to hop on a dolphin and woo his beloved if she is so sublime. In that poem Pulter uses Aurora to evoke the Petrarchan tradition of sensual female beauty, a discourse she also plays with in this poem in its moments of eroticism, as when she claims that Aurora’s beauty will enamour her own eyes (l. 6), and when she evokes the naked goddess Astraea, only to resolve that image into something divine (ll. 11-12).</p>
              <p>Aurora was a character that several early modern women writers used in their poetry, depicting her appearance and significance in different ways. In her poem “The Dream,” from <title rend="italic">Mortality’s Memorandum, with a Dream Prefixed, Imaginary in Manner, Real in Matter</title> (1621), Rachel Speght imagines her speaker sleeping at night, before “Aurora spread her glitt’ring beams / Or did with robes of light herself invest” (ll. 13-14; <title rend="italic">Women Writers in Renaissance England</title>, edited by Randall Martin, Longman, 1997, p. 433). But when her miraculous dream vision in which she gains an education at the hands of mostly female allegorical figures is interrupted by Death killing her mother, she is jolted awake, without the gentle guidance of the dawning morning. Aemilia Lanyer also uses the image of Aurora in her dream vision poem, “The Authors Dreame to the Ladie Marie, the Countesse Dowager of Pembrooke,” one of her prefatory poems to women which precedes her poem on the Passion of Christ, <title rend="italic">Salve Deus Rex Judaeorum</title> (1611). In this poem, the speaker sees Mary Sidney crowned and sitting in Honour’s chair in her mind’s eye. Bellona, goddess of war and wisdom, and Dictina or Pheobe, goddess of the moon, pay homage, but Aurora, “rising from her rosie bedde, / First blusht then wept, to see fair Phoebe grac’d” (ll. 61-62; <title rend="italic">The Poems of Aemilia Lanyer: Salve Deus Rex Judaeorum</title>, edited by Susanne Woods, Oxford UP, 1993, p. 24). Aurora tells Flora, goddess of the spring and flowers, that she will bring the sun to dull Phoebe’s beauty–“And I will give a greater light than she” (l. 70)–which Aurora achieves. Kari Boyd McBride has suggested that in this scene Lanyer is depicting a struggle for primacy between Queen Elizabeth I (Phoebe or Cynthia, a common identification for the Virgin Queen) and Queen Anne (Aurora). McBride sees Aurora’s summoning of the sun to dim Phoebe’s light as potentially a comment on James I’s power and thus by extension a suggestion that his consort’s own power is dependent on his (Kari Boyd McBride, “Sacred Celebration: The Patronage Poems,” <title rend="italic">Aemilia Lanyer: Gender, Genre, and the Canon</title>, edited by Marshall Grossman, UP of Kentucky, 1998, pp. 60-82 [p. 82 note 33]). Another interesting use of Aurora occurs in a work by Sor Juana Inés de la Cruz, a Hispanic writer who lived 1648-1695 and was a cloistered nun in colonial Mexico. Her dream vision poem, <title rend="italic">Primero sueño</title> [First Dream]–like Speght’s, a depiction of the soul’s quest for knowledge–also uses the figure of Aurora. Stephanie Merrim has suggested that, in this poem, the poet “gathers the daring, transgressive female (and male) characters [such as Phaethon] into Aurora,” and allows the goddess to stand as a “model and mask” for the poetic speaker (<title rend="italic">Early Modern Women’s Writing and Sor Juana Inés de la Cruz</title>, Vanderbilt UP, 1999, p. 209). I am grateful Regina Buccola for suggesting these women writers as parallels to Pulter in their use of Aurora.</p>
            </note>
          </rdg>
        </app>
      </head>

      <l n="1">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Look up Sad eyes behould the Smileing Morn:</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Look up, sad eyes, behold the smiling morn,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Look up Sad eyes <seg>behould the Smileing Morn<note type="critical">Pulter is addressing herself and contrasting her sadness with the dawn’s happiness. Pulter’s poetry outlines many reasons for sadness: the deaths of some of her children, the execution of Charles I, and her own exile in the country, though none of those issues are raised in this poem. Here, her yearning for heaven puts her in the pose of a supplicant, a common Christian stance, but one she complicates by populating her heaven with female figures instead of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghost.</note></seg>:</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="2">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">How Shee her Golden treſses doth Adorn</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">How <seg>she<note type="gloss">Aurora, goddess of dawn</note></seg> her golden <seg>tresses<note type="gloss">long locks of hair; braids of hair; figuratively applied to tendrils or rays of the sun</note></seg> doth adorn</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">How Shee her Golden <seg>tresses<note type="gloss">Aurora’s long locks of hair (“tresses”) are golden to represent the sun’s rays.</note></seg> doth Adorn</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="3">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">With Sparkling Ge<hi rend="overline">m</hi>s and Roses Redolent</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">With sparkling gems and roses <seg>redolent<note type="gloss">fragrant</note></seg>,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">With Sparkling Gem<hi rend="italic">m</hi>s and Roses Redolent</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="4">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">And Julyflowers, whose Aromatick Sent</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">And <seg>gillyflowers<note type="gloss">July flowers or carnations; flowers scented like cloves</note></seg> whose aromatic scent</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">And <seg>Julyflowers<note type="gloss">Aurora is associated in this and the previous line with beautiful sights (sparkling gems, which suggest light reflecting off of dew) and lovely scents (fragrant or “redolent” roses, and gillyflowers or carnations).</note></seg>, whose Aromatick <seg>Sent<note type="gloss">i.e., scent</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="5">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Perfumes the World, look but up and See</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Perfumes the world; look but up and see!</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Perfumes the World, <seg>look but up<note type="critical">Pulter reprises her call for her eyes to look up at the dawning day (“Look up,” l. 1).</note></seg> and See</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="6">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Trust mee her bevty will inamour thee</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Trust me, her beauty will enamor thee.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Trust mee her bevty will <seg>inamour<note type="critical">The word “enamour” introduces Petrarchan language: Aurora is fair, she has blushing cheeks, clear eyes, curling hair, and a fair breast (ll. 7-9). But while Pulter has introduced a potentially sexualized situation, she undercuts it with the description of Aurora nursing Truth or Astraea at ll. 9-10 (see also <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="23">To Astraea</ref>, ll. 1-4). The reader realizes that the love the speaker will feel for Aurora’s beauty is a spiritual one, and that the evocation of Aurora’s breasts is an image that fuses motherly nourishment with divine revelation. The same-sex eroticism of the female addressee becoming enamoured by a beautiful goddess is replaced by, but still potentially co-exists with, a spiritual interpretation.</note></seg> thee</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="7">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Shee is Soe Sweet, Soe young, soe Heavenly faire</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">She is so sweet, so young, so heavenly fair,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Shee is <seg>Soe Sweet, Soe young, soe Heavenly faire<note type="critical">Pulter uses anaphora, or the repetition of the first word in successive phrases, to emphasize Aurora’s sweetness, youth, and beauty, though the speaker insists on the spiritual quality of the goddess’s beauty.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="8">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">With blushing cheeks clear eyes, and curling Haire</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">With blushing cheeks, clear eyes, and curling hair.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">With <seg>blushing cheeks clear eyes, and curling Haire<note type="critical">As in the line above, a tripartite structure (in this case three adjective-noun pairings) emphasizes conventionally beautiful aspects of Aurora’s appearance.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="9">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">View that fair breast which in her prime of Youth</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">View that fair breast which, in her prime of youth,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">View that fair breast which in her prime of Youth</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="10">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Gave nouriſhment unto eternall truth</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Gave nourishment unto eternal <seg>Truth<note type="gloss">Astraea, goddess of justice, whom Pulter also identifies as the goddess of truth, born from Aurora</note></seg>.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Gave nourishment unto eternall truth</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="11">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Oh that I once could See that lovly Sight</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">O, that I once could see that lovely sight:</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Oh that I once could See that lovly Sight</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="12">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Astrea naked in the Arms of Light</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Astraea, naked in the arms of <seg>Light<note type="gloss">Aurora</note></seg>!</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>Astrea naked in the Arms of Light<note type="critical">This is another moment when Pulter is playing with erotic expectations, since a figure lying naked in another figure’s arms suggests an earthly, and potentially sinful, scene of desire. But the image brings in the abstract, divine qualities of Truth and Light, which the speaker goes on to note cannot be properly seen in this world but only in the afterlife. Again, all of these figures (Astraea, Aurora, and the addressee) are female, which raises the potential of same-sex eroticism that is discounted, at least on the surface. Instead, the image of a mother holding a child in her arms is evoked, reminding us of Pulter’s own frequent references in her poetry to being a mother, and to motherhood more generally (for example, in many of the animal examples of <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="57">Why Must I Thus Forever Be Confined</ref>). Several of the goddesses depicted below are also associated with their roles as mothers: Derceto, Cybele, Ceres, and Doris. Though Pulter does not mention it, in the myth, Leucothea throws herself into the sea holding her son, and Isis is, among other things, a fertility and mother goddess.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="13">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">But oh I ne’re can See it till aboue</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">But O, I ne’er can see it, till above</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">But oh I ne’re can See it till aboue</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="14">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">I am involv’d in endles Joy and Love</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">I am <seg>involved<note type="gloss">entangled, encompassed</note></seg> in endless joy and love.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">I am <seg>involv’d in endles Joy and Love<note type="gloss">The place depicted is heaven. Pulter frequently uses the word “involved” in her verse, meaning enfolded or enveloped.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="15">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">View then thoſe Robes <w lemma="which"><abbr>w:<hi rend="superscript">ch</hi></abbr></w> doth her limbs infold</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">View, then, those robes which doth her limbs enfold,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">View then those Robes w<hi rend="italic">hi</hi>ch doth her limbs infold</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="16">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Rich purple fring’d with <seg>never<note type="physical">“er” appears crowded before next word, in different hand</note></seg> wasting Gold</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Rich purple, fringed with <seg>never-wasting<note type="gloss">never-decaying</note></seg> gold.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Rich <seg>purple fring’d with never wasting Gold<note type="critical">Pulter characterizes Aurora as wearing purple robes fringed with gold, capturing the colours of dawn, but also suggesting with the phrase “never wasting” an image of eternity, which contrasts with the ever-changing sky (reminding us of the earthly and divine tension in the imagery).</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="17">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Pale Cinthie doth her Sickly bevty Shrow’d</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Pale <seg>Cynthie<note type="gloss">Cynthia, moon goddess</note></seg> doth her <seg>sickly<note type="gloss">pale, feeble</note></seg> beauty shroud,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Pale <seg>Cinthie doth her Sickly bevty Shrow’d<note type="critical">The goddess Cynthia here represents the moon. Her beauty is “sickly” because the moon is pale, reflecting the sun’s light. There may also be a pun on a sickle-shaped moon (my thanks to Leah Knight for this suggestion). She wears a dark cloud as a veil, presumably because she knows her beauty is inferior to Aurora’s.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="18">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">And for a vaile Shee wears a Sable Clowd</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">And for a veil <seg>she<note type="gloss">Cynthia</note></seg> wears a sable cloud;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">And for a vaile Shee wears a Sable Clowd</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">
                <fw type="catch" place="bottom">And</fw>
            </rdg>
        </app>
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">
                <pb ed="#ft" facs="#f7610_090" n="43v"/>
            </rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">
                <pb ed="#ee" facs="#f7610_090"/>
            </rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">
                <pb ed="#ae" facs="#f7610_090"/>
            </rdg>
        </app>
      <l n="19">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">And all <seg><add place="below">^</add><add place="above"><w lemma="the"><abbr>y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi></abbr></w></add><note type="physical">“e” is superscript to the superscription</note></seg> other Glittring Globes of Light</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">And all the other glitt’ring globes of light</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">And all the other Glittring Globes of Light</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="20">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Contract their beams, and trundle out of Sight</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Contract their beams and <seg>trundle<note type="gloss">to revolve, roll</note></seg> out of sight.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Contract <seg>their beams<note type="gloss">Again, Pulter is contrasting Aurora’s brightness with other heavenly bodies.</note></seg>, and <seg>trundle<note type="gloss">“To move along a surface by revolving; to roll” (<title rend="italic">OED</title> 1b). The image is of a lightening sky that makes the planets less visible, but Pulter has given the heavenly bodies agency in their action of diminishing their beams and rolling away. They seem to agree with the speaker’s assessment of Aurora’s superiority by abasing themselves before her.</note></seg> out of Sight</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="21">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Had I liv’d on the Multiplicity</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Had I lived on the multiplicity</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Had I liv’d on the Multiplicity</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="22">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Of Heathen Gods, my chief felicity</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Of heathen gods, my chief felicity</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Of Heathen Gods, my chief felicity</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="23">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Would Surely bee rich Temples to Adorn</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Would surely be rich temples to adorn</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Would Surely bee rich Temples to Adorn</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="24">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Unto the Riſeing luster of the Morn</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Unto the rising luster of the morn:</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Unto <seg>the Riseing luster of the Morn<note type="gloss">This and the previous three lines indicate that, had the speaker been born in an earlier era in which heathen gods were worshipped, then she no doubt would have been most happy to deck out temples devoted to Aurora.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="25">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Juno, Belona, and the Queen of Love</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee"><seg>Juno, Bellona, and the Queen of Love,<note type="gloss">Juno (chief Olympian goddess); Bellona (goddess of war); and Venus, “Queen” or goddess of love</note></seg></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>Juno, Belona, and the Queen of Love<note type="gloss">The catalogue of all of the other goddesses the speaker would neglect in favour of Aurora begins with three Roman goddesses: Juno, queen of the goddesses and wife of Jupiter; Bellona, goddess of war; and Venus, goddess of love.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="26">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">And Shee whoſe Daughter turnd into a Dove</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee"><seg>And she whose daughter turned into a dove,<note type="gloss">Assyrian goddess Derceto; mother of Semiramis, queen and goddess who founded the city of Babylon, led victorious armies, and, eventually, took the form of a dove and flew away</note></seg></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">And <seg>Shee whose Daughter turnd into a Dove<note type="gloss">Derceto was a Syrian goddess whose daughter Semiramis was fed by doves as an infant and was turned into a dove upon her death.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="27">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Ould Berecinthia and her numerous brood</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Old <seg>Berecynthia<note type="gloss">surname of Cybele; mother and fertility goddess whose worshippers went into ecstatic raptures</note></seg> and her numerous brood,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Ould <seg>Berecinthia and her numerous brood<note type="gloss">As Alice Eardley notes in her edition of Pulter’s poetry, Berecynthia was the surname of the Greek and Roman mother goddess Cybele (<title rend="italic">Poems, Emblems, and The Unfortunate Florinda by Lady Hester Pulter</title>, The Other Voice in Early Modern Europe: The Toronto Series vol. 32, Iter and Centre for Reformation and Renaissance Studies, 2014, p. 369). Her brood was likely her children or her followers, known for their ecstatic celebrations.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="28">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Cruell Diana pleasd with Virgins Blood</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Cruel <seg>Diana<note type="gloss">goddess of chastity</note></seg>, pleased with virgin’s blood,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>Cruell Diana pleasd with Virgins Blood<note type="gloss">Diana was the Roman goddess of chastity, who was also associated with the moon (like Cynthia) and the hunt. Presumably Diana is cruel and pleased with virgin’s blood because she enjoys killing, has no interest in erotic love, and wishes to attract other virgins to follow her.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="29">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">With wandring Ceris all these would I <seg>Sleight<note type="physical">“S” written over other letter, probably “f”</note></seg></rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">With wand’ring <seg>Ceres<note type="gloss">goddess of agriculture</note></seg>: all these would I slight,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">With wandring <seg>Ceris<note type="gloss">Ceres is the Roman goddess of agriculture, who wandered because she looked for her daughter Propserpina after Proserpina was abducted by Pluto to the underworld.</note></seg> all these would I <seg>Sleight<note type="gloss">i.e., slight, or treat with disdain</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="30">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">And victims offer unto none but Light</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">And victims offer unto none but Light.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">And <seg>victims offer unto none but Light<note type="gloss">The speaker is continuing her claim from ll. 21-22 that if she followed a heathen religion she would slight all other goddesses and only offer pagan sacrifice (or kill victims on an altar) to Aurora, or Light.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="31">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Blew Doris, and her &ff;loating froathy train</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Blue <seg>Doris<note type="gloss">sea goddess and mother of water nymphs</note></seg> and her floating frothy train,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Blew <seg>Doris, and her Floating froathy train<note type="gloss">Doris, a Greek sea nymph, is likely blue because of her association with water; her train, or followers (the fifty Nereids, or sea nymphs, who were her daughters), would have floated and made froth behind her due to their watery habitation.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="32">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Lucothia that in Stately Thebs did Reign</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee"><seg>Leucothea<note type="gloss">princess of Thebes, deified as sea goddess after throwing herself into the ocean when her son was killed</note></seg> that in stately Thebes did reign,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>Lucothia that in Stately Thebs did Reign<note type="gloss">Leucothea was a Greek sea goddess who was the daughter of Cadmus, the first king of Thebes.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="33">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Ises, the Cow, the Goddes, and the Maid</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee"><seg>Isis, the cow, the goddess, and the maid,<note type="gloss">Isis is the Egyptian fertility and mother goddess, who was wife and sister of Osiris; protector of seafarers; often depicted with cow’s horns framing a disc of the sun</note></seg></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>Ises, the Cow, the Goddes, and the Maid<note type="critical">Isis is an Egyptian goddess with many roles (see the Elemental Edition). Pulter mentions the cow because Isis is often depicted wearing cow horns, and perhaps calls her “the goddess” to evoke her importance and the scope of her power. Why Pulter also calls her “the maid” is unclear, unless it is to highlight her gender and perhaps her youth.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="34">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Even all that on the wavey Empire Swayed</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Even all that on the <seg>wavy empire<note type="gloss">the ocean</note></seg> <seg>swayed<note type="gloss">ruled</note></seg>;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Even <seg>all that on the wavey Empire Swayed<note type="gloss">This appears to be a general characterization of all goddesses who ruled the ocean, which the speaker then goes on to contrast with her own devotion to Aurora in the last four lines.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="35">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Nor Should Shee Olympick Jupiter invoke</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Nor should <seg>she<note type="gloss">Aurora</note></seg> <seg>Olympic Jupiter<note type="gloss">Olympus was the home of the gods; Jupiter was the supreme Roman deity as well as the god of light and of the heavens; here the speaker declares that if she had been a heathen, she would have built sacrificial fires so often to Aurora that Aurora would not have needed to appeal to Jupiter for redress for her lack of visible adoration (smoke).</note></seg> <seg>invoke<note type="gloss">summon, appeal to</note></seg></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Nor Should <seg>Shee<note type="gloss">i.e., Aurora</note></seg> Olympick <seg>Jupiter<note type="gloss">Ruler of the gods, who lives on Mount Olympus</note></seg> invoke</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="36">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Becauſe <seg>her<note type="physical">“h” written over imperfectly erased “d”</note></seg> Alters did noe oft<add place="below">^</add><add place="above">n</add>er Smoke</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Because her altars did no oft’ner smoke;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Because <seg>her Alters did noe oftner Smoke<note type="gloss">Aurora will not have to complain to Jupiter than she is not being worshipped enough with sacrifices being burned in her honour.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="37">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">&ff;or I with Incence would Soe clowd <w lemma="the"><abbr>y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi></abbr></w> Skies</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">For I, with incense, would so cloud the skies</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">For <seg>I with Incence would Soe clowd the Skies<note type="critical">In this line and the next, the speaker indicates that she would, if she lived in pagan times, worship Aurora so consistently that the smoke from her own altar would cause clouds to form and would darken the eyes of Light, or Aurora, herself. Pulter tones down the brutality of the “victims” of l. 30 that are offered to heathen deities by depicting herself merely burning incense. The mention of Aurora’s shining eyes recalls the speaker’s “sad eyes” of l. 1, and suggests that she is now focused on devotion, rather than on the despondency mentioned in the opening lines of the poem. This final image of obscuring through creating the smoke of worship is a positive rewriting of the other moments of dullness in the poem: Cynthia veiling herself in a dark cloud, presumably due to shame at not being as bright as the morning (ll. 17-18), and the “glittering globes of light” drawing in their beams and rolling out of sight (ll. 19-20). But this concluding image is also somewhat odd in the speaker’s desire to dim the brightness of Aurora’s eyes, and may reveal some desire for dominance, even in this act of worship.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="38">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">That Should obſcure the Luster of her eyes</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">That <seg>should<note type="gloss">it should</note></seg> obscure the luster of her eyes.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">That Should obscure the Luster of her eyes</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
