<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../src/vmachine.xsl"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
  schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI [

  <!ENTITY ff "<!-- ff ligature, representing capital modern day capital F, here represented as 'ff' -->ff">

  ]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mads.pp.65">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The Hope</title>
        <title type="sub">Poem #65</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Created by</resp>
          <persName>Leah Knight</persName>
          <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoded by</resp>
          <persName>Katherine Poland</persName>
          <persName>Matthew Taylor</persName>
          <persName>Betsy Cho u</persName>
          <persName>Emily Andrey</persName>
          <persName>Sam Nguyen</persName>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>IT-project consultation by</resp>
          <persName>Josh Honn</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
          <orgName>Brock University</orgName>
          <orgName>University of Leeds</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <principal>
          <persName/>
        </principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="1"/>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription, transformations, and notes</resp>
          <persName>Leah Knight</persName>
          <orgName>Brock University</orgName>
          <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
        </respStmt>
      </editionStmt>
      <extent/>
      <publicationStmt>
        <ab/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listBibl>
          <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
              <repository>See witness list.</repository>
            </msIdentifier>
          </msDesc>
        </listBibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p/>
      </projectDesc>
      <p>Transcriptions are encoded in TEI(P5)-conformant XML.</p>
      <samplingDecl>
        <p/>
      </samplingDecl>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction>
          <p>Apparent errors are preserved and editorial corrections provided using SIC and CORR tags, but only where the editor conjectures that the original scribe or compositor would have recognized the instance as an error. For example, what according to modern usage is incorrect subject/verb agreement might have been deemed acceptable to a seventeenth-century scribe or compositor. All such instances are treated instead using the ORIG and REG tags. (See below.)</p>
          <p>Corrections and annotations made within the scope of the original document either by its original authors, owners, and/or transcribers are noted using ADD tags. These annotations and may be further explained within NOTE tags, as added by the editors of this digital edition, for display within the apparatus.</p>
        </correction>
        <normalization>
          <p>Original spellings, abbreviations, and orthography are preserved. Where in the manuscripts a character's status as majuscule or minuscule is ambiguous, the editor has silently chosen one or the other based on context and judgment (i.e., does not register such ambiguity in either the markup or the notes).</p>
        </normalization>
        <quotation>
          <p>Original quotation marks, if any, are preserved.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation>
          <p>Original hyphenation is preserved.</p>
        </hyphenation>
      </editorialDecl>
      <charDecl>
        <!-- Ligature combinations for which there are currently no corresponding Unicode codepoints. -->
        <glyph xml:id="ffllig">
          <glyphName>Handwritten 'ff' ligature, used in handwriting to represent modern F</glyphName>
        </glyph>
      </charDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="DDC22">
          <bibl>
            <title>Dewey Decimal Classification</title>
            <edition/>
            <publisher/>
            <pubPlace/>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-GB">British English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <!-- dewey decimal system class code 821: English Poetry -->
        <classCode scheme="DDC22">821</classCode>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
    <!-- List of all images associated with this document -->
    <graphic url="./document_images/7610_179.jpg" xml:id="f7610_179"/>
  </facsimile>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="ft">Transcription of manuscript: By <persName xml:id="lknight">Leah Knight</persName> and <persName xml:id="wwall">Wendy Wall</persName>.</witness>
          <witness xml:id="ee">Elemental edition: By <persName>Leah Knight</persName> and <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>.</witness>
          <witness xml:id="ae">Amplified edition: By <persName>Elizabeth Scott-Baumann</persName>.</witness>
          <witness xml:id="a2">Amplified edition: By <persName>Liza Blake</persName>.</witness>
          <witness xml:id="a3">Amplified edition: By <persName>Liza Blake</persName>.</witness>
          <witness xml:id="a4">Amplified edition: By <persName>Liza Blake</persName>.</witness>
        </listWit>
      </div>
    </front>

    <body>
      <app>
        <rdg wit="#ft">
          <pb ed="#ft" facs="#f7610_179" n="88r"/>
        </rdg>
        <rdg wit="#ee">
          <pb ed="#ee" facs="#f7610_179"/>
        </rdg>
        <rdg wit="#ae">
          <pb ed="#ae" facs="#f7610_179"/>
        </rdg>
        <rdg wit="#a2">
          <pb ed="#a2" facs="#f7610_179"/>
        </rdg>
        <rdg wit="#a3">
          <pb ed="#a3" facs="#f7610_179"/>
        </rdg>
        <rdg wit="#a4">
          <pb ed="#a4" facs="#f7610_179"/>
        </rdg>
      </app>

      <head>
        <app type="title">
          <rdg wit="#ft"><fw facs="#f7610_069" type="pageNum" place="margin-topright">165</fw><seg>The Hope<note type="physical">poem in H2</note></seg><lb/>
            January   : 1665 :</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee"><seg>The Hope<note type="physical">This poem is in a different hand from that of the main scribe, probably Pulter’s. Below the title is the date “January, 1665” also in Pulter’s hand.</note></seg></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>The Hope<note type="critical">In both this poem’s title reference to ‘The Hope’ and its narrative of reduction to dust, Pulter may allude to the <hi rend="italic">Book of Common Prayer</hi> (which laid out the forms of worship for the post-Reformation church in England) and especially its burial service: “Forasmuch it hath pleased Almighty God of his great mercy to take unto himself the soul of our dear brother here departed: we therefore commit his body to the ground; earth to earth, ashes to ashes, dust to dust; in sure and certain hope of the Resurrection to eternal life, through our Lord Jesus Christ; who shall change our vile body, that it may be like unto his glorious body, according to the mighty working, whereby he is able to subdue all things to himself.” (See <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="#ctxs">Dust</ref> in ‘The Order for The Burial of the Dead’ in Curations for this poem.)</note></seg>
            January 1665 <seg type="context-within-title">Amplified Edition A</seg>
          </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#a2">The [Uncertain] Hope<lb/>January 1665 <seg type="context-within-title">Amplified Edition B</seg></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#a3">The Hope [for Resurrection]<lb/>January 1665 <seg type="context-within-title">Amplified Edition C</seg></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#a4">The Hope [for Final Death]<lb/> January 1665 <seg type="context-within-title">Amplified Edition D</seg></rdg>
        </app>
        <app type="editorialnote">
          <rdg wit="#ft">
            <note type="editorialnote">In these transcriptions we preserve as many details of the original material, textual, and graphic properties of Hester Pulter’s manuscript verse as we have found practical. Whenever possible, for instance, original spelling, punctuation, capitalization, lineation, insertions, deletions, alterations, spacing between words and lines, and indentation are all maintained; abbreviations and brevigraphs are not expanded; and superscript and subscript representations are retained. <ref target="//pulterproject.northwestern.edu/about-project-conventions.html#top" type="new-window-url">See full conventions for the transcriptions here.</ref></note>
          </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">
            <note type="editorialnote">The aim of the elemental edition is to make the poems accessible to the largest variety of readers, which involves modernizing spelling and punctuation as well as adding basic glosses. Spelling and punctuation reflect current standard American usage; punctuation highlights syntax which might otherwise be obscure. Outmoded but still familiar word forms (“thou,” “‘tis,” “hold’st”) are not modernized, and we do not modernize grammar when the sense remains legible. After a brief headnote aimed at offering a “way in” to the poem’s unique qualities and connections with other verse by Pulter or her contemporaries, the edition features a minimum of notes and interpretative framing to allow more immediate engagement with the poem. Glosses clarify synonyms or showcase various possible meanings in Pulter’s time. Other notes identify named people and places or clarify obscure material. We rely (without citation) primarily on the Oxford English Dictionary (OED), the Oxford Reference database, and the King James Version (KJV) of the Bible. When we rely on Alice Eardley’s edition of Pulter’s work, we cite her text generally (“Eardley”); other sources are cited in full. The result is an edition we consider a springboard for further work on Pulter’s poetry. <ref target="//pulterproject.northwestern.edu/about-project-conventions.html#elemental-edition" type="new-window-url">See full conventions for this edition here.</ref></note></rdg>

          <rdg wit="#ae">
            <note type="editorialnote">With an undergraduate and graduate student audience in mind, this poem has been modernised in spelling and punctuation. Where modernisation would affect form, priority has been given to the integrity of the poem’s formal features (so, for instance, verb endings -est and -eth have been retained unmodernised; where the meter requires it, the verb ending -ed is accented, e.g., “Then shall thy blessèd influence”). Nouns have been capitalized only when there is clear personification. The notes provide information essential to understanding the poem, while the Headnote aims to stimulate readers’ own interpretations through suggesting literary or historical contexts, possible influences, comparable poems (by Pulter and by her predecessors and peers) and relevant critical arguments.</note>
          </rdg>

          <rdg wit="#a2"><note type="editorialnote"><p>Modern editorial theory distinguishes between substantive and accidental features of a text, where “substantive” means, roughly, those features or variants that affect the meaning of a text, and “accidental” designates those features whose alteration would not significantly change a text’s meaning. Accidental features might typically include typeface, spelling, capitalization, or punctuation. While an editor usually feels the need to add a note when she introduces an emendation or alters a <hi rend="italic">substantive</hi> feature, she might feel free to silently modernize <hi rend="italic">accidental</hi> features to make a text easier for modern readers to access and comprehend (indeed, as I note below, I have silently modernized spelling and capitalization in each of these Amplified Editions). However, as Erick Keleman reminds us in <title rend="italic">Textual Editing and Criticism</title>, “whether one variant is substantive or accidental is a question of interpretation” <bibl>(Erick Keleman, <title rend="italic">Textual Editing and Criticism: An Introduction</title> [New York: W.W. Norton &amp; Company, 2009], 16)</bibl> and, as I argue in the headnote, this poem offers a prime example of how punctuation is not accidental to this poem, but essential to its comprehension. Pulter’s poem, therefore, offers a useful case study for this long-held debate in textual criticism and editorial theory.</p>
            <p>I have modernized the text’s spelling and capitalization to concur with the <title rend="italic">Oxford English Dictionary Online</title> headwords, and have expanded poetic abbreviations where such expansions would not affect the meter for a modern reader. Quotations from other Pulter poems are from <title rend="italic">The Pulter Project</title>, and are cited by line number. Notes gloss difficult words and sentences and call attention to interesting textual and interpretive ambiguities, including, especially in this poem, those ambiguities caused by the punctuation (and lack of punctuation) in the original manuscript. For a fuller account of the editorial decisions that went into the punctuation in this version of the poem, please see the Headnote.</p></note></rdg>

          <rdg wit="#a3">
            <note type="editorialnote"><p>Modern editorial theory distinguishes between substantive and accidental features of a text, where “substantive” means, roughly, those features or variants that affect the meaning of a text, and “accidental” designates those features whose alteration would not significantly change a text’s meaning. Accidental features might typically include typeface, spelling, capitalization, or punctuation. While an editor usually feels the need to add a note when she introduces an emendation or alters a <hi rend="italic">substantive</hi> feature, she might feel free to silently modernize <hi rend="italic">accidental</hi> features to make a text easier for modern readers to access and comprehend (indeed, as I note below, I have silently modernized spelling and capitalization in each of these Amplified Editions). However, as Erick Keleman reminds us in <title rend="italic">Textual Editing and Criticism</title>, “whether one variant is substantive or accidental is a question of interpretation” <bibl>(Erick Keleman, <title rend="italic">Textual Editing and Criticism: An Introduction</title> [New York: W.W. Norton &amp; Company, 2009], 16)</bibl> and, as I argue in the headnote, this poem offers a prime example of how punctuation is not accidental to this poem, but essential to its comprehension. Pulter’s poem, therefore, offers a useful case study for this long-held debate in textual criticism and editorial theory.</p>
              <p>I have modernized the text’s spelling and capitalization to concur with the <title rend="italic">Oxford English Dictionary Online</title> headwords, and have expanded poetic abbreviations where such expansions would not affect the meter for a modern reader. Quotations from other Pulter poems are from <hi rend="italic">The Pulter Project</hi>, and are cited by line number. Notes gloss difficult words and sentences and call attention to interesting textual and interpretive ambiguities, including, especially in this poem, those ambiguities caused by the punctuation (and lack of punctuation) in the original manuscript. For a fuller account of the editorial decisions that went into the punctuation in this version of the poem, please see the Headnote.</p></note>
          </rdg>

          <rdg wit="#a4">
            <note type="editorialnote"><p>Modern editorial theory distinguishes between substantive and accidental features of a text, where “substantive” means, roughly, those features or variants that affect the meaning of a text, and “accidental” designates those features whose alteration would not significantly change a text’s meaning. Accidental features might typically include typeface, spelling, capitalization, or punctuation. While an editor usually feels the need to add a note when she introduces an emendation or alters a <hi rend="italic">substantive</hi> feature, she might feel free to silently modernize <hi rend="italic">accidental</hi> features to make a text easier for modern readers to access and comprehend (indeed, as I note below, I have silently modernized spelling and capitalization in each of these Amplified Editions). However, as Erick Keleman reminds us in <title rend="italic">Textual Editing and Criticism</title>, “whether one variant is substantive or accidental is a question of interpretation” <bibl>(Erick Keleman, <title rend="italic">Textual Editing and Criticism: An Introduction</title> [New York: W.W. Norton &amp; Company, 2009], 16)</bibl> and, as I argue in the headnote, this poem offers a prime example of how punctuation is not accidental to this poem, but essential to its comprehension. Pulter’s poem, therefore, offers a useful case study for this long-held debate in textual criticism and editorial theory.</p>
              <p>I have modernized the text’s spelling and capitalization to concur with the <title rend="italic">Oxford English Dictionary Online</title> headwords, and have expanded poetic abbreviations where such expansions would not affect the meter for a modern reader. Quotations from other Pulter poems are from <hi rend="italic">The Pulter Project</hi>, and are cited by line number. Notes gloss difficult words and sentences and call attention to interesting textual and interpretive ambiguities, including, especially in this poem, those ambiguities caused by the punctuation (and lack of punctuation) in the original manuscript. For a fuller account of the editorial decisions that went into the punctuation in this version of the poem, please see the Headnote.</p></note>
          </rdg>

        </app>
        <app type="headnote">
          <rdg wit="#ee"><note type="headnote">“I have been half in love with easeful Death,” wrote Keats; “Call’d him soft names in many a mused rhyme, / To take into the air my quiet breath.” Pulter does as much in this poem, which begins like a love letter to Death. Its writer promises to throw herself into Death’s arms and let it use her body as it desires—if Death would only come. But the morbid seduction of the opening couplets soon shifts, as often in Pulter’s verse, to a fascinated meditation on the material reconfigurations which might follow our earthly life. Vital salt, vapor, atoms, and world-annihilating fire are all quickly canvassed as mere stages in a larger cosmological revolution directed by the only figure who upstages Death in Pulter’s <hi rend="italic">dramatis personae</hi>: the God who, she confidently predicts, shall turn the world upside-down by atomizing Death and returning her to life. The poem’s dramatic forward thrust through a single protracted sentence—driven by nearly breathless anaphoric hypotaxis, projecting us into an imagined future (“And then,” “Then,” “Nay, when,” “And when,” “And all,” “And even”)—is brought up short by a full stop and final confession: the speaker has no idea how what she envisions can actually come to be.</note></rdg>

          <rdg wit="#ae"><note type="headnote">From its opening, “Dear Death … I’ll throw myself into thy arms”, this poem evokes the panache and paradox of John Donne’s ‘Holy Sonnets’ (See <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="#ctxs">Dear Death</ref> in Curations for this poem). In his poem ’Batter my heart’, Donne deploys similar erotic metaphors of embrace, while his ‘Death, be not proud’ addresses Death directly as Pulter does here  (See also Pulter’s poem <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="19">The Welcome</ref> which opens “Dear death thou’rt welcome…”). Pulter’s characteristic approach, though, is to infuse this daring address to death with another register of imagery, that of alchemy: God breaks down and builds up the speaker not through ravishment, as with Donne, but through chemical transformation. In the original manuscript, this poem’s only full stop is halfway through the final line. This provides a sense of completion after the uplifting hope that God “Will raise me unto life”. Yet this hope is undercut by several other formal features: with fifteen lines, she extends beyond sonnet length; using a triplet after six couplets, she creates the anticipation of a further line which is not fulfilled; after the full stop in line 15 she creates abrupt uncertainty with the half line “I know not how”, a thought left hanging. The poem’s form questions its promised “hope”. (See Alice Eardley, ‘“I haue not time to point yr booke … which I desire you yourselfe to doe”: Editing the Form of Early Modern Manuscript Verse’ in <bibl><title rend="italic">The Work of Form: Poetics and Materiality in Early Modern Culture</title>, ed. Elizabeth Scott-Baumann and Ben Burton [Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2014], pp. 162-78)</bibl>.</note>
          </rdg>

          <rdg wit="#a2"><note type="headnote">
            <p>How hopeful is “The Hope”? Or rather, for what is it hopeful? The conventional wisdom is that, as a citation of <bibl><title rend="italic">The booke of the common prayer,</title></bibl><seg>1<note type="critical">See Elizabeth Scott-Baumann’s curation for this poem, <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="#ctxs">Dust</ref>, and her note on the title in A065a (Hester Pulter, <bibl>“The Hope. January 1665” [A065a], ed. Elizabeth Scott-Baumann, <title rend="italic">The Pulter Project: Poet in the Making</title></bibl>).</note></seg> “The Hope” refers to the “certain hope of resurrection” at the Final Judgment. However, the poem also indulges itself in a fantasy of total personal dissolution, on par with the <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="6">Universal Dissolution</ref> imagined earlier in Pulter’s manuscript, but here writ small into the confines of her body. She imagines being dissolved into dust, then broken down into salt (potentially a component of dust), then completely annihilated—but then reminds us that God, somehow, will be able to recreate enough matter to resurrect her: “I know not how.” These four words, placed after the poem’s only period, are the crux of the poem. Do they gesture to a boundless faith (I don’t know the science behind how he will do it, but I know he can because “He . . . hath supported me till now”)? Or do they gesture to a different kind of hope: a hope that maybe her death will not be the seed of a future resurrection, but an end? “I know not how” he could possibly bring me and my body (see <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="39">The Perfection of Patience and Knowledge</ref>) back from the complete material dissolution I have just imagined: maybe I can hope that he won’t, that death will actually just be the end.<seg>2<note type="critical">I am indebted for my reading of this poem to Marshelle Woodward, who argued for this poem’s ambiguity in a paper entitled “The Dissolving Worlds of Margaret Cavendish and Hester Pulter” at the International Margaret Cavendish Society Conference in 2017. The argument will be published as Marshelle Woodward, “Hester Pulter’s Dissolving Worlds,” in <title rend="italic">Worldmaking Women: New Essays on the Centrality of Women in Early Modern Literature and Culture</title>, ed. Pamela Hammons and Brandie Siegfried (Cambridge, Cambridge University Press, in progress).</note></seg></p>
              <p>This is one of three interrelated Amplified Editions of Pulter’s poem: Version B [The Uncertain Hope], Version C [The Hope for Resurrection], and Version D [The Hope for Final Death]. The editorial strategy underlying these three separate editions has been specifically designed to demonstrate this poem’s fascinating ambiguity, its ability to be read either as a poem hoping for final, absolute death, or as a poem hoping for resurrection. As I will discuss in this headnote, the ambiguity of the poem’s argument comes in large part from the almost complete lack of punctuation in the original manuscript. This headnote explains how it is that punctuation can so radically alter the meaning of Pulter’s “The Hope”; the end of the headnote describes the editorial principles and punctuating choices I have adopted for <hi rend="italic">this</hi> particular Amplified Edition (Version B [The Uncertain Hope]). If you wish to skip to the section of the headnote particular to this Amplified Edition, you can find it at the <ref type="pp-edition-section-ref" target="#a2-specific-headnote-section">bottom of this headnote</ref>, after the three asterisks (***).</p>
            <p>“The Hope” is unusual in comparison to other poems in Pulter’s manuscript collection in that it has especially sparse punctuation. In the original manuscript in which this poem (and all Pulter’s poems) can be found, “The Hope” has six punctuation marks in total: two parentheses enclosing a phrase, two commas used to break up a list, one comma used to break up a line, and one period before the final four words (“I know not how”).<seg>3<note type="critical">This count does not include apostrophes.</note></seg> In addition, the relative scarcity of punctuation in this poem may be authorial. While the majority of the manuscript is written in a neat (and likely professional/scribal) roundhand, this poem, and a few others, are written in a spiky italic hand that also has made frequent corrections to other poems in the manuscript. Though we don’t know for sure to whom any of the hands belong, most editors assume that the spiky hand that makes corrections throughout, and that writes “The Hope” (Poem 65) and <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="61">The Weeping Wish</ref>, is Pulter’s.<seg>4<note type="critical">Stefan Christian in his dissertation edition merely refers to the second, editorial hand; see <bibl>Hester Pulter, “The Poems of Lady Hester Pulter (1605?–1678): An Annotated Edition,” ed. Stefan Graham Christian (PhD diss., University of Massachusetts Amherst, 2012)</bibl>, 3–6 for his discussion. Alice Eardley in her edition asserts confidently that the hand is Pulter’s <bibl>(Hester Pulter, <title rend="italic">Poems, Emblems, and the Unfortunate Florinda</title>, ed. Alice Eardley [Toronto: Iter, Inc. and the Centre for Renaissance and Reformation Studies, 2014], 32–33, 180 n. 825)</bibl>, while Knight and Wall note that the hand is “probably Pulter’s”; see <bibl>Hester Pulter, “The Hope” (<ref target="/poems/ee/the-hope" type="new-window-url">Poem 65, Elemental Edition</ref>), ed. Leah Knight and Wendy Wall, <title rend="italic">The Pulter Project: Poet in the Making</title></bibl>, note on title.</note></seg></p>
            <p>Deciding where and how to punctuate this poem has the potential to radically change the argument of the poem. The poem moves from imagining death to imagining increasingly small dissolutions, to the burning even of atoms, to the turn to God’s abilities, in what Alice Eardley refers to as the poem’s “fluidity and gathering momentum"<seg>5<note type="critical"><bibl>Alice Eardley, “‘I haue not time to point yr booke . . . which I desire you yourselfe to doe’: Editing the Form of Early Modern Manuscript Verse,” in <title rend="italic">The Work of Form: Poetics and Materiality in Early Modern Culture</title>, ed. Ben Burton and Elizabeth Scott-Baumann (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2014), 166</bibl>; see Scott-Baumann’s Curation <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="#ctxs">Knowledge, Faith and Doubt</ref> for an excerpt from Eardley’s essay.</note></seg>—but, crucially for these three Amplified Editions, where one might punctuate the poem to pause that momentum radically changes the message. Adding a hard stop (e.g., a semi-colon or period) after line 6, for example, makes a poem unambiguously about the promise of resurrection. With a hard stop after line 6 the poem would divide into two parts, each of which would end with resurrective optimism: even after dissolution into dust, the still-more-essential “vital salt” can “be found out” (ll. 1–6); even when the world is turned into chaos, God will raise me unto life (ll. 7–15). If, on the other hand, one reads the first ten lines as a consecutive accumulation of destruction on increasingly minute scales (where lines 7–8 do not change the subject from line 6, but go on to destroy even the vital salt that has been “found out”), the poem seems to build instead to a darker hope, conjuring image after image of destruction only to end with the (ill-supported) idea that God may, nevertheless, find something to recover.</p>
            <p>I believe, therefore, that it is impossible for a modern editor to punctuate this poem in a way that preserves the question (What is the hope?) that I take to be constitutive of the poem itself.<seg>6<note type="critical">It is of course impossible to say whether Pulter intended her punctuation (or lack thereof) to function this way; early modern punctuation worked differently than modern punctuation. For an overview of early modern views on punctuation, see <bibl>Alicia Rodríguez-Álvarez, “Teaching Punctuation in Early Modern England,” <title rend="italic">Studia Anglica Posnaniensia</title> 46 (2010): 35–49</bibl>; see also my Curation <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="#ctxs">Punctuating Poetry</ref>.</note></seg> And this belief underlies the editorial strategy for these three editions.</p>
            <p>One option for an editor trying to decide what the poem means would be to consider it in light of other poems in the manuscript. Unfortunately, moving out to the rest of Pulter’s corpus only complicates the question of what “The Hope” hopes for. She is a pious poet, and many of her poems share the conviction that God’s “blessèd influence / [will] Triumph o’er Death, her impotence” (<ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="20">Dear God, Turn Not Away Thy Face</ref>, ll. 21–22). However, for every poem that trusts in God, there is a poem that fantasizes about the possible absoluteness of physical dissolution. In <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="1">The Eclipse</ref> she reminds the Earth of its “irrevocable dissolution, / As well as mine” (ll. 22–23), and <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="6">Universal Dissolution</ref> ends with the following unsettling advice: “Then my unsettled soul, be more resolved, / Seeing all this universe must be dissolved” (ll. 175–76). In <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="17">The Circle [1]</ref> she cries, “Then, gracious God, in Thee I’ll trust, / Although Thou crumble me to dust” (ll. 15–16): is the trust despite God’s crumbling ambitions, or because of them?<seg>7<note type="critical">One could accumulate many more examples: at times she imagines dust as the end of everything (see <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="21">The Circle [2]</ref>, ll. 13–14: “So man, the universe’s chiefest glory, / His primitive’s dust (alas) doth end his story”), and at other times she worries at the absolute finality of dust: “Should all annihilated be, / Which is as easy unto Thee; / Oh what would then become of me?” (see <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="16">The Revolution</ref>, ll. 22–24).</note></seg> The impossibility of pinning down “The Hope” is best embodied in the following paradox from her <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="6">Universal Dissolution</ref>: “When all’s to chaos turned, there will be peace” (l. 152). My Curation for this poem, <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="#ctxs">Wishing for the End</ref>, provides other examples of the somewhat unusual desire for absolute and final death, as well as examples of nihilism, in seventeenth-century poetry.</p>
              <p>In editing the poem, therefore, I have pursued the editorial strategy that I believe makes it most possible to experience the poem’s ambiguity to the fullest. This strategy has resulted in three separate Amplified Editions of the poem, which differ only in punctuation: Version B [The Uncertain Hope] contains only the manuscript’s punctuation, which allows readers to insert their own punctuation and to gauge their own readings of the poem; Version C [The Hope for Resurrection] is punctuated to bring out the resurrective reading; and Version D [The Hope for Final Death] is punctuated to bring out the reading that shows her yearning for a final death without resurrection.</p>
              <p>
                <seg id="a2-specific-headnote-section" rend="nl tac">***</seg>
              </p>
              <p>In the edition you are currently reading—Version B: The Uncertain Hope—I have retained the punctuation of the manuscript (and bolded those original punctuation marks, and colored them red, to call attention to them), but have not added any punctuation of my own. This version relies on the fundamental ambiguity created by the dearth of punctuation in the manuscript itself, which as I argued above leaves the ultimate message of the poem up to the interpreting reader’s personal punctuation decisions.</p>
              <p>In this edition I have left the punctuation in the manuscript intact, and have also added extra spaces between each of the words; I do this to invite readers, or students, to print (or copy-paste) the poem and to add their own punctuation, as a kind of exercise that will allow them to gauge their initial reading of the poem. Readers of this poem can also refer themselves to my two alternative Amplified Editions of the poem (Versions C and D), each of which punctuates the poem differently to bring out the resurrective and nihilistic readings, respectively. As the user of this digital edition, you can consult these alternate versions in a variety of ways: you might test your own reading on Version B before comparing your punctuation with my other two options, for instance. Or you might use <title rend="italic">The Pulter Project</title>’s built-in versioning tools to compare the multiple versions side by side, highlighting differences and discrepancies.</p></note></rdg>

          <rdg wit="#a3"><note type="headnote">
            <p>How hopeful is “The Hope”? Or rather, for what is it hopeful? The conventional wisdom is that, as a citation of <bibl><title rend="italic">The booke of the common prayer,</title></bibl><seg>1<note type="critical">See Elizabeth Scott-Baumann’s curation for this poem, <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="#ctxs">Dust</ref>, and her note on the title in A065a (Hester Pulter, <bibl>“The Hope. January 1665” [A065a], ed. Elizabeth Scott-Baumann, <title rend="italic">The Pulter Project: Poet in the Making</title></bibl>).</note></seg> “The Hope” refers to the “certain hope of resurrection” at the Final Judgment. However, the poem also indulges itself in a fantasy of total personal dissolution, on par with the <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="6">Universal Dissolution</ref> imagined earlier in Pulter’s manuscript, but here writ small into the confines of her body. She imagines being dissolved into dust, then broken down into salt (potentially a component of dust), then completely annihilated—but then reminds us that God, somehow, will be able to recreate enough matter to resurrect her: “I know not how.” These four words, placed after the poem’s only period, are the crux of the poem. Do they gesture to a boundless faith (I don’t know the science behind how he will do it, but I know he can because “He . . . hath supported me till now”)? Or do they gesture to a different kind of hope: a hope that maybe her death will not be the seed of a future resurrection, but an end? “I know not how” he could possibly bring me and my body (see <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="39">The Perfection of Patience and Knowledge</ref>) back from the complete material dissolution I have just imagined: maybe I can hope that he won’t, that death will actually just be the end.<seg>2<note type="critical">I am indebted for my reading of this poem to Marshelle Woodward, who argued for this poem’s ambiguity in a paper entitled “The Dissolving Worlds of Margaret Cavendish and Hester Pulter” at the International Margaret Cavendish Society Conference in 2017. The argument will be published as Marshelle Woodward, “Hester Pulter’s Dissolving Worlds,” in <title rend="italic">Worldmaking Women: New Essays on the Centrality of Women in Early Modern Literature and Culture</title>, ed. Pamela Hammons and Brandie Siegfried (Cambridge, Cambridge University Press, in progress).</note></seg></p>
            <p>This is one of three interrelated Amplified Editions of Pulter’s poem: Version B [The Uncertain Hope], Version C [The Hope for Resurrection], and Version D [The Hope for Final Death]. The editorial strategy underlying these three separate editions has been specifically designed to demonstrate this poem’s fascinating ambiguity, its ability to be read either as a poem hoping for final, absolute death, or as a poem hoping for resurrection. As I will discuss in this headnote, the ambiguity of the poem’s argument comes in large part from the almost complete lack of punctuation in the original manuscript. This headnote explains how it is that punctuation can so radically alter the meaning of Pulter’s “The Hope”; the end of the headnote describes the editorial principles and punctuating choices I have adopted for <hi rend="italic">this</hi> particular Amplified Edition (Version C [The Hope for Resurrection]). If you wish to skip to the section of the headnote particular to this Amplified Edition, you can find it at the <ref type="pp-edition-section-ref" target="#a3-specific-headnote-section">bottom of this headnote</ref>, after the three asterisks (***).</p>
            <p>“The Hope” is unusual in comparison to other poems in Pulter’s manuscript collection in that it has especially sparse punctuation. In the original manuscript in which this poem (and all Pulter’s poems) can be found, “The Hope” has six punctuation marks in total: two parentheses enclosing a phrase, two commas used to break up a list, one comma used to break up a line, and one period before the final four words (“I know not how”).<seg>3<note type="critical">This count does not include apostrophes.</note></seg> In addition, the relative scarcity of punctuation in this poem may be authorial. While the majority of the manuscript is written in a neat (and likely professional/scribal) roundhand, this poem, and a few others, are written in a spiky italic hand that also has made frequent corrections to other poems in the manuscript. Though we don’t know for sure to whom any of the hands belong, most editors assume that the spiky hand that makes corrections throughout, and that writes “The Hope” (Poem 65) and <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="61">The Weeping Wish</ref>, is Pulter’s.<seg>4<note type="critical">Stefan Christian in his dissertation edition merely refers to the second, editorial hand; see <bibl>Hester Pulter, “The Poems of Lady Hester Pulter (1605?–1678): An Annotated Edition,” ed. Stefan Graham Christian (PhD diss., University of Massachusetts Amherst, 2012)</bibl>, 3–6 for his discussion. Alice Eardley in her edition asserts confidently that the hand is Pulter’s <bibl>(Hester Pulter, <title rend="italic">Poems, Emblems, and the Unfortunate Florinda</title>, ed. Alice Eardley [Toronto: Iter, Inc. and the Centre for Renaissance and Reformation Studies, 2014], 32–33, 180 n. 825)</bibl>, while Knight and Wall note that the hand is “probably Pulter’s”; see <bibl>Hester Pulter, “The Hope” (<ref target="/poems/ee/the-hope" type="new-window-url">Poem 65, Elemental Edition</ref>), ed. Leah Knight and Wendy Wall, <title rend="italic">The Pulter Project: Poet in the Making</title></bibl>, note on title.</note></seg></p>
            <p>Deciding where and how to punctuate this poem has the potential to radically change the argument of the poem. The poem moves from imagining death to imagining increasingly small dissolutions, to the burning even of atoms, to the turn to God’s abilities, in what Alice Eardley refers to as the poem’s “fluidity and gathering momentum"<seg>5<note type="critical"><bibl>Alice Eardley, “‘I haue not time to point yr booke . . . which I desire you yourselfe to doe’: Editing the Form of Early Modern Manuscript Verse,” in <title rend="italic">The Work of Form: Poetics and Materiality in Early Modern Culture</title>, ed. Ben Burton and Elizabeth Scott-Baumann (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2014), 166</bibl>; see Scott-Baumann’s Curation <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="#ctxs">Knowledge, Faith and Doubt</ref> for an excerpt from Eardley’s essay.</note></seg>—but, crucially for these three Amplified Editions, where one might punctuate the poem to pause that momentum radically changes the message. Adding a hard stop (e.g., a semi-colon or period) after line 6, for example, makes a poem unambiguously about the promise of resurrection. With a hard stop after line 6 the poem would divide into two parts, each of which would end with resurrective optimism: even after dissolution into dust, the still-more-essential “vital salt” can “be found out” (ll. 1–6); even when the world is turned into chaos, God will raise me unto life (ll. 7–15). If, on the other hand, one reads the first ten lines as a consecutive accumulation of destruction on increasingly minute scales (where lines 7–8 do not change the subject from line 6, but go on to destroy even the vital salt that has been “found out”), the poem seems to build instead to a darker hope, conjuring image after image of destruction only to end with the (ill-supported) idea that God may, nevertheless, find something to recover.</p>
            <p>I believe, therefore, that it is impossible for a modern editor to punctuate this poem in a way that preserves the question (What is the hope?) that I take to be constitutive of the poem itself.<seg>6<note type="critical">It is of course impossible to say whether Pulter intended her punctuation (or lack thereof) to function this way; early modern punctuation worked differently than modern punctuation. For an overview of early modern views on punctuation, see <bibl>Alicia Rodríguez-Álvarez, “Teaching Punctuation in Early Modern England,” <title rend="italic">Studia Anglica Posnaniensia</title> 46 (2010): 35–49</bibl>; see also my Curation <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="#ctxs">Punctuating Poetry</ref>.</note></seg> And this belief underlies the editorial strategy for these three editions.</p>
            <p>One option for an editor trying to decide what the poem means would be to consider it in light of other poems in the manuscript. Unfortunately, moving out to the rest of Pulter’s corpus only complicates the question of what “The Hope” hopes for. She is a pious poet, and many of her poems share the conviction that God’s “blessèd influence / [will] Triumph o’er Death, her impotence” (<ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="20">Dear God, Turn Not Away Thy Face</ref>, ll. 21–22). However, for every poem that trusts in God, there is a poem that fantasizes about the possible absoluteness of physical dissolution. In <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="1">The Eclipse</ref> she reminds the Earth of its “irrevocable dissolution, / As well as mine” (ll. 22–23), and <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="6">Universal Dissolution</ref> ends with the following unsettling advice: “Then my unsettled soul, be more resolved, / Seeing all this universe must be dissolved” (ll. 175–76). In <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="17">The Circle [1]</ref> she cries, “Then, gracious God, in Thee I’ll trust, / Although Thou crumble me to dust” (ll. 15–16): is the trust despite God’s crumbling ambitions, or because of them?<seg>7<note type="critical">One could accumulate many more examples: at times she imagines dust as the end of everything (see <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="21">The Circle [2]</ref>, ll. 13–14: “So man, the universe’s chiefest glory, / His primitive’s dust (alas) doth end his story”), and at other times she worries at the absolute finality of dust: “Should all annihilated be, / Which is as easy unto Thee; / Oh what would then become of me?” (see <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="16">The Revolution</ref>, ll. 22–24).</note></seg> The impossibility of pinning down “The Hope” is best embodied in the following paradox from her <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="6">Universal Dissolution</ref>: “When all’s to chaos turned, there will be peace” (l. 152). My Curation for this poem, <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="#ctxs">Wishing for the End</ref>, provides other examples of the somewhat unusual desire for absolute and final death, as well as examples of nihilism, in seventeenth-century poetry.</p>
            <p>In editing the poem, therefore, I have pursued the editorial strategy that I believe makes it most possible to experience the poem’s ambiguity to the fullest. This strategy has resulted in three separate Amplified Editions of the poem, which differ only in punctuation: Version B [The Uncertain Hope] contains only the manuscript’s punctuation, which allows readers to insert their own punctuation and to gauge their own readings of the poem; Version C [The Hope for Resurrection] is punctuated to bring out the resurrective reading; and Version D [The Hope for Final Death] is punctuated to bring out the reading that shows her yearning for a final death without resurrection.</p>
            <p>
              <seg id="a3-specific-headnote-section" rend="nl tac">***</seg>
            </p>
            <p>In the version you are currently reading—Version C: The Hope for Resurrection—I punctuate the poem to bring out and make more readily available the reading that makes it seem as if Pulter unambiguously desires and hopes for a final resurrection after her death. This reading relies on the parts of the poem where Pulter openly announces both her prayers to and her trust in God (“God . . . Will raise me unto life”), and reads those frank protestations of trust as overwhelming any seeming kernels of doubt (“I know not how” God will manage to resurrect me when the matter that makes up my body has been dissolved—but I have faith he will manage).</p>
            <p>As mentioned above, the most crucial punctuation decision in this version is the addition of a full stop at the end of the sixth line, which breaks the poem into two equal parts, each of which takes its own journey down into doubt and then back up into reassurance. If there is a full stop at the end of line 6, then Pulter twice worries about physical dissolution, but each time comforts herself with the knowledge that even if she does not know the exact mechanics of how it will happen, God will find a way to resurrect her. This repeated journey—down into doubt about physical dissolution and then back up into faith—parallels that taken in other poems, including especially <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="63">Dear God, From Thy High Throne Look Down</ref>, which worries about her body being burned into dust, dissolved into tears, and sighed away into air, only to constantly reassure herself each time that no matter what dissolution she may experience, she can still trust in God.</p>
            <p>My other punctuation decisions in this edition also reinforce this reading of a faith in resurrection, and in addition to the basic glosses that appear in each version, I have added notes to this edition that highlight how specific punctuating decisions create a poem longing for resurrection. I encourage the reader to compare the alternate versions using <title rend="italic">The Pulter Project</title>’s versioning tools, to see how the punctuation differs across versions, and to consider what difference those changes make; if you would prefer to read the unpunctuated version first, <ref type="pp-edition-section-ref" target="#a2">read Version B</ref> before reading this one.</p></note></rdg>

          <rdg wit="#a4"><note type="headnote">
            <p>How hopeful is “The Hope”? Or rather, for what is it hopeful? The conventional wisdom is that, as a citation of <bibl><title rend="italic">The booke of the common prayer,</title></bibl><seg>1<note type="critical">See Elizabeth Scott-Baumann’s curation for this poem, <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="#ctxs">Dust</ref>, and her note on the title in A065a (Hester Pulter, <bibl>“The Hope. January 1665” [A065a], ed. Elizabeth Scott-Baumann, <title rend="italic">The Pulter Project: Poet in the Making</title></bibl>).</note></seg> “The Hope” refers to the “certain hope of resurrection” at the Final Judgment. However, the poem also indulges itself in a fantasy of total personal dissolution, on par with the <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="6">Universal Dissolution</ref> imagined earlier in Pulter’s manuscript, but here writ small into the confines of her body. She imagines being dissolved into dust, then broken down into salt (potentially a component of dust), then completely annihilated—but then reminds us that God, somehow, will be able to recreate enough matter to resurrect her: “I know not how.” These four words, placed after the poem’s only period, are the crux of the poem. Do they gesture to a boundless faith (I don’t know the science behind how he will do it, but I know he can because “He . . . hath supported me till now”)? Or do they gesture to a different kind of hope: a hope that maybe her death will not be the seed of a future resurrection, but an end? “I know not how” he could possibly bring me and my body (see <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="39">The Perfection of Patience and Knowledge</ref>) back from the complete material dissolution I have just imagined: maybe I can hope that he won’t, that death will actually just be the end.<seg>2<note type="critical">I am indebted for my reading of this poem to Marshelle Woodward, who argued for this poem’s ambiguity in a paper entitled “The Dissolving Worlds of Margaret Cavendish and Hester Pulter” at the International Margaret Cavendish Society Conference in 2017. The argument will be published as Marshelle Woodward, “Hester Pulter’s Dissolving Worlds,” in <title rend="italic">Worldmaking Women: New Essays on the Centrality of Women in Early Modern Literature and Culture</title>, ed. Pamela Hammons and Brandie Siegfried (Cambridge, Cambridge University Press, in progress).</note></seg></p>
            <p>This is one of three interrelated Amplified Editions of Pulter’s poem: Version B [The Uncertain Hope], Version C [The Hope for Resurrection], and Version D [The Hope for Final Death]. The editorial strategy underlying these three separate editions has been specifically designed to demonstrate this poem’s fascinating ambiguity, its ability to be read either as a poem hoping for final, absolute death, or as a poem hoping for resurrection. As I will discuss in this headnote, the ambiguity of the poem’s argument comes in large part from the almost complete lack of punctuation in the original manuscript. This headnote explains how it is that punctuation can so radically alter the meaning of Pulter’s “The Hope”; the end of the headnote describes the editorial principles and punctuating choices I have adopted for <hi rend="italic">this</hi> particular Amplified Edition (Version D [The Hope for Final Death]). If you wish to skip to the section of the headnote particular to this Amplified Edition, you can find it at the <ref type="pp-edition-section-ref" target="#a4-specific-headnote-section">bottom of this headnote</ref>, after the three asterisks (***).</p>
            <p>“The Hope” is unusual in comparison to other poems in Pulter’s manuscript collection in that it has especially sparse punctuation. In the original manuscript in which this poem (and all Pulter’s poems) can be found, “The Hope” has six punctuation marks in total: two parentheses enclosing a phrase, two commas used to break up a list, one comma used to break up a line, and one period before the final four words (“I know not how”).<seg>3<note type="critical">This count does not include apostrophes.</note></seg> In addition, the relative scarcity of punctuation in this poem may be authorial. While the majority of the manuscript is written in a neat (and likely professional/scribal) roundhand, this poem, and a few others, are written in a spiky italic hand that also has made frequent corrections to other poems in the manuscript. Though we don’t know for sure to whom any of the hands belong, most editors assume that the spiky hand that makes corrections throughout, and that writes “The Hope” (Poem 65) and <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="61">The Weeping Wish</ref>, is Pulter’s.<seg>4<note type="critical">Stefan Christian in his dissertation edition merely refers to the second, editorial hand; see <bibl>Hester Pulter, “The Poems of Lady Hester Pulter (1605?–1678): An Annotated Edition,” ed. Stefan Graham Christian (PhD diss., University of Massachusetts Amherst, 2012)</bibl>, 3–6 for his discussion. Alice Eardley in her edition asserts confidently that the hand is Pulter’s <bibl>(Hester Pulter, <title rend="italic">Poems, Emblems, and the Unfortunate Florinda</title>, ed. Alice Eardley [Toronto: Iter, Inc. and the Centre for Renaissance and Reformation Studies, 2014], 32–33, 180 n. 825)</bibl>, while Knight and Wall note that the hand is “probably Pulter’s”; see <bibl>Hester Pulter, “The Hope” (<ref target="/poems/ee/the-hope" type="new-window-url">Poem 65, Elemental Edition</ref>), ed. Leah Knight and Wendy Wall, <title rend="italic">The Pulter Project: Poet in the Making</title></bibl>, note on title.</note></seg></p>
            <p>Deciding where and how to punctuate this poem has the potential to radically change the argument of the poem. The poem moves from imagining death to imagining increasingly small dissolutions, to the burning even of atoms, to the turn to God’s abilities, in what Alice Eardley refers to as the poem’s “fluidity and gathering momentum"<seg>5<note type="critical"><bibl>Alice Eardley, “‘I haue not time to point yr booke . . . which I desire you yourselfe to doe’: Editing the Form of Early Modern Manuscript Verse,” in <title rend="italic">The Work of Form: Poetics and Materiality in Early Modern Culture</title>, ed. Ben Burton and Elizabeth Scott-Baumann (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2014), 166</bibl>; see Scott-Baumann’s Curation <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="#ctxs">Knowledge, Faith and Doubt</ref> for an excerpt from Eardley’s essay.</note></seg>—but, crucially for these three Amplified Editions, where one might punctuate the poem to pause that momentum radically changes the message. Adding a hard stop (e.g., a semi-colon or period) after line 6, for example, makes a poem unambiguously about the promise of resurrection. With a hard stop after line 6 the poem would divide into two parts, each of which would end with resurrective optimism: even after dissolution into dust, the still-more-essential “vital salt” can “be found out” (ll. 1–6); even when the world is turned into chaos, God will raise me unto life (ll. 7–15). If, on the other hand, one reads the first ten lines as a consecutive accumulation of destruction on increasingly minute scales (where lines 7–8 do not change the subject from line 6, but go on to destroy even the vital salt that has been “found out”), the poem seems to build instead to a darker hope, conjuring image after image of destruction only to end with the (ill-supported) idea that God may, nevertheless, find something to recover.</p>
            <p>I believe, therefore, that it is impossible for a modern editor to punctuate this poem in a way that preserves the question (What is the hope?) that I take to be constitutive of the poem itself.<seg>6<note type="critical">It is of course impossible to say whether Pulter intended her punctuation (or lack thereof) to function this way; early modern punctuation worked differently than modern punctuation. For an overview of early modern views on punctuation, see <bibl>Alicia Rodríguez-Álvarez, “Teaching Punctuation in Early Modern England,” <title rend="italic">Studia Anglica Posnaniensia</title> 46 (2010): 35–49</bibl>; see also my Curation <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="#ctxs">Punctuating Poetry</ref>.</note></seg> And this belief underlies the editorial strategy for these three editions.</p>
            <p>One option for an editor trying to decide what the poem means would be to consider it in light of other poems in the manuscript. Unfortunately, moving out to the rest of Pulter’s corpus only complicates the question of what “The Hope” hopes for. She is a pious poet, and many of her poems share the conviction that God’s “blessèd influence / [will] Triumph o’er Death, her impotence” (<ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="20">Dear God, Turn Not Away Thy Face</ref>, ll. 21–22). However, for every poem that trusts in God, there is a poem that fantasizes about the possible absoluteness of physical dissolution. In <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="1">The Eclipse</ref> she reminds the Earth of its “irrevocable dissolution, / As well as mine” (ll. 22–23), and <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="6">Universal Dissolution</ref> ends with the following unsettling advice: “Then my unsettled soul, be more resolved, / Seeing all this universe must be dissolved” (ll. 175–76). In <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="17">The Circle [1]</ref> she cries, “Then, gracious God, in Thee I’ll trust, / Although Thou crumble me to dust” (ll. 15–16): is the trust despite God’s crumbling ambitions, or because of them?<seg>7<note type="critical">One could accumulate many more examples: at times she imagines dust as the end of everything (see <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="21">The Circle [2]</ref>, ll. 13–14: “So man, the universe’s chiefest glory, / His primitive’s dust (alas) doth end his story”), and at other times she worries at the absolute finality of dust: “Should all annihilated be, / Which is as easy unto Thee; / Oh what would then become of me?” (see <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="16">The Revolution</ref>, ll. 22–24).</note></seg> The impossibility of pinning down “The Hope” is best embodied in the following paradox from her <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="6">Universal Dissolution</ref>: “When all’s to chaos turned, there will be peace” (l. 152). My Curation for this poem, <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="#ctxs">Wishing for the End</ref>, provides other examples of the somewhat unusual desire for absolute and final death, as well as examples of nihilism, in seventeenth-century poetry.</p>
            <p>In editing the poem, therefore, I have pursued the editorial strategy that I believe makes it most possible to experience the poem’s ambiguity to the fullest. This strategy has resulted in three separate Amplified Editions of the poem, which differ only in punctuation: Version B [The Uncertain Hope] contains only the manuscript’s punctuation, which allows readers to insert their own punctuation and to gauge their own readings of the poem; Version C [The Hope for Resurrection] is punctuated to bring out the resurrective reading; and Version D [The Hope for Final Death] is punctuated to bring out the reading that shows her yearning for a final death without resurrection.</p>
            <p>
              <seg id="a4-specific-headnote-section" rend="nl tac">***</seg>
            </p>
            <p>In the version you are currently reading—Version D: The Hope for Final Death—I punctuate the poem to bring out the reading that makes it seem as if Pulter fantasizes about an escalating, total dissolution of her physical body, a dissolution so absolute that it would be impossible for enough material remains to survive to allow God to resurrect her. This reading relies in particular on the two moments where she fantasizes about the destruction of supposedly indestructible things: when she imagines that the “little luz” (the supposedly indestructible bone that served as the kernel of bodily resurrection) will dissolve into dust; and when she insists that “even” atoms—the most fundamental particles of nature, commonly referred to as “indivisibles” in the period—will burn.</p>
            <p>My punctuation in this version, much like in the manuscript itself, refuses any hard stops from the moment Pulter starts imagining dissolution until the very last line of the poem. This decision makes the vast majority of the poem a breathy run-on sentence imagining increasing degrees of destruction, which then ends with an abrupt and seemingly ill-founded assertion of faith, that is in turn immediately undercut by a final return to doubt: “I know not how . . .” The poem, then, is a bit like Shakespeare’s Sonnet 129, “The expense of spirit in a waste of shame,” with each clause piling upon the last to communicate increasing mental agitation (in Sonnet 129, agitation born of misogyny; in “The Hope,” agitation born of an uncertainty about death and dissolution). Refusing to break the momentum of Pulter’s fantasies of dissolution in the middle of the poem (as happens in Version C) allows this escalation.</p>
            <p>My other punctuation decisions in this version also reinforce the reading of the poem as an escalation of fantasies of destruction so extreme that no feeble, vague protestation of faith can possibly overcome them. In addition to the basic glosses that appear in each version, I have added notes that highlight how these specific punctuating decisions create a poem longing for a dissolution so complete that it could not possibly seed any future resurrection. I encourage the reader to compare the alternate versions using <title rend="italic">The Pulter Project</title>’s versioning tools, to see how the punctuation differs across versions, and to consider what difference those changes make; if you would prefer to read the unpunctuated version first, <ref type="pp-edition-section-ref" target="#a2">read Version B</ref> before reading this one.</p>
          </note></rdg>

        </app>
      </head>

      <l n="1">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Deare Death deſolve theiſe mortall charms</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Dear Death, dissolve these mortal charms,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Dear Death, dissolve these mortal charms</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#a2"><seg rend="preserve-whitespace-soft">Dear  Death  </seg><seg>dissolve<note type="gloss">either “disintegrate, decompose”; or, figuratively, “loosen, unfasten, detach, release, set free”</note></seg><seg rend="preserve-whitespace-soft">  these  </seg><seg><seg rend="preserve-whitespace-soft">mortal  charms</seg><note type="gloss"> either those attractions of my living body; or those magical spells that hold my body together</note></seg></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#a3">Dear Death, <seg>dissolve<note type="gloss">either “disintegrate, decompose”; or, figuratively, “loosen, unfasten, detach, release, set free”</note></seg> these <seg>mortal charms<note type="gloss">either those attractions of my living body; or those magical spells that hold my body together</note></seg>,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#a4"><seg>Dear Death!<note type="critical">Adding an exclamation mark at the end of an opening apostrophe (a direct address to a real or allegorical figure) is a common editorial choice, and here additionally augments the passion she attaches to her conjuration of and invitation to “Dear” Death, into whose arms she wants to “throw” herself, and whom she invites to “use my carcass, as thou lust.”</note></seg> <seg>Dissolve<note type="gloss">either “disintegrate, decompose”; or, figuratively, “loosen, unfasten, detach, release, set free”</note></seg> these <seg>mortal charms<note type="gloss">either those attractions of my living body; or those magical spells that hold my body together</note></seg>,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="2">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">And then Ile throw my ſelfe into thy arms</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">And then I’ll throw myself into thy arms;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">And then I’ll throw myself into Thy arms.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#a2"><seg rend="preserve-whitespace-soft">And  then  I’ll  throw  my  self  into  thy  arms</seg></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#a3">And then I’ll throw my self into thy arms,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#a4">And then I’ll throw my self into thy arms;</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="3">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Then though mayest uſe my Carkes as thou lust</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Then thou may’st use my carcass as thou <seg>lust<note type="gloss">choose; please</note></seg>,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Then Thou may’st use my <seg>carcass<note type="gloss">dead body</note></seg> as Thou lust</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#a2"><seg rend="preserve-whitespace-soft">Then  thou  mayest  use  my  carcass  as  thou  </seg><seg>lust<note type="critical">The sexual connotations of the word “lust,” meaning desire (“you can do as you wish with my body”), add to the romantic or even erotic image already set up by line 2, where she imagines herself throwing herself into Death’s arms.</note></seg></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#a3">Then thou mayest use my carcass as thou <seg>lust<note type="critical">The sexual connotations of the word “lust,” meaning desire (“you can do as you wish with my body”), add to the romantic or even erotic image already set up by line 2, where she imagines herself throwing herself into Death’s arms.</note></seg>,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#a4">Then thou mayest use my carcass, as thou <seg>lust<note type="critical">The sexual connotations of the word “lust,” meaning desire (“you can do as you wish with my body”), add to the romantic or even erotic image already set up by line 2, where she imagines herself throwing herself into Death’s arms. As was mentioned above, adding an exclamation line at the end of the opening apostrophe enhances this reading.</note></seg>,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="4">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Untill my boans (and little Luz) bee dust</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Until my bones (and little <seg>luz<note type="critical">also known as the “os sacrum,” or sacred bone: a triangular bone low in the spine; in rabbinical legend, the nucleus of the body at the Resurrection</note></seg>) be <seg>dust<note type="critical">disintegrated matter; also original, formative physical elements; see Genesis 2:7: “And the Lord God formed man [of] the dust of the ground, and breathed into his nostrils the breath of life; and man became a living soul.”</note></seg>:</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Until my bones (and little <seg>luz<note type="critical">an esoteric term for a tiny spinal bone, originating from the Hebrew word for a nut and thought to be the seed of rebirth at the Day of Judgement. Some writers, like Nicholas Culpeper, dismissed the luz as a “ridiculous fable” (See <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="#ctxs">The ‘Little Luz’</ref> in Curations for this poem).</note></seg>) be dust.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#a2"><seg rend="preserve-whitespace-soft">Until  my  bones  </seg><hi rend="attention">(</hi><seg rend="preserve-whitespace-soft">and  little  </seg><seg>luz<note type="critical">As other editors have noted, the luz is a small bone, usually understood as indestructible and therefore imagined as the seed of bodily resurrection at the Final Judgment. See <bibl>John Gregory, <title rend="italic">Gregorii posthuma, or, Certain learned tracts</title> (London, 1649)</bibl>: “at the last Daie, a kinde of Plastical Dew shall fall down upon the Dead, and ingender with Luz, the little Bone spoken of before: and so out of this, all the rest of our Bones, and the whole Man shall spring forth” (70). See also Elizabeth Scott-Baumann’s Curation <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="#ctxs">The ‘Little Luz’</ref>. Emphasizing that even the seed of resurrection is to be turned into dust suggests, perhaps, a hope that nothing will remain to allow for resurrection.</note></seg><hi rend="attention">)</hi><seg rend="preserve-whitespace-soft">  be  dust</seg></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#a3">Until my bones (and little <seg>luz<note type="critical">As other editors have noted, the luz is a small bone, usually understood as indestructible and therefore imagined as the seed of bodily resurrection at the Final Judgment. See <bibl>John Gregory, <title rend="italic">Gregorii posthuma, or, Certain learned tracts</title> (London, 1649)</bibl>: “at the last Daie, a kinde of Plastical Dew shall fall down upon the Dead, and ingender with Luz, the little Bone spoken of before: and so out of this, all the rest of our Bones, and the whole Man shall spring forth” (70). See also Elizabeth Scott-Baumann’s Curation <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="#ctxs">The ‘Little Luz’</ref>. Emphasizing that even the seed of resurrection is to be turned into dust suggests, perhaps, a hope that nothing will remain to allow for resurrection.</note></seg>) be dust—</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#a4">Until my bones (and little <seg>luz<note type="critical">As other editors have noted, the luz is a small bone, usually understood as indestructible and therefore imagined as the seed of bodily resurrection at the Final Judgment. See <bibl>John Gregory, <title rend="italic">Gregorii posthuma, or, Certain learned tracts</title> (London, 1649)</bibl>: “at the last Daie, a kinde of Plastical Dew shall fall down upon the Dead, and ingender with Luz, the little Bone spoken of before: and so out of this, all the rest of our Bones, and the whole Man shall spring forth” (70). See also Elizabeth Scott-Baumann’s Curation <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="#ctxs">The ‘Little Luz’</ref>. Emphasizing that even the seed of resurrection is to be turned into dust suggests, perhaps, a hope that nothing will remain to allow for resurrection.</note></seg>) be <seg>dust:<note type="critical">I have put the hardest punctuation mark (until the final line) here, thereby breaking the poem into three distinct phases: the opening, with its loving and erotic conjuration of death (ll. 1–4); the escalating fantasies of physical dissolution (ll. 5–10), and the tentative affirmation and then doubt of God’s ability to resurrect her (ll. 11–15). Adding a colon here recasts the second section as an elaboration on line 4, as if the idea of Death using her until she is dust is what prompts the further fantasies of dissolution that follow immediately after.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="5">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Naye when that handfull is blow’n all about</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Nay, when that handful is blown all about,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Nay, when that handful is blown all about</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#a2"><seg>Nay<note type="critical">This “Nay” represents a major crux for potential punctuators; is it an emphatic exclamation as she realizes she hasn’t gone far enough and intends to go still further (no, dust isn’t enough: Death will find and break down that dust into the primary alchemical element of salt, smaller even than dust), or is it a cessation of the dissolving chain of thought and a turn to the positive (no, wait—even if I’m dust, God will find out the more fundamental salt)? The passive construction makes the subject of the “finding” impossible to discern.</note></seg><seg rend="preserve-whitespace-soft">  when  that  handful  is  blown  all  about</seg></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#a3"><seg>Nay:<note type="critical">This “Nay” represents a major crux for potential punctuators; is it an emphatic exclamation as she realizes she hasn’t gone far enough and intends to go still further, or is it a cessation of the dissolving chain of thought and a turn to the positive? The punctuation I have added here assumes the latter: the dash at the end of line 4 creates a hard break in her disturbing reflections on Death’s “use” of her carcass, and the colon after “Nay” makes the two lines that follow appear to be a longer restatement of that negation, as if she is saying: No: even when I am dust, God will find out the still more essential “vital salt.”</note></seg> when that handful is blown all about,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#a4"><seg>Nay<note type="critical">This “Nay” represents a major crux for potential punctuators; is it an emphatic exclamation as she realizes she hasn’t gone far enough and intends to go still further, or is it a cessation of the dissolving chain of thought and a turn to the positive? In failing to add any punctuation after “Nay” I suggest that it is the former, as if this line says: No, not just dust: Death will find the more essential alchemical element of salt, smaller even than dust, and scatter that as well.</note></seg> when that handful is blown all about,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="6">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Yett still the vitale ſalt will bee fownd out</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Yet still the <seg>vital salt<note type="gloss">The alchemist Paracelsus expanded the Arabic doctrine that two principles, sulfur and mercury, were the roots of all things by adding a third principle, salt.</note></seg> will be found out;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Yet still the <seg>vital salt<note type="critical">salt was one of the three first principles in alchemy, according to Paracelsus, along with mercury and sulphur. Salt represented the body and was found in the ashes (see <bibl>Lyndy Abraham, <title rend="italic">Dictionary of Alchemical Imagery</title>, Cambridge: CUP, 2001</bibl>). In Matthew 5.13 of the Bible, man is also described as “the salt of the earth”.</note></seg> will be found out;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#a2"><seg rend="preserve-whitespace-soft">Yet  still  the  </seg><seg><seg rend="preserve-whitespace-soft">vital  salt</seg><note type="critical">In Paracelsian philosophy, all objects had three “principles”: sulphur, which made things combustible; salt, which gave things solidity, and mercury, which made things fluid or vaporous (and gave them “virtues, powers and arcana”); see <bibl>Walter Pagel, <title rend="italic">Paracelsus: An Introduction to Philosophical Medicine in the Era of the Renaissance</title>, 2nd, revised ed. (Basel: Karger, 1982), 100–104, quotation from 101.</bibl> Pulter’s “vital salt” would be, therefore, more elemental or primary even than dust.</note></seg><seg rend="preserve-whitespace-soft">  will  be  </seg><seg><seg rend="preserve-whitespace-soft">found  out</seg><note type="critical">What punctuation one adds at the end of line 6 is, perhaps, the most significant indicator for how one reads the poem itself (see the headnote of this version for more detail), and is therefore an important decision for a punctuator: do you read lines 7–8 as a continuation of line 6, or as a new thought?</note></seg></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#a3">Yet still the <seg>vital salt<note type="critical">In Paracelsian philosophy, all objects had three “principles”: sulphur, which made things combustible; salt, which gave things solidity, and mercury, which made things fluid or vaporous (and gave them “virtues, powers and arcana”); see <bibl>Walter Pagel, <title rend="italic">Paracelsus: An Introduction to Philosophical Medicine in the Era of the Renaissance</title>, 2nd, revised ed. (Basel: Karger, 1982), 100–104, quotation from 101.</bibl> Pulter’s “vital salt” would be, therefore, more elemental or primary even than dust.</note></seg> will be <seg>found out.<note type="critical">By adding a period or full stop at the end of line 6, I have broken the poem into two balanced parts, each of which dips temporarily into doubt only to be redeemed by faith. For more detail on the importance of the punctuation at the end of this line, see the headnote to this version; it is this single punctuation mark, more than any other, that causes this poem to read as hopeful for resurrection.</note></seg></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#a4">Yet still the <seg>vital salt<note type="critical">In Paracelsian philosophy, all objects had three “principles”: sulphur, which made things combustible; salt, which gave things solidity, and mercury, which made things fluid or vaporous (and gave them “virtues, powers and arcana”); see <bibl>Walter Pagel, <title rend="italic">Paracelsus: An Introduction to Philosophical Medicine in the Era of the Renaissance</title>, 2nd, revised ed. (Basel: Karger, 1982), 100–104, quotation from 101.</bibl> Pulter’s “vital salt” would be, therefore, more elemental or primary even than dust.</note></seg> will be <seg>found out,<note type="critical">Punctuating the end of this line with a comma suggests that the “vital salt” will be found out so it can be further broken down or dispersed, and also allows the “And” that begins line 7 to more immediately and grammatically follow on what comes before.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="7">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">And when the vapour is breath’d out in Thunder</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">And <seg>when the vapor is breathed out in thunder<note type="critical">a theory of the source of thunder; see, e.g., “Thunder proceeds from a vapor lifted up from the earth.” <bibl>Stephen Gosson, <title rend="italic">The Trumpet of War</title> (London, 1598), A3r</bibl>.</note></seg></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">And when the vapour is breathed out in thunder</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#a2"><seg rend="preserve-whitespace-soft">And  </seg><seg><seg rend="preserve-whitespace-soft">when  the  vapor  is  breathed  out  in  thunder</seg><note type="critical">Following the invocation of Paracelsian “vital salt,” vapor also conjures the principle of mercury, sometimes associated with the spirit (with salt being associated with the body). In <title rend="italic">Meterologica</title> II.ix, Aristotle argues that thunder is caused by the forceful exhalation of air from a cloud <bibl>(Aristotle, <title rend="italic">Meteorologica</title>, ed. H.D.P. Lee [Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 1952], 223–25)</bibl>. The clause “When the vapor is breathed out in thunder” potentially works, therefore, both at the microcosmic level (when the spirit is forced out of the body: a “mortal’s loss, and pain”) and the macrocosmic level (some natural disaster leading to “mortals’ loss, and pain, and wonder”).</note></seg></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#a3">And <seg>when the vapor is breathed out in thunder<note type="critical">Following the invocation of Paracelsian “vital salt,” vapor also conjures the principle of mercury, sometimes associated with the spirit (with salt being associated with the body). In <title rend="italic">Meterologica</title> II.ix, Aristotle argues that thunder is caused by the forceful exhalation of air from a cloud <bibl>(Aristotle, <title rend="italic">Meteorologica</title>, ed. H.D.P. Lee [Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 1952], 223–25)</bibl>. The clause “When the vapor is breathed out in thunder” potentially works, therefore, both at the microcosmic level (when the spirit is forced out of the body: a “mortal’s loss, and pain”) and the macrocosmic level (some natural disaster leading to “mortals’ loss, and pain, and wonder”).</note></seg></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#a4">And <seg>when the vapor is breathed out in thunder<note type="critical">Following the invocation of Paracelsian “vital salt,” vapor also conjures the principle of mercury, sometimes associated with the spirit (with salt being associated with the body). In <title rend="italic">Meterologica</title> II.ix, Aristotle argues that thunder is caused by the forceful exhalation of air from a cloud <bibl>(Aristotle, <title rend="italic">Meteorologica</title>, ed. H.D.P. Lee [Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 1952], 223–25)</bibl>. The clause “When the vapor is breathed out in thunder” potentially works, therefore, both at the microcosmic level (when the spirit is forced out of the body: a “mortal’s loss, and pain”) and the macrocosmic level (some natural disaster leading to “mortals’ loss, and pain, and wonder”).</note></seg>,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="8">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Unto poore Mortalls Loſs, or paine, or wonder</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Unto poor mortals’ loss, or pain, or wonder,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Unto poor mortals’ loss, or pain, or wonder,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#a2"><seg rend="preserve-whitespace-soft">Unto  poor  mortals  </seg><seg>loss<hi rend="attention">,</hi><seg rend="preserve-whitespace-soft">  or  pain</seg><hi rend="attention">,</hi><seg rend="preserve-whitespace-soft">  or  wonder</seg><note type="critical">The list “loss, or pain, or wonder” is remarkable; if they are exclusive <hi rend="italic">or</hi>s, then the vapor brings either loss, pain, or wonder (but not all of them); if they are inclusive <hi rend="italic">or</hi>s, then “pain” is being used an an appositive redefinition of “loss,” and “wonder” redefines them both. Though the exclusive <hi rend="italic">or</hi> seems the more obvious choice, remember that Pulter elsewhere writes in paradox: “When all’s to chaos turned there will be peace” (<ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="6">Universal Dissolution</ref>, l. 152).</note></seg></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#a3">Unto poor mortal’s <seg>loss, or pain, or wonder<note type="critical">The list “loss, or pain, or wonder” is remarkable; if they are exclusive <hi rend="italic">or</hi>s, then the vapor brings either loss, pain, or wonder (but not all of them); if they are inclusive <hi rend="italic">or</hi>s, then “pain” is being used an an appositive redefinition of “loss,” and “wonder” redefines them both. Though the exclusive <hi rend="italic">or</hi> seems the more obvious choice, remember that Pulter elsewhere writes in paradox: “When all’s to chaos turned there will be peace” (<ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="6">Universal Dissolution</ref>, l. 152).</note></seg>,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#a4">Unto poor mortal’s <seg>loss, or pain, or wonder<note type="critical">The list “loss, or pain, or wonder” is remarkable; if they are exclusive <hi rend="italic">or</hi>s, then the vapor brings either loss, pain, or wonder (but not all of them); if they are inclusive <hi rend="italic">or</hi>s, then “pain” is being used an an appositive redefinition of “loss,” and “wonder” redefines them both. Though the exclusive <hi rend="italic">or</hi> seems the more obvious choice, remember that Pulter elsewhere writes in paradox: “When all’s to chaos turned there will be peace” (<ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="6">Universal Dissolution</ref>, l. 152).</note></seg>,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="9">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">And all that is in thee to Atoms turn’d</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">And all that is in thee to <seg>atoms<note type="gloss">in ancient Greek philosophy and new seventeenth-century science, minute and indivisible particles of which matter is composed</note></seg> turned,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">And all that is in Thee to <seg>atoms<note type="gloss">the smallest possible particle of which all matter is made</note></seg> turned</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#a2"><seg rend="preserve-whitespace-soft">And  all  that  is  in  </seg><seg>thee<note type="gloss">She presumably continues to address Death here.</note></seg>&#160;&#160;<seg><seg rend="preserve-whitespace-soft">to  atoms  turned</seg><note type="critical">Though Pulter is sometimes inconsistent in the way she talks about the fundamental particles of nature (see <bibl>Liza Blake, “Hester Pulter’s Particle Physics and the Poetics of Involution,” <title rend="italic">JEMCS</title> 20 (2020): 71–98</bibl>; and <bibl>Alice Eardley, “Hester Pulter’s ‘Indivisibles’ and the Challenges of Annotating Early Modern Women’s Poetry,” <title rend="italic">SEL</title> 52 [2012]: 117–41</bibl>), atoms were often also called “indivisibles” in the seventeenth century, and here may indicate the final and most extreme division of matter in the poem, which moves from “dust” to “salt” to “atoms”—and then imagines those atoms burned.</note></seg></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#a3">And all that is in <seg>thee<note type="gloss">She presumably continues to address Death here.</note></seg> <seg>to atoms turned<note type="critical">Though Pulter is sometimes inconsistent in the way she talks about the fundamental particles of nature (see <bibl>Liza Blake, “Hester Pulter’s Particle Physics and the Poetics of Involution,” <title rend="italic">JEMCS</title> 20 (2020): 71–98</bibl>; and <bibl>Alice Eardley, “Hester Pulter’s ‘Indivisibles’ and the Challenges of Annotating Early Modern Women’s Poetry,” <title rend="italic">SEL</title> 52 [2012]: 117–41</bibl>), atoms were often also called “indivisibles” in the seventeenth century, and here may indicate the final and most extreme division of matter in the poem, which moves from “dust” to “salt” to “atoms”—and then imagines those atoms burned.</note></seg>,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#a4">And all that is in <seg>thee<note type="gloss">She presumably continues to address Death here.</note></seg> <seg>to atoms turned<note type="critical">Though Pulter is sometimes inconsistent in the way she talks about the fundamental particles of nature (see <bibl>Liza Blake, “Hester Pulter’s Particle Physics and the Poetics of Involution,” <title rend="italic">JEMCS</title> 20 (2020): 71–98</bibl>; and <bibl>Alice Eardley, “Hester Pulter’s ‘Indivisibles’ and the Challenges of Annotating Early Modern Women’s Poetry,” <title rend="italic">SEL</title> 52 [2012]: 117–41</bibl>), atoms were often also called “indivisibles” in the seventeenth century, and here may indicate the final and most extreme division of matter in the poem, which moves from “dust” to “salt” to “atoms”—and then imagines those atoms burned.</note></seg>—</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="10">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">And even thoſe Atoms in this Orb is burn’d</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">And even those atoms in this <seg>orb<note type="gloss">Earth</note></seg> is burned,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">And even those atoms in <seg>this orb<note type="gloss">the earth; possibly also the circular vessel used for distillation in alchemy (see <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="#ctxs">Alchemical Circles</ref> in Curations for Poem 1).</note></seg> is burned,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#a2"><seg rend="preserve-whitespace-soft">And  even  those  atoms  in  </seg><seg><seg rend="preserve-whitespace-soft">this  orb</seg><note type="gloss">“this orb” is presumably the globe or Earth, but if one is tracing the exchanges between microcosm and macrocosm in the poem it could also possibly refer to the body.</note></seg>&#160;&#160;<seg><seg rend="preserve-whitespace-soft">is  burned</seg><note type="critical">Lines 9–10 potentially have a textual error, if you understand the singular verb “is” to modify the plural “atoms.” It can be fixed with punctuation, if you turn “And even those atoms in this orb” to an intensifying interjection, making the subject of the verb the “all” of line 9 (“all . . . is burned”).</note></seg></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#a3">And even those atoms in <seg>this orb<note type="gloss">“this orb” is presumably the globe or Earth, but if one is tracing the exchanges between microcosm and macrocosm in the poem it could also possibly refer to the body.</note></seg> <seg>[are] burned<note type="critical">Lines 9–10 potentially have a textual error, if you understand the singular verb “is” to modify the plural “atoms.” It can be fixed with punctuation, if you turn “And even those atoms in this orb” to an intensifying interjection, which makes the subject of the verb the “all” of line 9 (“all . . . is burned”). In the hopeful, resurrective reading of the poem, it would not make sense to intensify the destruction, so rather than fixing this grammatical error with punctuation, I have emended the “is” to “[are]”.</note></seg>,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#a4">And even those atoms in <seg>this orb<note type="gloss">“this orb” is presumably the globe or Earth, but if one is tracing the exchanges between microcosm and macrocosm in the poem it could also possibly refer to the body.</note></seg>—<seg>is burned,<note type="critical">Lines 9–10 potentially have a textual error, if you understand the singular verb “is” to modify the plural “atoms.” I have fixed this seeming error with punctuation, by turning “And even those atoms in this orb” to an intensifying interjection, making the subject of the verb the “all” of line 9 (“all . . . is burned”). This intensification seemed appropriate as the climax of the section of the poem that escalates destruction.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="11">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Yett still that God that can anihillate</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Yet still that God that can annihilate</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Yet still that God that can annihilate</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#a2"><seg rend="preserve-whitespace-soft">Yet  still  that  God  that  can  annihilate</seg></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#a3">Yet still that God that can annihilate</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#a4">Yet still that God that can annihilate</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="12">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">This all, and itt of nothinge recreate</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">This all, and it <seg>of nothing recreate<note type="gloss">the idea that the universe was created by God ex nihilo (“from nothing”) was a point of theological doctrine and debate.</note></seg>,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">This all, and it of nothing recreate,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#a2"><seg rend="preserve-whitespace-soft">This  all</seg><hi rend="attention">,</hi><seg rend="preserve-whitespace-soft">  and  </seg><seg>it<note type="critical">See the Curation <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="#ctxs">Manuscript Ambiguities</ref> for my discussion of the possibility that this word is possibly an “us” that was corrected or altered to “it.”</note></seg>&#160;&#160;<seg><seg rend="preserve-whitespace-soft">of  nothing  recreate</seg><note type="critical">One major school of thought, drawing on Genesis 1:1, advocated that God made the universe <foreign rend="italic">ex nihilo</foreign>, or out of nothing. Here, unusually, Pulter pairs the idea that God can create <foreign rend="italic">ex nihilo</foreign> with the reminder that he can also annihilate everything to create that nothingness in the first place.</note></seg></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#a3">This all, and <seg>it<note type="critical">See the Curation <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="#ctxs">Manuscript Ambiguities</ref> for my discussion of the possibility that this word is possibly an “us” that was corrected or altered to “it.” An editor trying to emphasize a resurrective reading of the poem (<hi rend="italic">if</hi> they agreed that the word “it” was initially written as “us”) might consider emending the word back to “us”—to edit for first intentions rather than final intentions—to show how she imagined God specifically resurrecting or recreating <hi rend="italic">us</hi> humans following the annihilation of “this all.”</note></seg> <seg>of nothing recreate<note type="critical">One major school of thought, drawing on Genesis 1:1, advocated that God made the universe <foreign rend="italic">ex nihilo</foreign>, or out of nothing. Here, unusually, Pulter pairs the idea that God can create <foreign rend="italic">ex nihilo</foreign> with the reminder that he can also annihilate everything to create that nothingness in the first place.</note></seg>—</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#a4">This all, and <seg>it<note type="critical">See the Curation <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="#ctxs">Manuscript Ambiguities</ref> for my discussion of the possibility that this word is possibly an “us” that was corrected or altered to “it.” An editor trying to emphasize a reading of the poem that refuses the possibility of resurrection might want not only to leave the change ("it" for "us"), but also to point out that if there is indeed a correction here, then it illustrates Pulter editing the the poem to make it less explicitly about resurrection. The edit (from "us" to "itt") changes the claim to make resurrection less certain: rather than God resurrecting <hi rend="italic">us</hi> humans, in the revised version God recreates <hi rend="italic">it</hi>, the universe as a whole, and the poem deliberately does not specify whether that newly recreated universe would also include <hi rend="italic">us</hi>.</note></seg> <seg>of nothing recreate<note type="critical">One major school of thought, drawing on Genesis 1:1, advocated that God made the universe <foreign rend="italic">ex nihilo</foreign>, or out of nothing. Here, unusually, Pulter pairs the idea that God can create <foreign rend="italic">ex nihilo</foreign> with the reminder that he can also annihilate everything to create that nothingness in the first place.</note></seg>,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="13">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft"><seg>E[<del>e</del>]ven<note type="physical">first “e” blotted out after “E”</note></seg> Hee that hath ſupported mee till now</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Even He that hath supported me till now,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Even He that hath supported me till now,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#a2"><seg rend="preserve-whitespace-soft">Even  He  that  hath  supported  me  till  now</seg></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#a3">Even He that hath supported me till now,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#a4">Even He, that hath supported me till now,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="14">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">To whom my ſoule doth praye and humbly bow</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">To whom my soul doth pray and humbly bow,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">To whom my soul doth pray and humbly bow,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#a2"><seg rend="preserve-whitespace-soft">To  whom  my  soul  doth  pray  and  humbly  bow</seg></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#a3"><seg>To whom my soul doth pray and humbly bow—<note type="critical">By setting lines 13–14 off by dashes, I have intensified her double affirmation of God’s power to resurrect even her scattered and destroyed body. With this version’s punctuation, lines 11–12 affirm God’s power <hi rend="italic">in general</hi>, and lines 13–14 interject his particularly positive track record of his support of her <hi rend="italic">in particular</hi>, which then combine to create her very justified belief that God “Will raise me unto life.”</note></seg></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#a4">To whom my soul doth pray and humbly bow,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="15">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Will raiſe mee unto liffe. I know not <seg>how<note type="physical">remaining third of page blank</note></seg></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Will <seg>raise me unto life<note type="gloss">allusion to the process, predicted in biblical book of Revelation, by which souls will be restored to their bodies and raised to heaven at the Resurrection, also known as the second coming of Christ or Final Judgment</note></seg>. I know not how.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Will raise me unto life. I know not how</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#a2"><seg><seg rend="preserve-whitespace-soft">Will  raise  me  unto  life</seg><note type="gloss">will resurrect me</note></seg><hi rend="attention">.</hi><seg rend="preserve-whitespace-soft">  I  know  not  how</seg></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#a3"><seg>Will raise me unto life<note type="gloss">will resurrect me</note></seg>. I know not how.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#a4"><seg>Will raise me unto life<note type="gloss">will resurrect me</note></seg>. I know not how <seg>…<note type="critical">The ellipses added to the end of the poem communicate the uncertainty behind the final four words in this version, which hopes for final death. This choice enhances the effect of the manuscript version, which trails off without punctuation. Another possibility might have been an exclamation mark to end the poem, which would connote less uncertainty and more exasperation or frustration at her inability to comprehend the mechanics of resurrection.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
