<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../src/vmachine.xsl"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
  schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI [

  <!ENTITY ff "<!-- ff ligature, representing capital modern day capital F, here represented as 'ff' -->ff">

  ]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mads.pp.97">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
          <title>The Lion and the Ass (Emblem 32)</title>
        <title type="sub">Poem 97</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Created by</resp>
          <persName>Leah Knight</persName>
          <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoded by</resp>
          <persName>Katherine Poland</persName>
          <persName>Matthew Taylor</persName>
          <persName>Betsy Chou</persName>
          <persName>Emily Andrey</persName>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>IT-project consultation by</resp>
          <persName>Josh Honn</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
          <orgName>Brock University</orgName>
          <orgName>University of Leeds</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <principal>
          <persName/>
        </principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="1"/>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription, transformations, and notes</resp>
          <persName>Leah Knight</persName>
          <orgName>Brock University</orgName>
          <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
        </respStmt>
      </editionStmt>
      <extent/>
      <publicationStmt>
        <ab/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listBibl>
          <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
              <repository>See witness list.</repository>
            </msIdentifier>
          </msDesc>
        </listBibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p/>
      </projectDesc>
      <p>Transcriptions are encoded in TEI(P5)-conformant XML.</p>
      <samplingDecl>
        <p/>
      </samplingDecl>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction>
          <p>Apparent errors are preserved and editorial corrections provided using SIC and CORR tags, but only where the editor conjectures that the original scribe or compositor would have recognized the instance as an error. For example, what according to modern usage is incorrect subject/verb agreement might have been deemed acceptable to a seventeenth-century scribe or compositor. All such instances are treated instead using the ORIG and REG tags. (See below.)</p>
          <p>Corrections and annotations made within the scope of the original document either by its original authors, owners, and/or transcribers are noted using ADD tags. These annotations and may be futher explained within NOTE tags, as added by the editors of this digital edition, for display within the apparatus.</p>
        </correction>
        <normalization>
          <p>Original spellings, abbreviations, and orthography are preserved. Where in the manuscripts a character's status as majuscule or miniscule is ambiguous, the editor has silently chosen one or the other based on context and judgment (i.e., does not register such ambiguity in either the markup or the notes).</p>
        </normalization>
        <quotation>
          <p>Original quotation marks, if any, are preserved.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation>
          <p>Original hyphenation is preserved.</p>
        </hyphenation>
      </editorialDecl>
      <charDecl>
        <!-- Ligature combinations for which there are currently no corresponding Unicode codepoints. -->
        <glyph xml:id="ffllig">
          <glyphName>Handwritten 'ff' ligature, used in handwriting to represent modern F</glyphName>
        </glyph>
      </charDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="DDC22">
          <bibl>
            <title>Dewey Decimal Classification</title>
            <edition/>
            <publisher/>
            <pubPlace/>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-GB">British English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <!-- dewey decimal system class code 821: English Poetry -->
        <classCode scheme="DDC22">821</classCode>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
    <!-- List of all images associated with this document -->
    <graphic url="./document_images/7610_227.jpg" xml:id="f7610_227"/>
    <graphic url="./document_images/7610_228.jpg" xml:id="f7610_228"/>
  </facsimile>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="ft">Transcription of manuscript: By <persName xml:id="lknight">Leah Knight</persName> and <persName xml:id="wwall">Wendy Wall</persName>.</witness>
          <witness xml:id="ee">Elemental edition: By <persName>Leah Knight</persName> and <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>.</witness>
<!--          <witness xml:id="ae">Amplified edition: By <persName>AE EDITOR</persName>.</witness>-->
        </listWit>
      </div>
    </front>

    <body>

      <!-- Each page break should be represented wih a block like this with the correct facs reference-->
      <app>
        <rdg wit="#ft">
          <pb ed="#ft" facs="#f7610_227" n="112r"/>
        </rdg>
        <rdg wit="#ee">
          <pb ed="#ee" facs="#f7610_227"/>
        </rdg>
        <rdg wit="#ae">
          <pb ed="#ae" facs="#f7610_227"/>
        </rdg>
      </app>

      <head>
        <app type="title">
          <rdg wit="#ft"><fw facs="#f7610_227" type="pageNum" place="margin-topright">32</fw>[Emblem 32]</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">The Lion and the Ass<lb/>(Emblem 32)</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">AE TITLE</rdg>
        </app>
        <app type="editorialnote">
          <rdg wit="#ft">
            <note type="editorialnote">In these transcriptions we preserve as many details of the original material, textual, and graphic properties of Hester Pulter’s manuscript verse as we have found practical. Whenever possible, for instance, original spelling, punctuation, capitalization, lineation, insertions, deletions, alterations, spacing between words and lines, and indentation are all maintained; abbreviations and brevigraphs are not expanded; and superscript and subscript representations are retained. <ref target="https://pulterproject.northwestern.edu/about-project-conventions.html#top" type="new-window-url">See full conventions for the transcriptions here.</ref></note>
          </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">
            <note type="editorialnote">The aim of the elemental edition is to make the poems accessible to the largest variety of readers, which involves modernizing spelling and punctuation as well as adding basic glosses. Spelling and punctuation reflect current standard American usage; punctuation highlights syntax which might otherwise be obscure. Outmoded but still familiar word forms (“thou,” “‘tis,” “hold’st”) are not modernized, and we do not modernize grammar when the sense remains legible. After a brief headnote aimed at offering a “way in” to the poem’s unique qualities and connections with other verse by Pulter or her contemporaries, the edition features a minimum of notes and interpretative framing to allow more immediate engagement with the poem. Glosses clarify synonyms or showcase various possible meanings in Pulter’s time. Other notes identify named people and places or clarify obscure material. We rely (without citation) primarily on the Oxford English Dictionary (OED), the Oxford Reference database, and the King James Version (KJV) of the Bible. When we rely on Alice Eardley’s edition of Pulter’s work, we cite her text generally (“Eardley”); other sources are cited in full. The result is an edition we consider a springboard for further work on Pulter’s poetry. <ref target="https://pulterproject.northwestern.edu/about-project-conventions.html#elemental-edition" type="new-window-url">See full conventions for this edition here.</ref></note></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">
            <note type="editorialnote"></note>
          </rdg>
        </app>
        <app type="headnote">
          <rdg wit="#ee">
              <note type="headnote">Jealousy: good or bad? It can be “noble” or not, in Pulter’s terms. The noble kind avoids pre-emptive strikes, such as the dramatic approach of the male wild ass, who bites off the testicles of its male newborns to prevent them mating with their mother (so Pulter’s sources claimed). It is not hard to understand her castigation of this approach to preventing infidelity; more surprising is her apparent endorsement, by contrast, of the lion’s and the elephant’s policy of uxoricide: the killing of their unfaithful mates. What makes the difference? The ass, cynically, predicts the worst--the infidelity and incest of both spouse and offspring--while the lion (like the elephant) waits until he “<hi rend="italic">knows</hi> she doth amiss” (emphasis added). The vice emblematized, therefore, is not jealousy, but “suspicion.” This poem joins Emblems 19 and 20 in their concern with marital fidelity, while sharpening the focus of the preceding emblem in the manuscript (<ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="96">Old Aeschylus (Emblem 31)</ref>) in a preoccupation with avoiding undue apprehension and preconception. “Let me not here anticipate the grave,” the speaker pleads, there, with herself; here, more indirectly, a similar message is proffered to an unspecified “you.”</note>
          </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">
            <note type="headnote"></note>
          </rdg>
        </app>
      </head>

      <l n="1">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft"><fw type="seqNum" place="inline">32</fw>   <seg>The<note type="physical">poem begins near bottom of page on which previous poem ends</note></seg> Lion Roars his vaſſals fear and tremble</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">The lion roars; his <seg>vassals<note type="gloss">subordinates, servants</note></seg> fear and tremble.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="2">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">But if hee comes where they doe all aſſemble</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">But if he comes where they do all assemble,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="3">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">They Stand examinated as they Say</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">They stand <seg>examinated<note type="gloss">examined, as a witness at a trial, or a student tested for competence. Pulter uses this word to suggest the lion’s “institutional” power over the subjects who are at his mercy.</note></seg>, as they say.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="4">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Thus Tirant like hee chooſeth out his prey</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Thus, tyrant-like, he chooseth out his prey;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="5">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Yet though his Subjects at his Mercie Lies</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Yet though his subjects at his mercy lies,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="6">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Yet hee’s a Slave unto his Love’s bright eyes</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Yet he’s a slave unto his love’s bright eyes,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>

        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">
                <fw type="catch" place="bottom">being</fw>
            </rdg>
        </app>

        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">
                <pb ed="#ft" facs="#f7610_228" n="112v"/>
            </rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">
                <pb ed="#ee" facs="#f7610_228"/>
            </rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">
                <pb ed="#ae" facs="#f7610_228"/>
            </rdg>
        </app>

      <l n="7">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Beeing most indulgent to his Lyones</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Being most indulgent to his <seg>lioness<note type="gloss">See Philemon Holland’s translation of Pliny for a parallel to the next few lines: “Lionesses are very lecherous, and this is the very cause that the lions are so fell and cruel. ... The lion knoweth by sent and smell of the pard [panther, leopard] when the lioness his mare hath played false, … and presently with all his might and maine runneth upon her for to chastise and punish her. And therefore when the lioness hath done a fault that way, she either goeth to a river, and washeth away the strong and rank savor of the pard, or els keepeth aloof, and followeth the lion far off, that he may not catch the said smell.” <bibl><title rend="italic">The History of the World</title> (London, 1634), p. 200</bibl>.</note></seg>;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="8">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Yet Kils her if hee Knows Shee <seg><add place="below">\</add><add place="above">do’th\</add><note type="physical">written in H2</note></seg> a miſs</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Yet kills her if he knows she doth amiss.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="9">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">&ff;or when hee Smels the Panthers Strong perfumes</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">For when he smells <seg>the panther’s strong perfumes<note type="gloss">“Perfumes” may refer to to any odors. See Philemon Holland’s translation of Pliny: “It is said, that all four-footed beasts are wonderfully delighted and enticed by the smell of panthers” <bibl><title rend="italic">The History of the World</title> (London, 1634), p. 204</bibl>.</note></seg>,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="10">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">That Shee hath Broke her &ff;aith he then p<add place="above">e</add>ſumes</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">That she hath broke her faith he then presumes.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="11">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">But if Shee waſh her in Some Criſtall Streams</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">But if she wash her in some crystal streams,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="12">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">That Shee is falce to him hee never dreams</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">That she is false to him he never dreams.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="13">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Such Noble Jealouſie all must co<hi rend="overline">m</hi>end</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Such noble jealousy all must commend.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="14">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">In this the Elaphant doth Soe Tranſcend</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">In this, the elephant doth <seg>so<note type="gloss">equally, to the same extent; or, possibly, short for “also.” The sense is that the lion and elephant equally transcend other creatures in the nobility of their jealousy. See <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="84">The Elephant (Emblem 19)</ref>: “For chastity this gallant creature’s crowned; / … / Yet, he’s so tender of his reputation / He kills his female if he doubts [fears] scortation [adultery].”</note></seg> transcend.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="15">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft"><seg>But<note type="physical">in left margin: “<add place="above">x</add> Plinie y<add place="above">e</add> 11 Boo / Chapter 30.”</note></seg> the wild hairbraind <seg>And<note type="physical">“n” appears to correct partly and imperfectly erased letter, possibly “ſ”</note></seg> Laſcivious <add place="above">x</add>Aſs</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">But the wild, hare-brained, and <seg>lascivious ass<note type="gloss">lustful or lewd donkey. A note in the margin refers readers to Chapter 30 of Pliny’s 11th book: a reference to an ancient compendium of natural history. For the meter, “lascivious” should take three syllables.</note></seg></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="16">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">All Creatures els in Jealouſie doth paſs</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">All creatures else in jealousy doth pass;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="17">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">&ff;or hee doth Watch <seg>his<note type="physical">“is” written over earlier “er”</note></seg> Young ones when they fall</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">For he doth watch his young ones <seg>when they fall<note type="gloss">when they are born</note></seg>;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="18">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Then to prevent all fear hee bites of all</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Then, <seg>to prevent all fear, he bites off all<note type="gloss">The father ass aims to avoid having his sons mate with their mother by castrating them at birth, with “all” referring here to testicles. See Philemon Holland’s translation of Pliny on wild asses (cited in the margin of this line to Chapter 30 of his eleventh book, in error for the eighth): “This beast is so jealous, that they look narrowly to the females great with young: for so soon as they have foaled, they bite off the cods [testicles] of the little ones that be males, and so geld [castrate] them.” <bibl><title rend="italic">The History of the World</title> (London, 1634), p. 212</bibl>.</note></seg>.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="19">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Hee’s Surely proud of’s Ears and fears the Horn</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">He’s surely proud <seg>of’s<note type="gloss">of his</note></seg> ears, and fears <seg>the horn<note type="gloss">a cuckold, an insulting term for the husband of an unfaithful wife was imagined to grow a horn or horns</note></seg>,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="20">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">When ’tis the Wittal is the peoples Scorn</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">When ’tis the <seg>wittol<note type="gloss">a husband who is aware of his wife’s infidelity and puts up with it</note></seg> is the people’s scorn.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="21">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Then by theſe Storyes you may plainly See</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Then by these stories you may plainly see</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="22">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">The Noblest Mind is from Suſpition &ff;ree</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">The noblest mind is from suspicion free;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="23">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">And by like Conſequence it comes to paſs</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">And by like consequence it comes to pass</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="24">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">None is Soe Jealous as the mad braind Aſs</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">None is so jealous as the mad-brained ass.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
