<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../src/vmachine.xsl"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
  schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI [

  <!ENTITY ff "<!-- ff ligature, representing capital modern day capital F, here represented as 'ff' -->ff">

  ]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mads.pp.78">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This Vast Leviathan (Emblem 12)</title>
        <title type="sub">Poem 78</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Created by</resp>
          <persName>Leah Knight</persName>
          <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoded by</resp>
          <persName>Katherine Poland</persName>
          <persName>Matthew Taylor</persName>
          <persName>Betsy Chou</persName>
          <persName>Emily Andrey</persName>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>IT-project consultation by</resp>
          <persName>Josh Honn</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
          <orgName>Brock University</orgName>
          <orgName>University of Leeds</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <principal>
          <persName/>
        </principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="1"/>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription, transformations, and notes</resp>
          <persName>Leah Knight</persName>
          <orgName>Brock University</orgName>
          <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
        </respStmt>
      </editionStmt>
      <extent/>
      <publicationStmt>
        <ab/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listBibl>
          <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
              <repository>See witness list.</repository>
            </msIdentifier>
          </msDesc>
        </listBibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p/>
      </projectDesc>
      <p>Transcriptions are encoded in TEI(P5)-conformant XML.</p>
      <samplingDecl>
        <p/>
      </samplingDecl>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction>
          <p>Apparent errors are preserved and editorial corrections provided using SIC and CORR tags, but only where the editor conjectures that the original scribe or compositor would have recognized the instance as an error. For example, what according to modern usage is incorrect subject/verb agreement might have been deemed acceptable to a seventeenth-century scribe or compositor. All such instances are treated instead using the ORIG and REG tags. (See below.)</p>
          <p>Corrections and annotations made within the scope of the original document either by its original authors, owners, and/or transcribers are noted using ADD tags. These annotations and may be further explained within NOTE tags, as added by the editors of this digital edition, for display within the apparatus.</p>
        </correction>
        <normalization>
          <p>Original spellings, abbreviations, and orthography are preserved. Where in the manuscripts a character's status as majuscule or minuscule is ambiguous, the editor has silently chosen one or the other based on context and judgment (i.e., does not register such ambiguity in either the markup or the notes).</p>
        </normalization>
        <quotation>
          <p>Original quotation marks, if any, are preserved.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation>
          <p>Original hyphenation is preserved.</p>
        </hyphenation>
      </editorialDecl>
      <charDecl>
        <!-- Ligature combinations for which there are currently no corresponding Unicode codepoints. -->
        <glyph xml:id="ffllig">
          <glyphName>Handwritten 'ff' ligature, used in handwriting to represent modern F</glyphName>
        </glyph>
      </charDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="DDC22">
          <bibl>
            <title>Dewey Decimal Classification</title>
            <edition/>
            <publisher/>
            <pubPlace/>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-GB">British English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <!-- dewey decimal system class code 821: English Poetry -->
        <classCode scheme="DDC22">821</classCode>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
    <!-- List of all images associated with this document -->
    <graphic url="./document_images/7610_200.jpg" xml:id="f7610_200"/>

  </facsimile>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="ft">Transcription of manuscript: By <persName xml:id="lknight">Leah Knight</persName> and <persName xml:id="wwall">Wendy Wall</persName>.</witness>
          <witness xml:id="ee">Elemental edition: By <persName>Leah Knight</persName> and <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>.</witness>
          <witness xml:id="ae">Amplified edition: By <persName>Christopher D. Jimenez</persName>.</witness>
        </listWit>
      </div>
    </front>

    <body>

      <!-- Each page break should be represented wih a block like this with the correct facs reference-->
      <app>
        <rdg wit="#ft">
          <pb ed="#ft" facs="#f7610_200" n="98v"/>
        </rdg>
        <rdg wit="#ee">
          <pb ed="#ee" facs="#f7610_200"/>
        </rdg>
        <rdg wit="#ae">
          <pb ed="#ae" facs="#f7610_200"/>
        </rdg>
      </app>

      <head>
        <app type="title">
          <rdg wit="#ft"><fw facs="#f7610_200" type="pageNum" place="margin-topright">12</fw>[Emblem 12]</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">This Vast Leviathan<lb/>(Emblem 12)</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">This Vast Leviathan (Emblem 12)</rdg>
        </app>
        <app type="editorialnote">
          <rdg wit="#ft">
            <note type="editorialnote">In these transcriptions we preserve as many details of the original material, textual, and graphic properties of Hester Pulter’s manuscript verse as we have found practical. Whenever possible, for instance, original spelling, punctuation, capitalization, lineation, insertions, deletions, alterations, spacing between words and lines, and indentation are all maintained; abbreviations and brevigraphs are not expanded; and superscript and subscript representations are retained. <ref target="//pulterproject.northwestern.edu/about-project-conventions.html#top" type="new-window-url">See full conventions for the transcriptions here.</ref></note>
          </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">
            <note type="editorialnote">The aim of the elemental edition is to make the poems accessible to the largest variety of readers, which involves modernizing spelling and punctuation as well as adding basic glosses. Spelling and punctuation reflect current standard American usage; punctuation highlights syntax which might otherwise be obscure. Outmoded but still familiar word forms (“thou,” “‘tis,” “hold’st”) are not modernized, and we do not modernize grammar when the sense remains legible. After a brief headnote aimed at offering a “way in” to the poem’s unique qualities and connections with other verse by Pulter or her contemporaries, the edition features a minimum of notes and interpretative framing to allow more immediate engagement with the poem. Glosses clarify synonyms or showcase various possible meanings in Pulter’s time. Other notes identify named people and places or clarify obscure material. We rely (without citation) primarily on the Oxford English Dictionary (OED), the Oxford Reference database, and the King James Version (KJV) of the Bible. When we rely on Alice Eardley’s edition of Pulter’s work, we cite her text generally (“Eardley”); other sources are cited in full. The result is an edition we consider a springboard for further work on Pulter’s poetry. <ref target="//pulterproject.northwestern.edu/about-project-conventions.html#elemental-edition" type="new-window-url">See full conventions for this edition here.</ref></note></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">
            <note type="editorialnote">This Amplified Edition seeks to preserve as closely as possible the manuscript’s Early Modern spelling in “This Vast Leviathan (Emblem 12)” as well as the spelling and formatting of its marginal notes. Thus, the notes included here serve to mirror those of the manuscript itself. One reason for this editorial choice is to provide readers a basic digital facsimile of the poem as transcribed. Another, more critical reason is to foreground for the reader a few of the poem’s irresolvable internal tensions regarding its scribal transpositions, which are discussed in more detail in the headnote and the first footnote. While the Elemental Edition provides invaluable historical insight into how to gloss the probable meanings of certain words and phrases, this Amplified Edition hopes to suggest that even seemingly “direct” citations in the manuscript might be at odds with their own “directness”, a point which might have been acutely felt by the scribe employed with the tricky task of transposing the presumptive “authoritative” original versions of Pulter’s poetry. While this scribal dilemma runs through the entire corpus and indeed may be considered the definitional challenge that universally faces all scribes, it is arguably particularly relevant to a reading of “This Vast Leviathan (Emblem 12)” in relation to the poem’s sustained emphasis on contemplating the diametrical contrasts that exist across various hierarchies of being: rich versus poor, natural versus spiritual, etc.—and to these we might also add authorial versus editorial.</note>
          </rdg>
        </app>
        <app type="headnote">
          <rdg wit="#ee">
              <note type="headnote">In this emblem, Pulter draws on two animals—the whale and the crocodile—to exemplify a common lesson: because people in a social hierarchy are interdependent, those at the top should appreciate the labors of those below. But there is nothing predictable about the vivid, or even lurid, scenarios she paints of creatures who are medicated and fed by the intestinal juices, waste products, and half-chewed food scraps of other creatures. Drawing on Jewish lore, the Bible, and natural history, the speaker first imagines Jonah’s three-day voyage into the belly of the beast as an invigorating retreat featuring a diet of fatty tissue with a side dish of “poignant sauce and unctuous caviar;” yet even the whale, whose powerful instrumentality as a host is divinely sanctioned, cannot survive without the help of a tiny fish, who benefits in turn from the whale’s leftovers. The Egyptian crocodile’s symbiotic relationship with a wren provides the second example: in sentences whose shifting pronouns make the identities of three animals dizzyingly unstable, the speaker shows that the powerful crocodile depends on a small bird’s warning that rats will crawl into its body to feast on its intestines; as a reward, the wren gets to pick half-eaten food from the beast’s teeth. The reader may remember the visceral disgust created by her examples more than Pulter’s simple if valuable moral about interdependency.</note>
          </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">
            <note type="headnote">
              <p>We might supplement Leah Knight and Wendy Wall’s excellent Elemental Edition of “This Vast Leviathan (Emblem 12)” by emphasizing the paradoxical relationship between consumption and corruption throughout the poem. On its surface, the poem’s “leviathan” is a straightforward reference to the divine sea creature depicted in the Hebrew Bible whose name etymologically means “twisted” or “coiled” (Hirsch et al.). Pulter extends this visceral metaphor to portray a monstrous body that dramatizes the geography and ecological cycles of Nature itself with its representations of “floods,” “sands,” and the earthly fields in which there is “labor at the plough.” Not only should we follow Knight and Wall’s injunction to track the poem’s “shifting pronouns” and its depiction of the “dizzyingly unstable” identities of various animals, but we should also strive to apprehend its representation of the macro- and microcosms of the natural world. These extend from the vast reaches of oceans in which swim “shoals of fishes” to the smaller spaces between crocodile “teeth” as well as other vivid examples that emphasize scalar relationships between animalistic bodies and civic order. In other words, Pulter’s vast leviathan represents a monolithic body made of a polyphony of material forces: social, biological, and political.</p>
              <p>Modern readers will note, then, that Pulter’s “This Vast Leviathan” anticipates what Thomas Hobbes would argue elsewhere in his famous treatise of a similar name: <title rend="italic">Leviathan</title>, published in 1651. One of Hobbes’ primary contentions in <title rend="italic">Leviathan</title> is that “Men are moved by appetites and aversions,” which comprise the seminal forces that urge and inform man’s “Will” and “Deliberation.” From this initial postulate, Hobbes suggests that understanding the complex organization of political society depends on the recognition of the simple mechanisms that move human bodies, from the inner workings of sense organs to those controlling the effluvia of emotions and cognition. Whether or not Pulter was familiar with Hobbes’ influential work when writing her poetry, it is against this materialist context that “The Vast Leviathan” presents an alternative reckoning with a multitude of social and theological concerns including class hierarchies, the relationship between humans and animals, and the sovereignty of God over all creation. Whereas the grand conclusion of Hobbes’ <title rend="italic">Leviathan</title> is that that all men necessarily struggle against each other for eminent power in political society, Pulter not only finds recourse in the ultimate sovereignty of God but indeed suggests that all oppositional struggles can be considered as mutual dependencies organized by Nature that likewise involve the perpetual contestation between vital appetite and worldly corruptions.</p>
              <p>The tension between the divine as represented through nature and animals, on one hand, and Pulter’s tempering attitude towards monarchs, on the other, thus complicates what Alice Eardley calls the poet’s “vehemently Royalist” sympathies (346), suggesting that Pulter’s politics extend beyond the particularity of a specific court and advance a more philosophical consideration of sovereignty in the abstract. Notably, while “This Vast Leviathan (Emblem 12)” lacks clear references to any specific monarch, a later poem in the manuscript, <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="107">“This Huge Leviathan (Emblem 42)”</ref> seems to take direct aim at Oliver Cromwell who rises “from the vulgar” common crowd to rule an unruly populace. Regardless of which ruler was in power at the time of the composition of these two emblems, Pulter’s political commentary evinces the stark contradictions inherent in the enormous yet limited influence that may be held by a human leader when compared to the grand or even spiritual sovereignty invoked by the figure of the leviathan. Further explaining the parallel between excessive consumption as typified by aristocracy and bodily corruption as represented by laboring subjects and animals in decay, Emma Rayner identifies that a strain of melancholia runs through Pulter’s poetry not only in relation to its nostalgia for Charles I but also in its mourning for figures in Pulter’s life such as her daughter Jane, who in 1646 died of smallpox (81). While the unknown relationship between the chronology of these events and the often undated composition of Pulter’s poetry complicates our capacity to read the emblems against them in any straightforward way, these biographical details still provide some illumination of the historical and interpersonal pressures that inform Pulter’s thematic tendency toward biopolitical discourses.</p>
              <p>Even without a clear sense of Pulter’s political motives, however, we readers may interpret significant meanings from the temporal and spatial slippages in Pulter’s verse as well as her reference to animals and the natural world throughout. Indeed, the scalar shifts employed by Pulter in the myriad images throughout “This Vast Leviathan” corroborate Liza Blake’s arguments in “Hester Pulter’s Particle Physics and the Poetics of Involution,” in which the author suggests that the conceptual meaning of “leviathan” to “coil” or “twist” might be compared to Pulter’s thematic emphasis on “involution.” As Blake puts it, to “involve” is “to wrap, envelop, and enfold; to (transitively) wind something into a spiral; but also to entwine, to join by winding . . . to implicate . . . to entangle” (71). In this way, the implicated terms of “involve”-ment and “leviathan” etymologically emphasize the interdependence between nature and species as well as the interdependence between economic and political classes. </p>
              <p>Thus, Pulter arguably participates in a longer tradition in Early Modern literature in which representations of the sea as well as sea monsters are used to interrogate social, economic, and political systems. In Shakespeare’s <title rend="italic">Pericles</title>, for instance, the titular character survives a shipwreck and laments, “Alas, the sea hath cast me on the rocks, / Wash’d me from shore to shore, and left my breath / Nothing to think on but ensuing death” (<title rend="italic">Pericles</title> 2.1.5–7). One of the fishermen who finds him remarks, “Why, as men do a-land: the great ones eat up the little ones. I can compare our rich misers to nothing so fitly as to a whale: he plays and tumbles, driving the poor fry before him and at last devours them all at a mouthful” (<title rend="italic">Pericles</title> 2.1.29–33). These lines express a politically and economically involved entanglement between the poor fishermen and a temporarily washed-up prince that is mediated through not only nature but also the sea creatures which inhabit and devour it. Likewise, as Dan Brayton has persuasively argued in an analysis of the “royal” fish in Shakespeare’s oeuvre, “Whales feature prominently in cultural narratives . . . in mediating the relationship of humanity with nature, and they do so under the weight of a cultural history that vacillates betweens a threatening alterity and an uncanny resemblance: whales are both monstrous and strangely familiar” (48). John Donne’s <title rend="italic">Metempsychosis</title> (1601) also makes use of the theme of monstrous consumption in relation to whales and their capacity to represent an inextricable interconnection between humans and nature: “So on his backe lyes this whale wantoning, / And in his gulfe-like throat, sucks every thing / That passeth neare. Fish chaseth fish, and all, / Flyer and follower, in this whirlepoole fall; . . .” (XXXIII, lines 4–7).</p>
              <p>For Pulter’s “This Vast Leviathan,” this involutional interplay with creatures is perhaps most strikingly narrated in the lines that speak of a crocodile’s “Mouth” into and out of which flies a “Wren” hoping to goad the reptile into eating the “Ichneumon,” which is a rat or mongoose which the wren considers as “foe.” In this poetic scene, Pulter leaves open the crocodile’s “gapeing” maw to redirect the reader’s attention to the wren’s own consumption of the “Putred flesh” between the crocodile’s teeth into her “Lothed Intralls.” In effect, readers are presented with a creature eating a creature eating a creature, all of which occupy what appear to be disproportionate positions of power but all of which are also ultimately relegated to the same biological needs. In stressing the chiasms between life and death, world and body, or rich and poor, Pulter’s poem adds moral nuance to the Shakespearean view of the world seen in Hamlet’s humbling reminder to his uncle, King Claudius, of the cyclic mortality of men: “A man may fish with the worm that hath eat of a king, and eat of the fish that hath fed of the worm . . . to show you how a king may go a progress through the guts of a beggar” (<title rend="italic">Hamlet</title> 4.3.24–7).</p>
              <p>For this reason, readers may also appreciate the irony produced by the poem’s own materiality as a textual object that has been prepared for readerly consumption by an entangled and overlapping set of editorial efforts, even as said efforts could be said to have “corrupted” Pulter’s original version of the poem. <title rend="italic">The Pulter Project</title> lays bare the coiled connections between these efforts in its functionality that allows readers to compare editions of poems side by side along with the manuscript, which itself is a scribal transposition of Pulter’s original work. That is, the poem itself might be considered a “Vast Leviathan, Whose Breathing blows” in the sense that its textual force has propagated throughout the centuries, conscripting readers and editors alike in the productive play of literary meaning.</p>
              <p>To this end, one final observation that this Amplified Edition seeks to highlight in its preservation of Early Modern spellings regards the variant forms of “lyes” and “lies” in lines 3 and 4. In these lines—“See whose fair Consort in Salt Pickle lyes / To feast the Jews or else their Talmond lies”—the lyes/lies could be interpreted as the same word that were made with variant spellings either via an unintentional mistake or else as an intentionally unresolved confusion passed on by the scribe who has transposed the original manuscript for us. That is, given the available evidence which suggests Pulter first wrote the poems in the 1640s and 50s but that an unidentified scribe produced the manuscript extant today, it is unclear whether Pulter intended those lines to end differently or if this was a consequence of scribal transposition. If the former, especially in the case where Pulter may have overseen the transpositions herself, we might consider another interplay of contradictions in Pulter’s verse, where the caustic alkaline solution invoked by salty “lyes” runs in direct contrast to the “lies” associated with feasts. If the latter, however, we readers have ostensibly witnessed yet another cyclic twist of the leviathan, where “lyes” and “lies” are words uneasily shared both by Pulter and the unknown scribe, with a single letter altered for no discernible reason beyond scribal whim or else leviathanic fate. </p>
            </note>
          </rdg>
        </app>
      </head>

      <l n="1">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft"><fw type="seqNum" place="inline">12</fw>This Vast Leviathan Whoſe Breathing blows</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">This vast <seg>leviathan<note type="gloss">a large sea animal; here, a whale</note></seg>, whose breathing blows</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>This Vast Leviathan<note type="critical">Compared to the Elemental Edition of “This Vast Leviathan (Emblem 12)”, which helpfully modernizes and standardizes the poem for contemporary English readers, this Amplified Edition leaves the text unaltered even where seemingly obvious scribal mistakes or misspellings have occurred. While the manuscript presents the word “Leviathan” similarly to how present-day audiences would expect, it is important to note that in Middle English there are variant spellings of the word, including leviethan, liviatan, liviaton, and eleviatham. Thus, Putler’s use of “Leviathan” could be considered a deliberate choice among multiple orthographic possibilities, suggesting the variant spellings of other words throughout the poem could be considered similarly deliberate even if they would be considered typographical mistakes to present-day readers. See Frances McSparran, et al., ed., “Leviathan,” in <title rend="italic">Middle English Compendium</title>, last modified July 2023. The reference to “leviathan” appears multiple times in the Old Testament (King James Version) in Psalms 74:14, Job 41:1–34, and Isaiah 27:1 among others. H. H. Rowley notes that some biblical scholars have “connected the name Levi with Leviathan” (132). See Harold H., Rowley, “Zadok and Nehushtan,” <title rend="italic">Journal of Biblical Literature</title> (1939): 113-141.</note></seg> Whose Breathing blows</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="2">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Huge &ff;loods and Sholes of &ff;iſhes through his Noſe</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Huge floods and <seg>shoals<note type="gloss">schools; a large number of sea creatures swimming together</note></seg> of fishes through his nose;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Huge floods and sholes of fishes through his Nose</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="3">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Hee whoſe &ff;air Conſort in Salt Pickle lyes</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">He <seg>whose fair consort in salt pickle lies<note type="gloss">According to rabbinical literature, God first produced a male and female leviathan, but to prevent the species from multiplying and destroying the world, he killed the female and preserved her flesh to serve at a banquet for the righteous after the Messiah arrives. See Emil G. Hirsch, Kaufmann Kohler, Solomon Schechter, Isaac Broydé, “Leviathan and Behemoth,” jewishencyclopedia.com.</note></seg></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">See whose fair Consort in <seg>Salt Pickle lyes<note type="critical"> In this line, the manuscript spelling of “lyes” resonates with the meanings of “salt” and “pickle” to suggest the process of brining foods in alkaline solutions for the purposes of preservation, emphasizing the poem’s theme of consumption. Additionally, the poem’s play on the word “lye” and the word “lie” in the following line could also be interpreted as evoking the themes of deceit (as in “liars tell lies”) and blame (as in “the blame lies with you”), emphasizing the relationship between physical consumption and moral corruption.
</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="4">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">To feast the Jewes or elce their Talmond lies</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">To feast the Jews (or else their <seg>Talmud<note type="gloss">body of Jewish laws and interpretations</note></seg> lies);</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">To feast the Jewes or else their Talmond lies</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="5">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Even hee who treated Jonas in his Belly</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Even <seg>he who treated Jonah in his belly<note type="gloss">When Jonah is cast into the sea by fellow mariners who suspect he brings misfortune, God sends a great fish, traditionally thought of as a whale, to swallow Jonah and save him; he remains in the belly of the fish for three days and three nights (Jonah 1:15-17).</note></seg></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Even hee who treated Jonas in his Belly</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="6">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft"><seg>With<note type="physical">imperfectly erased ascender over “i”</note></seg> wholſom Chilus and Provokeing Gelley,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">With wholesome <seg>chilus<note type="gloss">the milky bodily fluid formed during digestion of fatty food</note></seg> and <seg>provoking jelly<note type="gloss">seemingly a reference to whale wax or oil used as medicine (since it is “provoking”—possibly a purgative—and is used here to “treat” Jonah)</note></seg>,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>With wholsom Chilus and Provokeing Gelley<note type="critical">The original manuscript includes several notes in the margins at various places throughout the poem, some of which may be read as potential corrections or additions and others as mere citational references. After this particular line come two lines as follows: “With poynant sauce and Unctious Caveare / A Diet as restorative ar Rare.” An asterisk (*) lies vertically above the next word in the poem—“Even”—suggesting that these lines were added to be read directly after the line “With wholesome Chilus and Provokeing Gelley” and before the line “Even hee the Chief of all the Sons of Pride.”
</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="7">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft"><seg>E*ven<note type="physical">in left margin: “x*even hee [“x” and “even hee” not struck-through but erased] / With poynant Sauce / And Unctious Caveare / A Diet as reſtorative / ar Rare”</note></seg> hee the Chief of all the Sons of Pride</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">With <seg>poignant<note type="gloss">of a sharp taste or smell</note></seg> sauce and <seg>unctuous<note type="gloss">oily, greasy, fat, rich</note></seg> caviar,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Even* hee the Chief of all the Sons of Pride</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="8">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Cannot purſue his prey without a Guide</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">A diet as restorative as rare—</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Cannot pursue his prey without a Guide</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="9">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">The little Muſculus doth Swim before</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Even he, the <seg>chief of all the sons of pride<note type="gloss">Biblical description of the Leviathan: “a king over all the children of pride” (Job 41:34).</note></seg>,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">The little Musculus doth Swim before</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="10">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Least hee in Shelves or Sands his Bulk Should Moor</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Cannot pursue his prey without a guide.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Least hee in Shelves or Sands his Bulk should Moor</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="11">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">And of the Whales abundance Shee but lives</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee"><seg>The little musculus doth swim before<note type="gloss"> Pliny, in his natural history, writes of a fish “called Musculus Marinus, which goeth before the whale … as his guide”; elsewhere, in a chapter entitled, “Of the enmity and amity which is between fishes and other water beasts,” of the “society and fellowship” between whales and this fish: “whereas the whale aforesaid hath no use of his eyes … the other swimmeth before him, serveth him instead of eyes and lights, to show when he is near the shelves and shallows, wherein he may be soone grounded, so big and huge he is.” See Book 11, Chapter 37, and Book 9, Chapter 62, in Philemon Holland’s translation of The History of the World (London, 1601).</note></seg>,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">And of the Whales abundance shee but lives</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="12">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">The Emperious Monſter <seg>Sc<add place="above">r</add>apes<note type="physical">“r” appears in different hand from main scribe</note></seg>, and Ma<hi rend="overline">m</hi>ucks gives</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Lest <seg>he<note type="gloss">the leviathan, or whale</note></seg> in shelves or sands his bulk should moor.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">The Emperious Monster <seg>Scapes<note type="gloss">The manuscript includes a small “r” above “Scapes,” a likely correction meant to change the line to “The Emperious Monster Scrapes,” but the OED tells us that the uncorrected word “Scapes” could work as well in reference to, for example, an escape (“1. An act of escaping”), a transgression (“2. A transgression due to thoughtlessness; also, with different notion, a breaking out from moral restraint, an outrageous sin; often applied to a breach of chastity”), or a mistake (“3. An inadvertent mistake; esp. a slip of the tongue or a clerical error, a ‘fault escaped’”).</note></seg>, and Mammucks gives</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="13">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Soe may you See Nils Caymen gapeing lye</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee"><seg>And of the whale’s abundance she but lives<note type="gloss">That is, the whole diet of the musculus derives from the whale’s excess supply.</note></seg>;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Soe may you see Nils Caymen gapeing lye</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="14">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Whilst in and out his Mouth the<add place="above">x</add> Wren doth &ff;lie</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Th’imperious <seg>monster<note type="gloss">the whale</note></seg> scraps and <seg>mammocks<note type="gloss">scraps or shreds; broken or torn pieces</note></seg> gives.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Whilst in and out his Mouth the <seg>Wren<note type="physical">Marking the word “Wren” with a cross (+), the manuscript includes a marginal reference to “Trochilos Plinius / Book 11th: Chap: 3d.”</note></seg> doth flie</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="15">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft"><seg>To<note type="physical">in left margin: “<add place="above">x</add> Trochilos Plinie / Book 11:th Chap: 3d”</note></seg> wake him when the *Ichneumon her &ff;oe</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">So may you see Nile’s <seg>caiman<note type="gloss">a term loosely applied to some members of the crocodile family</note></seg> gaping lie</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">To wake him when the <seg>Ichneumon<note type="critical">Another asterisk (*) marks “Ichneumon” with the marginal note, “Or Indian Pharos / Rat Plinius Book 8 / chap: 23.” Various translations of Pliny the Elder’s <title rend="italic">Natural History</title>, commonly called <title rend="italic">The History of the World</title>, use different chapter numbers, but Pulter and/or her scribe are most likely referring to the translation completed by Philemon Holland first published in 1601. In that translation, Book 8, Chapter 23 discusses “Of Serpents,” but Chapter 24 is titled “Of the Rat of India, called Ichneumon.” The chapter begins as follows: “BESIDES the foresaid infirmitie, there is mortall warre betweene them and the Ichenumones or rats of India. A beast this is, well knowne to the Aspis, in this regard especially, that it is bred likewise in the same Ægypt.”</note></seg> her foe</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="16">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Into her Lothed Intralls Strives to goe</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Whilst in and out his mouth <seg>the wren<note type="physical">In the manuscript, an “x” between these words is keyed to a note in the left margin, which refers us to Pliny’s account of the “Trochilos”; the citation is to Book 11, Chapter 3, but in Philemon Holland’s translation, Book 8, Chapter 25 features this account of the Nile crocodile: “When he hath filled his belly with fishes, he lieth to sleep … and for that he is a great and greedy devourer, somewhat of the meat sticketh evermore between his teeth. In regard whereof cometh the wren, a little bird called there Trochilos, and the king of birds in Italy: and she, for her victual’s sake, hoppeth first about his mouth, falleth to pecking and picking it with her little neb or bill, and so forward to the teeth, which she cleanseth; and all to make him gape. Then getteth she within his mouth, which he openeth the wider, by reason that he taketh so great delight in this her scraping and scouring of his teeth and jaws.” <bibl>Philemon Holland, trans., C. Plinius Secundus, <title rend="italic">The Historie of the World</title> (London, 1601)</bibl>.</note></seg> doth fly</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Into her Lothed Intralls strives to goe</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="17">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">&ff;or which the Putred &ff;leſh Shee picks away</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">To wake him when the <seg>ichneumon<note type="physical">An asterisk by this word in the manuscript is keyed to a note in the margin referring us to Pliny’s natural history, Book 8, Chapter 23; while that chapter features the ichneumon (a type of mongoose), the poem’s account is actually a continuation of material from Chapter 25: “when [the crocodile] is lulled as it were fast asleep with this pleasure and contentment of his: the rat of India, or ichneumon ... spieth his vantage, and seeing him lie thus broad gaping, whippeth into his mouth, and shooteth himself down his throat as quick as an arrow, and then gnaweth his bowels, eateth an hole through his belly, and so killeth him.” <bibl>Philemon Holland, trans., C. Plinius Secundus, <title rend="italic">The Historie of the World</title> (London, 1601)</bibl>.</note></seg>, <seg>her<note type="critical">the caiman’s (or crocodile’s), whose gender, according to the pronouns, seemingly shifts from male to female. While this may be a scribal error, it was not corrected by the hand that is probably Pulter’s; as such, the gender confusion may enhance the general blurring of identities created by confusing pronouns designating the bird and crocodile in the next lines. Eardley alters this pronoun, as well as the next two referring to the crocodile, to “him,” which stabilizes the crocodile’s gender. A reader might just as legitimately alter the two pronouns used earlier to refer to the crocodile to create a consistently female-gendered animal.</note></seg> foe,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">For which the Putred flesh shee picks away</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="18">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft"><seg>Between<note type="physical">in left margin: “*Or Indian or [inserted in different hand from main scribe] Pharos /  Rat Plinie Book 8 / chap: 23”</note></seg> her teeth, this beeing all her pay</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Into her loathéd <seg>entrails<note type="gloss">internal organs, usually the intestines; here figuratively for the interior of the body</note></seg> strives to go;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Between her teeth, this beeing all her pay</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="19">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Soe greatest Monarchs poorest vaſſals need</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">For which the putrid flesh <seg>she<note type="gloss">the wren</note></seg> picks away</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Soe greatest Monarchs poorest vassals need</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="20">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Soe hungry Peſants pamper’d Nobles &ff;eed</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Between her teeth, this being all her pay.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Soe hungry Pesants pamper’d Nobles heed</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="21">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Then let thoſe that are placed the rest above</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">So greatest monarchs poorest vassals need;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Then let those that are placed the rest above</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="22">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Answer their labour with their care and Love</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">So hungry peasants pampered nobles feed.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Answer their labor with their care and Love</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="23">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft"><seg>And<note type="phsyical">in left margin: “Ecclesiasties / chap,5: v: 9”</note></seg> Pittie thoſe which labor at the Plough</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Then let those that are placed the rest above</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">And Pittie those which labour at the Plough</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="24">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">T’is God that made the difference and not thou.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Answer their labor with their care and love,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Tis God that made the difference <seg>and not thou.<note type="critical">A final marginal note without a directing marker is included in the manuscript next to the last three lines of the poem and references “Ecclesiastios / chap.5: v: 9.” Though punctuation is seldom used elsewhere throughout the poem, a diagonal line underscores the words “and not thou.” with a period added after the final word to mark the poem’s end.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="25">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ee"><seg>And pity those which labor at the plough<note type="physical">A note in the margin cites the biblical Ecclesiastes, Chapter 5, verse 9: “Moreover the profit of the earth is for all: the king himself is served by the field.”</note></seg>;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="26">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ee">’Tis God that made the difference and not thou.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
        <app>
            <rdg type="milestone" wit="#ft">
                <milestone unit="poem" rend="straight-ascendline"/>
            </rdg>
        </app>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
