<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../src/vmachine.xsl"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
  schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI [

  <!ENTITY ff "<!-- ff ligature, representing capital modern day capital F, here represented as 'ff' -->ff">

  ]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mads.pp.19">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
          <title>The Welcome [1]</title>
        <title type="sub">Poem #19</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Created by</resp>
          <persName>Leah Knight</persName>
          <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoded by</resp>
          <persName>Katherine Poland</persName>
          <persName>Matthew Taylor</persName>
          <persName>Betsy Chou</persName>
          <persName>Emily Andrey</persName>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>IT-project consultation by</resp>
          <persName>Josh Honn</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
          <orgName>Brock University</orgName>
          <orgName>University of Leeds</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <principal>
          <persName/>
        </principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="1"/>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription, transformations, and notes</resp>
          <persName>Leah Knight</persName>
          <orgName>Brock University</orgName>
          <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
        </respStmt>
      </editionStmt>
      <extent/>
      <publicationStmt>
        <ab/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listBibl>
          <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
              <repository>See witness list.</repository>
            </msIdentifier>
          </msDesc>
        </listBibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p/>
      </projectDesc>
      <p>Transcriptions are encoded in TEI(P5)-conformant XML.</p>
      <samplingDecl>
        <p/>
      </samplingDecl>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction>
          <p>Apparent errors are preserved and editorial corrections provided using SIC and CORR tags, but only where the editor conjectures that the original scribe or compositor would have recognized the instance as an error. For example, what according to modern usage is incorrect subject/verb agreement might have been deemed acceptable to a seventeenth-century scribe or compositor. All such instances are treated instead using the ORIG and REG tags. (See below.)</p>
          <p>Corrections and annotations made within the scope of the original document either by its original authors, owners, and/or transcribers are noted using ADD tags. These annotations and may be futher explained within NOTE tags, as added by the editors of this digital edition, for display within the apparatus.</p>
        </correction>
        <normalization>
          <p>Original spellings, abbreviations, and orthography are preserved. Where in the manuscripts a character's status as majuscule or miniscule is ambiguous, the editor has silently chosen one or the other based on context and judgment (i.e., does not register such ambiguity in either the markup or the notes).</p>
        </normalization>
        <quotation>
          <p>Original quotation marks, if any, are preserved.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation>
          <p>Original hyphenation is preserved.</p>
        </hyphenation>
      </editorialDecl>
      <charDecl>
        <!-- Ligature combinations for which there are currently no corresponding Unicode codepoints. -->
        <glyph xml:id="ffllig">
          <glyphName>Handwritten 'ff' ligature, used in handwriting to represent modern F</glyphName>
        </glyph>
      </charDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="DDC22">
          <bibl>
            <title>Dewey Decimal Classification</title>
            <edition/>
            <publisher/>
            <pubPlace/>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-GB">British English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <!-- dewey decimal system class code 821: English Poetry -->
        <classCode scheme="DDC22">821</classCode>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
    <!-- List of all images associated with this document -->
      <graphic url="./document_images/7610_081.jpg" xml:id="f7610_081"/>
  </facsimile>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="ft">Transcription of manuscript: By <persName xml:id="lknight">Leah Knight</persName> and <persName xml:id="wwall">Wendy Wall</persName>.</witness>
          <witness xml:id="ee">Elemental edition: By <persName>Leah Knight</persName> and <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>.</witness>
<!--          <witness xml:id="ae">Amplified edition: By <persName>AE EDITOR</persName>.</witness>-->
        </listWit>
      </div>
    </front>

    <body>
      <head>
        <app type="title">
            <rdg wit="#ft"><fw facs="#f7610_069" type="pageNum" place="margin-topright">PG#</fw>The Welcom</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">The Welcome [1]</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">AE TITLE</rdg>
        </app>
        <app type="editorialnote">
          <rdg wit="#ft">
            <note type="editorialnote">In these transcriptions we preserve as many details of the original material, textual, and graphic properties of Hester Pulter’s manuscript verse as we have found practical. Whenever possible, for instance, original spelling, punctuation, capitalization, lineation, insertions, deletions, alterations, spacing between words and lines, and indentation are all maintained; abbreviations and brevigraphs are not expanded; and superscript and subscript representations are retained. <ref target="http://pulterproject.northwestern.edu/about-project-conventions.html#top" type="new-window-url">See full conventions for the transcriptions here.</ref></note>
          </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">
            <note type="editorialnote">The aim of the elemental edition is to make the poems accessible to the largest variety of readers, which involves modernizing spelling and punctuation as well as adding basic glosses. Spelling and punctuation reflect current standard American usage; punctuation highlights syntax which might otherwise be obscure. Outmoded but still familiar word forms (“thou,” “‘tis,” “hold’st”) are not modernized, and we do not modernize grammar when the sense remains legible. After a brief headnote aimed at offering a “way in” to the poem’s unique qualities and connections with other verse by Pulter or her contemporaries, the edition features a minimum of notes and interpretative framing to allow more immediate engagement with the poem. Glosses clarify synonyms or showcase various possible meanings in Pulter’s time. Other notes identify named people and places or clarify obscure material. We rely (without citation) primarily on the Oxford English Dictionary (OED), the Oxford Reference database, and the King James Version (KJV) of the Bible. When we rely on Alice Eardley’s edition of Pulter’s work, we cite her text generally (“Eardley”); other sources are cited in full. The result is an edition we consider a springboard for further work on Pulter’s poetry. <ref target="http://pulterproject.northwestern.edu/about-project-conventions.html#elemental-edition" type="new-window-url">See full conventions for this edition here.</ref></note></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">
            <note type="editorialnote"></note>
          </rdg>
        </app>
        <app type="headnote">
          <rdg wit="#ee">
              <note type="headnote">In this brief poem, death is bid both welcome and farewell, as if in mimicry of its transient power in Pulter’s cosmology. Even the speaker’s easy personification and colloquial diction in the opening lines helps downgrade death as a threat. The speaker’s problem, indeed, is that she <hi rend="italic">cannot</hi> die: which is her fault, since a tender heart would have broken already (presumably from the grief she mentions more than once here, as in other poems alluding to the passing of Pulter’s political heroes and children). But her heart is hard, or “petrified,” a word which in Pulter’s time meant not scared but turned to stone. This image might suggest the speaker’s unfitness as a Christian; what is almost as bad, though, is that such hardness of heart has paradoxically protected her from an otherwise lethal grief: that is, grieving others’ deaths has delayed her own. But in this poem, the speaker seizes the opportunity to turn away from the past and toward her desired death–and with it, presumably, the equally desired end of the grief that forestalled her death until now.</note>
          </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">
            <note type="headnote"></note>
          </rdg>
        </app>
      </head>

      <l n="1">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Deare Death thou’rt welcom to my troubled Soul</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Dear Death, thou’rt welcome to my troubled soul.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="2">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Hark, is it not for mee the bell doth toll?</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Hark: is it not for me the bell doth toll?</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="3">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">How Sweet it Sounds? trust mee I wonder why</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">How sweet it sounds! Trust me, I wonder why</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="4">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Wee are Soe foolliſhly afraid to die</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">We are so foolishly afraid to die;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="5">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Ti’s but a Sigh and turning up the eye,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">’Tis but a sigh and turning up the eye,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="6">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">A few Sad farewels to our freinds to Speak</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">A few sad farewells <seg>to our<note type="critical">Pronounce as one syllable (i.e., “t’our”) to maintain meter.</note></seg> friends to speak,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="7">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">And <add place="below">^</add><add place="above">then</add> a tender heart will quickly break</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">And then a tender heart will quickly break.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="8">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">But my Sad heart (ay mee) is petrified</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">But my sad heart (ay me) is <seg>petrified<note type="gloss">converted to stone</note></seg>,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="9">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Or elce with Griefe I long agon had died</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Or else with grief I long ago had died;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="10">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">But now my Soul thou Shalt infranchiſed bee</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">But now, my soul, thou shalt <seg>enfranchised<note type="gloss">freed from confinement or subjection</note></seg> be,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="11">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Though my flesh trembles ti’s good news for thee</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Though my flesh trembles, ’tis good news for thee.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="12">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">&ff;or thou to heaven again Shall take thy fleight</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">For thou to heav’n again shall take thy flight</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="13">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">And bee involv’d in Joy, Life, Love, and Light</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">And be <seg>involved<note type="gloss">enveloped, entangled</note></seg> in joy, life, love, and light.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="14">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Then bid Adue to Death and her Curst <seg>train<note type="physical">“ain” written over other indiscernible letters</note></seg></rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Then bid adieu to Death and her cursed <seg>train<note type="gloss">treachery, trap, followers, artillery, manner of action, or consequences</note></seg>,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="15">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">&ff;or thou Shalt never more Return againe</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">For thou shalt never more return again</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="16">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">To bee aflicted here with Griefe &amp; paine.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">To be afflicted here with grief and pain.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
