<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../src/vmachine.xsl"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
  schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI [

  <!ENTITY ff "<!-- ff ligature, representing capital modern day capital F, here represented as 'ff' -->ff">

  ]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mads.pp.118">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
          <title>The Snail, the Tulip, and the Bee (Emblem 53)</title>
        <title type="sub">Poem #118</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Created by</resp>
          <persName>Leah Knight</persName>
          <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoded by</resp>
          <persName>Katherine Poland</persName>
          <persName>Matthew Taylor</persName>
          <persName>Betsy Chou</persName>
          <persName>Emily Andrey</persName>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>IT-project consultation by</resp>
          <persName>Josh Honn</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
          <orgName>Brock University</orgName>
          <orgName>University of Leeds</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <principal>
          <persName/>
        </principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="1"/>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription, transformations, and notes</resp>
          <persName>Leah Knight</persName>
          <orgName>Brock University</orgName>
          <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
        </respStmt>
      </editionStmt>
      <extent/>
      <publicationStmt>
        <ab/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listBibl>
          <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
              <repository>See witness list.</repository>
            </msIdentifier>
          </msDesc>
        </listBibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p/>
      </projectDesc>
      <p>Transcriptions are encoded in TEI(P5)-conformant XML.</p>
      <samplingDecl>
        <p/>
      </samplingDecl>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction>
          <p>Apparent errors are preserved and editorial corrections provided using SIC and CORR tags, but only where the editor conjectures that the original scribe or compositor would have recognized the instance as an error. For example, what according to modern usage is incorrect subject/verb agreement might have been deemed acceptable to a seventeenth-century scribe or compositor. All such instances are treated instead using the ORIG and REG tags. (See below.)</p>
          <p>Corrections and annotations made within the scope of the original document either by its original authors, owners, and/or transcribers are noted using ADD tags. These annotations and may be futher explained within NOTE tags, as added by the editors of this digital edition, for display within the apparatus.</p>
        </correction>
        <normalization>
          <p>Original spellings, abbreviations, and orthography are preserved. Where in the manuscripts a character’s status as majuscule or miniscule is ambiguous, the editor has silently chosen one or the other based on context and judgment (i.e., does not register such ambiguity in either the markup or the notes).</p>
        </normalization>
        <quotation>
          <p>Original quotation marks, if any, are preserved.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation>
          <p>Original hyphenation is preserved.</p>
        </hyphenation>
      </editorialDecl>
      <charDecl>
        <!-- Ligature combinations for which there are currently no corresponding Unicode codepoints. -->
        <glyph xml:id="ffllig">
          <glyphName>Handwritten 'ff' ligature, used in handwriting to represent modern F</glyphName>
        </glyph>
      </charDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="DDC22">
          <bibl>
            <title>Dewey Decimal Classification</title>
            <edition/>
            <publisher/>
            <pubPlace/>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-GB">British English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <!-- dewey decimal system class code 821: English Poetry -->
        <classCode scheme="DDC22">821</classCode>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
    <!-- List of all images associated with this document -->
      <graphic url="./document_images/7610_259.jpg" xml:id="f7610_259"/>
      <graphic url="./document_images/7610_260.jpg" xml:id="f7610_260"/>
      <graphic url="./document_images/7610_261.jpg" xml:id="f7610_261"/>
  </facsimile>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="ft">Transcription of manuscript: By <persName xml:id="lknight">Leah Knight</persName> and <persName xml:id="wwall">Wendy Wall</persName>.</witness>
          <witness xml:id="ee">Elemental edition: By <persName>Leah Knight</persName> and <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>.</witness>
          <witness xml:id="ae">Amplified edition: By <persName>Whitney Sperrazza</persName>.</witness>
        </listWit>
      </div>
    </front>

    <body>

      <app>
        <rdg wit="#ft">
            <pb ed="#ft" facs="#f7610_259" n="128r"/>
        </rdg>
        <rdg wit="#ee">
            <pb ed="#ee" facs="#f7610_259"/>
        </rdg>
        <rdg wit="#ae">
            <pb ed="#ae" facs="#f7610_259"/>
        </rdg>
      </app>

      <head>
        <app type="title">
          <rdg wit="#ft"><fw facs="#f7610_069" type="pageNum" place="margin-topright">PG#</fw><seg>[Emblem 53]<note type="physical">Unlike surrounding poems in the “Emblems” section, no number precedes this poem.</note></seg></rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">The Snail, the Tulip, and the Bee<lb/>(Emblem 53)</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">The Snail, the Tulip, and the Bee<lb/>(Emblem 53)</rdg>
        </app>
        <app type="editorialnote">
          <rdg wit="#ft">
            <note type="editorialnote">In these transcriptions we preserve as many details of the original material, textual, and graphic properties of Hester Pulter’s manuscript verse as we have found practical. Whenever possible, for instance, original spelling, punctuation, capitalization, lineation, insertions, deletions, alterations, spacing between words and lines, and indentation are all maintained; abbreviations and brevigraphs are not expanded; and superscript and subscript representations are retained. <ref target="http://pulterproject.northwestern.edu/about-project-conventions.html#top" type="new-window-url">See full conventions for the transcriptions here.</ref></note>
          </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">
            <note type="editorialnote">The aim of the elemental edition is to make the poems accessible to the largest variety of readers, which involves modernizing spelling and punctuation as well as adding basic glosses. Spelling and punctuation reflect current standard American usage; punctuation highlights syntax which might otherwise be obscure. Outmoded but still familiar word forms (“thou,” “‘tis,” “hold’st”) are not modernized, and we do not modernize grammar when the sense remains legible. After a brief headnote aimed at offering a “way in” to the poem’s unique qualities and connections with other verse by Pulter or her contemporaries, the edition features a minimum of notes and interpretative framing to allow more immediate engagement with the poem. Glosses clarify synonyms or showcase various possible meanings in Pulter’s time. Other notes identify named people and places or clarify obscure material. We rely (without citation) primarily on the Oxford English Dictionary (OED), the Oxford Reference database, and the King James Version (KJV) of the Bible. When we rely on Alice Eardley’s edition of Pulter’s work, we cite her text generally (“Eardley”); other sources are cited in full. The result is an edition we consider a springboard for further work on Pulter’s poetry. <ref target="http://pulterproject.northwestern.edu/about-project-conventions.html#elemental-edition" type="new-window-url">See full conventions for this edition here.</ref></note></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">
              <note type="editorialnote">In my editions of Pulter’s poems, I prioritize accessibility and use my annotations to prompt further exploration. To make the poems accessible to the widest possible audience, I have modernized spelling, punctuation, and capitalization according to American English standards. My longer critical notes aim to demonstrate the complexity of Pulter’s thinking, while opening space for the reader’s own analysis and interpretation. In that same vein, I briefly note Pulter’s revisions to the poem in order to foreground her poetic craft. Her manuscript features variants and revisions that invite multiple interpretations, and I encourage readers to refer to the manuscript transcriptions and images as they engage with Pulter’s writing. I offer some references to other early modern texts, but am most interested in drawing out how Pulter’s poems speak to each other as she reflects on clusters of ideas.</note>
          </rdg>
        </app>
        <app type="headnote">
          <rdg wit="#ft">
            <note type="headnote"></note>
          </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">
            <note type="headnote">We all know the cliché of the busy bee, but Pulter found in the bee an emblem not of virtuous industry but instead of overzealous curiosity, greed, and poor judgment. After praising “the active Amazonian maid” for her industriousness and herbalist know-how, this emblem tells of how the bee—having collected her fill of nectar, but unable to leave well enough alone—becomes trapped in a tulip when, at day’s end, its petals close around her. The bee works furiously to escape; a snail, similarly caught, falls asleep without a struggle. In the morning, when the petals reopen, the snail simply leaves, while the bee dies of exhaustion. Pulter sees in her garden an all-female community of vegetable, animal, and celestial beings demonstrating the moral which the poem then shows men to have enacted historically, in a sequence of exemplars warning against impatience and fighting fate. While that may be the overall moral, the poem also touches on the tension between confinement and freedom which so often preoccupies Pulter. The framing phrase for the emblem’s moral—“if no hope of liberty you see”—closely tracks the concluding declaration in “Why Must I Thus Forever Be Confined” (Poem 57): “I no liberty expect to see …” Did Pulter identify with the snail or the bee?</note>
          </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">
              <note type="headnote"><p>Emblem 53 offers a complex political allegory masquerading as a fable about a “covetous” honey bee, a patient snail, and a “painted” tulip. Alongside the poem’s political themes, Pulter raises questions about gender, science, and nature that echo her interest in these topics throughout the manuscript. Most significantly, there are glimpses in this poem of Pulter’s clever theorization of poetry itself—her ongoing exploration of how poetry makes meaning.</p><p>Three distinct, but related, mottoes drive this emblem. The first motto—”then let impatient spirits here but see / what ’tis to struggle with their destiny” (lines 37–8)—concludes the story Pulter tells of a honey bee, enticed by the poet’s sumptuous garden, who tries to gather more “nectar” than she can carry. Straying from the hive for far too long, the bee lands in a tulip alongside a snail just as the sun goes down and the tulip closes its petals. The second and third motto come in sequence at the poem’s end: “’tis valianter by far to live than die” (line 50) and “then if no hope of liberty you see, / think on the snail, the tulip, and the bee” (lines 51–52). These mottoes follow a catalogue of examples from classical history, mostly warnings about excessive pride and arrogance. Three mottoes is a lot for one emblem, which raises interesting questions as we read this poem. How do the three mottoes work together? Do the stories seem to unfold logically into their concluding mottoes or do the mottoes seem incongruous? How does Pulter use these multiple mottoes to invite us to consider the function of the motto as a feature of emblems?</p><p>Pulter’s emblem poems are “naked emblems,” as Millie Godfrey and Sarah C. E. Ross explain in their introduction to <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="67">“Mighty Nimrod” (Emblem 1)</ref>. Revising the traditional tripartite structure of the emblem (motto, visual image, and short epigrammatic verse), Pulter omits the visual image (<foreign rend="italic">pictura</foreign>) element such that the reader must glean meaning solely from words. But Pulter’s language in this and many of her emblems is meant to help the reader paint their own picture. Here, for instance, Pulter references specific flowers, tracks the bee’s movements as it flits around the poet’s garden, and fills her lines with evocative descriptions (the morning sun is “lapped in a robe of silver mixed with gray” [line 5]). The emblem’s central characters—the snail, the tulip, and the bee—would also have been easy visual reference points for Pulter’s readers. All three figures were frequently portrayed in early modern emblem books, textual illustrations, and artwork.</p><p>All three figures are also at the center of early modern debates surrounding gender and sexuality. Even though none of the poem’s mottoes directly concern these topics, this emblem has much to teach us about Pulter’s interest and intervention in these debates. I track this theme throughout my annotations on the poem, noting, for instance, that Pulter’s description of the bee as “the active Amazonian maid” (7) refers to a community of warrior women in Greek mythology (the Amazons), who were notoriously complicated gendered figures in early modern culture. “Demonstrating that women and men might be performatively interchangeable,” Kathryn Schwarz explains, “Amazons at once substantiate the signifiers of masculinity and threaten to replace the bodies to which they are attached.”<seg>1<note type="gloss">Source: <bibl>Schwarz, <title rend="italic">Tough Love: Amazon Encounters in the English Renaissance</title> (Duke University Press, 2000): 38</bibl>.</note></seg> Amazons were often at the center of crossdressing plots (Philip Sidney’s <title rend="italic">The Countess of Pembroke’s Arcadia</title>), tales of women’s military leadership (Margaret Cavendish’s Bell in <title rend="italic">Campo</title>), and stories about the relationship between desire and power (William Shakespeare’s <title rend="italic">A Midsummer Night’s Dream</title>).</p><p>Pulter’s comparison of the bee to an “Amazonian maid” draws on this popular trope, but we might also read the comparison as an opening nod to the poem’s formal structure. The poem’s first half outlines a distinctly female garden community, populated by “fair Aurora” (1), the “Amazonian” bee” (7), the poet herself (17), and even the snail that slides about “upon her unctuous breast” (29). When the bee’s plot ends at line 37, though, the poem shifts to solely male reference points. Pulter mentions Biron (39), Belisarius (41), Bajazeth (43), and Callisthenes (47) as she guides the reader toward the poem’s concluding motto. But, shifting once more in the final couplet, Pulter ends by reminding us to “think on the snail, the tulip, and the bee” (52), a return to the female cast of the poem’s first half. In the formal structure of her poem—the gender-bending shifts in metaphors—Pulter brings to mind the threat posed by the figure of the Amazon: the possibility “that women and men might be performatively interchangeable.” In both the content and form of this poem, Pulter raises questions about how gender signifies, and particularly how emblematic, gender-specific metaphors signify.</p></note>
          </rdg>
        </app>
      </head>

      <l n="1">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft"><fw type="seqNum" place="inline">53</fw>When fair Aurora drest with Raidient Light</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">When fair <seg>Aurora<note type="gloss">goddess of dawn</note></seg>, dressed with radiant light,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">When <seg>fair Aurora<note type="critical">Pulter’s opening reference to “fair Aurora” (Roman goddess of the dawn) initiates the gendered imagery of the poem’s first seven lines, which culminates with Pulter’s description of the bee as “the active Amazonian maid” (line 7). These opening lines, with the Amazon reference as a kind of anchor point, transform the morning garden into a female separatist community—a framing with important implications for how we read the rest of the poem. First, framing the bee’s actions within this context connects the labor of collecting nectar to women’s work, which then prompts us to read Pulter’s later references to poisonous herbs (lines 13–14) and “choice extractions” (line 15) as nods to domestic labor. Second, it links Emblem 53 to other writings in which Pulter explores the intimacies that develop within communities of women, most notably the female friendships throughout her prose romance, <title rend="italic">The Unfortunate Florinda</title>.</note></seg>, dressed with radiant light,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="2">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Had triumph’d o’re the Gloomey Shades of Night</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Had triumphed o’er the gloomy shades of night—</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Had triumphed o’er the gloomy shades of <seg>night<note type="critical">My editorial decision to add an em-dash here turns lines 3–6 into a clause that expands Pulter’s description of Aurora in lines 1–2 and emphasizes the unique formal structure of Pulter’s “naked emblems” (for more on this, see my headnote). Adding the em-dash marks how the concise description of Aurora waking up in the poem’s first two lines becomes a more expansive illustration of Aurora in lines 3–6, a kind of visual unfolding that nods to the pictura element of the traditional emblem structure. For more on the flexible structure of early modern emblems, see <bibl>Peter Daly, <title rend="italic">Literature in the Light of the Emblem</title> (University of Toronto Press, 1979)</bibl>.</note></seg>—</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="3">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">When Shee her Virgin beavty first diſcloſes</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">When she her <seg>virgin<note type="gloss">pure</note></seg> beauty first discloses,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">When she her <seg>virgin beauty<note type="critical">Associating Aurora with virginity, Pulter departs from classical tradition in which Aurora is often aggressively sexualized. Pulter retains some of the figure’s fraught sexual history, though, by drawing on conventional blazon imagery, describing Aurora wrapped in a “silver” robe with “roses” ornamenting her “dewy curls.” This description echoes language from earlier poems in the manuscript dedicated to Aurora: <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="22">“To Aurora [1]” (Poem 22)</ref>, <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="26">“To Aurora [2]” (Poem 26)</ref>, and <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="34">“To Aurora [3]” (Poem 34)</ref>. Poem 34 is particularly resonant here. In that earlier poem, Aurora “shakes her dewy curls” and fills the flowers—”each gold-enamelled cup”—with “honeydew” (lines 8–9). For more on Pulter’s use of blazon imagery throughout her poems, see Frances E. Dolan’s Exploration, <ref target="http://pulterproject.northwestern.edu/#hester-pulter-and-english-blazon" type="new-window-url">“Hester Pulter and the Blazon in Early Modern England.”</ref></note></seg> first <seg>discloses<note type="gloss">uncover or expose to view</note></seg>,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="4">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Her dewey Curles Stuck full of half blown Roſes</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Her dewy curls stuck full of <seg>half-blown<note type="gloss">half-blossomed</note></seg> roses,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Her dewy curls stuck full of <seg>half-blown<note type="gloss">half-bloomed, half-blossomed</note></seg> roses,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="5">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Lapt in A Robe of Silver mixt with graie</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee"><seg>Lapped<note type="gloss">wrapped up</note></seg> in a robe of silver mixed with gray,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Lapped in a robe of silver mixed with gray,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="6">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Which did prognoſticate a glorious day</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Which did <seg>prognosticate<note type="gloss">foretell</note></seg> a glorious day—</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Which did <seg>prognosticate<note type="gloss">foretell, forecast</note></seg> a glorious day–</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="7">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Out flew the active Amizonian Maid</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Out flew the <seg>active Amazonian maid<note type="gloss">Amazons were legendary female warriors who served a queen; here used figuratively to describe a bee</note></seg>;</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Out flew the <seg>active Amazonian maid<note type="critical"><p>The bee was a familiar subject of early modern emblems, frequently used as a model of ordered government (see <bibl>Andrea Alciato, <title rend="italic">Emblematum liber</title> [Padua, 1621], emblem 149</bibl>) or successful, interdependent economy (see <bibl>Geoffrey Whitney, <title rend="italic">Choice of Emblemes</title> [London, 1585], pages 200–201)</bibl>. One seventeenth-century compendium on insects, compiled from the writings of several natural historians, including Edward Wotton, Conrad Gesner, and Thomas Moffet, featured a beehive on its frontispiece and described bees as “patterns and precedents of political and economical virtues” (<bibl><title rend="italic">The Theatre of Insects, or Lesser Living Creatures</title> [London, 1658]</bibl>).</p><p>Pulter’s transformation of the bee into an Amazonian figure, however, is more unusual and even a bit contentious. The comparison enhances Pulter’s interrogation of gender in this poem (see my headnote) and connects this emblem to some of the manuscript’s more explicit political poetry (see Curation, <ref type="pp-curation-ref">The Political Bee</ref>).</p></note></seg>.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="8">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">The Hills and Dales, not onely Shee Surveyd</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">The hills and dales not only she surveyed,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">The hills and dales not only she surveyed,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="9">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">But out of every Gold <seg>Enameld<note type="physical">“E” and “e” appear written over earlier “i”s</note></seg> Cup</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">But out of every gold-enamelled cup</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">But out of every <seg>gold-enamelled cup<note type="gloss">flowers</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="10">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Her Mornings draught of Nectar Shee did Sup</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Her morning’s draught of nectar she did sup.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Her morning’s <seg>draft<note type="gloss">a quantity drawn or extracted</note></seg> of nectar she did sup.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="11">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Nay where the Toad, and Spider poyſons found</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Nay, where the toad and spider’s poison found</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Nay, where the toad and spider poisons found,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="12">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Mell Shee Extracts, for this <add place="below">^</add> <add place="above">her</add> Wisdome’s Crownd</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee"><seg>Mell<note type="gloss">honey</note></seg> she extracts; <seg>for this her wisdom’s crowned<note type="gloss">Bees were reputed to be able to turn poisons into honey.</note></seg>.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>Mell<note type="gloss">honey</note></seg> she extracts; for this <seg>her wisdom’s<note type="physical">revised in the manuscript; “for this <add place="below">^</add> <add place="above">her</add> wisdome’s crownd”</note></seg> crowned.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="13">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">On <seg>Nightſhade<note type="physical">“t” in different hand from main scribe</note></seg>, Henbane, Helliſh Acconite</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">On nightshade, henbane, hellish aconite,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">On nightshade, henbane, hellish aconite,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="14">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">On Opium, Hemlock, Shee doth Safely lite</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">On opium, <seg>hemlock<note type="gloss">This plant, like opium and the three in the previous line, are all poisonous.</note></seg> she doth safely <seg>light<note type="gloss">land</note></seg>.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">On opium, hemlock she doth <seg>safely light<note type="critical">All five plants catalogued in these lines are poisonous, but their pollen is not. Consequently, the bee can safely extract pollen but the toad and spider of line 11 (eating the plants’ leaves, flowers, or stems) find “poisons.” Pulter may have gained knowledge of these plants from direct, hands-on experience. There were also several popular herbals circulating by the time she was writing, including John Gerard’s <title rend="italic">The Herbal, or General History of Plants</title> (London, 1597) and Nicholas Culpeper’s <title rend="italic">The English Physician Enlarged</title> (London, 1653). The British Library offers a useful peek at <ref target="https://www.bl.uk/collection-items/poisons-sleep-inducing--plants-and-love-potions-in-gerards-herbal" type="new-window-url">Gerard’s <title rend="italic">Herbal</title></ref>, along with some context on Shakespeare’s use of “henbane” in <title rend="italic">Hamlet</title> and “nightshade” in <title rend="italic">Romeo and Juliet</title>.</note></seg>.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="15">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Thus being with choyce Extractions loaded well</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Thus being with choice extractions loaded well,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Thus being with <seg>choice extractions<note type="critical">John Milton also uses the verb “extract” to describe the bee’s work in Book 5 of <title rend="italic">Paradise Lost</title>. Adam calls Eve awake “to mark … how the bee / sits on the bloom extracting liquid sweet” (lines 20–25). The noun “extraction” and its verb form “extract” (line 12) had alchemical, medicinal, and culinary connotations in seventeenth-century use. “To extract” is “to obtain (constituent elements, juices, etc.) from a thing or substance by suction, pressure, distillation, or any chemical or mechanical operation” (<bibl>“extract, v.4a,” <title rend="italic">OED Online</title></bibl>). As evidence for this particular connotation of “extract,” the <title rend="italic">Oxford English Dictionary</title> cites <bibl>Hugh Plat’s <title rend="italic">The Jewel House of Art and Nature</title> (London, 1594)</bibl> and <bibl>Francis Bacon’s <title rend="italic">Sylva Sylvarum; or, A Natural History</title> (London, 1626)</bibl>, two popular early modern scientific texts with which Pulter may have been familiar. Is Pulter also demonstrating her knowledge of early modern herbals, texts that catalogued plants and their medicinal and culinary uses? If so, her uses of “extract” and “extraction” connect to the catalogue of poisonous plants in lines 13–14. For an extended exploration of “human art” in relation to plants, see <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="105">“View But This Tulip” (Emblem 40)</ref>.</note></seg> loaded well,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="16">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Shee turn’d to flie to her Sexanguler Cell</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">She turned to fly to her <seg>sexangular<note type="gloss">six-sided</note></seg> cell.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">She turned to fly to her <seg>sexangular cell<note type="gloss">six-sided; a reference to the comb shapes of a bee hive</note></seg>.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="17">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">But takeing of my Garden in her way</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">But <seg>taking of<note type="gloss">apprehending</note></seg> my garden in her way,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">But <seg>taking of<note type="gloss">to be caught or captured by; the bee is “taken with” the beauty of the narrator’s garden</note></seg> <seg>my garden<note type="criticial"><p>This is our first glimpse of the poem’s narrator, often a much more pervasive presence in Pulter’s poems. In early poems in the manuscript, like <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="31">“Made When I Was Sick, 1647” (Poem 31)</ref>, the entire poem revolves around the narrator’s experience and thoughts. The sparse, late use of the first-person pronoun here, though, is more typical of Pulter’s emblem poems, a few of which never reference the poet directly. See, for instance, <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="86">“Raccoons” (Emblem 21)</ref>.</p><p>It’s worth noting that this first reference to the poet (one of only two in the poem) is also connected to the garden and the all-female community of the poem’s first half. Perhaps even more interesting, the narrator’s garden is the site of the bee’s demise. We learn the story of the bee and the snail in the next few lines and we might even imagine that the poet is a first-hand witness, watching the snail “slid[e]” out of the tulip in the morning while the bee “fainting lie[s]” (line 35).</p></note></seg> in her way,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="18">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Though full before Shee could not chooſe but Stay</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Though full before, she could not choose but stay</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Though full before, she could not choose but stay</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="19">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">To See the <seg><add place="below">\</add> <add place="above">curious \</add><note type="physical">insertion in different hand from main scribe</note></seg> Ouricolas <seg><del>curious</del><note type="physical">double strike-through</note></seg> drest</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">To see the <seg>curious<note type="gloss">clever, elaborately made</note></seg> <seg>auriculas<note type="gloss">type of flower</note></seg> dressed</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">To see the <seg>curious<note type="physical">revised in the manuscript; “to see the <add place="below">\</add> <add place="above">curious \</add> ouricolas <del>curious</del> drest”</note></seg> <seg>auriculas<note type="gloss"><foreign rend="italic">primula auricula</foreign>; also known as mountain cowslip or bear’s ear (see Curation, <ref type="pp-curation-ref">Pulter’s Garden</ref>, for an image)</note></seg> dressed</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="20">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">More variously then Iris dewey breast</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">More variously than <seg>Iris’s<note type="gloss">goddess of the rainbow, also a flower</note></seg> dewy breast.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">More variously than <seg>Iris’s<note type="gloss">In Greek mythology, Iris is messenger of the gods and a personification of the rainbow. Iris is also another type of flower. In contemporary botany, iris is a genus of many species of flowering plants like the <foreign rend="italic">iris sibirica</foreign> (see Curation, <ref type="pp-curation-ref">Pulter’s Garden</ref>, for an image)</note></seg> dewy breast.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="21">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Then were my Tulips painted in there Pride</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Then were my tulips painted in their pride,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Then were my <seg>tulips painted<note type="critical">The tulip has special significance in Pulter’s emblem. She not only makes the center of this flower the location for her fable of the bee and snail (as we’re about to see); she also describes the tulip with language that evokes the “tulipmania” of the early seventeenth century: “painted” (here and again in line 27) and “gilded” (line 34). From the 1580’s to the mid-1630’s, tulips were a prized and elusive commodity, famous in aristocratic gardens and still life paintings, but notoriously difficult to study and classify given their infinite variety. In <bibl>John Gerard’s <title rend="italic">The Herbal, or General History of Plants</title> (London, 1597)</bibl>, Gerard describes the tulips as “a strange and foreign flower” and emphasizes that it is impossible to catalogue all of its varieties: “each new yeare bringeth forth new plants of sundry colours, not before seene” (<bibl>[London, 1597], Text Creation Partnership digital edition, <title rend="italic">Early English Books Online</title>, pages 137–140</bibl>). The craze surrounding the tulip culminated in the Dutch “tulipmania” of the 1630’s, when the price of tulip bulbs inflated drastically (the most expensive specimens went for around 5,000 guilders). We might speculate that Pulter has this recent cultural phenomenon in mind when she describes the tulips first as luxurious garden accessories (“painted in their pride”) and then as the bee’s “painted prison.” See this poem’s Curation (<ref type="pp-curation-ref">Pulter’s Garden</ref>) for examples of Gerard’s tulip woodcuts and Dutch still life paintings featuring the flower. For more on the tulip in early modern English contexts, see <bibl>Anna Pavord’s <title rend="italic">The Tulip: The Story of a Flower That Has Made Men Mad</title> (Bloomsbury, 1999)</bibl>, especially chapter 3.</note></seg> in their pride,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="22">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Which when this covetous Inſect Eſpi’de</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Which, when this covetous insect espied,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Which, when this <seg>covetous<note type="gloss">greedy</note></seg> insect espied,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="23">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">To carry home her wealth Shee’d not <w lemma="the"><abbr>y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi></abbr></w> power</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">To carry home her wealth she’d not the power</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">To carry home her wealth she’d not the power</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="24">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Till Shee had Search’d the Sweets of every &ff;lower</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Till she had searched the sweets of every flower.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Till she had searched the sweets of every flower.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">
                <fw type="catch" place="bottom">the</fw>
            </rdg>
        </app>
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">
                <pb ed="#ft" facs="#f7610_260" n="128v"/>
            </rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">
                <pb ed="#ee" facs="#f7610_260"/>
            </rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">
                <pb ed="#ae" facs="#f7610_260"/>
            </rdg>
        </app>
      <l n="25">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">The Sun, from home, all, Influence Receives</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">The sun, <seg>from whom all influence receives<note type="gloss">“whom” is spelled as “home” in the manuscript; all are influenced by the sun</note></seg>,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">The sun, from whom all influence receives,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="26">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Bid them decline, The Tulip cloſ’d her Leaves</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Bids them <seg>decline<note type="gloss">bend down, droop</note></seg>; the tulip closed her <seg>leaves<note type="gloss">petals</note></seg>,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Bid <seg>them<note type="gloss">the flowers</note></seg> decline; the tulip closed her leaves,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="27">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">And in that painted Priſon Shut the Bee</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">And in that painted prison shut the bee,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">And in that painted prison shut the bee.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="28">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">With her A Snail, who Slid about to See</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee"><seg>With<note type="gloss">and with</note></seg> her a snail, who slid about (to see</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">With her a <seg>snail<note type="critical">The third central character in Pulter’s emblem, the snail presented a unique sexual conundrum because of its shell, so early moderns hypothesized that the snail could spontaneously reproduce: “Thou thine own daughter then, and sire, / that son and mother art entire” (<bibl>Richard Lovelace, “The Snail”</bibl>). In medieval and early modern art, the snail was often linked to the Virgin Mary as a symbol of virginity. <bibl>Francesco del Cossa’s <title rend="italic">Annunciation</title></bibl>, for example, includes a snail in the painting’s foreground, positioned directly in front of Mary as she receives the news of her immaculate conception. Geneticist Steve Jones offers a useful account of the history of the snail as a symbol of “sex, age, and death” in his lecture, <bibl>“Snails in Art and the Art of Snails” (2014), available online through the Museum of London</bibl>. By the time Pulter was writing, the snail was increasingly cited in debates about the role of reproduction in the plant and animal worlds. Several decades after Pulter’s death in 1678, Dutch anatomist Jan Swammerdam proved that snails were hermaphrodites (<bibl><title rend="italic">Bybel der Natuure</title>, Leiden, 1737</bibl>). Before that point, as historian of science Domenico Bertolini Meli outlines, hermaphrodites were seen to be rare occurrences, even monsters. Swammerdam’s findings became the basis for arguments on the natural occurrence of hermaphrodites in nature (<bibl>Meli, “Of Snails and Horsetails: Anatomical Empiricism in the Early Modern Period,” <title rend="italic">Early Science and Medicine</title> 18.4/5 (2013): 435–452</bibl>).</note></seg>, who slid about to see</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="29">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Where to get out upon her Unctious brest</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Where to get out) upon her <seg>unctuous<note type="gloss">greasy</note></seg> breast;</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Where to get out upon her <seg>unctuous<note type="gloss">oily, greasy</note></seg> breast;</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="30">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">But Seeing noe hope, Shee laid her down to rest</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">But seeing no hope, she laid <seg>her<note type="gloss">herself</note></seg> down to rest,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">But seeing no hope, she laid her down to rest,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="31">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Whilst the Angrie Bee <seg><del>doth</del><note type="physical">double strike-through</note></seg> <seg><add place="below">\</add><add place="above">did \</add><note type="physical">in different hand from main scribe</note></seg> Such A &ff;luttring Keep</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Whilst the angry bee did such a flutt’ring <seg>keep<note type="gloss">make</note></seg>,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Whilst the angry bee <seg>did<note type="physical">revised in the manuscript; “bee <del>doth</del> <add place="below">\</add> <add place="above">did \</add> such a”</note></seg> such a flutt’ring keep,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="32">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Shee nor her fellow Priſner could not Sleep</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee"><seg>She<note type="gloss">Neither she</note></seg> nor her fellow pris’ner could not sleep.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">She nor her fellow pris’ner could not sleep.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="33">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">But Night being past, Delia diffuſ’d his Rais</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">But night being past, <seg>Delia<note type="gloss">here, Apollo, the sun god (named because he was from the island of Delos, usually called Delius)</note></seg> diffused his rays;</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">But night being past, <seg>Delia<note type="critical">Pulter’s use  of “Delia,” an unusual and distinctly feminized name for Apollo, the Greek sun god born on the island of Delos, marks a conscious shift from her use of “Aurora,” goddess of the dawn, at the start of the poem. As Victoria Burke notes in her Amplified Edition of <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="3">“Aurora [1]” (Poem 3)</ref>, the feminized Delia, as opposed to Delius, could be a transcription error, but Pulter does use Delia to refer to Apollo in several other poems, including <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="1">“The Eclipse” (Poem 1)</ref> and <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="12">“The Garden, or the Contention of Flowers” (Poem 12)</ref>. Given this emblem’s interrogation of gender, we might read Pulter’s slippage here as an invitation. As the female bee (“the active Amazonian maid”) dies and the poem shifts to a cluster of male figures in its closing lines, is Pulter’s switch from Aurora to Delia (and, perhaps, from Delius to Delia) meant to both mark and trouble this transition?</note></seg> <seg>diffused<note type="gloss">spread out</note></seg> his rays;</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="34">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">The Tulip then her gilded Leaves diſplais</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">The tulip then her gilded leaves displays.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">The tulip then her <seg>gilded<note type="gloss">adorned or embellished; a term most often associated with artificial objects</note></seg> leaves displays.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="35">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Out Slid the Snail, the Bee did fainting lie</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Out slid the snail; the bee did fainting lie</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Out slid the snail; the bee did fainting lie,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="36">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">And thus with Beating of her Self did die</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">And thus with beating of herself did die.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">And thus with beating of herself did die.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="37">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Then let impatient Spirits here but See</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Then let impatient spirits here but see</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Then let impatient spirits here but see</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="38">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">What ’tis to Struggle with their destinie</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">What ’tis to struggle with their destiny.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>What ’tis to struggle with their destiny<note type="critical">“Then let impatient spirits here but see / What ’tis to struggle with their destiny.” The first of the poem’s three possible mottoes. Pulter uses the fable of the snail, tulip, and bee to offer a lesson in struggling against destiny. The “impatient” bee struggles against her “painted prison” (line 27), while the patient snail “see[s] no hope” and “lay[s] … down to rest” (line 30). In the poem’s final motto, Pulter reminds us of the snail, tulip, and bee fable (“if no hope of liberty you see, / think on the snail, the tulip, and the bee” [lines 51–52]), but the lessons of the two mottoes are slightly different—enough to invite some critical thinking on the part of Pulter’s reader. This motto focuses on destiny, while the poem’s final motto foregrounds liberty. Who are the “impatient spirits” Pulter addresses with this lesson? Who is the “you” of the final motto’s direct address?</note></seg>.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="39">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Soe Stout Byrone in Priſon was inrag’d</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">So <seg>stout<note type="gloss">proud, arrogant</note></seg> <seg>Biron<note type="gloss">Charles de Gontant, duc de Biron; a celebrated sixteenth-century French soldier famed for his overweening pride and eventually executed for treason; in George Chapman’s play about him, <title rend="italic">The Conspiracy and Tragedy of Charles, Duke of Byron</title>, Biron’s sword is confiscated by the king.</note></seg> in prison was enraged,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">So <seg>stout<note type="gloss">proud, haughty</note></seg> <seg>Biron<note type="critical"><p>This comparison starts Pulter’s catalogue of male military leaders, rulers, and thinkers—four in total by the poem’s end. As I noted in my headnote, this cast of characters marks a significant gender shift from the female-centric opening of the poem. But this phrase is also formally noteworthy. Rather than using just one or two comparisons to illustrate her point, Pulter here offers an extensive catalogue of examples: “so stout Biron” (line 39), “when Belisarius” (line 41), “so miscre’nt Bajazeth” (line 43), and “when wise Callisthenes” (line 47). The anaphoric “so’s” and “when’s” of these final lines, very typical of Pulter’s emblems, signal her strategic accumulation of these examples. Again, how might Pulter be using her poems to explore how poetic language signifies? See my headnote for more on this question.</p><p>Charles de Gontaut, duc de Biron, was a sixteenth-century French military leader eventually involved in conspiracies against the French crown. He was jailed and beheaded for treason in 1602. Alice Eardley cites George Chapman’s play, <title rend="italic">The Conspiracy and Tragedy of Charles, Duke of Byron, Marshall of France</title> (1608) as one possible source for Pulter’s anecdote here. Biron was “notorious for his arrogance,” Eardley notes, and in Chapman’s play his sword is removed from him, “treatment he vigorously resists.” See <bibl><title rend="italic">Poems, Emblems, and The Unfortunate Florinda</title>, Ed. Alice Eardley, (Toronto: Iter, 2014), 263 n.513</bibl>.</p></note></seg> in prison was enraged,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="40">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Knowing his King was to his Sword ingag’d</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Knowing his king was to his sword engaged.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Knowing his king was to his sword engaged.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="41">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">When Bellizarus by A dog was led</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">When <seg>Belisarius<note type="gloss">successful general of sixth-century Roman emperor Justinian, later accused of conspiracy; reputedly, his eyes were put out and he ended his life as a beggar.</note></seg> by a dog was led,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">When <seg>Belisarius<note type="gloss">Belisarius was a famous military leader of the Byzantine Empire. Pulter here references the apocryphal story that Justinian ordered Belisarius’s eyes put out and that Belisarius became a beggar at the gates of Rome. Looking forward a bit beyond Pulter’s lifetime, Belisarius’s story was especially popular by the end of the eighteenth century. See, for instance, <bibl>Jean-François Marmontel’s <title rend="italic">Bélisaire: A Novel</title> (1767)</bibl>, <bibl>Margaretta Faugères’s closet drama, <title rend="italic">Belisarius: A Tragedy</title> (1795)</bibl>, and Jacques-Louis David’s painting, “Belisarius Begging for Alms” (1780).</note></seg> by a dog was led,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="42">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Being blind hee patiently did beg his Bread</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Being blind, he patiently did beg his bread.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Being blind, he patiently did beg his bread.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="43">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Soe miſcre’nt Bajazet did Shew his Rage</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">So <seg>miscre’nt<note type="gloss">villainous</note></seg> <seg>Bajazeth<note type="gloss">fourteenth-century Turkish Emperor captured in war by Tamburlaine (the “proud Tartar”); in Christopher Marlowe’s play, <title rend="italic">Tamburlaine</title>, Bajazeth kills himself on the bars of his prison.</note></seg> did show his rage</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">So <seg>miscre’nt<note type="gloss">an abbreviation of “miscreant”; heretical or pagan, but also villainous</note></seg> <seg>Bajazeth<note type="critical">In Alice Eardley’s edition of Pulter’s poems, she cites Christopher Marlowe’s <title rend="italic">Tamburlaine the Great</title> (published 1590) as a possible source for Pulter’s reference to the Turkish emperor Bajazeth. In Marlowe’s play, Tamburlaine defeats Bajazeth and keeps him in a cage, taking him out only to serve as Tamburlaine’s footstool. After a lengthy imprisonment, Bajazeth kills himself by smashing his head against the bars of his cage. See <bibl>Eardley (ed.), <title rend="italic">Poems</title>, 263 n.516</bibl>.</note></seg> did show his rage</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="44">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">When that proud Tarter put him in A Cage</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">When that proud Tartar put him in a cage;</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">When that proud Tartar put him in a cage;</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="45">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Scorning to bee A footstool to his Pride</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Scorning to be a footstool to his pride,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Scorning to be a footstool to his pride,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="46">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Hee daſh’d his Curſed Brains about &amp; died</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">He dashed his curséd brains about and died.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">He dashed his curséd brains about and died.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="47">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">When wiſe Calistines uſ’d with greater Scorn</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">When wise <seg>Callisthenes<note type="gloss">historian for Alexander the Great, reported by some to have been dismembered and displayed in a cage by Alexander in retribution for his criticisms; see Justin, <title rend="italic">Epitome of The Philippic History of Pompeius Trogus</title></note></seg>, used with greater scorn,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">When wise <seg>Callisthenes<note type="gloss">Callisthenes was a Greek historian, eventually the official historian of Alexander the Great until he was accused of plotting against Alexander. There are several different accounts of his death. Pulter seems to be referencing the version from Ptolemy in which Callisthenes is tortured and hanged in an iron cage. </note></seg>, used with greater scorn,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="48">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Tyrannically mangled Soe was Born</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Tyrannically mangled, <seg>so<note type="gloss">so it</note></seg> was <seg>borne<note type="gloss">endured</note></seg>,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Tyrannically mangled, so was borne,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">
                <fw type="catch" place="bottom">hee</fw>
            </rdg>
        </app>
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">
                <pb ed="#ft" facs="#f7610_261" n="129r"/>
            </rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">
                <pb ed="#ee" facs="#f7610_261"/>
            </rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">
                <pb ed="#ae" facs="#f7610_261"/>
            </rdg>
        </app>
      <l n="49">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Hee being unmov’d Shew’d his Philoſophy</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">He, being unmoved, showed his philosophy:</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">He, being unmoved, showed his philosophy:</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="50">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">T’is Valianter by far to live then die</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">’Tis valianter by far to live than die.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>’Tis valianter by far to live than die<note type="critical">The second of the poem’s three mottoes. This message seems specific to Pulter’s lines on Callisthenes, but the connection is puzzling given Callisthenes’s death in prison, without liberty. Is Pulter drawing our attention to the possible incongruities between her anecdotes and their concluding mottos? Or, perhaps, this motto becomes a thread for the poem’s broader message of stoic endurance: be patient and choose life.</note></seg>.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="51">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Then if noe hope <seg>of<note type="physical">imperfectly erased ascender follows</note></seg> Liberty you See</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Then if no hope of liberty you see</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Then if no hope of liberty you see,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="52">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Think on the Snail, the Tulip and the <seg>Bee<note type="physical">remainder of page blank, as is reverse</note></seg></rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Think on the snail, the tulip, and the bee.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>Think on the snail, the tulip, and the bee<note type="critical">“Then if no hope of liberty you see, / Think on the snail, the tulip, and the bee.” The final of the poem’s three mottoes. Pointing us back to the emblem’s central fable, Pulter’s final lines explicitly mark the snail, tulip, and bee story as a political allegory about liberty, resistance, and stoic endurance. But what of the poem’s complex gender politics? Where do they fit within such an allegory, particularly one written by a Royalist female poet at the height of the English Civil Wars? To explore further the intersections of gender and English Civil War politics, see <bibl>Hero Chalmers, <title rend="italic">Royalist Women Writers, 1650–1689</title> (Oxford University Press, 2004)</bibl>; and <bibl>Sarah C. E. Ross, <title rend="italic">Women, Poetry, and Politics in Seventeenth-Century Britain</title> (Oxford University Press, 2015)</bibl>, especially Chapter 4.</note></seg>.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
