<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../src/vmachine.xsl"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
  schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI [

  <!ENTITY ff "<!-- ff ligature, representing capital modern day capital F, here represented as 'ff' -->ff">

  ]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mads.pp.109">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
          <title>The Brahman (Emblem 44)</title>
        <title type="sub">Poem #109</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Created by</resp>
          <persName>Leah Knight</persName>
          <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoded by</resp>
          <persName>Katherine Poland</persName>
          <persName>Matthew Taylor</persName>
          <persName>Betsy Chou</persName>
          <persName>Emily Andrey</persName>
          <persName>Ashley Cole</persName>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>IT-project consultation by</resp>
          <persName>Josh Honn</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
          <orgName>Brock University</orgName>
          <orgName>University of Leeds</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <principal>
          <persName/>
        </principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="1"/>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription, transformations, and notes</resp>
          <persName>Leah Knight</persName>
          <orgName>Brock University</orgName>
          <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
        </respStmt>
      </editionStmt>
      <extent/>
      <publicationStmt>
        <ab/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listBibl>
          <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
              <repository>See witness list.</repository>
            </msIdentifier>
          </msDesc>
        </listBibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p/>
      </projectDesc>
      <p>Transcriptions are encoded in TEI(P5)-conformant XML.</p>
      <samplingDecl>
        <p/>
      </samplingDecl>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction>
          <p>Apparent errors are preserved and editorial corrections provided using SIC and CORR tags, but only where the editor conjectures that the original scribe or compositor would have recognized the instance as an error. For example, what according to modern usage is incorrect subject/verb agreement might have been deemed acceptable to a seventeenth-century scribe or compositor. All such instances are treated instead using the ORIG and REG tags. (See below.)</p>
          <p>Corrections and annotations made within the scope of the original document either by its original authors, owners, and/or transcribers are noted using ADD tags. These annotations and may be further explained within NOTE tags, as added by the editors of this digital edition, for display within the apparatus.</p>
        </correction>
        <normalization>
          <p>Original spellings, abbreviations, and orthography are preserved. Where in the manuscripts a character’s status as majuscule or minuscule is ambiguous, the editor has silently chosen one or the other based on context and judgment (i.e., does not register such ambiguity in either the markup or the notes).</p>
        </normalization>
        <quotation>
          <p>Original quotation marks, if any, are preserved.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation>
          <p>Original hyphenation is preserved.</p>
        </hyphenation>
      </editorialDecl>
      <charDecl>
        <!-- Ligature combinations for which there are currently no corresponding Unicode codepoints. -->
        <glyph xml:id="ffllig">
          <glyphName>Handwritten 'ff' ligature, used in handwriting to represent modern F</glyphName>
        </glyph>
      </charDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="DDC22">
          <bibl>
            <title>Dewey Decimal Classification</title>
            <edition/>
            <publisher/>
            <pubPlace/>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-GB">British English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <!-- dewey decimal system class code 821: English Poetry -->
        <classCode scheme="DDC22">821</classCode>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
    <!-- List of all images associated with this document -->
    <graphic url="./document_images/7610_246.jpg" xml:id="f7610_246"/>
    <graphic url="./document_images/7610_247.jpg" xml:id="f7610_247"/>
  </facsimile>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="ft">Transcription of manuscript: By <persName xml:id="lknight">Leah Knight</persName> and <persName xml:id="wwall">Wendy Wall</persName>.</witness>
          <witness xml:id="ee">Elemental edition: By <persName>Leah Knight</persName> and <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>.</witness>
          <witness xml:id="ae">Amplified edition: By <persName>Sophie Lawall</persName>.</witness>
        </listWit>
      </div>
    </front>

    <body>
      <app>
        <rdg wit="#ft">
          <pb ed="#ft" facs="#f7610_246" n="121v"/>
        </rdg>
        <rdg wit="#ee">
          <pb ed="#ee" facs="#f7610_246"/>
        </rdg>
        <rdg wit="#ae">
          <pb ed="#ae" facs="#f7610_246"/>
        </rdg>
      </app>

      <head>
        <app type="title">
          <rdg wit="#ft"><fw facs="#f7610_069" type="pageNum" place="margin-topright">PG#</fw>[Emblem 44]</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">The Brahman<lb/>(Emblem 44)</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Emblem 44:<lb/>The Brahman</rdg>
        </app>
        <app type="editorialnote">
          <rdg wit="#ft">
            <note type="editorialnote">In these transcriptions we preserve as many details of the original material, textual, and graphic properties of Hester Pulter’s manuscript verse as we have found practical. Whenever possible, for instance, original spelling, punctuation, capitalization, lineation, insertions, deletions, alterations, spacing between words and lines, and indentation are all maintained; abbreviations and brevigraphs are not expanded; and superscript and subscript representations are retained. <ref target="//pulterproject.northwestern.edu/about-project-conventions.html#top" type="new-window-url">See full conventions for the transcriptions here.</ref></note>
          </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">
            <note type="editorialnote">The aim of the elemental edition is to make the poems accessible to the largest variety of readers, which involves modernizing spelling and punctuation as well as adding basic glosses. Spelling and punctuation reflect current standard American usage; punctuation highlights syntax which might otherwise be obscure. Outmoded but still familiar word forms (“thou,” “‘tis,” “hold’st”) are not modernized, and we do not modernize grammar when the sense remains legible. After a brief headnote aimed at offering a “way in” to the poem’s unique qualities and connections with other verse by Pulter or her contemporaries, the edition features a minimum of notes and interpretative framing to allow more immediate engagement with the poem. Glosses clarify synonyms or showcase various possible meanings in Pulter’s time. Other notes identify named people and places or clarify obscure material. We rely (without citation) primarily on the Oxford English Dictionary (OED), the Oxford Reference database, and the King James Version (KJV) of the Bible. When we rely on Alice Eardley’s edition of Pulter’s work, we cite her text generally (“Eardley”); other sources are cited in full. The result is an edition we consider a springboard for further work on Pulter’s poetry. <ref target="//pulterproject.northwestern.edu/about-project-conventions.html#elemental-edition" type="new-window-url">See full conventions for this edition here.</ref></note></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">
            <note type="editorialnote"><p>With three exceptions, this edition retains the manuscript’s seventeenth-century spelling, capitalization, and punctuation throughout. First, since, in secretary hand, initial “ff” represents “F,” all initial “ff”s have been transcribed as “F”. Second, due to the difficulty of distinguishing capital short “s” from initial lowercase short “s,” initial short “s” has been transcribed as capital and initial long “s” has been transcribed as lowercase throughout. Finally, for clarity, I have silently added possessive apostrophes in lines 10, 20, and 38. This edition ignores the crossings-out, flourishes, and engrossed letters, and silently accepts minor corrections in the manuscript.</p>
            <p>Unless stated otherwise, all definitions come from the <title rend="italic">Oxford English Dictionary</title> and all other modern reference works are in Oxford Reference Online. All references to Plutarch’s <title rend="italic"><ref target="//name.umdl.umich.edu/A09802.0001.001" type="new-window-url">Lives</ref></title> are to Thomas North’s 1579 translation, titled <title rend="italic">The Lives of the Noble Grecians and Romans</title>. All references to Pliny’s <title rend="italic"><ref target="//name.umdl.umich.edu/A09763.0001.001" type="new-window-url">Natural History</ref></title> are to Philemon Holland’s 1634 translation, titled <title rend="italic">The Historie Of The World: Commonly Called, The Naturall Historie Of C. Plinius Secundus</title>. All references to the Bible are to the 1611 <ref target="//www.biblegateway.com/versions/King-James-Version-KJV-Bible/" type="new-window-url">King James Version</ref>.</p>
            <p>In writing footnotes, I have aimed to define unusual words, especially ones not defined in the Elemental Edition of <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="109">The Brahman (Emblem 44)</ref>; to provide context for Pulter’s classical and biblical allusions; and to point out analogues for Pulter’s ideas in other early modern works.</p>
            <p>Finally, I would like to thank Prof. Victoria Burke at the University of Ottawa for introducing me to this project and for providing feedback on early drafts of this edition.</p></note>
          </rdg>
        </app>
        <app type="headnote">
          <rdg wit="#ee">
              <note type="headnote">“Who would not such a blessed change explore?” asks the speaker in this poem, contemplating a transformative suicide that will purify the soul. After all, the first two examples she conjures up suggest a glorious, if painful, rebirth: the philosopher Calanus, in frying himself on his own funeral pyre, renders his soul “pristine,” and the mythological Phoenix’s death preserves an essence that reassumes extravagantly splendid feathered form. Although she rejects the actions of two non-Christian examples, Pulter proclaims a willingness to shed her mortality like a well-worn set of clothes or a theatrical costume, with faith that God will gather up her deteriorated bits of flesh at the Last Judgment and reunite her body with her soul in eternal heaven. The poem uses the prospect of death to reflect on Pulter’s role as a writer, first in her reference to herself as Hadassah, the biblical Queen Esther whom Pulter chose as her authorial pseudonym (one of the manuscript’s titles is <title rend="italic">Poems Breathed Forth by the Noble Hadassas</title>). Second, it is telling that her future vision of death and salvation involves a re-enactment of the Word’s (God’s) creation of the world that ends in artistic production. When God will “reinspire” or breathe into her scattered mortal remains, they will convert into ascending atoms and burst forth in poetic hymns of praise.</note>
          </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">
            <note type="headnote"><p>“The Brahman” deals with the theme of self-sacrificial suicide in hopes of salvation through two lenses: first, she writes of two pagan examples of the virtuous who immolated themselves to escape mortal pains, Calanus and the phoenix; second, she contrasts her pagan examples with the death of Aaron, who, in her reading, accepts his death when it is God’s will, rather than seeking it out. Although Pulter seems to admire her pagan models, in this poem, her Christian faith means that she “cannot” and “dare[s] not” (ln. 20; 21) take their route away from the pain of mortal life; instead of suicide, she ultimately places her trust in the knowledge that, eventually, she will die by God’s will and rejoin Christ in heaven.</p>
            <p>Pulter begins the poem by describing the death of Calanus, the titular Brahman, from Plutarch’s “Life of Alexander the Great.” Although Pulter, on the grounds of Christian piety, rejects the actions of Calanus and the phoenix (her second example, introduced at line 9) in deliberately immolating themselves, she clearly sympathizes with the desire to be rid of the pains and impurities of the mortal body. After these two classical examples, Pulter turns to the death of the biblical Aaron, using it to express a desire to be permitted by God to die, so that she may be a spirit in Heaven until the resurrection at the end of days. In the Old Testament, after God tells Aaron and Moses that they will not see the Promised Land because they expressed doubt that God could bring forth the waters of Meribah, God tells Moses that Aaron will die:</p>
            <cit><quote>“And the Lord spake unto Moses and Aaron in mount Hor, by the coast of the land of Edom, saying, Aaron shall be gathered unto his people: for he shall not enter into the land which I have given to the people of Israel, because ye rebelled against my word at the water of Meribah. Take Aaron and Eleazar his son, and bring them up unto mount Hor: And strip Aaron of his garments, and put them upon Eleazar his son: and Aaron shall be gathered unto his people, and shall die there. And Moses did as the Lord commanded: and they went up into mount Hor in the sight of all the congregation. And Moses stripped Aaron of his garments, and put them upon Eleazar his son; and Aaron died there in the top of the mount: and Moses and Eleazar came down from the mount.”</quote><bibl>(KJV Numbers 20.23–28)</bibl></cit>
            <p>This passage presents Aaron as knowing his death is coming and, because it is a calling from God, he therefore willingly allows himself to die. By using Aaron as her Christian counter-example, Pulter returns to the image of deliberately removing one’s mortal life—the literal body, in the case of Calanus and the phoenix, and his priestly robes in the case of Aaron—in order to reveal the inner spirit in death. Although the biblical passage emphasizes Aaron’s passivity, as Moses is the one who removes Aaron’s clothes and gives them to Eleazar, Pulter gives Aaron some agency in his death, writing that “old Aaron did put of his Cloaths” (ln. 11), implying his active participation in accepting God’s will, and therefore in his death. Despite this agency, however, Aaron’s death is not a suicide; he accepts his death, rather than causing it.</p>
            <p>The tension shown in this poem, between Pulter’s admiration of pagan models and her Christian faith, is present elsewhere in Pulter’s poetry. In particular, another of Pulter’s classical emblems, <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="96">Old Aeschylus (Emblem 31)</ref>, has a similar structure of enumerating several classical examples of her theme and then embracing the proper Christian response, using an example from the Old Testament. In this emblem, Pulter explores the idea of trying to know or avoid one’s fate, offering King Hezekiah’s successful prayer for reprieve from a fatal plague as an alternative to pagan attempts to either avoid or ignore one’s fate, such as those of Aeschylus and Caesar (<ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="96" target="ae">Old Aeschylus (Emblem 31)</ref>, ln. 13–16). She concludes by rejecting both foreknowledge of death and even the desire to avoid death, writing:</p>
              <cit>
                <quote>
                  <lg>
                    <l>Then let me never Know my Destiny,</l>
                    <l>But every day So live that when I die,</l>
                    <l>I may with comfort lay these Ruins down</l>
                    <l>In dust; ’tis softer far than finest Down,</l>
                    <l>Nor is that Pillow Stuffed with Cares or fears,</l>
                    <l>Nor Shall I wake as now to Sighs and tears.</l>
                  </lg>
                </quote>
                <bibl>(ln. 25–30)</bibl>
              </cit>
            <p>Here, like in “The Brahman,” Pulter finds solace in the eventual peace of death and the promise of resurrection. By embracing death as the release from life’s hardships and the first step of heaven’s reward for good Christians in both of these poems, Pulter distances her emblems’ morals from her emblems’ pagan subjects and demonstrates her own deeply Christian piety.</p>
            <p>However, Pulter does not always reject pagan examples in her poetry; nor, indeed, does she always reject suicide, as demonstrated in <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="43">Of a Young Lady at Oxford, 1646 (Poem 43)</ref>. In this poem, Pulter recounts the story of a young woman who commits suicide after the death of her royalist lover in battle. She then compares this young woman to pagan examples of suicide driven by honour (Lucrece) and love (Thisbe). Instead of going on to reject their examples, however, Pulter concludes by begging her soul to emulate their heroic suicides and leave her body so that she may rejoin Christ in Heaven:</p>
              <cit>
                <quote>
                  <lg>
                    <l>Thus do these stories and these fables teach</l>
                    <l>And show to us how far our love may reach;</l>
                    <l>But He (my soul) His precious blood did lose</l>
                    <l>For us (ay me), for us: His curséd foes.</l>
                    <l>Considering this, my soul, how canst thou stay?</l>
                  </lg>
                </quote>
                <bibl>(ln. 67–71)</bibl>
              </cit>
            <p>Furthermore, in this poem, Pulter even applauds the actions of the titular “young lady” who commits suicide after the death of her royalist lover, and writes that “As this declares a magnanimous spirit, / So she the glory of it doth inherit” (ln. 30–31). Nowhere in this poem does Pulter state or imply that suicide is impious or will lead to damnation. As Lara Dodds notes in her Curation for “Of a Young Lady,” this poem engages with the Stoic idea of heroic suicide (Dodds <ref type="pp-curation-ref" target="/poems/ee/of-a-young-lady-at-oxford/#heroic-suicide">Heroic Suicide and Women’s Writing</ref>), which experienced a revival during the early modern period (Hunter 242). However, in “The Brahman,” Pulter explicitly rejects “Stoicall tricks” (ln. 22) like Calanus’s heroic suicide. It is difficult to reconcile the opposing portrayals of suicide in “Of a Young Lady” and “The Brahman,” but it is worth noting that what Pulter wishes for herself in both poems is, in fact, quite similar: she seeks a natural death. Even in “Of a Young Lady,” Pulter begs her soul to follow Christ’s to heaven, like the souls of newborn infants that “Do often fly to their eternal rest” (ln. 76).</p>
            <p>Although there are similarities in how Pulter expresses her own desire for death in these two poems, the opposition in their portrayal of heroic suicide, and Pulter’s use of classical figures in exploring both sides of it, reflect a broader conversation and anxiety about suicide during the early modern period. John Donne’s Christian defense of suicide, <title rend="italic">Biathanatos</title>, written in 1608 but published in 1647, draws more on Catholic and Protestant theology than classical philosophy (including Stoic philosophy) in its justification of suicide (Rudick and Battin xxi-xxiv), but, as Elizabeth Hunter argues, the revival of Stoicism in this period also played a role in the conversation surrounding suicide. According to Hunter, in the late sixteenth and early seventeenth centuries, although many of the Neo-stoics themselves rejected the concept, the revival of the Stoic idea of heroic or honourable suicide, including in the context of early Christian martyrs, provoked counterarguments from more orthodox Protestant English clergy (Hunter 242–45). In “The Brahman,” therefore, Pulter is engaging with this conversation through the contradiction between heroic suicide and conventional Christian doctrine. In fact, Pulter’s use of Calanus in a poem arguing against suicide has an analogue in Thomas Philipot’s treatise <title rend="italic"><ref target="//name.umdl.umich.edu/A54679.0001.001" type="new-window-url">Self-Homicide-Murther, or, Some Antidotes and Arguments Gleaned out of the Treasuries of Our Modern Casuists and Divines against That Horrid and Reigning Sin of Self-Murther by T.P., Esq</ref></title> (1674), in which he uses Calanus as an example of Greek authors condemning suicide: “[a]nd <title rend="italic">Strabo</title> informs us, that the <title rend="italic">Indian</title> Priests and Wise men, blam’d the Fact of <title rend="italic">Calanus</title>, and that they resented with Regret and Hatred the hasty Deaths of Proud and Impatient Persons” (24). Philipot, like Pulter in “The Brahman,” rejects suicide as a sin to be avoided through faith in God (Philipot 22–23), and, by speaking against pagan examples of supposedly righteous suicide, both authors participate in their culture’s anxiety over how to incorporate un-Christian aspects of ancient writings.</p>
            <p>In reading “The Brahman,” therefore, we see Pulter exploring the disjunction between her use of classical models and her own religious values as well as between Christianity’s rejection of suicide and its portrayal of the ecstasy of righteous souls after death. Although Pulter clearly desires her pagan examples’ purifying deaths, her Christian faith keeps her from deliberate self-destruction, leaving her to instead place her hope for heaven’s bliss following a natural death.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Works Cited</hi></p>
            <p><bibl><title rend="italic">Holy Bible</title>, <ref target="https://www.biblegateway.com/versions/King-James-Version-KJV-Bible/" type="new-window-url">King James Version</ref>. <title rend="italic">Bible Gateway</title>, Accessed 10 Apr. 2023.</bibl></p>
            <p><bibl>Hunter, Elizabeth K. “‘Between the Bridge and the Brook’: Suicide and Salvation in England, c.1550–1650.” <title rend="italic">Reformation &amp; Renaissance Review</title>, vol. 15, no. 3, Nov. 2013, pp. 237–57. <title rend="italic">Taylor and Francis+NEJM.</title></bibl></p>
            <p><bibl>Philipot, Thomas. <title rend="italic"><ref target="//name.umdl.umich.edu/A54679.0001.001" type="new-window-url">Self-Homicide-Murther, or, Some Antidotes and Arguments Gleaned out of the Treasuries of Our Modern Casuists and Divines against That Horrid and Reigning Sin of Self-Murther by T.P., Esq</ref></title>. London, 1674, <title rend="italic">Early English Books Online</title>.</bibl></p>
            <p><bibl>Rudick, Michael, and M. Pabst Battin. “Introduction.” <title rend="italic">Biathanatos</title>, by John Donne, edited by Michael Rudick and M. Pabst Battin, Garland, 1982.</bibl></p>
            </note>
          </rdg>
        </app>
      </head>

      <l n="1">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft"><fw type="seqNum" place="inline">44</fw><seg>The<note type="physical">poem begins two-thirds down the page; previous poem concludes at top of the page followed by blank space</note></seg> Brackman Th’angrie Deities to appeas</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">The <seg>Brahman<note type="gloss">Hindu priest, here referring to the legendary philosopher and gymnosophist Calanus (or Kalanus) who self-immolated in the presence of Alexander the Great. See <bibl>Plutarch, <title rend="italic">The Lives of the Noble Grecians and Romans</title>, trans. Thomas North (London, 1579), p. 759.</bibl></note></seg>, th’angry deities to appease,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">The <seg>Brackman<note type="gloss">Alternate spelling of Brahmin. Modern definition: a member of the highest caste in the traditional Indian caste system. Pulter’s usage: a generic term for an Indian priest and a reference to Plutarch’s “Life of Alexander the Great,” in which the Indian philosopher Calanus sacrifices himself upon a pyre to free himself of the agony of illness. See <bibl>Plutarch. <ref target="//name.umdl.umich.edu/A09802.0001.001" type="new-window-url"><title rend="italic">The Lives of the Noble Grecians and Romanes Compared Together by That Graue Learned Philosopher and Historiographer, Plutarke of Chæronea</title></ref>, translated by Thomas North and James Amyot, London, 1579, p. 759, <title rend="italic">Early English Books Online</title>.</bibl></note></seg> Th’angrie Deities to appeas</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="2">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Hee being afflicted with a Sad diſeaſe</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">He being afflicted with a sad disease,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Hee being afflicted with a Sad disease</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="3">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Unwilling to bee grated thus aſunder</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Unwilling to be <seg>grated<note type="gloss">scraped, pulverized; figuratively, irritated (here, by an intestinal disorder)</note></seg> thus asunder,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Unwilling to bee grated thus asunder</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="4">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Hee did an Act made Alexander wonder</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">He did an act made Alexander wonder:</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Hee did an Act made <seg>Alexander<note type="gloss">Alexander the Great, king of Macedonia 336–323 BC. The Alexandrian empire reached all the way to India and, according to Plutarch, Calanus was sent with Alexander when he left India. Along with featuring in Plutarch’s <title rend="italic">Lives</title>, Alexander was a popular character in medieval romances, and the most famous English Alexander romance, <title rend="italic">King Alisaunder</title>, was printed in 1525 and 1711. See Plutarch’s <ref target="//name.umdl.umich.edu/A09802.0001.001" type="new-window-url"><title rend="italic">Lives</title></ref>; Holt, Frank L., and Andrew Stewart. “Alexander the Great.” <title rend="italic">The Oxford Encyclopedia of Ancient Greece and Rome</title>, edited by Michael Gagarin, Oxford University Press, 2010; Birch, Dinah, editor. “Alexander the Great” and “King Alisaunder." <title rend="italic">The Oxford Companion to English Literature</title>, 7th ed, Oxford University Press, 1 Jan. 2009.</note></seg> wonder</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="5">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">&ff;or on his &ff;unerall, fllagrant, <seg>Pile<note type="physical">“le” written over other letters</note></seg> hee lies</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">For on his funeral <seg>flagrant<note type="gloss">burning</note></seg> <seg>pile<note type="gloss">that is, the heap of fuel, or pyre, for his cremation</note></seg> he lies,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">For on his Funerall, Flagrant, Pile hee lies</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="6">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Becoming thus both Priest and Sacrifice</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Becoming thus both priest and sacrifice.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Becoming thus both Priest and Sacrifice.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="7">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">What was Corporeall the &ff;ire Conſumes</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">What was corporeal, the fire consumes;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">What was Corporeall the Fire Consumes</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="8">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">His Soul its <seg>Priſtine<note type="physical">second “i” in different ink over earlier “e”; final “e” appears added later, in different ink</note></seg> Glory Reaſſumes</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">His soul its pristine glory reassumes.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">His Soul its Pristine Glory Reassumes</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="9">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Soe doth the Phœnix &ff;an her guilded Wings</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">So doth the <seg>Phœnix<note type="gloss">the Egyptian bird who was reborn from her ashes after burning in a sacrificial fire</note></seg> fan her gilded wings</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Soe doth the <seg>Phœnix<note type="gloss">A mythological bird which was consumed by fire and then reborn from its own ashes. By Pulter’s period, it was widely considered a symbol of the resurrection in the Christian world, and Pulter’s contemporaries, such as John Dryden, use it as a metaphor for rebirth after disaster. See <bibl>Pliny the Elder. <ref target="//name.umdl.umich.edu/A09763.0001.001" type="new-window-url"><title rend="italic">The Historie of the World: Commonly Called, The Naturall Historie of C. Plinius Secundus</title></ref>. Translated by Philemon Holland, London, 1634, p. 271, <title rend="italic">Early English Books Online</title></bibl>; <bibl>Louth, Andrew, editor. “Phoenix.” <title rend="italic">The Oxford Dictionary of the Christian Church</title>, 4th ed., Oxford University Press, 2022</bibl>;  Birch, Dinah, editor. “Phoenix.” <title rend="italic">The Oxford Companion to English Literature</title>, 7th ed, Oxford University Press, 1 Jan. 2009.</note></seg> Fan her guilded Wings</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="10">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Till Phœbus Raiſe her Gaudy &ff;eathers Sings</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Till <seg>Phœbus’s<note type="gloss">the sun god’s</note></seg> rays her gaudy feathers <seg>sings<note type="gloss">a northern British form of “singes,” pronounced to rhyme with “wings”</note></seg>;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Till <seg>Phœbus’<note type="gloss">Another name of Apollo, especially in his roles as sun god and the leader of the muses; here this is used to refer to the sun itself. See <bibl>Dent, Susie, editor. “Phoebus.” Brewer’s Dictionary of Phrase &amp; Fable, 19th ed., Chambers Harrap Publishers, 2012.</bibl></note></seg> <seg>Raise<note type="critical">Possibly a pun on “rays.” See following note for possible glosses of this line.</note></seg> her Gaudy Feathers <seg>Sings<note type="critical">As noted in the Elemental Edition of <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="109">The Brahman (Emblem 44)</ref>, an alternate spelling of “singes,” or burns. Pulter’s use of this alternate spelling may also be a play on words, as the phoenix was thought to have a beautiful song (as in <bibl>Lactantius. “Phoenix.” Minor Latin Poets, translated by A. M. Duff and J. Wight Duff, Harvard University Press, 2014, pp. 643–67. Loeb Classical Library, ln. 45–48</bibl>; see note 7 below). This line glosses as either “Till Phoebus’ <title rend="italic">rising</title> her gaudy feathers <title rend="italic">singes</title>” or “Till Phoebus’ <title rend="italic">rays</title> her gaudy feathers <title rend="italic">singe</title>” (italics mine).</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
        <app>
        <rdg wit="#ft">
          <fw type="catch" place="bottom">then</fw>
        </rdg>
      </app>
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">
                <pb ed="#ft" facs="#f7610_247" n="122r"/>
            </rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">
                <pb ed="#ee" facs="#f7610_247"/>
            </rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">
                <pb ed="#ae" facs="#f7610_247"/>
            </rdg>
        </app>

      <l n="11">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Then in that Light in which Shee lives Shee &ff;ryes</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Then, in that light in which she lives, she fries—</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Then in that Light in which Shee lives Shee Fryes</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="12">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">A glorious Virgin Victim, thus Shee Dies</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">A glorious virgin victim; thus she dies.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">A glorious <seg>Virgin<note type="critical">There was thought to only ever be one phoenix in existence at a time, which would live in a cycle of immolation and resurrection; therefore, the phoenix is a virgin. The third-century Latin poem “The Phoenix,” attributed to the Christian poet Lactantius, reads “felix quae veneris foedera nulla colit: / mors illi venus est, sola est in morte volupta” (ln. 164–65; “she regards not any unions of love: to her, death is love; and her sole pleasure lies in death” (trans. J. Wight Duff, Arnold M. Duff)). While we do not know whether Pulter read this poem, it expresses a similar sentiment to this emblem in an equally Christian framework: namely, the desire to find love, peace, and rebirth in death.</note></seg> Victim, thus Shee Dies
          </rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="13">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Thus though the <seg>&ff;ire<note type="physical">“re” written over other letters, possibly “er</note></seg> her groſſer part conſumes</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Thus though the fire her <seg>grosser<note type="gloss">more material, substantial, dense (than, by implication, the spirit or soul); more perceptible to the senses</note></seg> part consumes,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Thus though the Fire her <seg>grosser part<note type="gloss">The material part; implicitly, the corporeal body.</note></seg> consumes</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="14">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">A principle is left which Reaſſumes</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">A principle is left which reassumes</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">A <seg>principle<note type="gloss">The source or origin; implicitly, the soul.</note></seg> is left which Reassumes</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="15">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">The Azure, Purple, Skarlet, Golden Plumes</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">The <seg>azure<note type="gloss">blue</note></seg>, purple, scarlet, golden <seg>plumes<note type="gloss">feathers</note></seg></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">The <seg>Azure, Purple, Skarlet, Golden Plumes<note type="gloss">See Pliny’s description of the phoenix “as yellow and bright as gold, (namely all about the necke;) the rest of the bodie a deep red purple the taile azure blew, intermingled with feathers among of rose carnation color” (Pliny, <ref target="//name.umdl.umich.edu/A09763.0001.001" type="new-window-url"><title rend="italic">Natural History</title>, p. 271</ref>).</note></seg></rdg>

        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="16">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Which did Adorn, her Gorgious gaudy Mother</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Which did adorn her gorgeous <seg>gaudy<note type="gloss">highly ornate, showy (not, at this time, necessarily in a negative sense, as now)</note></seg> mother;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Which did Adorn, her Gorgious gaudy Mother</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="17">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Thus they ſucceed and Still exceed each other</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Thus they succeed and still exceed each other.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Thus they succeed and Still exceed each other</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="18">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Who would not ſuch a bleſſed change explore</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Who would not such a blessed change <seg>explore<note type="gloss">investigate, consider</note></seg>?</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Who would not such a blessed change explore</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="19">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Or who would Such a change as this deplore</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Or who would such a change as this <seg>deplore<note type="gloss">lament, regret</note></seg>?</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Or who would Such a change as this deplore</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="20">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Although I cannot in Sols &ff;ulgour &ff;rie</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Although I cannot in <seg>Sol’s fulgor<note type="gloss">the sun’s dazzling brightness</note></seg> fry,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Although I cannot in Sol’s <seg>Fulgour<note type="gloss">A bright, dazzling light.</note></seg> Frie</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="21">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Nor dare not like this Gymnoſophist die</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Nor dare not like this <seg>Gymnosophist<note type="gloss">ancient Hindu mystical contemplative sect whose members wore very little clothing, ate no meat, and practiced asceticism and self-inflected hardships</note></seg> die</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Nor dare not like this <seg>Gymnosophist<note type="gloss">A member of a sect of ancient Hindu ascetic philosophers, described in Plutarch’s “Life of Alexander the Great.” Here it refers to Calanus, the poem’s titular Brahman, although, in Plutarch, Calanus not one of the gymnosophists (<bibl>Plutarch, <ref target="//name.umdl.umich.edu/A09802.0001.001" type="new-window-url"><title rend="italic">Lives</title></ref>, p. 757–9</bibl>). Pulter appears to use both Brahman and Gymnosophist as generic terms for Indian philosophers.</note></seg> die</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="22">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Such <seg>Stoicall<note type="physical">imperfectly erased descender below “c”</note></seg> tricks a Chriſtian Spirit loaths</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">(Such <seg>Stoical<note type="gloss">traits of those practicing the philosophy of Stoicism, commonly identified as austerity, indifference to pleasure and pain, acceptance of suffering, and repression of feeling</note></seg> tricks a Christian spirit loathes),</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Such <seg>Stoicall<note type="gloss">Of or belonging to the Stoics; characteristic of the Stoic philosophy. This was a school of philosophy founded by Zeno and flourishing in the 4th century BCE, “characterized by the austerity of its ethical doctrines for some of which the name has become proverbial” (Oxford English Dictionary). Calanus was not a Stoic, and Pulter’s characterization of him as such is another example of her conflation of pagan philosophies (see note 12 above).</note></seg> tricks a Christian Spirit loaths</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="23">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Yet as old Aaron did put of his Cloaths</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Yet as old <seg>Aaron did put off his clothes<note type="gloss">On God’s command, Moses stripped his brother Aaron of his clothes before Aaron’s death (Aaron died for disobeying God). See Numbers 20: 23–29.</note></seg>,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Yet as old Aaron did <seg>put of his Cloaths<note type="gloss">i.e., put off his clothes. This references Aaron’s death on Mount Hor. At God’s command, Moses removes Aaron’s priestly garments before Aaron’s death and passes them to his son Eleazar. See <title rend="italic">Holy Bible</title>, <ref target="https://www.biblegateway.com/versions/King-James-Version-KJV-Bible/" type="new-window-url">King James Version</ref>, Numbers 20.22–29; Barton, John. “Aaron.” <title rend="italic">The Oxford Dictionary of the Christian Church</title>, edited by Andrew Louth, 4th ed., Oxford University Press, 17 Feb. 2022.
          </note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="24">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Soe I being Worn with Sorrow, Sin, and Age,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">So I, being worn with sorrow, sin, and age,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Soe I being Worn with Sorrow, Sin, and Age,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="25">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Quite tird with Acting in this Scene and Stage</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Quite tired with acting in this scene and stage,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Quite tird with Acting in this <seg>Scene and Stage<note type="gloss">The metaphor of the world as a stage and people as actors was common in the early modern period. Today, the most famous example is William Shakespeare’s the “All the World’s a Stage” speech in <title rend="italic">As You Like It</title> (<bibl><title rend="italic">As You Like It</title>. <title rend="italic">The Riverside Shakespeare</title>, edited by G. Blakemore Evans and J. J. M. Tobin, 2nd ed, Houghton Mifflin, 1997, 2.7.139–66</bibl>).</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="26">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Would gladly my Mortality lay by</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Would gladly my mortality lay by.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Would gladly my Mortality lay by</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="27">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Who then can Say Hadaſſah here doth Lie</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Who then can say, “<seg>Hadassah<note type="gloss">Pulter’s chosen pseudonym, the Hebrew form of the name of the heroic biblical Queen Esther (Esther being a variant of Hester)</note></seg> here doth <seg>lie<note type="gloss">to remain in a recumbent position or posture of subjection; to dwell or be quartered in; be passive, tell an untruth</note></seg>,”</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Who then can Say <seg>Hadassah<note type="gloss">As noted in the Elemental Edition of <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="109">The Brahman (Emblem 44)</ref>, Hadassah, the Hebrew form of Queen Esther’s name, is Pulter’s pseudonym as a poet.</note></seg> here doth Lie</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="28">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">When as my Soul ſhall Reaſſend above</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee"><seg>Whenas<note type="gloss">seeing that; at a time which</note></seg> my soul shall reascend above</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">When as my Soul shall Reassend above</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="29">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">To God the &ff;ount of Life, Light, Joy, and Love.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">To God, the fount of life, light, joy, and love?</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">To God the Fount of Life, Light, Joy, and Love.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="30">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Nor Shall my Scattred dust forgotten Rest</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Nor shall my scattered dust forgotten rest,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Nor Shall my Scattred dust forgotten Rest</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="31">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">But <seg>like<note type="physical">erased descender under the “k”</note></seg> the <seg>Embryo[<del>?</del>]<note type="physical">“yo” written over other letters, in darker ink; two following letters scribbled out in same ink</note></seg> in the Phœnix Nest</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">But like the embryo in the Phœnix nest,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">But like the Embryo in the Phœnix Nest</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="32">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">That Word that Nothing did create in vain</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee"><seg>That Word that nothing did create in vain<note type="gloss">God’s word as creative force: “In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was God … All things were made by him; and without him was not any thing made that was made” (John 1: 103)</note></seg></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">That Word that Nothing did create in vain</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="33">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Shall Reinſpire my Dormient Duſt again</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Shall reinspire my <seg>dormant dust<note type="gloss">in biblical accounts, the dormant (slumbering, inert) material from which life derives to and to which it will return; see Genesis 3:19: “for dust thou art, and unto dust shalt thou return.”</note></seg> again;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Shall Reinspire my <seg>Dormient Dust<note type="gloss">As noted in the Elemental Edition of <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="109">The Brahman (Emblem 44)</ref> and Eardley’s edition: the material out of which the body comes and to which it will return in the Bible, e.g. Genesis 3.19; <bibl>Eardley, Alice, editor. “The Brahman.” <title rend="italic">Poems, Emblems, and the Unfortunate Florinda</title>, by Hester Pulter, University of Chicago Press, 2014, (n. to ln. 33</bibl>). Pulter returns to this image of “dormant dust” repeatedly, especially in reference to resurrection, e.g. <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="105">View But this Tulip (Emblem 40)</ref>.</note></seg> again</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="34">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">And from obſcurity my Atomes Raiſe</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">And from obscurity my atoms raise</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">And from obscurity my <seg>Atomes<note type="gloss">The smallest particle of matter, in use with this meaning in scientific circles by the seventeenth century. Although it is often considered a secular or even atheistic concept, here and in other poems, Pulter spiritualizes the concept of the atom and uses it as a synonym for dust (see note 17 above).</note></seg> Raise</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="35">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">To ſing in Joy his Everlasting praiſe</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">To sing in joy His everlasting praise,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">To sing in Joy his Everlasting praise</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="36">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">And Reunite my Body to my Spirit</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee"><seg>And reunite my body to my spirit<note type="gloss">a reference to the Christian belief in the reunion of the dead body and spirit in heaven at the Final Judgment or end of the world. The next lines link such salvation to Christ’s sacrifice.</note></seg>,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">And Reunite my Body to my <seg>Spirit<note type="gloss">As noted in the Elemental Edition of <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="109">The Brahman (Emblem 44)</ref>, a reference to the Christian belief that the faithful will be resurrected following the Second Coming of Jesus Christ.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="37">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">That wee may thoſe Eternall Joys inherit</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">That we may those eternal joys inherit,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">That wee may those Eternall Joys inherit</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="38">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Which I may claim by my dear Saviours Merrit.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Which I may claim by my dear Savior’s merit.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Which I may claim by my dear <seg>Saviour’s Merrit<note type="critical">Unlike Calanus and the phoenix, both of whom implicitly will be redeemed on the basis of their own virtues, Pulter hopes for salvation through the virtue of Christ.</note></seg>.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
        <app>
            <rdg type="milestone" wit="#ft">
                <milestone unit="poem" rend="straight-horline"/>
            </rdg>
        </app>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
