<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../src/vmachine.xsl"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
  schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI [

  <!ENTITY ff "<!-- ff ligature, representing capital modern day capital F, here represented as 'ff' -->ff">

  ]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mads.pp.14">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
          <title>On the Horrid Murder of that Incomparable Prince</title>
        <title type="sub">Poem #14</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Created by</resp>
          <persName>Leah Knight</persName>
          <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoded by</resp>
          <persName>Katherine Poland</persName>
          <persName>Matthew Taylor</persName>
          <persName>Betsy Chou</persName>
          <persName>Emily Andrey</persName>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>IT-project consultation by</resp>
          <persName>Josh Honn</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
          <orgName>Brock University</orgName>
          <orgName>University of Leeds</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <principal>
          <persName/>
        </principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="1"/>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription, transformations, and notes</resp>
          <persName>Leah Knight</persName>
          <orgName>Brock University</orgName>
          <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
        </respStmt>
      </editionStmt>
      <extent/>
      <publicationStmt>
        <ab/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listBibl>
          <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
              <repository>See witness list.</repository>
            </msIdentifier>
          </msDesc>
        </listBibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p/>
      </projectDesc>
      <p>Transcriptions are encoded in TEI(P5)-conformant XML.</p>
      <samplingDecl>
        <p/>
      </samplingDecl>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction>
          <p>Apparent errors are preserved and editorial corrections provided using SIC and CORR tags, but only where the editor conjectures that the original scribe or compositor would have recognized the instance as an error. For example, what according to modern usage is incorrect subject/verb agreement might have been deemed acceptable to a seventeenth-century scribe or compositor. All such instances are treated instead using the ORIG and REG tags. (See below.)</p>
          <p>Corrections and annotations made within the scope of the original document either by its original authors, owners, and/or transcribers are noted using ADD tags. These annotations and may be further explained within NOTE tags, as added by the editors of this digital edition, for display within the apparatus.</p>
        </correction>
        <normalization>
          <p>Original spellings, abbreviations, and orthography are preserved. Where in the manuscripts a character’s status as majuscule or minuscule is ambiguous, the editor has silently chosen one or the other based on context and judgment (i.e., does not register such ambiguity in either the markup or the notes).</p>
        </normalization>
        <quotation>
          <p>Original quotation marks, if any, are preserved.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation>
          <p>Original hyphenation is preserved.</p>
        </hyphenation>
      </editorialDecl>
      <charDecl>
        <!-- Ligature combinations for which there are currently no corresponding Unicode codepoints. -->
        <glyph xml:id="ffllig">
          <glyphName>Handwritten 'ff' ligature, used in handwriting to represent modern F</glyphName>
        </glyph>
      </charDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="DDC22">
          <bibl>
            <title>Dewey Decimal Classification</title>
            <edition/>
            <publisher/>
            <pubPlace/>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-GB">British English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <!-- dewey decimal system class code 821: English Poetry -->
        <classCode scheme="DDC22">821</classCode>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
    <!-- List of all images associated with this document -->
      <graphic url="./document_images/7610_071.jpg" xml:id="f7610_071"/>
  </facsimile>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="ft">Transcription of manuscript: By <persName xml:id="lknight">Leah Knight</persName> and <persName xml:id="wwall">Wendy Wall</persName>.</witness>
          <witness xml:id="ee">Elemental edition: By <persName>Leah Knight</persName> and <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>.</witness>
          <witness xml:id="ae">Amplified edition: By <persName>David Norbrook</persName>.</witness>
        </listWit>
      </div>
    </front>

    <body>
      <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft"><pb ed="#ft" facs="#f7610_071" n="34r"/></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee"><pb ed="#ee" facs="#f7610_071"/></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><pb ed="#ae" facs="#f7610_071"/></rdg>
      </app>
      <head>
        <app type="title">
            <rdg wit="#ft"><fw facs="#f7610_069" type="pageNum" place="margin-topright">PG#</fw>On the Horrid Murther of that incomparable –
                Prince, King Charles the &ff;irst
            </rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">On the Horrid Murder of that <seg>Incomparable Prince<note type="gloss">In the manuscript, the title specifies: “King Charles the First.” In the English civil war between royalists and parliamentarians, Charles I was sentenced to death and beheaded in 1649.</note></seg>
            </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">On the Horrid Murder of that Incomparable Prince, King Charles the First</rdg>
        </app>
        <app type="editorialnote">
          <rdg wit="#ft">
            <note type="editorialnote">In these transcriptions we preserve as many details of the original material, textual, and graphic properties of Hester Pulter’s manuscript verse as we have found practical. Whenever possible, for instance, original spelling, punctuation, capitalization, lineation, insertions, deletions, alterations, spacing between words and lines, and indentation are all maintained; abbreviations and brevigraphs are not expanded; and superscript and subscript representations are retained. <ref target="//pulterproject.northwestern.edu/about-project-conventions.html#top" type="new-window-url">See full conventions for the transcriptions here.</ref></note>
          </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">
            <note type="editorialnote">The aim of the elemental edition is to make the poems accessible to the largest variety of readers, which involves modernizing spelling and punctuation as well as adding basic glosses. Spelling and punctuation reflect current standard American usage; punctuation highlights syntax which might otherwise be obscure. Outmoded but still familiar word forms (“thou,” “‘tis,” “hold’st”) are not modernized, and we do not modernize grammar when the sense remains legible. After a brief headnote aimed at offering a “way in” to the poem’s unique qualities and connections with other verse by Pulter or her contemporaries, the edition features a minimum of notes and interpretative framing to allow more immediate engagement with the poem. Glosses clarify synonyms or showcase various possible meanings in Pulter’s time. Other notes identify named people and places or clarify obscure material. We rely (without citation) primarily on the Oxford English Dictionary (OED), the Oxford Reference database, and the King James Version (KJV) of the Bible. When we rely on Alice Eardley’s edition of Pulter’s work, we cite her text generally (“Eardley”); other sources are cited in full. The result is an edition we consider a springboard for further work on Pulter’s poetry. <ref target="//pulterproject.northwestern.edu/about-project-conventions.html#elemental-edition" type="new-window-url">See full conventions for this edition here.</ref></note></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">
            <note type="editorialnote">The poem appears on p. 63 of the manuscript, the verso of the preceding page being blank apart from the number 62 in the scribe’s hand; p. 61 contains poem 13, <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="13">Upon the Imprisonment of his Sacred Majesty, That Unparalleled Prince, King Charles the First</ref>. This is the first blank page in the manuscript, and for the reader, turning the page moves us from the king’s captivity to the aftermath of his death. <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="15">Let None Sigh More for Lucas or for Lisle [On the Same (2)]</ref> is followed by another blank page. Whether this was an intentional effect cannot be determined–the political poems in the MS are not placed in chronological order, with poem 13 predating poems <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="7">On those Two Unparalleled Friends, Sir George Lisle and Sir Charles Lucas, Who Were Shot to Death at Colchester</ref> and <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="8">On that Unparalleled Prince Charles the First, His Horrid Murder</ref>, and there are later blank spaces without clear significance; it does seem possible, however, that poems 14 and 15 had been written together on a folded sheet or “separate.” The text is unpunctuated except for brackets at “Ay mee” (l. 6). For the present text, punctuation has been inserted and spelling changed to modern usage. However, the page images are easily available and make it possible to understand the experience of early readers, with the page layout highlighting the structure of the couplets, and capitalization often highlighting balanced words: this is not just something said but something made.</note>
          </rdg>
        </app>
        <app type="headnote">
          <rdg wit="#ee">
            <note type="headnote">This poem follows one <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="13">Upon the Imprisonment of his Sacred Majesty, That Unparalleled Prince, King Charles the First</ref>; it thus follows not only in the manuscript’s arrangement, but in chronology. Charles, jailed in 1647, was in 1649 beheaded by his opponents in England’s civil wars. The monstrous singularity of this event seems reflected in the volume’s preceding blank page, paired with another after the next poem, <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="15">On the Same</ref>: these two poems, in their efforts to grieve a beloved, murdered ruler, huddle together between visible, almost legible stretches of silence. Here, the speaker draws on the authority of conventional poetic claims of ineffability associated with praising monarchs. But now it is not just words that fail; now, even tears and sighs won’t serve — a devastating claim for a poet who figures much of her verse as tears and sighs. Instead, this poem insists the only fitting response to the king’s dismemberment is a kind of self-vivisection by mourners who are exhorted to weep not tears, but eyeballs, and to sigh not air, but their very souls: that is, to grieve themselves to death.</note>
          </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">
            <note type="headnote">
                <p>This poem is placed in the manuscript after <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="13">Upon the Imprisonment of his Sacred Majesty, That Unparalleled Prince, King Charles the First</ref>, which may have been written in early 1647 (See Ruth Connolly’s Headnote to the <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="13" target="ae">Amplified Edition</ref>). The juxtaposition, whether intentional or not, calls attention to the dramatic changes in the king’s fate (see further Exploration: <ref target="//pulterproject.northwestern.edu/#pulter-and-political-revolution" type="pp-exploration-ref">Pulter and Political Revolution</ref>). If Pulter was shocked by the rebels who had thrown their sovereign in prison, she now had to find words for the outrage of their putting him on trial and sentencing him to death. He was beheaded on 30 January 1649. While some earlier English monarchs had been put to death, now not only the monarch but the monarchy was destroyed, with the declaration of a republic. As the editors of the Elemental Edition put it: “The monstrous singularity of this event seems reflected in the volume’s preceding blank page, paired with another after the next poem: these two poems, in their efforts to grieve a beloved, murdered ruler, huddle together between visible, almost legible stretches of silence.” The change is reflected in the imagery of tears: from “ask no more why I’m in tears dissolv’d” (Poem 13, line 16) to “Let none presume to weep; tears are too weak…” (Poem 14, line 1). The word ‘unparall[ell]ed’ — which Pulter often used to comprehend a period of such radical changes — is now transferred from the king to his death (<ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="15">Let None Sigh More for Lucas or for Lisle [On the Same (2)]</ref>, line 15). There was an outpouring of royalist rage and lament in poetry and prose, from women like Pulter and Katherine Philips writing in manuscript, to printed collections of verse rushed out in defiance of the republican government’s censorship, and above all the king’s own (ghost-written) testament, the <title rend="italic">Eikon Basilike</title>, which compared his own fate to the crucifixion of Christ. After that extreme parallel, there was in effect nowhere for poets to go. Many of the elegies, especially a series of poems by John Quarles, reflected their authors’ grief in rambling and disjointed structures:</p>
                <cit>
                    <quote>
                      <lg>
                        <l>Where shall I run, to whom shall I address</l>
                        <l>My burthened self, or how shall I express</l>
                        <l>My uncontrouled sorrows, or relate</l>
                        <l>Th’ unhappy discord of my <hi rend="italic">factious State</hi>?…</l>
                        <l>This is my want, and till I find relief,</l>
                        <l>I’le lie and tumble in the shades of grief,</l>
                        <l>And glut the ayr with sighs; my hideous cries</l>
                        <l>Shall roar like thunder in the troubled skies:</l>
                        <l>O that my <hi rend="italic">eyes</hi> were <hi rend="italic">Oceans</hi>, that I may</l>
                        <l>Drown all my sorrows in one stormy day;</l>
                        <l>Or would pleas’d <hi rend="italic">Heaven</hi>, enable me to strain,</l>
                        <l>To gulp up <hi rend="italic">Seas</hi>, and weep them out again,</l>
                        <l>Then should my briny streams gush forth so fast,</l>
                        <l>That every tear should strive to be the last;</l>
                        <l>So the swift current of my swelling eyes</l>
                        <l>Should overflow my heap’d up miseries.</l>
                      </lg>
                    </quote>
                    <bibl>
                     An excerpt from John Quarles’ “Englands Complaint,” in <title rend="italic">Fons Lachrymarum, or, A Fountain of Tears from whence doth flow Englands Complaint…with Divine Meditations, and an Elegy upon that Son of Valor Sir Charles Lucas</title> (London, 1648–9), pp. 3–5.
                    </bibl>
                </cit>
                <p>“On the Horrid Murder of that Incomparable Prince” reads as if Pulter has surveyed this material and decided to push in the opposite direction, towards extreme concentration, though her language remains hyperbolic. Two lines consist entirely of monosyllables. In this tightly structured poem, Pulter considers two forms of response, weeping and sighing, and in each half of the poem rejects them as too commonplace, with parallel final couplets offering an alternative; at the half-way point we are told to weep out our eyes, but the sighing “ay me” is immediately countered by a ban on sighing, and the second couplet-refrain adds that we should breathe out our souls. The “prince” of the earlier refrain becomes “king.” Comparable patterning is found within lines — “such a prince/king in such a manner,” “We do too little, if we do no more.” The concluding hyperboles gain new force from the constrained frame from which they emerge. Having forbidden sighs at line 7, in the final line Pulter calls on us to “suspire our souls.” The Latin-derived verb, which can mean both “sigh” and “breathe,” offers a reduplicated pattern of sibilants that reinforces the extreme sense: sighing so hard that breath leaves the body altogether. The image thus takes to an extreme a theme of the whole manuscript, whose title-page has the inscription “Poems Breathed forth By The Nobel Haddassas.” The line is then completed: “weep out our eyes.” Many Renaissance and baroque poems juxtaposed tears and eyes: Andrew Marvell would condense the tradition in “Eyes and Tears”:</p>
                <cit>
                    <quote>
                      <lg>
                        <l>Thus let your streams o’erflow your springs,</l>
                        <l>Till eyes and tears be the same things:</l>
                        <l>And each the other’s diff’rence bears;</l>
                        <l>These weeping eyes, those seeing tears.</l>
                       </lg>
                    </quote>
                </cit>
                <p>But though Marvell rings the changes of eye imagery, he does not go to the extreme of having the weeper expel her own eyes. Some royalist elegies do link tears with the writing or publishing of elegies as a gesture of political defiance, and Pulter’s hyperbole takes on these connotations of resistance. Compare:</p>
                <cit>
                    <quote>
                      <lg>
                        <l rend="tab-1">let every word invite</l>
                        <l>A <hi rend="italic">tear</hi>; each <hi rend="italic">tear</hi>, a <hi rend="italic">sigh</hi>; that every <hi rend="italic">Eye</hi>,</l>
                        <l>That reads, may melt into an <hi rend="italic">Elegie</hi>.</l>
                       </lg>
                    </quote>
                    <bibl>
                       An excerpt from John Quarles’ “Englands Complaint,” p.2; and see John McWilliams, “‘A Storm of Lamentations Writ’: <title rend="italic">Lachrymae Musarum</title> and Royalist Culture after the Civil War,” <title rend="italic">The Yearbook of English Studies 33</title> (2003), 273–89 (282–3).
                      </bibl>
                  </cit>

                <p>Strikingly, Pulter here opposes her own verse to that of village girls, plebeians, the vulgar. She often attacks the revolutionaries as plebeian monsters, but here, in her concern to cast her own poetry as rejecting stock responses, she seems to mark herself off from popular royalism. John Milton, attacking the people’s devotion to tyrants, complained that support for tyrannicide had to be “swett and labour’d out amidst the throng and noises of <hi rend="italic">vulgar</hi> and irrationall men,” who “plead for him, pity him, extoll him, protest against those that talk of bringing him to the tryal of Justice, which is the Sword of God, superior to all mortal things, in whose hand soever by apparent signes his testified will is to put it” (<title rend="italic">The Tenure of Kings and Magistrates</title>, London, 1649, p. 3). Pulter differentiates herself from vulgar royalism even as she tries to surpass it. She also rejects the uncontrolled emotionalism often associated with women, even though her conclusion also avoids a conventionally masculine stoicism.</p>
             </note>
          </rdg>
        </app>
      </head>

      <l n="1">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Let none preſume to weep, tears are to weak</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Let none presume to weep; tears are too weak</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Let none presume to weep; tears are too weak</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="2">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Such an <seg>unparreld<note type="physical">“e” written over “i” (with dot still visible)</note></seg> loſs as this to Speak</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee"><seg>Such<note type="gloss">of such</note></seg> an <seg>unparall’d<note type="critical">Spelled “unparelled” (for “unparalleled”) in the manuscript, we have maintained an abbreviation for the sake of the meter.</note></seg> loss as this to speak.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>Such<note type="gloss">of such.</note></seg> an <seg>unparall’d<note type="critical">unparallelled (“unparelld” in manuscript): a word whose frequent use by Pulter reflects her sense of living in times of crisis.</note></seg> loss as this to speak.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="3">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Poor village Girles doe Soe expreſs their grief</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Poor village girls do so express their grief,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Poor village girls do so express their grief,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="4">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">And in that Sad expreſſion find relief</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">And in that sad expression find relief.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">And in that sad expression find relief.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="5">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">When Such a Prince in Such a manner Dies</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">When such a <seg>prince<note type="physical">sovereign ruler</note></seg> in such a manner dies,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">When such a <seg>Prince<note type="gloss">sovereign ruler.</note></seg> in such a manner dies,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="6">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Let us (ay mee) noe more drop tears but eyes</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Let us (ay me!) no more drop tears, but eyes;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Let us (ay me!) no more <seg>drop tears, but eyes<note type="gloss">exaggerates the common trope of weeping for the king by grotesquely literalizing “eyedrop.”</note></seg>;</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="7">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Nor let none dare to Sigh or Strike their breast</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Nor let none dare to sigh or strike their breast</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Nor let none dare to sigh or strike their breast</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="8">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">To Shew a grief that Soe tranſcends the rest</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">To show a grief that so transcends the rest.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">To show a grief that so transcends the rest.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="9">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft"><seg>Plebeans<note type="physical">“b” possibly written over an existing later, perhaps a “v”</note></seg> Soe each vulgar loſs <seg>deplore<del>s</del><note type="physical">“s” erased</note></seg></rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee"><seg>Plebeians<note type="gloss">commoners</note></seg> so each vulgar loss <seg>deplore<note type="gloss">mourn</note></seg>;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>Plebeians<note type="gloss">commoners, a term borrowed from the Roman categories of plebeians and patricians: compare <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="12">The Garden, or The Contention of Flowers</ref>, line 428.</note></seg> so each <seg>vulgar<note type="gloss">“Of, relating to, or characteristic of ordinary or common people” (<title rend="italic">Oxford English Dictionary</title>, II.8; compare Latin <hi rend="italic">vulgus</hi>).</note></seg> loss <seg>deplore<note type="gloss">weep for, mourn.</note></seg>;</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="10">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Wee doo too little if wee doo noe more</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">We do too little, if we do no more.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">We do too little, if we do no more.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="11">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">When Such a King in Such a manner Dies</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">When such a king in such a manner dies,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">When such a King in such a manner dies,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="12">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Let us suſpire our Soules, weep out <w lemma="our"><abbr>o:<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></abbr></w> eyes.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Let us <seg>suspire<note type="gloss">sigh, breathe out</note></seg> our souls, weep out our eyes.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Let us <seg>suspire<note type="gloss">sigh, breathe out (from Latin <hi rend="italic">suspirare</hi>).</note></seg> our souls, weep out our eyes.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
