<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../src/vmachine.xsl"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
  schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI [

  <!ENTITY ff "<!-- ff ligature, representing capital modern day capital F, here represented as 'ff' -->ff">

  ]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mads.pp.68">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
          <title>Come, My Dear Children (Emblem 2)</title>
        <title type="sub">Poem #68</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Created by</resp>
          <persName>Leah Knight</persName>
          <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoded by</resp>
          <persName>Katherine Poland</persName>
          <persName>Matthew Taylor</persName>
          <persName>Betsy Chou</persName>
          <persName>Emily Andrey</persName>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>IT-project consultation by</resp>
          <persName>Josh Honn</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
          <orgName>Brock University</orgName>
          <orgName>University of Leeds</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <principal>
          <persName/>
        </principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="1"/>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription, transformations, and notes</resp>
          <persName>Leah Knight</persName>
          <orgName>Brock University</orgName>
          <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
        </respStmt>
      </editionStmt>
      <extent/>
      <publicationStmt>
        <ab/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listBibl>
          <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
              <repository>See witness list.</repository>
            </msIdentifier>
          </msDesc>
        </listBibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p/>
      </projectDesc>
      <p>Transcriptions are encoded in TEI(P5)-conformant XML.</p>
      <samplingDecl>
        <p/>
      </samplingDecl>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction>
          <p>Apparent errors are preserved and editorial corrections provided using SIC and CORR tags, but only where the editor conjectures that the original scribe or compositor would have recognized the instance as an error. For example, what according to modern usage is incorrect subject/verb agreement might have been deemed acceptable to a seventeenth-century scribe or compositor. All such instances are treated instead using the ORIG and REG tags. (See below.)</p>
          <p>Corrections and annotations made within the scope of the original document either by its original authors, owners, and/or transcribers are noted using ADD tags. These annotations and may be futher explained within NOTE tags, as added by the editors of this digital edition, for display within the apparatus.</p>
        </correction>
        <normalization>
          <p>Original spellings, abbreviations, and orthography are preserved. Where in the manuscripts a character's status as majuscule or miniscule is ambiguous, the editor has silently chosen one or the other based on context and judgment (i.e., does not register such ambiguity in either the markup or the notes).</p>
        </normalization>
        <quotation>
          <p>Original quotation marks, if any, are preserved.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation>
          <p>Original hyphenation is preserved.</p>
        </hyphenation>
      </editorialDecl>
      <charDecl>
        <!-- Ligature combinations for which there are currently no corresponding Unicode codepoints. -->
        <glyph xml:id="ffllig">
          <glyphName>Handwritten 'ff' ligature, used in handwriting to represent modern F</glyphName>
        </glyph>
      </charDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="DDC22">
          <bibl>
            <title>Dewey Decimal Classification</title>
            <edition/>
            <publisher/>
            <pubPlace/>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-GB">British English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <!-- dewey decimal system class code 821: English Poetry -->
        <classCode scheme="DDC22">821</classCode>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
    <!-- List of all images associated with this document -->
      <graphic url="./document_images/7610_186.jpg" xml:id="f7610_186"/>
      <graphic url="./document_images/7610_187.jpg" xml:id="f7610_187"/>
  </facsimile>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="ft">Transcription of manuscript: By <persName xml:id="lknight">Leah Knight</persName> and <persName xml:id="wwall">Wendy Wall</persName>.</witness>
          <witness xml:id="ee">Elemental edition: By <persName>Leah Knight</persName> and <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>.</witness>
            <witness xml:id="ae">Amplified edition: By <persName>Millie Godfery</persName> and <persName>Sarah C. E. Ross</persName>.</witness>
        </listWit>
      </div>
    </front>

    <body>

      <app>
        <rdg wit="#ft">
            <pb ed="#ft" facs="#f7610_186" n="91v"/>
        </rdg>
        <rdg wit="#ee">
            <pb ed="#ee" facs="#f7610_186"/>
        </rdg>
        <rdg wit="#ae">
            <pb ed="#ae" facs="#f7610_186"/>
        </rdg>
      </app>

      <head>
        <app type="title">
            <rdg wit="#ft"><fw facs="#f7610_069" type="emblemNum" place="margin-topleft">2</fw>[Emblem 2]</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Come, My Dear Children<lb/>(Emblem 2)</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Come, My Dear Children (Emblem 2)</rdg>
        </app>
        <app type="editorialnote">
          <rdg wit="#ft">
            <note type="editorialnote">In these transcriptions we preserve as many details of the original material, textual, and graphic properties of Hester Pulter’s manuscript verse as we have found practical. Whenever possible, for instance, original spelling, punctuation, capitalization, lineation, insertions, deletions, alterations, spacing between words and lines, and indentation are all maintained; abbreviations and brevigraphs are not expanded; and superscript and subscript representations are retained. <ref target="http://pulterproject.northwestern.edu/about-project-conventions.html#top" type="new-window-url">See full conventions for the transcriptions here.</ref></note>
          </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">
            <note type="editorialnote">The aim of the elemental edition is to make the poems accessible to the largest variety of readers, which involves modernizing spelling and punctuation as well as adding basic glosses. Spelling and punctuation reflect current standard American usage; punctuation highlights syntax which might otherwise be obscure. Outmoded but still familiar word forms (“thou,” “‘tis,” “hold’st”) are not modernized, and we do not modernize grammar when the sense remains legible. After a brief headnote aimed at offering a “way in” to the poem’s unique qualities and connections with other verse by Pulter or her contemporaries, the edition features a minimum of notes and interpretative framing to allow more immediate engagement with the poem. Glosses clarify synonyms or showcase various possible meanings in Pulter’s time. Other notes identify named people and places or clarify obscure material. We rely (without citation) primarily on the Oxford English Dictionary (OED), the Oxford Reference database, and the King James Version (KJV) of the Bible. When we rely on Alice Eardley’s edition of Pulter’s work, we cite her text generally (“Eardley”); other sources are cited in full. The result is an edition we consider a springboard for further work on Pulter’s poetry. <ref target="http://pulterproject.northwestern.edu/about-project-conventions.html#elemental-edition" type="new-window-url">See full conventions for this edition here.</ref></note></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">
              <note type="editorialnote">Our priority in editing these poems has been to modernise, and to achieve interpretative and visual clarity, in order to make the poems as accessible as possible to as wide a modern audience as is possible. Spelling is modernised, as is punctuation. Modernising the latter, in particular, often involves a significant act of editorial interpretation, but in our view this is one of the most productive areas of editorial intervention, particularly for a manuscript text such as Pulter’s where the punctuation is erratic compared to modern usage (and, indeed, compared to early modern printed texts). All biblical references are to the King James Version (1612).</note>
          </rdg>
        </app>
        <app type="headnote">
          <rdg wit="#ee">
              <note type="headnote">Building on the last lines of the previous emblem, which portray the speaker’s spiritual ascent up a staircase, Pulter imagines her children joining her in the arduous and difficult climb toward the shining heaven where her eight dead children now reside. In this poem, the speaker adopts the role of a spiritual teacher and revises the invitation genre, which Pulter uses elsewhere in <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="2">The Invitation to the Country</ref> and <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="68">Come, My Dear Children</ref>. She invites her children to learn the sequence of stages in which twelve personified virtues should be mastered as part of an ascent toward God. The guide for this journey is scripture, personified as the Greek figure Aletheia (or Truth), who lends a steady hand to keep the aspiring Christian from plunging headlong backwards (or to Hell). The speaker’s authority strikingly inheres in her position as a Christ-like mediator of Truth: “Even as I follow Christ, so follow me,” she states. In the manuscript, the didacticism of the poem is enhanced by a numbered list of the virtues inscribed in the left margin.</note>
          </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">
            <note type="headnote">
                <p>Pulter’s second emblem completes what can be read as a prefatory pair. The image of godly steps established in <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="67">Mighty Nimrod (Emblem 1)</ref> is pursued, as Pulter invokes a figurative sequence of steps via a list of twelve virtues, suggesting that, by following them exactly, one will achieve everlasting happiness. These steps are not only described in the poem, they are also outlined in the left-hand margin, and the presentation of this list in the manuscript deserves attention: the notes are written in the scribal hand, suggesting they are part of the original text, and they are carefully numbered. Because this suggests that the marginal notes are integral to the poem, we have retained them as part of the main text in this edition.</p>
                <p>The visual effect of this marginal listing is striking, as it sets out in a clear sequence the virtuous steps that the didactic poem details.  George Herbert’s pattern poems in <title rend="italic">The Temple</title> (1633) are salient examples of giving language “visual and sacred significance”, and they would have been well known to Pulter.  See “The Altar” and “Easter wings” (Wilcox, <title rend="italic">The English Poems of George Herbert</title> [New York: Cambridge University Press, 2007], 89-94, 143-149), and “The Church-floore”, which closely parallels this emblem. Herbert aligns each step up “the gentle [rise]” to the quire with a specific virtue, visualizing these steps in the poem’s layout to aid his didactic preoccupation (Wilcox 244):</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="/images/poems/p68-1.jpg" xml:id="p68-1">
                    </graphic>
                  <figDesc>
                    Scan of <title>The Church-floore</title> which includes:
                    <quote>
                      <lg>
                        <l>Mark you the floore ? that ſquare &amp; ſspeckled ſstone,</l>
                        <l>Which looks ſo firm and ſstrong,</l>
                        <l>Is <hi rend="italic">Patience :</hi></l>
                      </lg>
                      <lg>
                        <l>And th'other black and grave, wherewith each one</l>
                        <l>Is checker’d all along,</l>
                        <l><hi rend="italic">Humilitie :</hi></l>
                      </lg>
                      <lg>
                        <l>But the ſweet cement, chich one ſure band</l>
                        <l>Ties the whole frame, is <hi rend="italic">Love</hi></l>
                        <l>And <hi rend="italic">Charitie .</hi></l>
                      </lg>
                    </quote>
                  </figDesc>
                  <caption>Source: <bibl>George Herbert, <title rend="italic">The Temple</title> ([1633], 56), RB 61378, The Huntington Library, San Marino, California.</bibl></caption>
                </figure>
                <p>Pulter similarly uses what Leah Marcus calls “visual punning”, a technique used by Herbert, which shows the poet “building words into a sacred game for the glory of his heavenly father” (<title rend="italic">Childhood and Cultural Despair</title> [Pittsburgh: University of Pittsburgh Press, 1978], 110). Pulter therefore maintains her use of “naked” emblems while employing a visual representation, via the listing, of the steps she will “ascend” (Wilcox 110; Eardley 28).</p>
                <p>In this emblem, Pulter explicitly addresses her children, engaging in a modified version of the invitation poem as she solicits them to learn  and practice the sequential stages of virtue which must be followed to ascend God’s path to Heaven. (For more on Pulter’s use of the invitation genre, see note for line 1.) Combining Christian religion with classical mythology, Pulter draws on God and Aletheia, the Greek goddess of truth, as her guides along the path of virtue. The invitational aspects of this poem grant her a sense of authority, as she utilizes both her poetic and motherly status to enhance the moral didacticism of the emblem. This feminized rhetoric of instruction also draws on the ‘mother’s legacy’ genre, which was a popular genre women utilised to creative private, often posthumous, communication with their children. See Elizabeth Joscelin’s poetry in <title rend="italic">Women’s Writing in Stuart England: The Mothers’ Legacies of Dorothy Leigh, Elizabeth Joscelin, and Elizabeth Richardson</title>, ed. by Sylvia Brown [Stroud: Sutton, 1999]. Evidently conscious of her feminized position as a mother and woman writer, Pulter conveys a linear sense of moral education in her second emblem, as she finds guidance in “God’s word” and the hand of Aletheia, and then imparts this to her children. She becomes a mediator to guide them on the difficult path of virtue to avoid any “tumbl[ing] down” into Hell (line 29).</p>
            </note>
          </rdg>
        </app>
      </head>

      <l n="1">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Come my Dear Children come and Happy bee</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Come, my dear children, come and happy be;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>Come, my dear children<note type="critical">Pulter plays with the conventions of the invitation poem, a genre which features the trope of rural retreat, or the act of drawing away from a political landscape into a space of devout meditation; see Pulter’s pastoral poems <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="2">The Invitation into the Country</ref> and <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="38">To My Dear Jane, Margaret, and Penelope Pulter, They Being at London, I at Broadfield</ref> in which she implores her children to retreat with her to Broadfield, her country estate. In this emblem, Pulter’s invitation, while addressed to her children, diverges in that it asks them to “come” and be happy in faith. This edifying imperative is given by Christ in Matthew 11.28, as he implores “Come unto me, all ye that labour and are heavy laden, and I will give you rest” (KJV). George Herbert’s <title rend="italic">The Temple</title> (1633) also gives similar religious invitations: “The Invitation,” for instance, uses a refrain to solicit “all” (sinners) to “Come … hither” at communion (Helen Wilcox, ed., <title rend="italic">The English Poems of George Herbert</title> [New York: Cambridge University Press, 2007], 625 n.1).</note></seg>, come and happy be;</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="2">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Even as I follow Christ Soe &ff;ollow mee</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee" >Even as I follow Christ, so follow me.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae" >Even as I follow Christ, so follow me.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="3">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Eight of your Number finiſhed have their Story</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee"><seg>Eight of your number finished have their story,<note type="gloss">Presumably this was written when eight of Pulter’s fifteen children had died; Pulter often uses the word “story” as a synonym for “life.”</note></seg></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>Eight of your number finished have their story,<note type="critical">Pulter references her eight children who have passed away. In <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="6">Universal Dissolution</ref>, Pulter refers to her son John as being her fifteenth child, although Eardley only finds records of fourteen, suggesting either the parish registers are incomplete, the other child was baptized elsewhere, or Pulter included a miscarriage. Pulter’s children, in order of death, were: Mary (d.1631); Hester (1630-2); William (1634-9); Charles (d. 1640); Elizabeth (1641-2); Jane (1625-45); Penelope (1633-55); James (1627-59); Edward (1638-65); Ann (1635-66); Mary (d. 1674); John (1648-77); Arthur (1636-80); Margaret (1629-86) (Alice Eardley, “An Edition of Lady Hester Pulter’s Book of ‘Emblemes’”. PhD diss., University of Warwick [2008], 41-42). This would therefore suggest this poem was written either after the death of Penelope in 1655, or James in 1659, depending on when the missing fifteenth child was born and died.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="4">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">And now their Souls doe Shine in endles Glory</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">And now their souls do shine in endless glory.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">And now their souls do shine in endless glory;</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="5">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Then by these Bleſſed Steps let us Aſſend</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Then by these blesséd steps let us ascend</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Then by these <seg>blessed steps<note type="critical">The principal image in this emblem is invoked here. Pulter expands on her first emblem’s image of “mount[ing]” God’s throne via his direction, using Emblem 2 as a figurative and visual representation of the virtuous steps which will, as her didactic message insists, lead us to “glory”. See “Mighty Nimrod” (Emblem 1) for a similar discussion of this theme; see also George Herbert’s poetry, which utilizes this trope of blessed steps and which possibly influenced not only Pulter’s thematic concerns, but the visualisation of the virtuous ladder via the marginal notations (see Headnote). Herbert’s <title rend="italic">The Temple</title> is organised in a tripartite structure: “The Church-porch”, “The Church”, and “The Church Militant”. The architectonic nature of the collection evokes the site of a spiritual temple (symbolising God) and the process of entering it via certain steps; Herbert’s God is “Thy bounteous Lord”, providing “choise of paths” to which “no by-wayes” should be taken (“The Church-porch”, lines 13-14).</note></seg> let us ascend</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="6">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Unto that Joy that <seg>n<del>er</del>’er<note type="physical">darker ink on “n,” final “r,” and (possibly) medial “r” suggests “er’e” corrected to “ne’er”; “n” and final “r” in different hand from main scribe</note></seg> ſhall have end</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Unto that joy that never shall have end.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Unto that joy that never shall have end.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft"><label n="Aletheia" rend="left-gutter">Aletheia</label></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee"><label n="Aletheia" rend="left-gutter">Aletheia</label></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><label n="Aletheia" rend="left-gutter">Aletheia</label></rdg>
        </app>
      <l n="7">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">&ff;irst let Gods Word Your Sole Director bee</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee"><seg>First<note type="physical">Beginning with this line, twelve personified virtues are numbered and listed in the left margin in this order: Humility, Patience, Temperance, Chastity, Prudence, Just[ice], Contentation, Constancy, Fortitude, Faith, Hope, and Charity (which appears as the annotation for “Love”). Pulter’s ordering and selection seem to be her own design.</note></seg>, let <seg>God’s word<note type="critical">In the margin is written “Aletheia” (the Greek personification of Truth), which glosses “God’s word” and thus fuses classical and Christian traditions. The “Truth” that directs the spiritual journey is biblical scripture but this phrase might refer to the representation of Christ as language. See John 1.1: “In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was God.”</note></seg> your sole director be,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>First<note type="physical">"Aletheia" written in left-hand margin in scribal hand</note></seg>, <seg>let God’s word your sole director be<note type="critical">written in the margin in the scribal hand is “Aletheia”, referring to the Greek goddess of truth. While Aletheia is not directly referenced until line 21, this marginal notation suggests a fusion of classical mythology with Christian religion, as Pulter aligns “God’s word” with the truth characterised by the classical goddess. See <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="32">Aletheia’s Pearl</ref>, which gives an account of the speaker’s relationship with the personified figure of truth as Aletheia. In that poem, the speaker seeks to emphasise the fragility of truth, which she does via the metaphor of the pearl. See also Rachel Speght’s <title rend="italic">A Dreame</title>, which similarly contains a personified Truth (though not identified explicitly as Aletheia) as guide for the speaker, offering encouragement in her pursuit of education: “Take courage, and be constant in thy course, / Though irksome be the path, which thou must tread” (“Mortalities Memorandum, with a Dreame Prefixed”, in <title rend="italic">The Polemics and Poems of Rachel Speght</title>, ed. Barbara Kiefer Lewalski [Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1996], 55, lines 177-8). Elizabeth Melville is another female writer who invokes similar images of Christ as a guide leading the speaker of the poem up steps to heavenly truth: “On stately stepps, most stoutly I ascended. / Without his help I thought to enter there.” (<title rend="italic">A Godlie Dreame compiled by Elizabeth Melvill, Ladie Culros younger, at the request of a friend</title> [Edinburgh, 1620], stanza 30). Pulter hence draws on a popular didactic invocation of God, often embodied through the value of a personified Truth, as the only guide one needs through life.</note></seg>,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft"><label n="1" rend="left-gutter" corresp="#pp_l8ft"><w lemma="first"><abbr>1:<hi rend="superscript">st</hi></abbr></w> Humility</label></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee"><label n="1" rend="left-gutter" corresp="#pp_l8ee">1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> Humility</label></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><label n="1" rend="left-gutter" corresp="#pp_l8ae">1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> Humility</label></rdg>
        </app>
      <l n="8">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft" xml:id="pp_l8ft">Which Sweetly Leads you to Humilitye</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" xml:id="pp_l8ee">Which sweetly leads you to Humility,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" xml:id="pp_l8ae">Which sweetly leads you to <seg>Humility<note type="physical">Beginning with “Humility”, the twelve virtues which are personified in the emblem are numbered and listed in the left-hand margin alongside the relevant lines of the poem. This marginal listing is written in the scribal hand. See Headnote for discussion.</note></seg>,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="9">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Through whoſe Low Rooft Temple all did goe</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Through whose low rooféd temple all did go</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>Through<note type="critical">Beginning with this line, the emblem goes on to list twelve virtues, seven of which are identifiable as the Christian neo-Stoic virtues of Temperance, Prudence, Fortitude, Faith, Hope, Charity, and Justice. Pulter also personifies a further five virtues: Humility, Patience, Chastity, Grace, and Truth. These virtues are listed in the left margin, which has the effect of giving a visual representation of the methodical steps one must follow, figuratively and literally, to reach heaven; see Headnote for further discussion.</note></seg> whose <seg>low-roofed<note type="critical">Pulter personifies “Humility” as being “low-roofed”, a conventional trope  which emphasises modesty and humbleness, in comparison to grand extravagance. Joseph Hall writes of the humble man as “a true Temple of God built with a low roofe” (<title rend="italic">Characters of Virtues and Vices</title> [1608], 31).This trope also appeared commonly in the country house poems of the 17th century; see Jonson’s <title rend="italic">To Penshurst</title>, which depicts Robert Sidney’s estate as “not … built to envious show” (Fowler, <title rend="italic">The Country House Poem</title> [Edinburgh: Edinburgh University Press, 1994], 53, line 1); see also Marvell’s <title rend="italic">Upon Appleton House</title> lines 1-72, which constructs Appleton House as a “sober frame” unlike those “columns … [which] so high be raised / To arch the brows that on them gazed” (Fowler 281. 1-8).</note></seg> <seg>temple<note type="critical"> note the four main biblical meanings of the word “temple”; (1) the site of Jewish worship in the Old Testament; (2) a symbol of Christ in the New Testament; (3) the Christian Church and God’s dwelling place in the New Testament; and (4) the human body, which itself becomes a temple (Helen Wilcox. <title rend="italic">The English Poems of George Herbert</title> [New York; Cambridge University Press, 2007], 39-40). Herbert’s <title rend="italic">The Temple</title> (1633) uses the site of the religious temple, or Church, as a metaphor for God, serving a similar purpose as Pulter does here.</note></seg> all did go</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="10">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">That Worſhip’t Honour, Ethenicks this did know</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">That worshipped honor: <seg>ethnics<note type="gloss">heathens, pagans</note></seg> this did know.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">That worshiped Honour; <seg>ethnics<note type="critical">In Pulter’s manuscript, it is difficult to interpret whether this word is spelt “Ethenicks” or “Elhenicks” due to the faintness of the letter that might be “l” or “t” and an ink blotting on the “h”. Alice Eardley (2014) and Knight and Wall (Elemental Edition) have modernised the word to “ethnic”, referring to a non-Christian, non-Jewish person; a heathen (<title rend="italic">OED</title> 1). In her 2008 thesis, however, Eardley suggests that Pulter means “Hellenics”, which refers to Greek peoples during the period of Ancient Greece (“An Edition of Lady Hester Pulter’s Book of ‘Emblemes’”. PhD diss., University of Warwick [2008], 14 n. 10; <title rend="italic">OED</title> 1). This interpretation is interesting in comparison to the glossing of “God’s word” as the Greek goddess “Aletheia” in line 7, which would endorse Pulter’s notion that “Hellenics did …  know” of the principles such as “Humility” and “Honour” that are linked to God, and thus to Aletheia.</note></seg> this did know.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft"><label n="2" rend="left-gutter" corresp="#pp_l11ft"><w lemma="second"><abbr>2:<hi rend="superscript">d</hi></abbr></w> Patience</label></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee"><label n="2" rend="left-gutter" corresp="#pp_l11ee">2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> Patience</label></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><label n="2" rend="left-gutter" corresp="#pp_l11ae">2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> Patience</label></rdg>
        </app>
      <l n="11">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft" xml:id="pp_l11ft">Next patience &ff;its you for the &ff;irey <seg>Triall<note type="physical">“T” appears written over “S”; subsequent illegible letters appear written over and/or erased</note></seg></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" xml:id="pp_l11ee">Next, Patience fits you for the fiery trial;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" xml:id="pp_l11ae">Next, Patience fits you for the <seg>fiery trial<note type="critical">Eardley suggests this is in reference to the “trial in which Christian faith is forged through hardship” (188 n. 15). Given Pulter’s Protestant beliefs, this phrase lends itself to the ideas surrounding martyrdom introduced in John Foxe’s <title rend="italic">Actes and Monuments</title>, which recounts counts the trials of Protestant figures who became martyrs during Catholic rule.</note></seg>;</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="12">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Noe Goeing further <w lemma="without"><abbr>w:<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>out</abbr></w> <seg>Self<note type="physical">“l” appears corrected from imperfectly erased “f”.</note></seg> deniall</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">No going further without self-denial.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">No going further without self-denial.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft"><label n="3" rend="left-gutter" corresp="#pp_l13ft"><w lemma="third" ><abbr>3:<hi rend="superscript">d</hi></abbr></w> Temperance</label></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee"><label n="3" rend="left-gutter" corresp="#pp_l13ee">3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> Temperance</label></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><label n="3" rend="left-gutter" corresp="#pp_l13ae">3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> Temperance</label></rdg>
        </app>
      <l n="13">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft" xml:id="pp_l13ft">Then Temperance be Sure you doe not Mis</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" xml:id="pp_l13ee">Then, Temperance be sure you do not miss,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" xml:id="pp_l13ae">Then Temperance be sure you do not miss,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft"><label n="4" rend="left-gutter" corresp="#pp_l14ft"><w lemma="fourth"><abbr>4:<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></abbr></w> Chastitie</label></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee"><label n="4" rend="left-gutter" corresp="#pp_l14ee">4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Chastity</label></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><label n="4" rend="left-gutter" corresp="#pp_l14ae">4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Chastity</label></rdg>
        </app>
      <l n="14">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft" xml:id="pp_l14ft">That Chastities white hand you next may kiſs</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" xml:id="pp_l14ee">That Chastity’s white hand you next may kiss.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" xml:id="pp_l14ae">That Chastity’s white hand you next may kiss.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft"><label n="5" rend="left-gutter" corresp="#pp_l15ft"><w lemma="fifth"><abbr>5:<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></abbr></w> Prudence</label></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee"><label n="5" rend="left-gutter" corresp="#pp_l15ee">5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Prudence</label></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><label n="5" rend="left-gutter" corresp="#pp_l15ae">5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Prudence</label></rdg>
        </app>
      <l n="15">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft" xml:id="pp_l15ft">Then Prudence that all <seg><w lemma="action"><abbr>Ac<hi rend="overline">con</hi>s</abbr></w><note type="physical">tilde curled under on left, crossed diagonally at centre</note></seg> doth &ff;oreſee</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" xml:id="pp_l15ee">Then, Prudence that all actions doth foresee;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" xml:id="pp_l15ae">Then Prudence that all actions doth foresee;</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft"><label n="6" rend="left-gutter" corresp="#pp_l16ft"><w lemma="sixth"><abbr>6:<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></abbr></w> Just</label></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee"><label n="6" rend="left-gutter" corresp="#pp_l16ee">6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Just</label></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><label n="6" rend="left-gutter" corresp="#pp_l16ae">6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Just</label></rdg>
        </app>
      <l n="16">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft" xml:id="pp_l16ft">Without Her, Just you <w lemma="can"><abbr>ca<hi rend="overline">n</hi>ot</abbr></w> poſſible bee</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" xml:id="pp_l16ee">Without her, Just you cannot <seg>possibly<note type="physical">corrected from “possible” in the manuscript</note></seg> be.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" xml:id="pp_l16ae">Without her, Just you cannot <seg>possibly<note type="physical">MS = possible</note></seg> be.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft"><label n="7" rend="left-gutter"><w lemma="seventh"><abbr>7:<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></abbr></w> Contentation</label></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee"><label n="7" rend="left-gutter">7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Contentation</label></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><label n="7" rend="left-gutter">7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Contentation</label></rdg>
        </app>
      <l n="17">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft" xml:id="pp_l17ft">Then bee Content or you your Self delude</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" xml:id="pp_l17ee">Then, be Content, or you yourself delude,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" xml:id="pp_l17ae">Then be <seg>Content<note type="gloss">Contentation: the state of being content or satisfied (<title rend="italic">OED</title>)</note></seg>, or you yourself delude,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft"><label n="8+9" rend="left-gutter" corresp="#pp_l18ft"><w lemma="eigth"><abbr>8:<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></abbr></w> Conſtancy <w lemma="ninth"><abbr>9:<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></abbr></w> ffortitude</label></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee"><label n="8+9" rend="left-gutter" corresp="#pp_l18ee">8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Constancy, 9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Fortitude</label></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><label n="8+9" rend="left-gutter" corresp="#pp_l18ae">8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Constancy + 9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Fortitude</label></rdg>
        </app>
      <l n="18">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft" xml:id="pp_l18ft"><seg>And<note type="physical">in left margin, two words enclosed by bracket to right:  “8:<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Conſtancy” and, directly below, “9:<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> &ff;ortitude”</note></seg> Constantly goe on to &ff;ortitude</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" xml:id="pp_l18ee">And Constantly go on to Fortitude.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" xml:id="pp_l18ae">And Constantly go on to Fortitude.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft"><label n="10+11" rend="left-gutter" corresp="#pp_l19ft"><w lemma="tenth"><abbr>10:<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></abbr></w> &ff;aith <w lemma="eleventh"><abbr>11:<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></abbr></w> Hope</label></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee"><label n="10+11" rend="left-gutter" corresp="#pp_l19ee">10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Faith, 11<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Hope</label></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><label n="10+11" rend="left-gutter" corresp="#pp_l19ae">10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Faith + 11<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Hope</label></rdg>
        </app>
      <l n="19">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft" xml:id="pp_l19ft"><seg>By<note type="physical">in left margin, two words enclosed by bracket to right: “10:<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> &ff;aith” and, directly below, “11:<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> “Hope”</note></seg> &ff;aith and Hope wee then Shall mount above</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" xml:id="pp_l19ee">By Faith and Hope we then shall mount above</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" xml:id="pp_l19ae"><seg>By Faith and Hope we then shall mount above<note type="critical">In the Bible, the virtues of Faith, Hope, and Love are addressed together by Apostle Paul in 1 Corinthians 13:13. He identifies that, while they are “three [virtues] that last forever”, it is Love that is “the greatest of them all”, because there is no limit to “its faith, its hope, and its endurance” (<title rend="italic">New English Bible</title> 13: 7-13). Here, Love is not identified as a human Virtue, but instead with the Divine himself; see 1 John 4:8, “God is Love”. Pulter assures us it is “by Faith and Hope” we can reach “eternal Love”.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft"><label n="12" rend="left-gutter" corresp="#pp_l20ft"><w lemma="twelfth"><abbr>12:<hi rend="superscript">th</hi></abbr></w> Charitie</label></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee"><label n="12" rend="left-gutter" corresp="#pp_l20ee">12<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Charity</label></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><label n="12" rend="left-gutter" corresp="#pp_l20ae">12<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Charity</label></rdg>
        </app>
      <l n="20">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft" xml:id="pp_l20ft">Into the Boſome of Eternall Love</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee" xml:id="pp_l20ee">Into the bosom of eternal Love.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae" xml:id="pp_l20ae">Into the bosom of eternal Love.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="21">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Thy Hand dear Alithea least I miſs one Round</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee"><seg>Thy hand<note type="gloss">Give me thy hand</note></seg>, dear Aletheia, lest I miss one <seg>round<note type="gloss">here a step, but generally a link in a chain; the passage of time in cyclical periods; route, course, or circuit habitually used</note></seg>;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>Thy hand<note type="gloss">Pulter directly addresses Aletheia, the  goddess of truth, to guide her methodically through each step so she does not “miss one”. See note to line 7.</note></seg>, dear Aletheia, lest I miss one round;</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="22">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Who Skips but one Precipitates to Ground</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Who skips but one <seg>precipitates<note type="gloss">falls suddenly or violently down</note></seg> to ground.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Who skips but one <seg>precipitates<note type="gloss">falls, plunges; descends steeply or vertically (<title rend="italic">OED</title> 2b). Pulter is contrasting the fate of those who do not religiously follow each godly step with the image of herself and her children carefully “ascend[ing]” these steps of virtue (line 5).</note></seg> to ground.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="23">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Theſe were Got up, but yet you See they &ff;ell</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee"><seg>These<note type="gloss">the people who skipped necessary stages or steps</note></seg> were got up, but yet you see they fell</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>These<note type="gloss">those who ambitiously skip the necessary steps Pulter has outlined</note></seg> were got up, but yet you see they fell</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="24">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Into thoſe Senſuall Wayes which leads to Hell</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Into those <seg>sensual<note type="gloss">involving enjoyment derived from the senses</note></seg> ways, which leads to Hell.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Into those <seg>sensual<note type="gloss">involving gratification of the senses; relating to physical (especially sexual) urges or desires and not the intellect or spirit (<title rend="italic">OED</title> 1)</note></seg> ways which <seg>lead<note type="physical">MS = “leads”</note></seg> to Hell.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">
                <fw type="catch" place="bottom">Some</fw>
            </rdg>
        </app>
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">
                <pb ed="#ft" facs="#f7610_187" n="92r"/>
            </rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">
                <pb ed="#ee" facs="#f7610_187"/>
            </rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">
                <pb ed="#ae" facs="#f7610_187"/>
            </rdg>
        </app>
      <l n="25">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Some that theſe Steps too Tedious are doe Say</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Some that these steps too tedious are do say;</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Some that these steps too tedious are do say;</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="26">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Therefore they Climeber up a nearer way</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Therefore they <seg>climber<note type="gloss">obsolete form of “clamber”: to climb by catching hold with hands and feet; to climb with difficulty and effort</note></seg> up a <seg>nearer<note type="gloss">more direct, immediate, or unimpeded</note></seg> way,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Therefore they <seg>clamber<note type="physical">MS = “Climeber”</note></seg> up a nearer way,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="27">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Leaving &ff;air Truth and her Celestiall Train</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Leaving fair Truth and her celestial train,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Leaving fair Truth and her celestial train,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="28">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Beeing guided by the Spirit as they &ff;ain</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Being guided by the <seg>Spirit<note type="gloss">in Christianity, the Holy Spirit</note></seg> as <seg>they fain<note type="critical">“they” refers to those who are taking shortcuts, and being guided by the Holy Spirit only intermittently, as they are inclined or disposed. Given that “fain” might also imply its homophone “feign” (meaning “to shirk or avoid a duty; dissemble; or believe erroneously”), the line might also suggest that the non-virtuous deceptively imagine their errors to be divinely directed.</note></seg>.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Being guided by the spirit as they <seg>fain<note type="critical">obligated; inclined or disposed to (<title rend="italic">OED</title> 2b, 3a); also could imply the homophone “feign”, meaning to shirk or to avoid one’s duty by false pretense; or to believe erroneously (<title rend="italic">OED</title> 13a, 4b)</note></seg>.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="29">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">But See my Children how they Tumble Down</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">But see, my children, how they tumble down</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">But see, my children, how they tumble down,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="30">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">And for their own <w lemma="chimera"><abbr>Chi<hi rend="overline">m</hi>era</abbr></w> loſe a Crown</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">And for their own <seg>chimera<note type="gloss">unreal creature of the imagination, a term derived from the fabled fire-breathing monster of Greek mythology, who had a lion’s head, goat’s body, and serpent’s tail</note></seg> lose a crown.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">And for their own <seg>chimera<note type="gloss">in Greek mythology, a fabled fire-breathing monster with a lion’s head, a goat’s body, and a serpent’s tail. Milton draws on this creature in his description of Hell and the “Abominable, unutterable” monsters that inhabit it (<title rend="italic">Paradise Lost</title>, 2.624-628)</note></seg> lose a crown.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="31">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Let Grace and Truth then guid us in our Story</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Let Grace and Truth then guide us in our story;</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Let Grace and Truth then guide us in our story;</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="32">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">By theſe degrees wee Shall ariſe to Glory</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">By these <seg>degrees<note type="gloss">steps in an ascent or descent; steps or rungs of a ladder; stages in a process. See also Pulter’s <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="105">View But This Flower (Emblem 40)</ref>: “Dust is but four degrees removed from glory.”</note></seg> we shall arise to glory.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">By these degrees we <seg>shall arise to glory<note type="critical">Pulter’s conclusion to this poem resonates with the conclusion of <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="67">Mighty Nimrod (Emblem 1)</ref>: “Then by his steps I’ll mount his glorious throne”. The change from first pronoun “I’ll” to second pronoun “we”, observes the role Pulter decides to take on as teacher and mediator, while also highlighting her children as the specific audience of her emblems. Hence, it serves to emphasizes the didactic message which the prefatory pair of emblems introduce, as the godly steps of virtue become an extended metaphor for the moral trajectory the collection of emblems embarks on.</note></seg>.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
        <app>
            <rdg type="milestone" wit="#ft">
                <milestone unit="poem" rend="curline-right"/>
            </rdg>
        </app>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
