<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../src/vmachine.xsl"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
  schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI [

  <!ENTITY ff "<!-- ff ligature, representing capital modern day capital F, here represented as 'ff' -->ff">

  ]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mads.pp.119">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>An Old Man, a Stripling, and an Ass (Emblem 54)</title>
        <title type="sub">Poem 119</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Created by</resp>
          <persName>Leah Knight</persName>
          <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoded by</resp>
          <persName>Katherine Poland</persName>
          <persName>Matthew Taylor</persName>
          <persName>Betsy Chou</persName>
          <persName>Emily Andrey</persName>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>IT-project consultation by</resp>
          <persName>Josh Honn</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
          <orgName>Brock University</orgName>
          <orgName>University of Leeds</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <principal>
          <persName/>
        </principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="1"/>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription, transformations, and notes</resp>
          <persName>Leah Knight</persName>
          <orgName>Brock University</orgName>
          <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
        </respStmt>
      </editionStmt>
      <extent/>
      <publicationStmt>
        <ab/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listBibl>
          <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
              <repository>See witness list.</repository>
            </msIdentifier>
          </msDesc>
        </listBibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p/>
      </projectDesc>
      <p>Transcriptions are encoded in TEI(P5)-conformant XML.</p>
      <samplingDecl>
        <p/>
      </samplingDecl>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction>
          <p>Apparent errors are preserved and editorial corrections provided using SIC and CORR tags, but only where the editor conjectures that the original scribe or compositor would have recognized the instance as an error. For example, what according to modern usage is incorrect subject/verb agreement might have been deemed acceptable to a seventeenth-century scribe or compositor. All such instances are treated instead using the ORIG and REG tags. (See below.)</p>
          <p>Corrections and annotations made within the scope of the original document either by its original authors, owners, and/or transcribers are noted using ADD tags. These annotations and may be further explained within NOTE tags, as added by the editors of this digital edition, for display within the apparatus.</p>
        </correction>
        <normalization>
          <p>Original spellings, abbreviations, and orthography are preserved. Where in the manuscripts a character’s status as majuscule or minuscule is ambiguous, the editor has silently chosen one or the other based on context and judgment (i.e., does not register such ambiguity in either the markup or the notes).</p>
        </normalization>
        <quotation>
          <p>Original quotation marks, if any, are preserved.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation>
          <p>Original hyphenation is preserved.</p>
        </hyphenation>
      </editorialDecl>
      <charDecl>
        <!-- Ligature combinations for which there are currently no corresponding Unicode codepoints. -->
        <glyph xml:id="ffllig">
          <glyphName>Handwritten 'ff' ligature, used in handwriting to represent modern F</glyphName>
        </glyph>
      </charDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="DDC22">
          <bibl>
            <title>Dewey Decimal Classification</title>
            <edition/>
            <publisher/>
            <pubPlace/>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-GB">British English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <!-- dewey decimal system class code 821: English Poetry -->
        <classCode scheme="DDC22">821</classCode>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
    <!-- List of all images associated with this document -->
    <graphic url="./document_images/7610_263.jpg" xml:id="f7610_263"/>
    <graphic url="./document_images/7610_264.jpg" xml:id="f7610_264"/>
  </facsimile>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="ft">Transcription of manuscript: By <persName xml:id="lknight">Leah Knight</persName> and <persName xml:id="wwall">Wendy Wall</persName>.</witness>
          <witness xml:id="ee">Elemental edition: By <persName>Leah Knight</persName> and <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>.</witness>
          <witness xml:id="ae">Amplified edition: By <persName>Anna-Rose Shack</persName> and <persName>Kristine Johanson</persName>.</witness>
        </listWit>
      </div>
    </front>

    <body>

      <!-- Each page break should be represented wih a block like this with the correct facs reference-->
      <app>
        <rdg wit="#ft">
          <pb ed="#ft" facs="#f7610_263" n="130r"/>
        </rdg>
        <rdg wit="#ee">
          <pb ed="#ee" facs="#f7610_263"/>
        </rdg>
        <rdg wit="#ae">
          <pb ed="#ae" facs="#f7610_263"/>
        </rdg>
      </app>

      <head>
        <app type="title">
          <rdg wit="#ft"><fw facs="#f7610_069" type="pageNum" place="margin-topright">PG#</fw>[Emblem 54]</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">An Old Man, a Stripling, and an Ass<lb/>(Emblem 54)</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">An Old Man, a Stripling, and an Ass</rdg>
        </app>
        <app type="editorialnote">
          <rdg wit="#ft">
            <note type="editorialnote">In these transcriptions we preserve as many details of the original material, textual, and graphic properties of Hester Pulter’s manuscript verse as we have found practical. Whenever possible, for instance, original spelling, punctuation, capitalization, lineation, insertions, deletions, alterations, spacing between words and lines, and indentation are all maintained; abbreviations and brevigraphs are not expanded; and superscript and subscript representations are retained. <ref target="//pulterproject.northwestern.edu/about-project-conventions.html#top" type="new-window-url">See full conventions for the transcriptions here.</ref></note>
          </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">
            <note type="editorialnote">The aim of the elemental edition is to make the poems accessible to the largest variety of readers, which involves modernizing spelling and punctuation as well as adding basic glosses. Spelling and punctuation reflect current standard American usage; punctuation highlights syntax which might otherwise be obscure. Outmoded but still familiar word forms (“thou,” “‘tis,” “hold’st”) are not modernized, and we do not modernize grammar when the sense remains legible. After a brief headnote aimed at offering a “way in” to the poem’s unique qualities and connections with other verse by Pulter or her contemporaries, the edition features a minimum of notes and interpretative framing to allow more immediate engagement with the poem. Glosses clarify synonyms or showcase various possible meanings in Pulter’s time. Other notes identify named people and places or clarify obscure material. We rely (without citation) primarily on the Oxford English Dictionary (OED), the Oxford Reference database, and the King James Version (KJV) of the Bible. When we rely on Alice Eardley’s edition of Pulter’s work, we cite her text generally (“Eardley”); other sources are cited in full. The result is an edition we consider a springboard for further work on Pulter’s poetry. <ref target="//pulterproject.northwestern.edu/about-project-conventions.html#elemental-edition" type="new-window-url">See full conventions for this edition here.</ref></note></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">
              <note type="editorialnote"><p>We offer here a modernized edition of this emblem in order to facilitate engagement with the text. Reflecting the manuscript’s origins, we use contemporary British spelling. Capitalization has been regularized; we have expanded thorns and ampersands; we have included possessive apostrophes where necessary. With punctuation we have tried to capture the way the poem creates momentum through its relative absence of punctuation by restricting our interventions to commas and full stops.</p><p>Due to a scribal error, there is no Emblem 18 in Pulter’s manuscript: Emblem 17 is followed by Emblem 19. Therefore, as The Pulter Project retains the numbering used in the manuscript (and in Alice Eardley’s edition), Emblem 54 is in fact the fifty-third and final emblem.</p></note>
          </rdg>
        </app>
        <app type="headnote">
          <rdg wit="#ee">
              <note type="headnote">You can’t please all of the people all of the time: Pulter transforms that truism into both political history and prophecy in a poem which begins as a light-hearted fable before taking a darkly murderous turn. The villain here is the instability and inconstancy of public opinion, figured commonly as a multi-headed Hydra. Pulter uses the Aesopian tale of how people mercilessly mock any choice made by a man riding through town to threaten Oliver Cromwell and those who came to power with him in the aftermath of the civil war: Cromwell will undoubtedly be hoisted on his own petard and suffer the violent fates of others in history who relied on popular acclamation to overthrow sovereignty.</note>
          </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">
            <note type="headnote"> <p>In this emblem, an old man, a young boy, and an ass perform various configurations of walking, riding and carrying each other as an observing crowd mocks their progress. The crowd enacts judgment and attempts to influence the travelers’ behavior by deploying laughter to publicly shame them. In so doing, this laughing community, to use the term mobilized by Werner Röcke and Hans Rudolf Velten (2005), operates as a paradigm of inclusion and exclusion: a means by which to solidify the laughing group’s boundaries and norms by drawing attention to those deemed to have transgressed. At the same time, the poem also highlights how the notion of inclusivity itself is fickle, its boundary constantly redefined by the whims of the crowd, Pulter’s “Hydrian monstrosity” (25) (see Victoria Burke's curation <ref type="pp-curation-ref" target="/poems/ee/aurora-1/#the-many-headed-hydra">The Many-Headed Hydra</ref>). (In Greek mythology, the Hydra was a many-headed monster whose heads reproduced each time one was cut off; Herakles had to kill it as one of his labors.)</p><p>The old man is at pains to avoid public censure. He risks being perceived as too proud or merciless towards the child for making him walk beside the ass while he rides; too easily manipulated by the same child for letting the child ride the ass in his place; or too cruel towards his ass for forcing the animal to bear their dual weight. Even when neither ride the ass or when they both carry the animal, they still fail to appease the onlookers. The old man and his companions are caught in a net of shifting demands that reinforces the “giddy” (28) behavior of the crowd.</p><p>As such, while the crowd’s uproarious mirth at the sight of the travelers dramatizes Pulter’s critique of the old man and his companions (by contorting yourself to please others you end up pleasing no one) she also finds fault with the crowd itself. This roaring “Hydrian monstrosity” (25), as noted above, embodies the fickle instability of public opinion. In the face of relentless pressure, the old man abandons all hope of pleasing the onlooking crowd and sadly flings his ass into the sea. Following his spectacular failure to assert self-sovereignty, the old man’s killing of his ass offers an expedient if disappointing way out of his predicament.</p><p>It is at this point that Pulter shifts to a prophetic mode, making a series of allusions to deposed rulers from antiquity and the Middle Ages to suggest that Oliver Cromwell’s reliance on populist support will lead to his downfall. Ultimately, this emblem suggests that those who rely on “Hydra’s love” (33)—popular opinion—to determine their actions will suffer an ignominious end.</p><p>While the precise source of Pulter’s emblem remains unclear, it is evident that the story of the old man, the boy, and the ass circulated across early modern Europe. Blague’s Schole of Wise Conceytes (London, 1572) includes a translation of Poggio Bracciolini’s (also known as Poggio Fiorentino) fable of this triumvirate (Christian 2012); a sixteenth-century, hand-colored, Dutch woodcut print by Cornelis Anthonisz (1509–1553) exists with this fable inscribed beneath associated images; and William Warner’s Albions England, first published in 1586, offers a verse form in rhyming couplets. It is this text’s 1612 edition that Alice Eardley (2014) points to as an alternative version of the emblem and which to us seems the likeliest candidate as Pulter’s source. Additionally, this fable has been mischaracterized as “Aesopian” or “pseudo-Aesopian” (Knight and Wall, Elemental Edition Headnote; Christian 385): this tale is not only absent from Aesop’s fables, but in those tales the animals are the main protagonists, and it is through their interaction with others (human or animal) that they teach a lesson to the reader. Here, the ass has no agency, it doesn’t speak and it possesses no character.</p>
                  <p><hi rend="bold"></hi>Citations</p>
                  <p><bibl>Christian, Stefan Graham. “The Poems of Lady Hester Pulter (1605?–1678): An Annotated Edition.” PhD diss., University of Massachusetts Amherst, 2012. ProQuest Dissertations Publishing (3545910).</bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl>Eardley, Alice. <title rend="italic">Poems, Emblems, and The Unfortunate Florinda.</title> By Hester Pulter. Toronto: Iter and Centre for Reformation and Renaissance Studies, 2014.</bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl>Knight, Leah and Wendy Wall, eds. “An Old Man, a Stripling, and an Ass,” by Hester Pulter. (Poem 119, Elemental Edition). In <title rend="italic"> The Pulter Project: Poet in the Making,</title> edited by Leah Knight and Wendy Wall, 2018.</bibl></p>
                  <p> <bibl>Röcke, Werner and Hans Rudolf Velten. <title rend="italic"> Lachgemeinschaften: Kulturelle Inszenierungen und soziale Wirkungen von Gelächter im Mittelalter und in der Frühen Neuzeit.</title> De Gruyter, 2005.</bibl></p>
              </note>
          </rdg>
        </app>
      </head>

      <l n="1">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft"><seg>An<note type="physical">Unlike surrounding poems in the “Emblems” section, no number precedes this poem.</note></seg> old Man through a Town did often paſs</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">An old man through a town did often pass;</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">An old man through a town did often pass,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="2">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">With him a pretty Stripling and an Aſs</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">With him, a pretty <seg>stripling<note type="gloss">a youth</note></seg> and an ass.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">With him a pretty <seg>stripling <note type ="gloss">stripling: a youth, with connotations of coming of age. The  OED suggests that the word derives from “a strip”, meaning “one whose figure is not yet filled out.”<p><bibl>“stripling, n.” OED Online, Oxford University Press, March 2023, www.oed.com/view/Entry/191697. Accessed 5 April 2023.</bibl></p></note></seg> and an ass.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="3">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">The Man did Ride, the Boy was Pedester</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">The man did ride; the boy was <seg>pedester<note type="gloss">on foot</note></seg>,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>The <note type="physical">The: Throughout the manuscript, the scribe has added a superscript e to the end of many words ending in “e” in the text.</note></seg> man did ride, the boy was <seg>pedester <note type="gloss"> pedester: walking; on foot; pedestrian.</note> </seg>,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="4">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">As fit it was, he wait upon his Master</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee"><seg>As fit it was, he wait upon his master<note type="gloss">since it was suitable for him to serve his master</note></seg>.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><seg> As fit as it was <note type="gloss">As fit it was: as was fitting. Importantly here, the speaker notes that the initial arrangement mirrors conventional ideas about hierarchy and respect for old age over youth.  </note></seg>,he wait upon his master.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="5">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">At this the people Laughed out alowd</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">At this, the people laughéd out aloud,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">At this the people <seg>laughéd <note type="gloss"> laughéd: The accent in the word “laughéd” continues the pentameter that is established in the poem.</note></seg><seg>out loud<note type="critical"> The people laughed out aloud: This is the first of four times across the poem where Pulter notes that the crowd is explicitly laughing. By including laughter Pulter chooses to depict the crowd as both mocking the trio and treating them as entertainment.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="6">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Saying the Man was mercieles or proud</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Saying the man was merciless or proud</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>Saying the man was merciless or proud<note type="critical"> Merciless or proud: The description of the man as merciless or proud suggests a tyrannical individual; the people seek to shame the man by suggesting explicitly that he is sinful. The critique of pride is a common theme in Pulter’s emblems (see for example, <ref type = "pp-poem-ref" corresp="79">“The Porcupine” (Emblem 13)</ref>or <ref type= "pp-poem-ref" corresp="106">“The Ostrich” (Emblem 41).</ref></note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="7">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">To let the pretty Child goe Swetting by</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">To let the pretty child go sweating by,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">To let the pretty child go sweating by</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="8">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Whils’t hee Rode Ambling in his Majestie</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Whilst he rode, ambling in his majesty.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Whilst he rode <seg>ambling<note type="gloss"> ambling: smooth, easy or leisurely. The OED indicates that this verb particularly relates to the pace of a quadruped (e.g., a horse).<p><bibl>“amble, v.” OED Online, Oxford University Press, March 2023, www.oed.com/view/Entry/6181. Accessed 5 April 2023.</bibl></p></note></seg><seg>in his majesty.<note type ="critical">  Majesty: Given the poem’s political valences, this is a significant noun. Considering that majesty is associated with monarchy, the tone may be understood as sarcastic or ironic; the use of the word “majesty” seems to be the speaker ventriloquizing the crowd, taking on the crowd’s judgment of the old man. When married with the “merciless and proud” description, this again implies a tyrannical strain in this old man. “Majesty” arriving on an ass also possesses latent imagery of Jesus’s arrival in Jerusalem on a donkey, an act similarly disruptive but which was much more positively received by the public. Both situations invite a questioning of hierarchy and power.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="9">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">The boy Rode next the Man did trudg a foot</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee"><seg>The boy rode next<note type="gloss">That is, the man dismounted and the boy mounted the horse.</note></seg>; the man did trudge afoot:</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>The boy rode next, the man did trudge<note type = "gloss"> Trudge: This evocative contrast with “ambling” (line 8) emphasizes the sluggish, weary movement of the man on foot. Interestingly, this moment also suggests some sympathy on the speaker’s part for the old man.</note></seg>afoot.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="10">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">But then the people did Soe laugh and Shout</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">But then, the people did so laugh and shout</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">But then the people did so laugh and shout</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="11">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Becauſe the Man did favour Soe the Lad</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Because the man did favor so the lad</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>Because the man did favour<note type = "critical">Favour: Notably, unlike with the child, the people are not concerned about the welfare of the man, but that there is a hierarchical boundary crossed: that the child should be so “favour[ed]” and thus implicitly spoiled.</note></seg>so the lad</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="12">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">To goe a foot whilst hee Rode on his Pad</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">To go afoot whilst he rode on his <seg>pad<note type="gloss">usually, a riding horse; here, the ass; alternatively, a saddle or saddle pad</note></seg>.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>To go afoot whilst he rode on his pad.<note type="gloss">Pad: Pulter characterizes the ass as a saddle horse.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="13">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Next time this poor Man through <w lemma="the"><abbr>y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi></abbr></w> Town did Paſs</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Next time this poor man through the town did pass,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><seg> Next time this poor<note type = "gloss"> poor: The speaker’s sympathy, suggested at line 9, is made explicit here and continues with the repetition of “poor” at line 24.</note></seg>man through the town did pass,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="14">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">The Man and Boy got both upon the Aſs</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">The man and boy got both upon the ass;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">The man and boy got both up on the ass.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="15">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">But then the People bad him lite for Shame</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">But then the people bade him <seg>light, for shame<note type="gloss">“light” as in alight or dismount; “for shame” ventriloquizes the people’s admonition, as does the next line.</note></seg>;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><seg> But then the people bade him light<note type = "gloss">  bade him light: alight, i.e., the people instructed the man to dismount. </note></seg><seg>for shame,<note type="gloss"> for shame: Again, the speaker ventriloquizes the crowd, which shames the old man.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="16">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Hee’d Spoyl the Aſs or make him Sick or Lame</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">He’d <seg>spoil<note type="gloss">injure</note></seg> the ass, or make him sick, or lame.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>He’d spoil<note type="gloss"> spoil: injure, thus rendering the ass less useful.</note></seg>the ass or make him sick or lame.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="17">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Next time beſide the Aſs they both did walk</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Next time, beside the ass they both did walk;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Next time beside the ass they both did walk,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="18">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">But then they were the Town and Countreys talk</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">But then they were the town and county’s talk.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>But then they were the town and country’s<note type="critical">town and country’s: The most recent configuration of the travelers is so radical that the people’s censure spreads beyond the town to the countryside. “Country” could also signal the nation.</note></seg>talk.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="19">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">The people laughd and made the Welken Ring</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">The people laughed and <seg>made the welkin ring<note type="gloss">an expression indicative of a loud noise (with “welkin” meaning the sky)</note></seg>;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>The people laughed and made the welkin ring,<note type="gloss"> laughed and made the welkin ring: That this laughter is described as reaching the sky (i.e., “the welkin”) develops the idea that censure is growing exponentially.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="20">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Children their &ff;olly up and down did Sing</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Children their folly up and down did sing.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>Children their folly up and down did sing.<note type = "critical"> sing: Within the interior world of the emblem, the story of the foolish traveling companions is related through children’s songs. Again, the emblem repeats the description of ridicule spreading through space and becoming even something of lore, perhaps, immortalized in song. Notably, the emblem genre itself was, in seventeenth-century England, evolving into a form particularly aimed at children.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="21">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Once more the Man Reſolvd the Road to paſs</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Once more the man resolved the road to pass,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Once more the man resolved the load to pass</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="22">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">And then the Youth and hee did bear the Aſs</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">And then the youth and he did <seg>bear<note type="gloss">carry</note></seg> the ass,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>And then the youth and he did bear<note type="gloss"> bear: To carry, with the implication that the load is particularly heavy and cumbersome.</note></seg>the ass,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">
                <fw type="catch" place="bottom">at</fw>
            </rdg>
        </app>
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">
                <pb ed="#ft" facs="#f7610_264" n="130v"/>
            </rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">
                <pb ed="#ee" facs="#f7610_264"/>
            </rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">
                <pb ed="#ae" facs="#f7610_264"/>
            </rdg>
        </app>

      <l n="23">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">At which the people did Soe laugh &amp; Rore</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">At which the people did so laugh and roar</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>At which the people did so laugh and roar<note type="critical"> laugh and roar: This bestial depiction of laughter not only aligns the crowd with animal behavior but foreshadows Pulter’s scathing description of it as a Hydrian monstrosity.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="24">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">That the poor Man would never more explore</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">That the poor man would ne’er more <seg>explore<note type="gloss">attempt</note></seg></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">That the poor man would never more explore</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="25">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">The Hidrian monſtossity to pleaſe</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">The <seg>Hydrian monstrosity<note type="gloss">The Hydra was the many-headed serpent in classical mythology that could grow additional heads when one was cut off; the adjective can be used to refer to anything similarly destructive, multi-headed, or hard to kill.</note></seg> to please,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>The Hydrian monstrosity<note type = "critical"> Hydrian monstrosity: The crowd is like the Hydra not because they are unruly per se (as Eardley suggests), but because each attempt to appease an opinion only spurs more opinions (just as cutting off a hydra’s heads only causes more to grow in their place), making satisfaction impossible.</note></seg> to please,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="26">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">But Sadly <hi rend="subscript">^</hi><hi rend="superscript">flung</hi> his Aſs into the Seas</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">But sadly flung his ass into the seas.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>But sadly<note type = "critical"> sadly: Once more, Pulter’s speaker offers a pitying note that contrasts with the violent mockery of the crowd; she offers a sympathetic description of the old man’s state of mind, the bearing this has on his decision to drown his ass, and the manner in which this action is performed. </note></seg><seg>flung<note type="physical"> flung: “Flung” is inserted above the line. This may be Pulter’s own correction.</note></seg>his ass into the seas.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="27">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">By this you See they doe themſelvs delude</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">By this you see they do themselves delude</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">By this you see they do themselves delude</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="28">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">That think to pleas the giddy multitude</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">That think to please the <seg>giddy<note type="gloss">flighty, inconstant; whirling with bewildering speed</note></seg> multitude.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>That think to please the giddy multitude.<note type = "critical"> giddy multitude: Once again Pulter emphasizes both the inconstancy and the enormity of the crowd and suggests the inability to control it.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="29">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Andronicus did make this Story good</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee"><seg>Andronicus<note type="gloss">Andronicus had his joint emperor of Greece, Alexius, killed; the people then revolted against and tortured Andronicus.</note></seg> did make this story good;</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>Andronicus<note type="gloss"> Andronicus: In 1182, during the Byzantine Empire’s Comnenus dynasty, Andronicus (c.1118-1185) seized power and subsequently murdered the young Emperor Alexius II (1169-1183) and his regent mother, Maria of Antioch (c. 1140s-1182/3). Andronicus was a cousin of Alexius II’s father, Emperor Manuel I (1118-80). Widely regarded as a tyrant who inaugurated a reign of terror, the populace ultimately turned against Andronicus. He was tortured to death by a mob in Constantinople in 1185.</note></seg>did make this story good,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="30">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Even hee <w lemma="that"><abbr>y:<hi rend="superscript">t</hi></abbr></w> Shed his Royall Soverraigns blood</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Even he that shed his royal sovereign’s blood,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>Even he that shed his royal sovereign’s blood.<note type="critical"> Even he that shed his royal sovereign’s blood: This is an ambiguous line in the manuscript. While other editors (Knight and Wall) have added punctuation to make the line modify “Sejanus”, historically Sejanus did not murder his emperor as Andronicus did. We read the line as an emphatic repetition of the previous line. Our choice also balances out the speaker’s attention to these two historical examples: two lines each are devoted to Andronicus and Sejanus.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="31">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Sejanus Soe by popular breath up born</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee"><seg>Sejanus<note type="gloss">an influential officer in ancient Rome who was arrested and executed (with his body was torn to pieces by the crowd) on suspicion of intent to kill the emperor Tiberius</note></seg>, so by pop’lar breath up borne,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>Sejanus<note type="critical"> Sejanus: While it is unlikely that Pulter would have known Ben Johnson’s Sejanus (1603/1605), she demonstrates her humanist education and familiarity with humanist literary practice in her reference to the historical personage Lucius Aelius Sejanus (20 BC - AD 31), a soldier from an eminent political family in ancient Rome. He was suspected of plotting to overthrow Emperor Tiberius (42 BC - AD 37) and consequently was torn to pieces by a bloodthirsty crowd loyal to the emperor. As Christian notes in his edition of the poems, Sejanus’ “story would have been familiar to Pulter from the accounts of Tacitus, Suetonius, and Juvenal; his fate was proverbial for the consequences of ambition and pride” (386).</note></seg><seg>so by popular breath<note type="critical"> by popular breath: Like the roaring crowd in this emblem, Sejanus’ fate is sealed by popular opinion which, as the image of “breath” suggests, is insubstantial. In early modern literature, the people’s breath was often interpreted as stinking and disgusting.</note></seg>up born</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="32">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">By Barrierus was in peeces Torn</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">By <seg>Briareus<note type="gloss">The manuscript reads “Barrierus,” which Eardley interprets as Briareus, a monster in ancient Greek mythology with a hundred arms and fifty heads.</note></seg> was in pieces torn.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>By Barrierus<note type ="gloss"> Barrierus: Previous editors concur that Barrierus is a reference to Briareaus, one of the Hekatoncheires found in ancient Greek mythology. With a hundred arms and fifty heads, this gargantuan monster, along with his two brothers, Cottes and Gyges, was often associated with the destructive power of natural elements.</note></seg><seg> was in pieces torn.<note type="critical"> in pieces torn: Here Barrierus represents a monstrous crowd that tears Sejanus into pieces.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="33">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Soe Some alive the Hidras love will Rue</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">So <seg>some alive<note type="gloss">Oliver Cromwell and those who came to power in his regime, supported by popular opinion</note></seg> the Hydra’s love will rue</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>So some alive the Hydra’s love will rue<note type ="critical"> So some alive the Hydra’s love will rue: This is the beginning in a shift of the moral Pulter has been offering; first, the old man is likened to those who delude themselves hoping to please the multitude; then, those who have the love of the multitude (i.e., who are no longer just trying to obtain its love) will “rue” this situation as they will receive what is owed to them. Indeed, she suggests that possessing the people’s favor is itself worthy of censure.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="34">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">When as to them they give to theſe their due</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee"><seg>Whenas<note type="gloss">When</note></seg> <seg>to them they give to these their due<note type="gloss">When people rely on popular opinion (referred to in the line above as the “Hydra’s love”); to give someone their due is to pay respect to them.</note></seg>.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>When as to them they give to these their due.<note type="critical"> give to these their due: To give someone their due is to give them what is owed to them for their actions. Here Pulter suggests that there is now something negative owed, “due” to those (“them” / “these”) who possess the Hydra’s/people’s love.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="35">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">&ff;or certainly ’twill one day come to paſs</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">For certainly ’twill one day come to pass</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>For certainly ’twill one day come to pass<note type = "critical"> For certainly ’twill one day come to pass: Pulter shifts into a prophetic mode, drawing on historical example and common wisdom.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="36">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">They’l have the death and Buriall of this <seg>Aſs<note type="physical">poem followed by blank page</note></seg></rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">They’ll have the death and burial of <seg>this ass<note type="gloss">Cromwell, whom the speaker hopes will be rejected and destroyed like the ass in the fable</note></seg>.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>They’ll have the death and burial of this ass.<note type="critical"> They’ll have the death and burial of this ass: Pulter’s shift at the end of the poem surprisingly turns Cromwell into the ass. Her derision of Cromwell repeats ideas present in e.g. <ref type = "pp-poem-ref" corresp="84">Emblem 19</ref>, where she laments the Royalists’ moral failings and Cromwell’s association with commoners: “had not lords in noble breeding failed, / Tinkers and cobblers never had prevailed” (ll.30-1). As Laura Longer Knoppers has shown, Royalist satire associated Cromwell with such “mechanicals” and popular opinion by depicting him as a brewer despite his status as a gentleman (2000). In transforming Cromwell into the ass, Pulter renders guilty what in the poem is in fact an innocent animal; the ass becomes the symbol of the negative, detrimental, irrational and violent ends of wanting to please everyone all the time.<p><bibl>Knoppers, Laura Longer. “‘Sing Old Noll the Brewer’: Royalist Satire and Social Inversion, 1648–64.” The Seventeenth Century, vol. 15, no. 1, 2000, pp. 32–52, https://doi.org/10.1080/0268117X.2000.10555466</bibl></p></note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
