<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../src/vmachine.xsl"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
  schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI [

  <!ENTITY ff "<!-- ff ligature, representing capital modern day capital F, here represented as 'ff' -->ff">

  ]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mads.pp.83">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The Piper of Hamelin (Emblem 17)</title>
        <title type="sub">Poem 83</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Created by</resp>
          <persName>Leah Knight</persName>
          <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoded by</resp>
          <persName>Katherine Poland</persName>
          <persName>Matthew Taylor</persName>
          <persName>Betsy Chou</persName>
          <persName>Emily Andrey</persName>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>IT-project consultation by</resp>
          <persName>Josh Honn</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
          <orgName>Brock University</orgName>
          <orgName>University of Leeds</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <principal>
          <persName/>
        </principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="1"/>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription, transformations, and notes</resp>
          <persName>Leah Knight</persName>
          <orgName>Brock University</orgName>
          <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
        </respStmt>
      </editionStmt>
      <extent/>
      <publicationStmt>
        <ab/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listBibl>
          <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
              <repository>See witness list.</repository>
            </msIdentifier>
          </msDesc>
        </listBibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p/>
      </projectDesc>
      <p>Transcriptions are encoded in TEI(P5)-conformant XML.</p>
      <samplingDecl>
        <p/>
      </samplingDecl>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction>
          <p>Apparent errors are preserved and editorial corrections provided using SIC and CORR tags, but only where the editor conjectures that the original scribe or compositor would have recognized the instance as an error. For example, what according to modern usage is incorrect subject/verb agreement might have been deemed acceptable to a seventeenth-century scribe or compositor. All such instances are treated instead using the ORIG and REG tags. (See below.)</p>
          <p>Corrections and annotations made within the scope of the original document either by its original authors, owners, and/or transcribers are noted using ADD tags. These annotations and may be further explained within NOTE tags, as added by the editors of this digital edition, for display within the apparatus.</p>
        </correction>
        <normalization>
          <p>Original spellings, abbreviations, and orthography are preserved. Where in the manuscripts a character's status as majuscule or minuscule is ambiguous, the editor has silently chosen one or the other based on context and judgment (i.e., does not register such ambiguity in either the markup or the notes).</p>
        </normalization>
        <quotation>
          <p>Original quotation marks, if any, are preserved.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation>
          <p>Original hyphenation is preserved.</p>
        </hyphenation>
      </editorialDecl>
      <charDecl>
        <!-- Ligature combinations for which there are currently no corresponding Unicode codepoints. -->
        <glyph xml:id="ffllig">
          <glyphName>Handwritten 'ff' ligature, used in handwriting to represent modern F</glyphName>
        </glyph>
      </charDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="DDC22">
          <bibl>
            <title>Dewey Decimal Classification</title>
            <edition/>
            <publisher/>
            <pubPlace/>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-GB">British English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <!-- dewey decimal system class code 821: English Poetry -->
        <classCode scheme="DDC22">821</classCode>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
    <!-- List of all images associated with this document -->
    <graphic url="./document_images/7610_206.jpg" xml:id="f7610_206"/>
    <graphic url="./document_images/7610_207.jpg" xml:id="f7610_207"/>
  </facsimile>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="ft">Transcription of manuscript: By <persName xml:id="lknight">Leah Knight</persName> and <persName xml:id="wwall">Wendy Wall</persName>.</witness>
          <witness xml:id="ee">Elemental edition: By <persName>Leah Knight</persName> and <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>.</witness>
<!--         <witness xml:id="ae">Amplified edition: By <persName>Thomas Ward</persName>.</witness>-->
        </listWit>
      </div>
    </front>

    <body>

      <!-- Each page break should be represented with a block like this with the correct facs reference-->
      <app>
        <rdg wit="#ft">
          <pb ed="#ft" facs="#f7610_206" n="101v"/>
        </rdg>
        <rdg wit="#ee">
          <pb ed="#ee" facs="#f7610_206"/>
        </rdg>
        <rdg wit="#ae">
          <pb ed="#ae" facs="#f7610_206"/>
        </rdg>
      </app>

      <head>
        <app type="title">
          <rdg wit="#ft"><fw facs="#f7610_206" type="pageNum" place="margin-topright">17</fw>[Emblem 17]</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">The Piper of Hamelin<lb/>(Emblem 17)</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Emblem 17</rdg>
        </app>
        <app type="editorialnote">
          <rdg wit="#ft">
            <note type="editorialnote">In these transcriptions we preserve as many details of the original material, textual, and graphic properties of Hester Pulter’s manuscript verse as we have found practical. Whenever possible, for instance, original spelling, punctuation, capitalization, lineation, insertions, deletions, alterations, spacing between words and lines, and indentation are all maintained; abbreviations and brevigraphs are not expanded; and superscript and subscript representations are retained. <ref target="http://pulterproject.northwestern.edu/about-project-conventions.html#top" type="new-window-url">See full conventions for the transcriptions here.</ref></note>
          </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">
            <note type="editorialnote">The aim of the elemental edition is to make the poems accessible to the largest variety of readers, which involves modernizing spelling and punctuation as well as adding basic glosses. Spelling and punctuation reflect current standard American usage; punctuation highlights syntax which might otherwise be obscure. Outmoded but still familiar word forms (“thou,” “‘tis,” “hold’st”) are not modernized, and we do not modernize grammar when the sense remains legible. After a brief headnote aimed at offering a “way in” to the poem’s unique qualities and connections with other verse by Pulter or her contemporaries, the edition features a minimum of notes and interpretative framing to allow more immediate engagement with the poem. Glosses clarify synonyms or showcase various possible meanings in Pulter’s time. Other notes identify named people and places or clarify obscure material. We rely (without citation) primarily on the Oxford English Dictionary (OED), the Oxford Reference database, and the King James Version (KJV) of the Bible. When we rely on Alice Eardley’s edition of Pulter’s work, we cite her text generally (“Eardley”); other sources are cited in full. The result is an edition we consider a springboard for further work on Pulter’s poetry. <ref target="http://pulterproject.northwestern.edu/about-project-conventions.html#elemental-edition" type="new-window-url">See full conventions for this edition here.</ref></note></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">
            <note type="editorialnote">
              <p>For this edition I have chosen to modernize spelling for accessibility, with two exceptions: for the modern place-name “Hamelin” I have retained the manuscript’s “Hamelle” (line 13) as the form that appeared most commonly in printed sources from the seventeenth century, and for “talisman” I have opted for the manuscript’s “Telesma” (line 27) out of respect for a possible irony the more etymologically sensitive spelling of that word might activate. In general, I have added some light punctuation for clarity but have refrained from doing so in instances where such clarity would come at the cost of obscuring an interesting ambiguity (as in the case of line 6). My notes and headnote are informed by the same errant principle I take to be driving the poem’s own – often ironic – relationship to its emblematic subject, highlighting the poem’s shifting moralizing framework by drawing particular attention to repeated and contradictory addresses to the reader, grammatical ambiguities, and features of the material text that threaten (or promise) to lead readers astray. Additionally, I have attempted to place Emblem 17 in the context of other versions of the Pied Piper story in order to show Pulter’s particular engagement with a popular legend just at the moment when it was beginning to emerge into the popular English consciousness through printed sources.</p>
              <p>I should say something about an important omission from this edition: to my surprise, given my own scholarly interest in early modern musical discourses, I found I had nothing much to say about the piper’s Orphic powers over the rats and the children in Pulter’s telling. I attribute this omission to the way the poem seems deliberately to avoid the possibility of magical music when it seeks alternative explanations for how the piper performed his feat in lines 24-29. However, readers who are interested in considering the poem in this light (perhaps for a future Amplified Edition) might consult the work of Linda Phyllis Austern, Penelope Gouk, Gary Tomlinson, and others who discuss early modern magical and natural philosophical theories of music’s power over human and animal realms.</p>
            </note>
          </rdg>
        </app>
        <app type="headnote">
          <rdg wit="#ee">
              <note type="headnote">What begins as a poem heralding God’s ability to use animals to punish errant humans dramatically changes into a fable in which animal control is just a commercial venture gone bad. This poem briefly surveys a host of divine plagues, powered by the weapons of mass destruction that are God’s creatures: rabbits, moles, frogs, snakes, insects (even <hi rend="italic">lice</hi>!), as well as that most notorious plague beast, the rat—which leads to a retelling of the still-familiar story of the pied piper of Hamelin kidnapping an entire town’s children when the town failed to pay him for clearing the rats. No mere horror story about stranger danger, as it has become for children and parents both today, this is Pulter’s unexpected morality tale about the problems of avarice and the importance of keeping one’s word. Grief for lost children, which Pulter represents so poignantly and personally elsewhere in her poems, is here just punishment for dishonorable action.</note>
          </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">
            <note type="headnote">
              <p>Emblem 17 tells the familiar story of the Pied Piper of Hamelin (or Hamelle, as Hester Pulter and her contemporaries tended to say), in which a mysterious stranger lures away the town’s children in order to punish the townspeople for greedily withholding the payment they owe him for ridding the town of rats. In connecting the natural world – specifically vermin – with cosmic or divine justice, the poem recalls several other of Pulter’s emblem poems in which even the lowliest and most contemptible parts of Creation are given a providential purpose. <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="111">The Bishop and the Rats (Emblem 46)</ref>, for example, narrates how the Bishop of Mainz was consumed by rats as punishment for burning a group of starving peasants during a grain shortage, and gives numerous examples of how “each despiséd reptile or insect / He [i.e. God] can empower, when we his laws neglect.” Along similar lines, Emblem 17 opens with a series of generalization about how God “will not neglect,” or scorn, to use even “reptile[s] or insect[s] / Or basest animal[s]” to inflict total destruction on a disobedient people, and the examples that follow – all taken from a section of Pliny’s <title rend="italic">Natural History</title> dealing with the “much hurt and dammage [that] hath ben known to come from small contemptible creatures, which otherwise are of no reckoning and account” – suggest that we are in for a lecture on how God uses base means to humble the proud.<seg>1<note type="gloss"><bibl>C. Plinius Secundus, <title rend="italic">The Historie of the World</title>. Trans. Philemon Holland (London, 1601), p. 212.</bibl></note></seg></p>
              <p>However, the poem does not make good on its initial promise. Unlike the “contemptible creatures” that bring proud civilizations and tyrannical rulers to their knees, the rats of Hamelle actually end up having nothing to do with divine punishment – or, if they do, the initial sin that incurred such punishment is never identified. The “vermin” are simply introduced as a “rout” afflicting the town, so that, like the townspeople, readers might well “stand in doubt” as to whether the infestation arose from supernatural or merely natural causes. Instead of a moral about God’s punishment through base means, the poem abruptly shifts in line 20 with the announcement of a new ostensible moral, for which nothing in the poem so far has prepared us: “The fruits of curséd avarice now see.” Ironically, within this new moralizing frame, the rats serve not as the punishment for sin but, rather, its occasion, when the stingy townspeople notoriously rip off the piper after he has lured the pests to their death in the river Weser. But even this new moral does not fully survive until the end of the poem. Omitting a detail from her source (Richard Verstegan’s <title rend="italic">A Restitution of Decayed Intelligence</title> [1605]), in which the townspeople’s miserliness is foregrounded when they attempt to offer the piper “far less then hee lookt for,” the poem ends with yet another explicitly moralizing pronouncement – “Now see how breach of promise is accursed” – shifting the focus once again, this time away from the specific vice of avarice and toward the more general sin of bad faith.<seg>2<note type="gloss"><bibl>Richard Verstegan, <title rend="italic">A Restitution of Decayed Intelligence</title> (London, 1605), p. 85.</bibl></note></seg> Having been lured into what initially seemed to be a story about divinely ordained plagues of vermin only to find a quite different moral lesson about avarice and then promise-breaking, readers might end up feeling faintly defrauded of their initial investment in the poem.</p>
              <p>As it turns out, the shifting moral frames in Emblem 17 reflect an apparent uncertainty among other seventeenth-century tellers of the tale as to its significance. The version published in James Howell’s <title rend="italic">Epistolae Ho-Elianae</title> (1645), which is framed by an account of “som odd fellows” who “went skulking up and down <hi rend="italic">London</hi>-streets, and with Figs and Reasons [i.e. raisins] allur’d little children, and so pourloy’d them away from their parents,” probably comes the closest to the story’s modern associations with literal stranger danger (along with its homophobic undertones).<seg>3<note type="gloss"><bibl>James Howell, <title rend="italic">Epistolae Ho-elianae</title> (London, 1645), p. 71.</bibl> For the modern association between child kidnapping and homophobia, see Paul M. Renfro, <title rend="italic">Stranger Danger: Family Values, Childhood, and the American Carceral State</title> (Oxford University Press, 2020), esp. Chapter 1. Robert Dixon’s <title rend="italic">Canidia, or, The witches</title> (London, 1683) notably associates the Pied Piper with sexual deviance, listing the “Roguish Clown” who “lo[st] all the Boys in <hi rend="italic">Hammel Town</hi>” alongside “Eels and Frogs” that “have no sex” and “Others” who “from between their Legs did speak, / And act many a Haggish feat” (p. 60).</note></seg> Interestingly, Howell reprints a somewhat different version of the story in <title rend="italic">A German Diet</title> (1653), where it appears in the context of an anti-German oration by one “John Gulielm of Retwitz” and identifies the piper with “the devill” himself.<seg>4<note type="gloss"><bibl>James Howell, <title rend="italic">A German Diet</title> (London, 1653), pp. 34-35.</bibl></note></seg> Similarly, Robert Burton mentions the Hamelle disappearance in <title rend="italic">The Anatomy of Melancholy</title> (1621) in “A Digression of the Nature of Spirits, Bad Angels, or Devils, and how they cause Melancholy.”<seg>5<note type="gloss"><bibl>Robert Burton, <title rend="italic">The Anatomy of Melancholy</title> (London, 1621), p. 68.</bibl></note></seg> The piper’s association with diabolical powers pervades a number of seventeenth-century versions. An anonymous anti-Ranter pamphlet, <title rend="italic">The Black and Terrible Warning Piece</title> (1653), writes the piper out of the story altogether, the children simply “being carried away by the Devil in a flame of fire” after the townspeople, “holding the same Tenents with the Ranters, Shakers, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> Of our times,” set them upon a hill in a deliberate attempt “to dare and defie the Lord of all spirits.”<seg>6<note type="gloss"><bibl><title rend="italic">The Black and Terrible Warning Piece</title> (London, 1653), pp. 3-4.</bibl></note></seg> While such retellings present the occurrence as a literal example of Satan’s power on earth, Thomas Hodges’s <title rend="italic">The Growth and Spreading of Hæresie</title> (1647) allegorizes the tale in terms of the “pyde piper <hi rend="italic">Haeresie</hi>” that might lead “those that are near and deare unto you, you know not whither.”<seg>7<note type="gloss"><bibl>Thomas Hodges, <title rend="italic">The Growth and Spreading of Hæresie</title> (London, 1647), pp. 36-37.</bibl></note></seg> Striking in all of these accounts is their attribution of the children’s disappearance to the piper’s (or devil’s) own sinister nature, rather than presenting it as retribution for the wrong the townspeople commit by not paying him. Indeed, John Gaule’s <title rend="italic">Pus-mantia the Mag-astro-mancer</title> (1652) turns the story into a cautionary tale about “the danger, misery, and ruine of such as have affectedly favoured, or preferred, and superstitiously credited, or consulted Magicall and Astrologicall predictors.”<seg>8<note type="gloss"><bibl>John Gaule, <title rend="italic">Pus-mantia the Mag-astro-mancer</title> (London, 1652), pp. 364, 366.</bibl></note></seg> If the townspeople’s sin in Pulter’s poem is their “breach of promise” to the piper, in Gaule’s account it is their foolish decision to employ such a “Magicall” charmer in the first place.</p>
              <p>The polysemous nature of the Pied Piper story helps to account for its presence in some surprising places, such as William Ramesey’s discourse on parasitic worms, <title rend="italic">Helminthologia</title> (1668), which explicitly cites Verstegan’s account as an example of the “wonderful permission of GOD to the Rage of the <hi rend="italic">Devil</hi>,” who, like the vermicular pest Ramesey discusses, “destroys life and all, where he can.”<seg>9<note type="gloss"><bibl>William Ramesey, <title rend="italic">Helminthologia</title> (London, 1668), p. 66.</bibl></note></seg> Verstegan himself presents the Hamelle story not with any kind of moralizing import but, unexpectedly, as part of his discussion of the Saxon diaspora – specifically, as a fanciful explanation (which he ends up dismissing) for why “among the Saxons in Transilvnia” there are some “that have lyke surnames unto divers of the burgers of Hamel.”<seg>10<note type="gloss"><bibl>Verstegan, <title rend="italic">A Restitution</title>, p. 87.</bibl></note></seg> Appropriately enough, given its theme, Verstegan introduces the story as something that has lured him away from his main topic, “one digression [having] drawn on another.”<seg>11<note type="gloss"><bibl>Verstegan, <title rend="italic">A Restitution</title>, p. 85.</bibl></note></seg> It is with a similar apology that the tale is prefaced in another unlikely source, <title rend="italic">The Vanitie of the Eye, first begun for the comfort of a gentlewoman bereaved of her sight</title> (1615), whose author, George Hakewell, “confess[es]” that he has included it “not so much for the fitnesse, as the strangeness of the story.”<seg>12<note type="gloss"><bibl>George Hakewell, <title rend="italic">The Vanitie of the Eye, first begun for the comfort of a gentlewoman bereaved of her sight</title> (London, 1615), p. 61.</bibl></note></seg> Relieved of the imperative to “fit” the story to any particular end (moralizing, geographical, mag-astro-mantical, or otherwise), perhaps the <hi rend="italic">least</hi> surprising context in which the Pied Piper appears in the seventeenth century is in collections of miraculous occurrences such as <title rend="italic">The Wonders of the Little World</title> (1673) or <title rend="italic">Extraordinary Adventures and Discoveries of Several Famous Men</title> (1683), which simply introduce the event as a “strange Accident.”<seg>13<note type="gloss"><bibl><title rend="italic">Extraordinary Adventures and Discoveries of Several Famous Men</title> (London, 1683), p. 188.</bibl></note></seg></p>
              <p>Read in the context of these various (and variously explicated) versions, Pulter’s transformation of the Pied Piper legend into an emblem with shifting significances also transforms the genre itself from one of static exposition of a calcified moral into a dynamic meditation on the complex relationships between divine and human justice, avarice and fair trade, labor and exploitation, promise and betrayal, as well as the human and the non-human. Working backwards from what may seem like its overly trite conclusion (“Then keep your word, for better or for worse”), the poem unravels into a promiscuous array of competing possibilities that intermingle and coalesce in unexpected ways, like the mythemes of the legend itself in its various guises. For instance, given early modern associations between avarice and sodomy, Pulter’s tale of a piper luring the “pretty boys” of the town away through the use of some kind of unmentionable means (“what he did, I think no man can say”) potentially emerges as a sublimated form of poetic justice.<seg>14<note type="gloss">The piper’s queerness is emphasized in several of the early modern versions, which, in addition to emphasizing his flamboyant dress, often describe him with the epithet “odd,” as in Verstegan’s characterization of him as “an od kynd of compagnion” (p. 85). For the connection between avarice and sodomy, see, for example, <bibl>John Harris, <title rend="italic">The destruction of sodome</title> (London, 1625), p. 35</bibl>: “And had couetousnesse a habitation in Sodome? and was filthy auarice a cause of her desolation? then Lord bee mercifull vnto our Land, that hath many a member in it, who out of a couetous desire, haue made a marriage with siluer, and giuen a bill of diuorce to Iesus Christ!” For a larger discussion connecting sodomy more broadly to the misuse of money, particularly through usury and counterfeiting, see <bibl>Will Fisher, “Queer Money” <title rend="italic">ELH</title> 66 (1999): 1-23.</bibl></note></seg> The poem’s odd (and oddly unnecessary) citation of 1 Samuel 6 as a possible explanation for “how ‘twas done” (along with the five golden mice the Philistines offered Jehovah to mitigate their rodent infestation, they also presented five golden “emerods” to alleviate the divine smiting that was afflicting them “in their secret parts”) probably raises more questions than it answers.<seg>15<note type="gloss">Even more suggestively, the Latin Vulgate describes the Philistines’ offering as “quinque anos aureos” (“five golden anuses”). For the premodern interpretation of the plagues of 1 Samuel 5-6 specifically in relation to both avarice and “sodomitirie,” see <bibl>Robert Mills, “Seeing Sodomy in the <title rend="italic">Bibles moralisées</title>” <title rend="italic">Speculum</title> 87 (2012): 413-468.</bibl></note></seg></p>
              <p>Indeed, the ambiguous relationship between the rats and divine punishment in Emblem 17 suggests a type of pest that refuses to be controlled either by literal extermination or by providentialist narratives. As Lucinda Cole points out, “given their endless reproducibility and the unpredictable nature of their swarming motion,” rats, mice, and other vermin represented in early modern texts “may actually threaten the ideas of an orderly universe and the regeneration of Nature symbolized by Noah’s Ark,” often resisting neat ontological (and even taxonomic) categorization.<seg>16<note type="gloss"><bibl>Lucinda Cole, <title rend="italic">Imperfect Creatures: Vermin, Literature, and the Sciences of Life, 1600-1740</title> (Ann Arbor: University of Michigan Press, 2016), 17.</bibl></note></seg> Thus, in seventeenth-century depictions of the biblical plagues of Egypt, for example, it is unclear whether “lice, frogs, and swarming things [are] to be read allegorically or literally” and, indeed, whether the story is “about political sovereignty or natural populations.”<seg>17<note type="gloss"><bibl>Cole, <title rend="italic">Imperfect Creatures</title>, 19.</bibl></note></seg> Similarly, behind Pulter’s moralizing representation of rats in Emblem 17 may lurk concerns about the real historical presence of rodents in seventeenth-century England (and a future Amplified Edition might fruitfully connect the poem to such on-the-ground conditions).</p>
              <p>Ultimately, the poem’s shifting moral framework can have the effect of making Emblem 17 feel like two poems: one about Old-Testament-style divine retribution involving plagues of locusts, frogs, serpents – and, of course, rats – and the other about the all-too-human world of greed, bad faith, and revenge, in which such pests are simply the given facts of life, part of the meaningless chaos of existence. In fact, this doubleness is arguably reflected in a scribal error in Pulter’s manuscript: a neatly-written “18” at the top of folio 102, after the page-break, indicates what its writer evidently mistook for the beginning of a new poem: Emblem 18. Realizing her mistake, the scribe crossed it out; however, by then it was too late: having already continued numbering the next poem (<ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="84">The Elephant (Emblem 19)</ref>) as number 19, making the correction would necessarily mean leaving out a number from the total sequence. Like the missing children of Hamelle, Emblem 18 ends up being an absent presence in Pulter’s manuscript: itself an emblem, perhaps, for the material vicissitudes of textual production and circulation that strain against the text’s own pursuit of a world whose meanings are legible in the form of emblems – a world (“Though some may think’t a fiction or a dream”) where betrayal, destruction, and loss are more easily attributable to divine ordination, rather than to the unaccountable and stupid realm of the “strange Accident.”</p>
            </note>
          </rdg>
        </app>
      </head>

      <l n="1">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft"><fw type="seqNum" place="inline">17</fw>When God (who is to Mercie most inclin’d)</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">When God (who is to mercy most inclined)</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">When God (who is to mercy most inclined)</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="2">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">  To puniſh or to trie hath once deſign’d</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">To punish or to <seg>try<note type="gloss"> to subject to trial</note></seg> hath once <seg>designed<note type="gloss">marked out, designated; appointed, assigned, destined</note></seg></rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>To punish or to try<note type="critical">The tortuous syntax of the opening lines encourages misreading. Immediately following the prepositional phrase “to mercy,” the infinitive phrases “to punish” and “to try” suggest a parallel between God’s mercy and the punishments and trials he metes out on his people. The humble closed-parenthesis is the only thing that separates a God “who is to mercy most inclined” from a God who is “most inclined) / To punish or to try.”</note></seg> hath once designed</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="3">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">A People, each Reptell or inſect</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">A people, each reptile or insect</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">A people, each reptile or insect</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="4">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Or baſest Animal will not neglect</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Or basest animal <seg>will not neglect<note type="gloss">that is, God will not neglect these creatures</note></seg>,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Or basest animal will not <seg>neglect<note type="gloss">That is, God will not scorn to use these base creatures as instruments of punishment. See <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="111">The Bishop and the Rats (Emblem 46)</ref>, lines 25-26: “For each despiséd reptile or insect / He can empower, when we his laws neglect.” An account of the Bishop of Mainz and his unfortunate encounter with rats appears immediately before a retelling of the Pied Piper story in <bibl>James Howell, <title rend="italic">A German Diet</title> (London, 1653), p. 34.</bibl></note></seg>,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="5">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">But will their Habitation Soe Annoy</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">But will their habitation so annoy,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">But will <seg>their<note type="critical">The antecedent of “their” is “people” (3), but it could easily be mistaken for “each reptile or insect / Or basest animal” (3-4), suggesting perhaps a conflation between the human objects and the non-human instruments of punishment. This conflation also foreshadows the way in which humans and animals turn out to be equally susceptible to the alluring sound of the piper’s pipe later in the poem.</note></seg> habitation so annoy</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="6">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Without a Countermand they’l all deſtroy</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee"><seg>Without a countermand, they’ll all destroy<note type="gloss">The sense of the poem’s opening sentence is that, without a divine “countermand” (an order revoking God’s previous command), the creatures he has designated as plagues upon a given people will destroy everything in their path.</note></seg>.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>Without a countermand<note type="critical">A lot depends on the placement of the implied “that” completing the “so” of line 5. If it follows “annoy,” then the sense is that the vermin will “all destroy” <hi rend="italic">unless</hi> God issues a “countermand” (leaving open the possibility that God could perhaps relent). On the other hand, placing the implied “that” after “countermand” makes God’s decree seem more absolute and unchanging: in this reading, “without a countermand” functions less as a conditional specifying the circumstances (however unlikely) under which the destruction would be less than total, and more as a categorical denial that such a retraction would ever occur: the pests will simply and ruthlessly “so annoy / Without a countermand,” that “they’ll all destroy.” The lack of punctuation in Pulter’s manuscript effectively confronts readers with the same hedging uncertainty that led the townspeople of Hamelle to renege on their payment: a God – or a Piper – who is inclined more to mercy than to punishment and who thus does not always follow through with his threats is also one whose bluff might more safely be called (or so the townspeople think, to their peril).</note></seg> <seg>they’ll<note type="critical">This time, the third-person-plural pronoun takes “each reptile or insect / Or basest animal” (3-4) as its antecedent, but, again, the syntax (as well as the fact that “each” is singular) encourages a misreading that attaches the pronoun to “people” (3), requiring readers to take special care to distinguish between man and beast.</note></seg> all destroy.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="7">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Thus Spain by Rabbits, Moles made Theſaly</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee"><seg>Thus<note type="gloss">In this and the next five lines, Pulter summarizes Pliny’s <title rend="italic">Natural History</title> where he writes (in Book 8, Chapter 29) of “what cities and nations have been utterly destroyed by little beasts.” After noting that “much hurt and damage hath been known to come from small contemptible creatures, which otherwise are of no reckoning and account,” Pliny mentions many of the same creatures and locales as Pulter does. (<bibl>C. Plinius Secundus <title rend="italic">The Historie of the World</title>. Trans. Philemon Holland [1601]: pp. 192-234, https://penelope.uchicago.edu/holland/pliny8.html</bibl>).</note></seg> Spain by rabbits, <seg>moles made Thessaly<note type="gloss">This phrase is completed in the next line: “moles made Thessaly … a desert lie.”</note></seg>,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>Thus<note type="critical">The section of Pliny’s <title rend="italic">Natural History</title> from which Pulter draws the examples in lines 7-11 focuses on how “much hurt and dammage hath ben known to come from small contemptible creatures, which otherwise are of no reckoning and account,” recalling the poem’s opening claim about how God “each reptile or insect / Or basest animal will not neglect” in his punishment of disobedient people (<bibl>C. Plinius Secundus, <title rend="italic">The Historie of the World</title>, Trans. Philemon Holland [London, 1601], p. 212</bibl>).</note></seg> Spain by rabbits, moles made Thessaly,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="8">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Locusts made Affrica a Deſert lye</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Locusts made Africa a desert lie;</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Locusts made Africa a desert lie;</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="9">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">&ff;rance &ff;rogs, Amycle Serpents, did deſtroy</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">France frogs, <seg>Amyclæ<note type="gloss">a city near Sparta in ancient Peloponnesia</note></seg> serpents, did destroy;</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">France frogs, Amyclæ serpents, did destroy;</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="10">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">&ff;lyes, Lice, and &ff;rogs, all Egypt did Annoy</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Flies, lice, and frogs, all Egypt did annoy;</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Flies, <seg>lice<note type="gloss">See <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="111">The Bishop and the Rats (Emblem 46)</ref>, line 28: “Sulla and Herod by a louse did die.”</note></seg>, and frogs, all Egypt did <seg>annoy<note type="critical">The reversal of the order of the rhyming words “annoy”/“destroy” from lines 5-6 sits in ironic counterpoint to the notion of a destruction that is supposed to occur “without a countermand” (6).</note></seg>;</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="11">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Gyaros Rats, and too too many more</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee"><seg>Gyaros<note type="gloss">a Greek island</note></seg>, rats; and too, too many more</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Gyaros, rats; and too, too many more</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="12">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Their Sufferings (though not Sins) did then deplore</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Their sufferings (though not sins) did then <seg>deplore<note type="gloss">lament, mourn, tell with grief</note></seg>.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Their sufferings <seg>(though not sins)<note type="critical">The relegation of “sins” to parentheses mirrors the people’s spiritually negligent failure to “deplore” their sins as the just cause of their divinely ordained “sufferings.”</note></seg> did then deplore.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="13">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">This made the Town of <seg>Hamell<note type="physical">final “l” appears written over “e”</note></seg> Stand in Doubt</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">This made the town of <seg>Hamelin<note type="gloss">a market town in Lower Saxony, Germany</note></seg> <seg>stand in doubt<note type="gloss">to continue in a state of doubt, or, more likely here, “doubt” in the sense of apprehension or dread</note></seg>,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>This<note type="critical">The poem never specifies what the citizens of Hamelle did to invite the plague of rats in the first place; oddly, we don’t know what sin the vermin are meant to punish.</note></seg> made the town of <seg>Hamelle<note type="gloss">a town in Lower Saxony, Germany, more commonly known from the Pied Piper legend as Hamelin.</note></seg> stand in doubt</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="14">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Cauſe of thoſe vermine they had Such a Rowt</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">’Cause <seg>of those vermin they had such a rout<note type="gloss">Pulter refers to the legend of the Pied Piper of Hamelin, in which the town was infested with a rat plague (or “rout”: a crowd or pack, especially a noisy, disordered, or violent one).</note></seg>.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">’Cause of those vermin they had such a rout.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="15">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">They tri’de all <add place="below">^</add><add place ="above">waies, as</add> poyſons, Traps, and Catts.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">They tried all ways, <seg>as<note type="gloss">such as</note></seg> poisons, traps, and cats,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">They tried all <seg>ways, as<note type="physical">The words “waies, as” were added to the line with a caret.</note></seg> <seg>poisons, traps, and cats<note type="gloss">For some of the methods the townspeople might have tried, see Leonard Mascall, <title rend="italic">A booke of engines and traps to take polcats, buzardes, rattes, mice and all other kindes of vermine and beasts whatsoever, most profitable for all warriners, and such as delight in this kinde of sport and pastime</title> (London, 1590).</note></seg>,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="16">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Yet Still their Houſes pesterd were with Rats</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Yet still their houses pestered were with rats.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Yet still their houses pestered were with rats.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="17">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">At last a Piper chance’d to come that way</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">At last a piper chanced to come that way,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">At last a <seg>piper<note type="critical">The poem itself never refers to the piper as “Pied,” although the word does appear in a marginal note referring readers to “the story of this Pied Piper” in <bibl>Richard Verstegan’s <title rend="italic">A Restitution of Decayed Intelligence</title> (London, 1605).</bibl> (The page number in the note (85) indicates that Pulter was using one of the first three editions of the book: 1605, 1628, or 1634.) Verstegan explains how the piper earned his popular epithet “for the fantastical cote which hee wore beeing wrought with sundry colours,” another common feature in various tellings of the story that is left out of Pulter’s poem (p. 85).</note></seg> chanced to come that way,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="18">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">With whom they bargaind for a Certain pay</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">With whom they bargained, for a certain pay,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">With whom they bargained, for a certain pay,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="19">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Their Town of this baſe Loathſom Beaſts to free</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee"><seg>Their town of these base loathsome beasts to free<note type="physical">In the manuscript’s left margin, just below this poetic summary of the tale, is a reference to her source “See the story of this pied piper at large in Verstegan, folio 85”; see <bibl><title rend="italic">A Restitution of Decayed Intelligence</title> (London, 1605), 85</bibl>.</note></seg>.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Their town of <seg>this<note type="critical">The (perhaps unintentionally) ungrammatical singular form, as it appears in the manuscript, may indicate that Pulter is thinking of the rats as a single mass, as in the “rout” of line 14.</note></seg> base loathsome beasts to free.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="20">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft"><seg>The<note type="physical">in left margin: “See the Story / of this Pied Piper/ at Larg in Verstegan / ffolio 85”</note></seg> &ff;ruits of Curſed Avarice now See</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">The fruits of curséd avarice now see.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>The fruits of curséd avarice now see.<note type="critical">This first direct address to the reader moralizes the tale in terms of the townspeople’s greed in withholding payment from the piper.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="21">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">This &ff;ellow pipeing went to <seg>Weaſers<note type="physical">“W” appears written over “w”</note></seg> brim</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">This fellow piping went to <seg>Weser<note type="gloss">a river in Germany</note></seg> brim,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">This fellow piping went to Weser brim,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="22">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">And all the Rats Ran danceing after him</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">And all the rats ran dancing after him;</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">And all the rats ran dancing after him;</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>

        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">
                <pb ed="#ft" facs="#f7610_207" n="102r"/>
            </rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">
                <pb ed="#ee" facs="#f7610_207"/>
            </rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">
                <pb ed="#ae" facs="#f7610_207"/>
            </rdg>
        </app>

      <l n="23">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft"><fw type="seqNum" place="inline"><del>18</del></fw>Then instantly they Skipt into the Stream</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Then instantly they skipped into the stream.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>Then instantly they skipped into the stream.<note type="physical"> This first line after a page break in the middle of the poem is preceded by a marginal “18” that has been crossed out, indicating that its writer mistook this line as the beginning of a new poem. Since the person numbering the poems had continued with 19 for the next poem in the sequence (<ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="84">The Elephant (Emblem 19)</ref>) before realizing the mistake, there is no Emblem 18.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="24">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Though Some may thinkt a &ff;iction or A dream</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Though some may <seg>think’t<note type="gloss">think it</note></seg> a fiction or a dream,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Though some may think’t a fiction or a dream,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="25">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Yet true it is for drowning was their &ff;ate</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Yet true it is, for drowning was their fate;</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Yet true it is, for drowning was their fate;</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="26">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">But how <seg>t’was<note type="physical">“s” written over former letter with ascender, possibly “t”</note></seg> don noe Story doth Relate</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">But how ’twas done, no story doth relate.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">But how ’twas done, no story doth relate.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="27">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">&ff;or whether a Teleſma hee did take</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">For whether a <seg>talisman<note type="gloss">charm</note></seg> he did take,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">For whether a <seg>Telesma<note type="critical">An object meant to ward off various evils, including pests. Cognate with “talisman,” Pulter's more unusual spelling reflects the word’s Greek root from τέλεσμα, “payment,” which often appears in the context of religious rites in the sense of “propitiation,” as of a deity – a kind of supernatural “protection money.” This sense of the word is especially ironic given the townspeople's <hi rend="italic">refusal</hi> to pay the piper for ridding the town of rats. Although the accent is on the first syllable in the Greek, Pulter appears to be scanning the word with an accented second syllable. She uses a similar spelling in <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="111">The Bishop and the Rats (Emblem 46)</ref>, where the Bishop of Mainz is unsuccessful in his attempt to ward off a rodent swarm either by magical or more this-worldly means: “by Tel’sma or Gun” (line 16). In suggesting that some means other than the sound of the piper’s instrument were responsible for luring away the rats and the children, Pulter may be drawing on Nathaniel Ingeno’s prose romance <title rend="italic">Bentivoglio and Urania</title> (London, 1660), which asks, “Who knows but the Piper of <hi rend="italic">Halberstade</hi> was of this Profession [i.e. a magician], and had some Talismans in his Pocket when he drove the Rats into the River and the Boys into the Hill?” (p. 158).</note></seg> he did take,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="28">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">&ff;ive such of Gold The Philiſtin’s did make</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee"><seg>Five such of gold the Philistines did make<note type="gloss">God punishes the Philistines with destruction and hemorrhoids for taking the Ark of Covenant; to be relieved of their sufferings, the Philistines are told to present to God five golden emerods and five golden mice.</note></seg>,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>Five such of gold the Philistines did make,<note type="critical">In 1 Samuel 5-6, the Philistines of Ashdod are visited with a plague of mice and a plague of “emerods [hemorrhoids, tumors, or boils] in their secret parts” after capturing the Ark of the Covenant. Following the counsel of their priests and diviners, the Philistines return the Ark along with a “trespass offering” of “five golden emerods and five golden mice.” These objects were regarded with some ambivalence by early modern commentators. Arthur Jackson, in his <title rend="italic">Annotations upon the remaining historicall part of the Old Testament</title> (London, 1646), considers the possibility “that the sending of such absurd and ridiculous gifts with the Ark, as emerods and mice, was suggested by Sathan to their diviners in contempt of God,” and remarks on “what a shame must it needs be to the Philistines to send to the Israelites the images of their secret parts, thus tortured with an ignominious disease” (p. 238). Of particular interest in relation to Pulter’s characterization of these objects as “Telesma” in line 27 is John Chetwynd’s <title rend="italic">Anthologia historica</title> (London, 1674), which lists the biblical “Images of Emrods and Mice” that “were made by the Astrologers directions and were Telesmatical signes” alongside accounts of other “Telesmatical practices” used to ward off scorpions, crocodiles, flies, serpents, and dormice (pp. 322-25).</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="29">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Or what hee did I think noe man can Say</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Or what he did, I think no man can say;</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Or what he did, I think no man can say;</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="30">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">But when hee came and aſked for his pay</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">But when he came and askéd for his pay,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">But when he came and askéd for his pay,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="31">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">The <seg>Burger’s<note type="physical">“’s” in darker ink; “r” could be another “s”</note></seg> in their Gravitie Refuſ’d</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">The <seg>burghers<note type="physical">“’s” in darker ink; “r” could be another “s”</note></seg> in their gravity refused</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">The burghers in their gravity refused</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="32">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">To pay the Sa<hi rend="overline">m</hi>e, the Piper thus abuſ’d</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">To pay the same; the piper, thus abused,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">To pay the same; the piper, thus abused,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="33">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">did vow Reveng, they bid him doe his worst</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Did vow revenge; they bid him do his worst.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>Did vow revenge; they bid him do his worst.<note type="critical">Pulter lifts this language directly from Verstegan: “hee threatened them with revenge; they bad him do his wurst” (p. 66).</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="34">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Now See how Breach of Promiſe is Accurst</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Now see how breach of promise is accursed.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>Now see how breach of promise is accursed.<note type="critical"> Repeating “now see” from line 20, this second direct address to the reader compounds the ostensible moral about “curséd avarice” with a new one about promise-breaking and, in doing so, asks readers to consider the relationship between the two vices.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="35">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">The &ff;ellow Pipeing went away againe</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">The fellow piping went away again,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">The fellow piping went away again,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="36">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">A Hundred and Thirty Children in his Train</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">A hundred and thirty children in his train;</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>A hundred and thirty<note type="critical">Pulter follows Verstegan in her account of how many children went missing. Many other early modern English versions of the story also specify the number as 130.</note></seg> children in his train;</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="37">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Into a hill hee led theſe pretty Boys</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Into a hill he led these <seg>pretty boys<note type="critical">Several early modern English sources for the Pied Piper story, including Verstegan’s, say that it was specifically the town’s boys that the piper lured away, whereas others do not specify the gender of the children. Interestingly, Peter Heylyn’s <title rend="italic">Mikrokosmos</title> (London, 1625) explicitly draws his account from “a story recited by Verstegan,” but instead of “a number of boyes,” it is “all the children male and female of the Towne” who follow the piper in his account (p. 364).</note></seg>,</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>Into a hill he led these pretty boys,<note type= "crtical">Several early modern English sources for the Pied Piper story, including Verstegan’s, say that it was specifically the town’s boys that the piper lured away, whereas others do not specify the gender of the children. Interestingly, Peter Heylyn’s <title rend="italic">Mikrokosmos</title> (London, 1625) explicitly draws his account from “a story recited by Verstegan,” but instead of “a number of boyes,” it is “all the children male and female of the Towne” who follow the piper in his account (p. 364).</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="38">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">And thus <seg>their<note type="physical">perhaps written over earlier letters</note></seg> Parents lost their hopes, and Joys,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">And thus their parents lost their hopes and joys;</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">And thus their parents lost their hopes and joys;</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="39">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Which with Sad Hearts they now too late deplore</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Which, with sad hearts, they now too late <seg>deplore<note type="gloss">lament; tell with grief; mourn; give up as hopeless</note></seg>,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Which, with sad hearts, they now too late deplore,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="40">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">&ff;or they nor hee were ever heard of more</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">For they, nor he, were ever heard of more.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">For they, nor he, were ever heard of more.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="41">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">By theſe their grievous Suff’rings you may See</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">By these, their grievous suff’rings, you may see</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">By these, their grievous suff’rings, <seg>you may see<note type="critical">With this third direct address to the reader (compare lines 20 and 34), and after introducing at least two other possible morals (i.e. God’s use of base creatures to mete out punishment; the evils of avarice), the poem ends by repeating the moral stated in line 34.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="42">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">that breach of Promiſe puniſhd Sure will bee</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">That breach of promise punished sure will be.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">That breach of promise punished sure will be.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="43">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Then keep your word for better or for worſ</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Then keep your word, for better or for worse,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Then keep your word, for better or for worse,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="44">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Lest with theſe Saxons you pertake like Curſ</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Lest with these <seg>Saxons<note type="gloss">inhabitants of Saxony, here referring to the people of Hamelin in Lower Saxony</note></seg> you partake like curse.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Lest with these Saxons you partake <seg>like curse<note type="critical"> Given Verstegan’s heavy investment in recovering England’s Saxon identity, it is ironic that Pulter ends her poem warning English readers not to “partake like curse” with their Saxon cousins. For Verstegan and England’s Saxon cultural identity, see <bibl>Richard W. Clement, “Richard Verstegan's Reinvention of Anglo-Saxon England: A Contribution from the Continent,” <title rend="italic">Reinventing the Middle Ages and the Renaissance: Constructions of the Medieval and Early Modern Periods</title> (Turnhout: Brepols, 1998), 19-36.</bibl></note></seg>.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
