<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../src/vmachine.xsl"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
  schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI [

  <!ENTITY ff "<!-- ff ligature, representing capital modern day capital F, here represented as 'ff' -->ff">

  ]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mads.pp.101">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
          <title>Doves and Pearls (Emblem 36)</title>
        <title type="sub">Poem #101</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Created by</resp>
          <persName>Leah Knight</persName>
          <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoded by</resp>
          <persName>Katherine Poland</persName>
          <persName>Matthew Taylor</persName>
          <persName>Betsy Chou</persName>
          <persName>Emily Andrey</persName>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>IT-project consultation by</resp>
          <persName>Josh Honn</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
          <orgName>Brock University</orgName>
          <orgName>University of Leeds</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <principal>
          <persName/>
        </principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="1"/>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription, transformations, and notes</resp>
          <persName>Leah Knight</persName>
          <orgName>Brock University</orgName>
          <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
        </respStmt>
      </editionStmt>
      <extent/>
      <publicationStmt>
        <ab/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listBibl>
          <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
              <repository>See witness list.</repository>
            </msIdentifier>
          </msDesc>
        </listBibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p/>
      </projectDesc>
      <p>Transcriptions are encoded in TEI(P5)-conformant XML.</p>
      <samplingDecl>
        <p/>
      </samplingDecl>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction>
          <p>Apparent errors are preserved and editorial corrections provided using SIC and CORR tags, but only where the editor conjectures that the original scribe or compositor would have recognized the instance as an error. For example, what according to modern usage is incorrect subject/verb agreement might have been deemed acceptable to a seventeenth-century scribe or compositor. All such instances are treated instead using the ORIG and REG tags. (See below.)</p>
          <p>Corrections and annotations made within the scope of the original document either by its original authors, owners, and/or transcribers are noted using ADD tags. These annotations and may be futher explained within NOTE tags, as added by the editors of this digital edition, for display within the apparatus.</p>
        </correction>
        <normalization>
          <p>Original spellings, abbreviations, and orthography are preserved. Where in the manuscripts a character's status as majuscule or miniscule is ambiguous, the editor has silently chosen one or the other based on context and judgment (i.e., does not register such ambiguity in either the markup or the notes).</p>
        </normalization>
        <quotation>
          <p>Original quotation marks, if any, are preserved.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation>
          <p>Original hyphenation is preserved.</p>
        </hyphenation>
      </editorialDecl>
      <charDecl>
        <!-- Ligature combinations for which there are currently no corresponding Unicode codepoints. -->
        <glyph xml:id="ffllig">
          <glyphName>Handwritten 'ff' ligature, used in handwriting to represent modern F</glyphName>
        </glyph>
      </charDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="DDC22">
          <bibl>
            <title>Dewey Decimal Classification</title>
            <edition/>
            <publisher/>
            <pubPlace/>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-GB">British English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <!-- dewey decimal system class code 821: English Poetry -->
        <classCode scheme="DDC22">821</classCode>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
    <!-- List of all images associated with this document -->
      <graphic url="./document_images/7610_232.jpg" xml:id="f7610_232"/>
      <graphic url="./document_images/7610_233.jpg" xml:id="f7610_233"/>
  </facsimile>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="ft">Transcription of manuscript: By <persName xml:id="lknight">Leah Knight</persName> and <persName xml:id="wwall">Wendy Wall</persName>.</witness>
          <witness xml:id="ee">Elemental edition: By <persName>Leah Knight</persName> and <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>.</witness>
          <witness xml:id="ae">Amplified edition: By <persName>Millie Godfery</persName> and <persName>Sarah C. E. Ross</persName>.</witness>
        </listWit>
      </div>
    </front>

    <body>

      <app>
        <rdg wit="#ft">
            <pb ed="#ft" facs="#f7610_232" n="114v"/>
        </rdg>
        <rdg wit="#ee">
            <pb ed="#ee" facs="#f7610_232"/>
        </rdg>
        <rdg wit="#ae">
            <pb ed="#ae" facs="#f7610_232"/>
        </rdg>
      </app>
      <head>
        <app type="title">
            <rdg wit="#ft"><fw facs="#f7610_069" type="pageNum" place="margin-topright">PG#</fw>[Emblem 36]</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Doves and Pearls<lb/>(Emblem 36)</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Doves and Pearls<lb/>(Emblem 36)</rdg>
        </app>
        <app type="editorialnote">
          <rdg wit="#ft">
            <note type="editorialnote">In these transcriptions we preserve as many details of the original material, textual, and graphic properties of Hester Pulter’s manuscript verse as we have found practical. Whenever possible, for instance, original spelling, punctuation, capitalization, lineation, insertions, deletions, alterations, spacing between words and lines, and indentation are all maintained; abbreviations and brevigraphs are not expanded; and superscript and subscript representations are retained. <ref target="http://pulterproject.northwestern.edu/about-project-conventions.html#top" type="new-window-url">See full conventions for the transcriptions here.</ref></note>
          </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">
            <note type="editorialnote">The aim of the elemental edition is to make the poems accessible to the largest variety of readers, which involves modernizing spelling and punctuation as well as adding basic glosses. Spelling and punctuation reflect current standard American usage; punctuation highlights syntax which might otherwise be obscure. Outmoded but still familiar word forms (“thou,” “‘tis,” “hold’st”) are not modernized, and we do not modernize grammar when the sense remains legible. After a brief headnote aimed at offering a “way in” to the poem’s unique qualities and connections with other verse by Pulter or her contemporaries, the edition features a minimum of notes and interpretative framing to allow more immediate engagement with the poem. Glosses clarify synonyms or showcase various possible meanings in Pulter’s time. Other notes identify named people and places or clarify obscure material. We rely (without citation) primarily on the Oxford English Dictionary (OED), the Oxford Reference database, and the King James Version (KJV) of the Bible. When we rely on Alice Eardley’s edition of Pulter’s work, we cite her text generally (“Eardley”); other sources are cited in full. The result is an edition we consider a springboard for further work on Pulter’s poetry. <ref target="http://pulterproject.northwestern.edu/about-project-conventions.html#elemental-edition" type="new-window-url">See full conventions for this edition here.</ref></note></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">
            <note type="editorialnote">Our priority in editing these poems has been to modernise, and to achieve interpretative and visual clarity, in order to make the poems as accessible as possible to as wide a modern audience as is possible. Spelling is modernised, as is punctuation. Modernising the latter, in particular, often involves a significant act of editorial interpretation, but in our view this is one of the most productive areas of editorial intervention, particularly for a manuscript text such as Pulter’s where the punctuation is erratic compared to modern usage (and, indeed, compared to early modern printed texts).<seg>[1]<note type="gloss">See Alice Eardley, “‘I haue not time to point yr booke … which I desire you yourselfe to doe’: Editing the Form of Early Modern Manuscript Verse”, in <hi rend="italic">The Work of Form: Poetics and Materiality in Early Modern Culture</hi>, ed. Ben Burton and Elizabeth Scott-Baumann (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2014), pp. 162-178.</note></seg> All biblical references are to the King James Version (1612).</note>
          </rdg>
        </app>
        <app type="headnote">
          <rdg wit="#ee">
            <note type="headnote">Emblem 36 addresses “my dear pledges of our constant loves”: apparently, the poet’s own children, of which Pulter had fifteen (though not all lived to hear this poem). They are summoned to share the poet’s vision of some pearl-eating birds—an unusual sight, and so a compelling invitation. But the moral of the story is more ordinary: like the birds with their permanently internalized pearls, the speaker enjoins her offspring to “treasure sacred truths within your heart.” Pulter then raises the stakes by vividly imagining the “tyrant lapidaries” who might try to mine those jewel-like truths out of her children’s hearts, as well as “swine”-like folk who won’t just trample pearls (a biblical allusion) but also “rend” the “bowels” of those who throw them. The poem suggests the importance of maintaining one’s truth, at least internally; but it also acknowledges the countervailing need to protect oneself and one’s offspring from the often lethal treatment Pulter’s compatriots suffered in England’s civil wars (to which the poem also alludes).</note>
          </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">
              <note type="headnote"><p>An essential element of Pulter’s emblem series is her shifting mode of address, as she directs her emblematic wisdom sometimes explicitly to her children, and sometimes to a broader audience. “Doves and Pearls”, like <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="68">"Come, My Dear Children" (Emblem 2)</ref>, addresses her children directly in an emblematic reworking of the invitation genre.</p><p>The emblem opens with Pulter imploring her children to notice the acts of doves, who by nature display loving devotion to one partner. The doves swallow orient pearls, which she uses as an emblem of a sacred “cordial, which our greatest faintings ease”, and she goes on to urge her readers to “treasure sacred truths within [the] heart”, as the doves do (lines 4, 6). The emblem moves to warn readers of “those swine” which, conversely, disregard “God’s word”; here, Pulter is inspired by multiple biblical references which cast swine as irreligious. An analogous emblem to this one is <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="99">“Mark but those Hogs” (Emblem 34)</ref>, in which Pulter contrasts the image of “thankless” hogs “grunt[ing] for more” with “innocent doves” (lines 4, 6, 17). In that emblem, she urges the reader to “try which best he loves / To imitate, base hogs or turtledoves”, and concludes with an expression of her “soul’s sole desire” to embody the same qualities as the “spotless dove” (lines 19-20).</p><p>Towards the final lines of “Doves and Pearls” Pulter’s religious concerns become explicitly political as she criticizes the poor treatment of “sacred fane[s]” under the Protectorate, specifically referencing the use of St Paul’s Cathedral for irreligious activities (line 20). She further condemns republicans, referencing the treatment of “nobles”—meaning royalist soldiers—after the 1645 Battle of Naseby (line 24). In a typical display of emblematic didacticism, however, Pulter concludes in consolation, reminding her children that God will “[scourge] out” the unfaithful (line 26). By applying Pulter’s conceit of doves and pearls to this final resolution, the message becomes clear: keep faith and fidelity with God, unlike those who “ramp and rave” (line 16).</p>
              </note>
          </rdg>
        </app>
      </head>

      <l n="1">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Come my Dear Pledges of our Conſtant Loves</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Come, my dear <seg>pledges<note type="gloss">signs or tokens of favor, loyalty, love, or as guarantee; here, children as evidence of mutual love and duty between parents</note></seg> of our constant loves:</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>Come<note type="gloss">For a similar opening address, see <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="68">“Come, My Dear Children” (Emblem 2)</ref>; and see our note to line 1 of the Amplified Edition of that poem.</note></seg>, my dear <seg>pledges<note type="gloss">a name for children considered as a tokens or evidence of mutual love and duty between parents (<title rend="italic">OED</title> 4b)</note></seg> of <seg>our<note type="gloss">Hester Pulter and her husband Arthur Pulter</note></seg> constant loves,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="2">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Come look upon theſe pretty innocent Doves</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Come look upon these pretty, innocent doves!</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Come look upon these pretty, innocent <seg>doves<note type="gloss">Pulter uses the turtledove throughout her poetry to thematise chastity, spiritual virtue, and equitable love. See, for example, <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="71">“The Manucodiats” (Emblem 5)</ref>; <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="85">“This Poor Turtle Dove” (Emblem 20)</ref>, where the turtledove is praised for her “kind and constant” love for her deceased partner (line 2); and <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="57">"Why Must I Thus Forever Be Confined" (Poem 57)</ref>. Pliny writes of the dove: “they be passing chaste, and neither male nor female change their mate, but keep together one true unto the other” (<bibl><title rend="italic">The Historie of the World: Commonly Called, the Naturall Historie of C. Plinius Secundus</title>. Trans. Philemon Holland. Vol. 1 [1635], 290</bibl>).</note></seg>,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="3">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">See how they Swallow Orient Pearls like Peas</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee"><seg>See how they swallow orient pearls like peas:<note type="critical">The speaker instructs her children to observe doves eating pearls (which were sometimes considered medicinal). The source of this claim is not known; too late as a source for Pulter, but relatively contemporary, is a passing reference to “A cloudy pearl in a dove’s paunch,” in Robert Dixon’s <title rend="italic">Canidia, or, The Witches</title> (London, 1683), p. 208. Orient pearls are from the seas around India, versus those of less beauty in European mussels; generally, the phrase signifies a brilliant or precious pearl.</note></seg></rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">See how they swallow <seg>orient pearls<note type="critical">pearls from the seas around India, as distinguished from those of less beauty found in European mussels; (hence, more generally) a brilliant or precious pearl (OED 1b). Pulter also connects orient pearls with truth in <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="32">“Aletheia’s Pearl” (Poem 32)</ref>, in which “Fair Aletheia”, the goddess of truth, offers the speaker an orient pearl to represent their pledge of truthfulness and faith in God (lines 1-4). It is also worth noting the medicinal properties of pearls, which further codifies the pearl as an emblem of truth which the doves ingest as a healing “cordial” (<title rend="italic">OED</title> 2a; line 4).</note></seg> like peas;</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="4">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">A Cordiall which our greatest faintings Eas</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">A <seg>cordial<note type="gloss">medicine</note></seg> which our greatest faintings ease;</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">A <seg>cordial<note type="gloss">a medicine, food, or beverage which invigorates the heart and stimulates the circulation; a comforting or exhilarating drink (<title rend="italic">OED</title> 2a). See Pulter’s similar use of the word in <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="61">“The Weeping Wish” (Poem 61)</ref>, line 19. In that poem, the bezoar is the “cordial”; in this poem, the orient pearls, emblematic of truth, are the medicine (see note to line 3).</note></seg>, which our greatest <seg>faintings<note type="gloss">growing feeble or faint-hearted; depressed (<title rend="italic">OED</title> 1)</note></seg> ease.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="5">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">And with their lives e’re with theſe Pearls the’l part</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">And with their lives <seg>ere<note type="gloss">before</note></seg> with these pearls they’ll part:</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">And with their lives ere with these pearls they’ll part;</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="6">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Soe treaſure Sacred truths within <w lemma="your"><abbr>yo<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>:</abbr></w> heart</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">So treasure sacred truths within your heart.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">So, treasure sacred truths within your heart.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="7">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Though Tyrant Lapidaries Shew their Spight</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Though tyrant <seg>lapidaries<note type="gloss">workers who cut, polish, set, and sell gems</note></seg> show their spite,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Though tyrant <seg>lapidaries<note type="gloss">artificers who cut, polish, or engrave gems or precious stones; those who are  skilled in the nature and kinds of gems or precious stones (<title rend="italic">OED</title> 1a, b). Pulter refers to this profession at lines 7 and 8, comparing the work of lapidaries who cut and engrave already precious stones like the pearl, with that of “tyrant[s]” who attempt to alter people’s faith and virtue. This manipulation, Pulter insists, merely expose the faults of tyrants, while making steadfast devotees “shine more bright”.</note></seg> show their spite,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="8">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Your graces like theſe pearles will Shine more bright</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Your graces, like these pearls, will shine more bright.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Your graces, like these pearls, will shine more bright.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="9">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Deſpair not though you at their mercie lie</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Despair not, though you at their mercy lie:</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Despair not, though you at their mercy lie;</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="10">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Your vertues live although your bodys die</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Your <seg>virtues<note type="gloss">meaning not only morally good qualities but, in a medicinal context, strengthening or healing powers</note></seg> live, although your bodies die.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Your virtues live although your bodies die.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="11">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Then if you will in glory live above</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Then, if you will in glory live above,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Then if you will in glory live above,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="12">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Like theſe white Doves thoſe bleſſed Unions Love</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Like these white doves, those blesséd unions love;</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Like these white doves those <seg>blessed unions<note type="gloss"> the consecrated love which is upheld in the marital fidelity of doves, the commitment that makes them a common emblem for purity and faith; see note to line 2.</note></seg> love,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="13">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">But Shun thoſe people which are like thoſe Swine</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">But shun those people which are like those swine</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">But shun those people which are like those <seg>swine<note type="critical">Pulter uses the image of swine throughout her emblem collection to refer to the unchaste and irreligious. Multiple biblical passages no doubt underpin this. See for instance, Mat. 7.6., “neither cast ye your pearls before swine, lest they trample them under their feet”, and Pet. 2.22, “the sowe that was washed, to her wallowing in the mire”. See also Pulter's analogous emblem, <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="99">"Mark but those Hogs" (Emblem 34)</ref>.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="14">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Which at Gods word and Ministers Repine</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Which at God’s word and minister’s <seg>repine<note type="gloss">grumble, complain</note></seg>:</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Which at God’s word and ministers <seg>repine<note type="gloss">express discontent or dissatisfaction; grumble, complain (<title rend="italic">OED</title> 1a)</note></seg>.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="15">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Throw them the choicest Orient Pearls you have</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Throw them the choicest orient pearls you have,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Throw them the choicest orient pearls you have,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="16">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">They’ll trample’m in <w lemma="the"><abbr>y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi></abbr></w> dirt and Ramp &amp; Rave</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">They’ll trample’m in the dirt and <seg>ramp<note type="gloss">rear on the hind legs; act in a furious, threatening way; rush about wildly; (of a woman) behave immodestly</note></seg> and rave;</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">They’ll <seg>trample’m in the dirt<note type="gloss">a biblical reference to Mat. 7.6; see note for line 13.</note></seg> and <seg>ramp<note type="gloss">Of a person: to rush, storm, or rage with violent gestures; to behave in a furious or threatening manner (<title rend="italic">OED</title> 3a)</note></seg> and rave,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="17">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">And when you think their malice at an end</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">And when you think their malice at an end,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">And when you think their malice at an end,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="18">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">If God Restrain not they’ll <w lemma="your"><abbr>yo:<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></abbr></w> bowels Rend</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">If God restrain not, they’ll your bowels <seg>rend<note type="gloss">See Matthew 7:6: “Give not that which is holy unto the dogs, neither cast ye your pearls before swine, lest they trample them under their feet, and turn again and rend you” (“rend” meaning tear or wound).</note></seg>.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">If God restrain not, they’ll your bowels <seg>rend<note type="gloss">tear, split; rupture (<title rend="italic">OED</title>)</note></seg>.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="19">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Of theſe the Bore God’s vinyards that destroy</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Of these, <seg>the boar God’s vineyards<note type="gloss">See Psalms 80:8-13: “Thou hast brought a vine out of Egypt: … The boar out of the wood doth waste it.”</note></seg> <seg>that<note type="gloss">did</note></seg> destroy</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Of these, <seg>the boar God’s vineyards that destroy<note type="gloss">A reference to Psalm 80.8-13, in which God is questioned for planting a “vine out of Egypt” and then allowing it to be “broken down” and “pluck[ed]”, “the boar out of the wood… wast[ing] it”.</note></seg>,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="20">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">And with their &ff;ilth his Sacred Phane Annoy</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">And with their filth his sacred <seg>fane<note type="gloss">temple</note></seg> annoy.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">And with their filth His <seg>sacred fane annoy<note type="gloss">The "fane" is a temple (<title rend="italic">OED</title> 2). This line refers to Isaiah 66.3, which describes the “abomination” of “offer[ing] swines blood” as a sacrifice, an act which taints the sacred place of the church.</note></seg>.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="21">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Soe mad Antiochus the Temple Stain’d</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee"><seg>So mad Antiochus the temple stained<note type="gloss">Antiochus Epiphanes, King of Syria, in 169 BCE defiled Jerusalem’s Temple.</note></seg>;</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">So mad <seg>Antiochus<note type="gloss">Antiochus IV, King of the Seleucids, 175-164 BC, known for his coercive manner and desire to Hellenize the Jewish race. In the Bible, he is criticised for polluting and profaning “the sanctuary and holy people” by sacrificing “swine’s flesh” (I Mac. 1.46-7).</note></seg> the temple stained,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="22">
        <app>
          <rdg wit="#ft">Even Soe our <seg>Janizaries<note type="physical">“i” appears adapted from second part of earlier “m”, and “z” to be written over another letter, perhaps “a”</note></seg> Po’les prophan’d</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Even so <seg>our janizaries Paul’s prophaned<note type="gloss">Janizaries were Turkish soldiers, here identified with parliamentarians in England’s civil wars; “Paul’s” is St. Paul’s Cathedral, which had long been a resort for gossips, idlers, and disreputable people, and in the wars parliamentarians turned parts of it into cavalry barracks.</note></seg>,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Even so <seg>our janissaries<note type="gloss">A body of Turkish infantry, constituting the Sultan's guard and the main part of the standing army. The body was first organized in the 14th century, and was composed mainly of tributary children of Christians (OED). Pulter uses this term in a derogatory sense in reference to the English army led by parliamentarians.</note></seg> <seg>Paul’s profaned<note type="gloss">Parliamentarians used St Paul’s Cathedral in London as a stables during the civil war; see William Dugdale’s account in his <bibl><title rend="italic">The History of St Paul’s Cathedral</title></bibl>, where he states “that God would be turned out of Churches into Barnes… (robbed of all dignity and respect)… all order, discipline and Church-government left to newness of opinion and men’s fancies” ([1658], The Epistle).</note></seg>,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">
                <fw type="catch" place="bottom">making</fw>
            </rdg>
        </app>
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">
                <pb ed="#ft" facs="#f7610_233" n="115r"/>
            </rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">
                <pb ed="#ee" facs="#f7610_233"/>
            </rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">
                <pb ed="#ae" facs="#f7610_233"/>
            </rdg>
        </app>
      <l n="23">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Makeing the Church a Stable and a Stews</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Making the church a stable and a <seg>stews<note type="gloss">brothel</note></seg></rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Making the church a <seg>stable<note type="gloss">See notes for line 22.</note></seg> and a <seg>stews<note type="gloss">brothels (OED 4). Eardley notes there is no specific reference to St Paul’s being used as a brothel; however, Henry Foulis records that in Westminster Abbey soldiers from the English Army were “breaking down the Organs, pawning the pipes of them for Ale, eating, drinking, smoking Tobacco at the Communion Table, and easing themselves in most parts of the Church; Nor was this all, but keeping their whores in the Church, and lying with them upon the very Altar it self” (<bibl>Eardley, “An Edition of Lady Hester Pulter’s Book of ‘Emblemes’”, PhD diss., University of Warwick, [2008], 106 n.22-3</bibl>; <bibl>Foulis, <title rend="italic">The history of the wicked plots and conspiracies of our pretended saints representing the beginning, constitution, and designs of the Jesuite</title> [1662], 138</bibl>).</note></seg>,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="24">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">The while impriſoning Nobles in <w lemma="the"><abbr>y<hi rend="superscript">e</hi></abbr></w> Mews</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">The while <seg>imprisoning nobles in the mews<note type="critical">royal stables in London; Eardley cites a pamphlet claiming 4,500 royalists were jailed there after defeat at the Battle of Naseby. See <title rend="italic">The Manner How the Prisoners Are to Be Brought Into the City of London</title> (London, 1645), A4v.</note></seg>.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">The while <seg>imprisoning nobles in the mews<note type="gloss">“mews” was the term coined for the royal stables formerly at Charing Cross in London, a name given as they were built on the site of the royal hawk mews (OED). Pulter is likely referring to an event in which 4,500 royalist soldiers were kept there “guarded by the trained bands” with the threat of a “gibbet” (gallows) to aid against “disorderly” behavior, after being defeated at the Battle of Naseby by parliamentarian forces (<bibl><title rend="italic">The Manner How the Prisoners Are to Be Brought Into the City of London</title> [London: T.F and J. Coe, 1645], 1-6</bibl>).</note></seg>.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="25">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">The greatest Mirackle our Saviour wrought</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">The greatest miracle our Savior wrought</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">The greatest miracle our saviour wrought</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="26">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Was when he Scourg’d out thoſe <w lemma="which"><abbr>w:<hi rend="superscript">ch</hi></abbr></w> Sould &amp; bought.</rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">Was when he <seg>scourged<note type="gloss">drove by force</note></seg> out <seg>those which sold and bought<note type="gloss">See Matthew 21:12: “Jesus went into the temple of God, and cast out all them that sold and bought in the temple, and overthrew the tables of the moneychangers, and the seats of them that sold doves …”</note></seg>.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Was when <seg>He scourged out those which sold and bought<note type="gloss">See Mat. 21.12: “Jesus went into the temple of God, and cast out all them that sold and bought in the temple, and overthrew the tables of the money-changes, and the seats of them that sold Doves”.</note></seg>.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
        <app>
            <rdg type="milestone" wit="#ft">
                <milestone unit="poem" rend="curled-line"/>
            </rdg>
        </app>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
