<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../src/vmachine.xsl"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
  schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI [

  <!ENTITY ff "<!-- ff ligature, representing capital modern day capital F, here represented as 'ff' -->ff">

  ]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mads.pp.64">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
          <title>And Must the Sword this Controverse Decide</title>
        <title type="sub">Poem #64</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Created by</resp>
          <persName>Leah Knight</persName>
          <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoded by</resp>
          <persName>Katherine Poland</persName>
          <persName>Matthew Taylor</persName>
          <persName>Betsy Chou</persName>
          <persName>Emily Andrey</persName>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>IT-project consultation by</resp>
          <persName>Josh Honn</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
          <orgName>Brock University</orgName>
          <orgName>University of Leeds</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <principal>
          <persName/>
        </principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="1"/>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription, transformations, and notes</resp>
          <persName>Leah Knight</persName>
          <orgName>Brock University</orgName>
          <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
        </respStmt>
      </editionStmt>
      <extent/>
      <publicationStmt>
        <ab/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listBibl>
          <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
              <repository>See witness list.</repository>
            </msIdentifier>
          </msDesc>
        </listBibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p/>
      </projectDesc>
      <p>Transcriptions are encoded in TEI(P5)-conformant XML.</p>
      <samplingDecl>
        <p/>
      </samplingDecl>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction>
          <p>Apparent errors are preserved and editorial corrections provided using SIC and CORR tags, but only where the editor conjectures that the original scribe or compositor would have recognized the instance as an error. For example, what according to modern usage is incorrect subject/verb agreement might have been deemed acceptable to a seventeenth-century scribe or compositor. All such instances are treated instead using the ORIG and REG tags. (See below.)</p>
          <p>Corrections and annotations made within the scope of the original document either by its original authors, owners, and/or transcribers are noted using ADD tags. These annotations and may be futher explained within NOTE tags, as added by the editors of this digital edition, for display within the apparatus.</p>
        </correction>
        <normalization>
          <p>Original spellings, abbreviations, and orthography are preserved. Where in the manuscripts a character’s status as majuscule or miniscule is ambiguous, the editor has silently chosen one or the other based on context and judgment (i.e., does not register such ambiguity in either the markup or the notes).</p>
        </normalization>
        <quotation>
          <p>Original quotation marks, if any, are preserved.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation>
          <p>Original hyphenation is preserved.</p>
        </hyphenation>
      </editorialDecl>
      <charDecl>
        <!-- Ligature combinations for which there are currently no corresponding Unicode codepoints. -->
        <glyph xml:id="ffllig">
          <glyphName>Handwritten 'ff' ligature, used in handwriting to represent modern F</glyphName>
        </glyph>
      </charDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="DDC22">
          <bibl>
            <title>Dewey Decimal Classification</title>
            <edition/>
            <publisher/>
            <pubPlace/>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-GB">British English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <!-- dewey decimal system class code 821: English Poetry -->
        <classCode scheme="DDC22">821</classCode>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
    <!-- List of all images associated with this document -->
      <graphic url="./document_images/7610_177.jpg" xml:id="f7610_177"/>
  </facsimile>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="ft">Transcription of manuscript: By <persName xml:id="lknight">Leah Knight</persName> and <persName xml:id="wwall">Wendy Wall</persName>.</witness>
          <witness xml:id="ee">Elemental edition: By <persName>Leah Knight</persName> and <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>.</witness>
          <witness xml:id="ae">Amplified edition: By <persName>Elizabeth Sauer</persName>.</witness>
        </listWit>
      </div>
    </front>

    <body>
      <app>
        <rdg wit="#ft">
            <pb ed="#ft" facs="#f7610_177" n="87r"/>
        </rdg>
        <rdg wit="#ee">
            <pb ed="#ee" facs="#f7610_177"/>
        </rdg>
        <rdg wit="#ae">
            <pb ed="#ae" facs="#f7610_177"/>
        </rdg>
      </app>
      <head>
        <app type="title">
          <rdg wit="#ft"><fw facs="#f7610_069" type="pageNum" place="margin-topright">PG#</fw>[Untitled]</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">And Must the Sword this Controverse Decide</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">And Must the Sword this Controverse Decide</rdg>
        </app>
        <app type="editorialnote">
          <rdg wit="#ft">
            <note type="editorialnote">In these transcriptions we preserve as many details of the original material, textual, and graphic properties of Hester Pulter’s manuscript verse as we have found practical. Whenever possible, for instance, original spelling, punctuation, capitalization, lineation, insertions, deletions, alterations, spacing between words and lines, and indentation are all maintained; abbreviations and brevigraphs are not expanded; and superscript and subscript representations are retained. <ref target="http://pulterproject.northwestern.edu/about-project-conventions.html#top" type="new-window-url">See full conventions for the transcriptions here.</ref></note>
          </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">
            <note type="editorialnote">The aim of the elemental edition is to make the poems accessible to the largest variety of readers, which involves modernizing spelling and punctuation as well as adding basic glosses. Spelling and punctuation reflect current standard American usage; punctuation highlights syntax which might otherwise be obscure. Outmoded but still familiar word forms (“thou,” “‘tis,” “hold’st”) are not modernized, and we do not modernize grammar when the sense remains legible. After a brief headnote aimed at offering a “way in” to the poem’s unique qualities and connections with other verse by Pulter or her contemporaries, the edition features a minimum of notes and interpretative framing to allow more immediate engagement with the poem. Glosses clarify synonyms or showcase various possible meanings in Pulter’s time. Other notes identify named people and places or clarify obscure material. We rely (without citation) primarily on the Oxford English Dictionary (OED), the Oxford Reference database, and the King James Version (KJV) of the Bible. When we rely on Alice Eardley’s edition of Pulter’s work, we cite her text generally (“Eardley”); other sources are cited in full. The result is an edition we consider a springboard for further work on Pulter’s poetry. <ref target="http://pulterproject.northwestern.edu/about-project-conventions.html#elemental-edition" type="new-window-url">See full conventions for this edition here.</ref></note></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">
              <note type="editorialnote">Originally one of the few untitled poems, “And Must the Sword this Controverse Decide” (Poem 64) is in Pulter’s hand but may also be in two other hands,<seg>[1]<note type="gloss">Christian, “The poems of Lady Hester Pulter,” 85.</note></seg> its collective composition thus complementing its tradition themes and the shared royalist sentiments of the intellectual circles in which she worked. As Alice Eardley observes, “the opening up of a poem’s potential contexts involves establishing the bounds of the knowledge that may legitimately be brought to bear on the material.”<seg>[2]<note type="gloss"><bibl>Alice Eardley, “Hester Pulter’s ‘Indivisibles’ and the Challenges of Annotating Early Modern Women’s Poetry,” <title rend="italic">SEL: Studies in English Literature 1500-1900</title> 52.1 (2012): 122 (117-41).</bibl></note></seg> My editorial insertions and comments are intended to enrich the interpretative experience of “And Must the Sword” by recourse to writings on royalist history and cross-references to books Pulter may have consulted—an inventory of which scholars have attempted to reconstruct on the basis of intrinsic textual evidence—and by comparisons to other poems in her oeuvre. The poem in iambic pentameter couplets appeared as a single stanza, which I divided to highlight the unusually bold break in the argument and, at the same time, to underscore the performance of the poet and the restoration of order and truth over the confusion resulting from the civil wars, regicide, and divine judgement described in the poem’s first half.<seg>[3]<note type="critical">By introducing this division, I forge formal connections between Poem 64 and Geffrey Whitney’s two-part emblem “Veritas temporis filia” <bibl>(Whitney, <title rend="italic">A Choice of Emblemes, and Other Devises</title> [Leiden, 1586], 4)</bibl>. See the note on line 21 below.</note></seg> For the same reason, I have capitalized the first letters of the names and figures of divine agents in the poem, and inserted endstops, which are entirely lacking in the manuscript version, including at the end of the text. Some lines require enjambment (see lines 16-17, for example). The inclusion of endstops throws into relief those lines whose significances are enhanced by enjambment. I have also modernized most of the spelling for the modern reader.</note>
          </rdg>
        </app>
        <app type="headnote">
          <rdg wit="#ee">
              <note type="headnote">This poem begins <foreign rend="italic">in medias res</foreign>: mid-sentence (“And”), and apparently in the midst of England’s civil wars, but sometime after the beheading of Charles I in 1649. In her opening query, the speaker seems to regret the inevitability of violence (“the sword”) as a solution to her country’s misrule, yet she still invokes divine vengeance upon her foes. Although she appears to implore God to condemn <hi rend="italic">all</hi> factions, Pulter evidently excluded her own party from this condemnation: factions were dissidents; royalists were loyalists. The invocation of the “Lord of Hosts,” an epithet from the Hebrew Bible, suits the eye-for-an-eye endgame envisioned here: if the speaker has her way, the bloodthirsty shall be quenched by each other’s blood, and as they were mercilessly deaf to the cries of the innocent, so God shall be to theirs, at the end of their earthly lives or (implicitly) in a hellish hereafter. The speaker then prays for the eternal salvation of those she considers God’s chosen, and for the restoration at the end of time of their slain king: not, in this context, Christ, but Charles I (although the two were often identified in royalist imagery). As though to usher in this future peace (for some, anyhow), the concluding hortatory anaphora (“Let … Let”) and personified abstractions (time, grace, truth) evoke a serenity utterly at odds with the bloody clashes earlier in the poem.</note>
          </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">
            <note type="headnote">
                <p>This lyrical poem resonates with Pulter’s three elegies on Charles I, which were influenced by the culture and aesthetics of kingship and martyrdom in the wake of the regicide (1649). In an age before political parties, royalism—which is on full display in Pulter’s poetry—emerged as a political, cultural, and literary phenomenon that resisted Cromwellian rule while upholding monarchical authority. Composed c. 1651, “And Must the Sword this Controverse Decide” reflects on the British civil wars, the ongoing political and civil disputes, and on the persistence of royalist sentiment and the value of literary production well after the regicide, implied by the reference to the king’s death, which “hath been deplored / So long by us.”</p>
                <p>The tone of Pulter’s royalist verse is serious, and not reflective of the Anacreontic mid seventeenth-century literary mode, which emerged in the experience of royalist defeat, and which represents one branch of the heterogeneous Cavalier poetic tradition. Anacreon, the ancient Greek poet known for his drinking lyrics, was the inspiration for the witty, masculinist verse of some English Cavalier lyricists.<seg>[1]<note type="gloss"><bibl>Karen Britland, “Conspiring with ‘friends’: Hester Pulter’s Poetry and the Stanley Family at Cumberlow Green,” <title rend="italic">The Review of English Studies</title>, NS, 69.292 (2018): 846-49 (832–54).</bibl></note></seg> Unsurprisingly, neither Pulter nor her like-minded (female) contemporaries, notably Margaret Cavendish and Katherine Philips, indulge and toast the courtly ideals of fine living, drinking, socializing, and versifying in the spirit of sprezzatura (a casual grace).<seg>[2]<note type="gloss"><bibl>Ann Baynes Coiro, “The Personal Rule of Poets: Cavalier Poetry and the English Revolution,” <title rend="italic">The Oxford Handbook of Literature and the English Revolution</title>, ed. Laura Lunger Knoppers (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2012), 206-37.</bibl> The poems by Cavendish and Philips post-date Pulter’s Poem 64, but they display similar convictions. Pulter likely owned a copy of Cavendish’s <title rend="italic">Poems, and Fancies written by the Right Honourable, the Lady Margaret Newcastle</title> (London, 1653). Philips defended the (dead) king’s reputation against the libel of Fifth Monarchist and Approver of Ministers, Vavasor Powell, in “Upon the Double Murther of K. Charles I,” which was not published until 1667, but was written in the early 1650s. See <bibl>Philips, <title rend="italic">Poems by the most deservedly Admired Mrs. Katherine Philips, the matchless Orinda</title> (London, 1667), 1-2.</bibl></note></seg> Among the Cavalier poets who produced meditative verses on retreat, loss, exile, and death, which may have influenced Pulter, was Thomas Carew. His posthumous 1640 volume, titled “Poems,” is assumed to be among Pulter’s library holdings. Pulter likely also possessed a copy of Robert Herrick’s <title rend="italic">Hesperides</title> or, <title rend="italic">The works both humane &amp; divine of Robert Herrick, Esq.</title> (1648) among whose poetic themes are the civil wars and Charles I’s stellification. “To the King,” for example, describes “my <hi rend="italic">Charles</hi> [who] shines here, / A Publike Light (in this immensive Sphere).” Herrick’s <title rend="italic">Noble Numbers: or, His Pious Pieces</title> (1647) in <title rend="italic">Hesperides</title> (1648) contains various poems hailing the king, including “Good Friday: <foreign rend="italic">Rex Tragicus</foreign>; or, Christ Going to His Crosse,” which eerily predicts Charles’s execution and prophesies his ascent: “begin, great King! Ascend Thy throne, / And thence proceed, to act Thy Passion / To such an height, to such a period rais’d, / As Hell, and Earth, and Heav’n may stand amazed.”<seg>[3]<note type="gloss"><bibl>Herrick, <title rend="italic">Hesperides</title> or, <title rend="italic">The works both humane &amp; divine of Robert Herrick, Esq.</title> (London, 1648), 278; <title rend="italic">His Noble Numbers: or, His Pious Pieces</title>, in <title rend="italic">Hesperides</title>, 74.</bibl></note></seg> Pulter’s Poem 64 will also commemorate and raise Charles to the spheres.</p>
                <p>Pulter’s pro-monarchy poems are solemn, biblical, and formal—in line with many of the elegiac works composed in response to the regicide and the release of the most popular book of the seventeenth century, <title rend="italic">Eikon Basilike</title>, a copy of which Pulter probably owned.<seg>[4]<note type="critical">Stefan Graham Christian categorizes <title rend="italic">Eikon Basilike</title> as a “possible” holding in Pulter’s library. See <bibl>Christian’s authoritative and valuable list of Pulter’s library books, certain and probable, in Christian, “The Poems of Lady Hester Pulter (1605?–1678): An Annotated Edition” (2012), 60–64. Doctoral Dissertations Available from Proquest. AAI3545910.</bibl> Pulter was introduced in London to William Dugard, the printer of <title rend="italic">Eikon Basilike</title> (<bibl>Sarah C. E. Ross and Elizabeth Scott-Baumann, eds., <title rend="italic">Women Poets of the English Civil War</title> [Manchester: Manchester University Press, 2018], 90</bibl>). Charles’s book is heavily reliant on the Psalms, as is Pulter’s poetry; in the case of Poem 64, note, for example, the indebtedness to Psalm 137.</note></seg> Purportedly in prayer, Charles I appeals in <title rend="italic">Eikon Basilike</title> to a higher form of truth and justice, and performs acts of self-examination and devotion, for which James I, John Donne, and George Herbert had supplied examples.<seg>[5]<note type="critical">Refer to the Curation entitled <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="#ctxs">Pulter reads <title rend="italic">Eikon Basilike</title></ref> for the foldout and title page of <title rend="italic">Eikon Basilike</title>. Authored by Charles I and John Gauden, <title rend="italic">Eikon Basilike. The pourtraicture of His sacred Majestie in his solitudes and sufferings</title> was printed by William Dugard (London, 1649). Charles was indebted to Sandys’s metrical translation of the psalter, <bibl><title rend="italic">A Paraphrase Upon the Psalmes of David in A Paraphrase Upon the Divine Poems</title> (London, 1636, rev. ed. 1638, rpt. 1648)</bibl>, which was dedicated to the monarch and his spouse, and intended for singing in the Chapel Royal.</note></seg> Pulter also adopted these writers as literary models, and in Poem 64, in the role of “Time’s fair Virgin Daughter,” unsheathes not a sword but a stylus to justify the legitimacy and legacy of kingship. The poet-speaker opens by asking Job’s question to God about whether “the sword this controverse [must] decide.” In the course of the poem, she demonstrates—as in the Epistle to the Hebrews 4:12 and in a contemporary book Pulter likely owned, Robert Burton’s 1621 <title rend="italic">Anatomy of Melancholy</title>—that “It is an old saying, <hi rend="italic">A blow with a word, strikes deeper then a blow with a sword</hi>.”<seg>[6]<note type="gloss"><bibl>Robert Burton, <title rend="italic">The Anatomy of Melancholy</title> (Oxford, 1621), 1.2.4.4, p. 196.</bibl></note></seg> Poem 64 delivers a blow in verse form.</p>
                <p>“And Must the Sword” resonates with other poems in Pulter’s oeuvre, including the tearful <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="14">On the Horrid Murder of that Incomparable Prince</ref>, <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="15">Let None Sigh More for Lucas or for Lisle [On the Same [2]]</ref>, which takes up the theme of Poem 14, and <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="27">On the King’s Most Excellent Majesty</ref>. Pre-1649 Pulter poems that set the scene and supply interpretative frames for those on the regicide are <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="13">Upon the Imprisonment of his Sacred Majesty</ref>, written in 1647, and <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="7">On those Two Unparalleled Friends, Sir George Lisle and Sir Charles Lucas</ref>, written c. 1648. These royalist poems provide her with a venue for political commentary, an uncharacteristic mode of expression for a female poet whose repertoire consists largely of personal poetry. However, she (Hester) identifies herself repeatedly in her oeuvre with and as the Noble Hadassah, a savior of her chosen nation.</p>
            </note>
          </rdg>
        </app>
      </head>

      <l n="1">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft"><seg>And<note type="physical">This poem is in a different hand from the main scribe, and is on paper that was tipped into the manuscript after binding.</note></seg> must the ſword this controverce deſide</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee"><seg>And<note type="physical">This poem is probably in Pulter’s hand.</note></seg> must the sword this <seg>controverse<note type="gloss">obsolete form of “controversy”</note></seg> decide:</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>And must the sword this controverse decide<note type="critical"><p>The line is paraphrased rather liberally from the Book of Job 9:23 (“If the scourge slay suddenly, he will laugh at the trial of the innocent”). Pulter is indebted to <bibl>George Sandys’s <title rend="italic">A Paraphrase Upon Job in A Paraphrase Upon the Divine Poems</title> (London, 1638), 14-15</bibl>, which Sandys dedicates to King Charles. The relevant passage from <title rend="italic">A Paraphrase Upon Job</title> is in the Curation entitled <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="ctxs">Pulter Reads George Sandys’s <title rend="italic">Paraphrase Upon Job</title></ref>. Neither the Geneva Bible nor the King James Bible (KJB)—which is the “Authorized Version” for readers of the time—provides the translation or paraphrase of Job 9:23 that Pulter uses for the opening line of Poem 64. And neither Stefan Christian nor Alice Eardley mentions Sandys’s <title rend="italic">A Paraphrase Upon Job</title> in their editions of Pulter’s poems (for Eardley, see <bibl><title rend="italic">Lady Hester Pulter: Poems, Emblems, and The Unfortunate Florinda</title>, ed. Alice Eardley [Toronto: University of Toronto Press, 2014]</bibl>).</p>
                <p>Many of the themes and figures used by Sandys in his paraphrase (or what we might call an amplified edition) of Job appear in Pulter’s present poem, which reflects on providence and divine judgement. However, by virtue of rendering “And with his Sword the controverse decides” into a rhetorical question, Pulter is re-paraphrasing Sandys’s <title rend="italic">A Paraphrase Upon Job</title>. That Pulter is generally fascinated by Job is apparent as well in <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="13">Upon the Imprisonment of his Sacred Majesty</ref>, in which she describes Charles: “Then let our Job-like saint rise from the ground / For piety and patience so renowned / That for the best of kings he may be crowned” (Elemental Edition, lines 13-15).</p></note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="2">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Which of theſe &ff;actions shall this kingdome ride</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Which of these <seg>factions<note type="gloss">depreciative term for political (and often dissenting and disputatious) groups, here apparently alluding to warring sides in England’s civil wars</note></seg> shall this kingdom <seg>ride<note type="gloss">in this context, likely meaning dominate or control, oppress or tyrannize; connotations include gaining (unearned) advantage or aggrandizement from, and several senses related to violence (serving in a cavalry; going on horseback into battle; parading as punishment); figuratively, to ride hard (or to death).</note></seg>?</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Which of these factions shall this kingdom ride?</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="3">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Great God loock <seg><del>down</del><note type="physical">double strike-through</note></seg> on their pride and heere their bosts</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Great God, look on their pride and hear their boasts;</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Great God, <seg>look on their pride<note type="critical">“down” appeared between the words “look” and “on” in the manuscript edition of the poem, but was struck out. It is still implied here, and the phrase appears in a number of Pulter’s poems, such as, <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="63">Dear God, from Thy High Throne Look Down</ref>, which is in Pulter’s hand. <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="24">How Long Shall My Dejected Soul</ref> features “Oh then look down” (line 9). In line 3 of Poem 64, Pulter recalls KJB Genesis 11:5: “And the LORD came down to see the city and the tower, which the children of men builded.” See also Psalm 137.</note></seg> and hear their boasts;</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="4">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Declare thy ſelfe alone the Lord of Hosts</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Declare thy self alone the <seg>Lord of Hosts<note type="gloss">epithet for God used often in the Old Testament, sometimes alluding to the multitude of attending angels and sometimes to Israel’s armies; in latter sense, suggestive of “God of armies or battles.”</note></seg>;</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Declare thy self alone the Lord of Hosts;</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="5">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Confound their plotts and curs’t Imagination</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Confound their plots and cursed imagination</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>Confound<note type="critical">to confuse; to overthrow. Pulter deliberately uses this word to connect the divine retribution against the proud builders of Babel to the cry for justice against the Cromwellian government. “Confound their language” is repeated within two verses of the KJB (Genesis 11:7, 9).</note></seg> their plots and cursed <seg>imagination<note type="critical"><p>See KJB Genesis 11:6: “And the LORD said, Behold, … this they begin to do: and now nothing will be restrained from them, which they have imagined to do.”</p>
                <p>Pulter’s <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="67">Mighty Nimrod (Emblem 1)</ref> is replete with references to the delusions and folly of the builders “Foolishly dreaming” (l. 9). Verses 19-20 in the manuscript read “Let their Accursed plots prove their delusion / For Fance’d Glory let them find confusion.”</p>
            </note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="6">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">That haue allmost desroy’d this Church and Nation</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">That have almost destroyed this church and nation.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">That have almost destroyed this <seg>church and nation<note type="gloss">refers to the concept of a stable, unified country, now devastated by the builders of Babel / the doomed Cromwellian government</note></seg>.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="7">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">&ff;or blood they thirst, <seg>O<note type="physical">two short upright marks atop</note></seg> lett them bee imbrued</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">For blood they thirst: O, let them be <seg>imbrued<note type="gloss">stained, dyed, especially with blood; earlier also sometimes with the sense of “defiled”</note></seg></rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">For blood they thirst: O, let them be <seg>imbrued<note type="gloss">stained or bloodied one’s hands or sword. The adversaries use swords; God and the poet wield words.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="8">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">In one anothers, that haue of bedu’ed</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">In one another’s, that have <seg>oft<note type="physical">The manuscript reads “of.”</note></seg> bedewed</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">In one another’s, that have oft bedewed</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="9">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">With tears ſad Widdows, and poore Orphans, eyes</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">With tears sad widows’ and poor orphans’ eyes;</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">With tears sad <seg>widows’ and poor orphans’<note type="critical">This biblical phrase often appears in cries for justice for the oppressed; see, for example, James 1:27. Sandys writes, “Sad widowes, by thee rifled, weepe in vaine: / And ruin’d Orphants of thy Rapes complaine” (<title rend="italic">A Paraphrase Upon Job</title>, 29). Poet Anne Bradstreet wrote about the crises of the “present troubles” in like terms, and textual evidence in Pulter’s poetry suggests she owned a copy of Bradstreet’s 1650 <title rend="italic">The Tenth Muse lately sprung up in America. Or severall poems, compiled with great variety of wit and learning, full of delight ... By a Gentlewoman in those parts</title> (London, 1650). See the Curation entitled <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="#ctxs">Pulter Reads Bradstreet’s <title rend="italic">Tenth Muse</title></ref>. Composed in 1643, Bradstreet’s “A Dialogue between Old <hi rend="italic">England</hi> and New, concerning their present troubles. Anno 1642,” which laments the civil wars, is greatly indebted to French Huguenot poet Guillaume de Salluste Du Bartas’s “Dialogue upon the Troubles past: Betweene Heraclitus and Democritus, the weeping and the laughing Philosophers.” Pulter probably owned a copy of Du Bartas in translation—<title rend="italic">Du Bartas his Devine Weekes and Workes</title> by Josuah Sylvester (London, 1611). “A Dialogue” appears on pp. 759-63. Although she was a Puritan, Bradstreet, like her community, championed the cause of the king and decried the sufferings of the victims of war.</note></seg> eyes;</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="10">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Bee deffe <seg><del>the</del><note type="physical">double strike-through</note></seg> to theirs as they were to their cries</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Be deaf to <seg>theirs, as they were to their<note type="gloss">“theirs” and “they” refer to the warring factions; “their” to the widows and orphans.</note></seg> cries.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>Be deaf to theirs, as they<note type="critical">“theirs” and “they” reverberate and reinforce the theme of just deserts. The cry for vengeance recalls Psalm 137: “without pity heare their dying grones” (<bibl>George Sandys, <title rend="italic">A Paraphrase Upon the Psalmes</title> in <title rend="italic">A Paraphrase Upon the Divine Poems</title> [London, 1638], 160</bibl>).</note></seg> were to their cries.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="11">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">As in their highth they <seg>merrie<note type="physical">second “r” could be “t”</note></seg> ne’r would know</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">As in their <seg>height<note type="gloss">not only a high or the highest point (spatially), but eminence or elevation in status or exalted rank; haughtiness; the highest point or degree</note></seg> they mercy ne’er would know,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">As in their <seg>height<note type="critical">of pride. The references to height and, in the following line, to “extremes,” extend the comparison between the proud (nameless) builders of Babel and the Rump, who warred against king and country.</note></seg> they mercy ne’er would know,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="12">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">In their extremes noe Mertie <seg><add place="above"><del>r</del></add><note type="physical">floating superscript “r” is blotted out in ink</note></seg> to them ſhow</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee"><seg>In their extremes<note type="gloss">in the last moments or stage of life (as in the Latin <foreign rend="italic">in extremis</foreign>); given the spatial imagery in the line above (“height”), the meaning of “extreme” as a figurative position furthest from the (divine) center also resonates.</note></seg> no mercy to them show.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">In <seg>their extremes<note type="gloss">the phrase complements the aforementioned “their height” but also references “the last moments or stage of life” (OED, C.<hi rend="italic">n</hi>.2b.)</note></seg> <seg>no mercy<note type="critical">a reverberation of the cry for just deserts, a variation on the entreaty made two lines earlier</note></seg> to them show.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="13">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Butt in that dismale, Black, and Blooddy daye</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">But in that dismal, black, and bloody <seg>day<note type="gloss">the Day of Judgment at the end of time, when God will judge the living and resurrected dead and reward them with eternal “life” (see next line) or punish them accordingly</note></seg>,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>But<note type="critical">acts as a volta in the argument and signals the start of the second and final section of the poem which is marked by alternating anaphoras (“And …. and”; “Let … let”). The pronouncements commencing with “And” are designed as responses to the poem’s opening rhetorical question, which begins with “And” and which a poet can best answer. The imperatives throughout the poem establish continuity between the two parts.</note></seg> in that <seg>dismal, black, and bloody day<note type="critical"><foreign rend="italic">dies mali</foreign>; unfortunate, unpropitious day; a cry for justice and judgement that links the present moment to doomsday or the Day of Judgement</note></seg>,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="14">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Give all thy choſen ones their liffe a praye</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Give all thy <seg>chosen ones<note type="gloss">originally, Israelites (“O ye seed of Israel his servant, ye children of Jacob, his chosen ones” [1 Chronicles 16:13]); in Protestant readings, any of God’s elect, chosen for salvation at the Day of Judgment</note></seg> their life, I pray,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Give all thy <seg>chosen ones<note type="critical">The alignment of Protestant English with the chosen Israelites was a very common historical and literary practice. See, for example, the Curation entitled <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="#ctxs">Pulter Reads Bradstreet’s <title rend="italic">Tenth Muse</title></ref>.</note></seg> their life, I pray,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="15">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">And lett our Longeinge eyes behold restor’d</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">And let our longing eyes behold, restored,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">And let our longing eyes behold, restored,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="16">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Our Gratious Kinge, whos loſs hath bin <seg>deplor’ed<note type="physical">second “e” scribbled out</note></seg></rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Our gracious <seg>king<note type="gloss">Charles I; the next line (“let him rest above”) suggests the poem was written after his beheading, which would prevent his being “restored” on earth; the speaker anticipates his restoration at the Day of Judgment instead.</note></seg>, whose loss hath been <seg>deplored<note type="gloss">lamented</note></seg></rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Our gracious king, whose loss hath been deplored</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="17">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">ſoe longe by us <seg>O<note type="physical">two short upright marks atop</note></seg> lett him rest above <seg><del>in providence</del><note type="physical">double strike-through</note></seg></rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">So long by us. O, let him rest above</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>So long<note type="critical">signals the prolonged experience of loss, which has been bewailed (deplored). The phrase helps date the poem as post-1649, the year of the regicide, after which conflicts involving the English, Irish, and Scottish Royalists and Presbyterians, and Covenanters continued through to 1651, when Pulter likely composed the poem. Laments and cries resound throughout the elegiac poem. The pivotal clause “whose loss hath been deplored” continues the enjambed verse.</note></seg> by us. O, let him rest above</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="18">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">In providence, and in the Orb of <seg>love<note type="physical">to right, after a space, vertical line curving to right at top</note></seg></rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">In <seg>providence<note type="gloss">God’s omniscient and protective care</note></seg>, and in the <seg>orb of love<note type="gloss">apparently a reference to the divine realm (the Christian God being sometimes identified with love); “orb” as world, or a celestial sphere (as in a sun or planet); in astronomy, a hollow sphere thought to surround the earth and carry the planets and stars in their revolution.</note></seg></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>In providence<note type="critical">In the manuscript, “in providence” is crossed out and moved to the following line, thus fittingly suspending “above” while aligning “providence” with “Orb of love.” And of course the couplet reappears in the poem’s final distich, though this time as “love” followed by “above.”</note></seg>, and in the <seg>Orb of love<note type="critical">An orb is a ring (from Latin orbis “ring”). Here divine providence is figured as an orb of love, which encircles, envelops, orders, and directs the planets, stars, and worlds. The king moves in the orb of love’s orbit (the <foreign rend="italic">primum mobile</foreign>). Cf. <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="27">On the King’s Most Excellent Majesty</ref>, line 15. <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="2">The Invitation into the Country</ref>, composed in 1647, prays for the stellification of the king and queen: “Just heaven, hear our prayers and tears / And place them in their shining spheres” (lines 187-88). Refer to the reference in the headnote to Herrick, who exalts Charles I as a “Publike Light (in this immensive Sphere).”</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="19">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Lett all his actions move as in his youth</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Let all his actions move, as in his youth;</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Let all his actions move, as in his youth;</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="20">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">And lett them turn upon the Poles of <del>th</del> truth</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">And let them turn upon the <seg>poles of truth<note type="critical">a metaphor extending the astronomical sense of the “orb of love” above, with “poles” signifying the ends of an axis on which something rotates (in this case, the axis being truth, and the actions of Charles I turning on that axis).</note></seg>.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">And let them turn upon the <seg>Poles of Truth<note type="critical"> an astronomical figure, displaying Pulter’s interest in astronomy. The poles serve as a magnet which draws the king and around which his movements revolve. “Truth” is pivotal, ending this line and beginning the next (Truth is Time’s daughter).</note></seg>.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="21">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Let tym’s faire Virgin Daughter <seg><del>pe[?]</del><note type="physical">unidentified third letter crossed out</note></seg> pen his story</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Let <seg>Time’s fair virgin daughter<note type="gloss">Proverbially, Truth is the daughter of Time.</note></seg> pen his story,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Let <seg>Time’s fair Virgin Daughter<note type="critical"><p>Pulter would have known Geffrey Whitney’s emblem “Veritas temporis filia,” in which truth is personified as father Time’s “daughter deare” (Whitney, <title rend="italic">A Choice of Emblemes, and Other Devises</title> [Leiden, 1586], 4, line 4). See the Curation <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="#ctxs">Pulter Reads Whitney’s <title rend="italic">Emblemes</title></ref>. Whitney’s very popular <title rend="italic">Choice of Emblemes</title> is a highly likely candidate for inclusion among Pulter’s library holdings. In “And Must the Sword,” Pulter’s speaker assumes the role of Truth (aligned with the “Poles of Truth”) who writes and transports the king into truth’s orbit. The poet thus “pen[s] his story” and immortalizes him, as she did in <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="27">On the King’s Most Excellent Majesty</ref> (1649-1651), in which his own “valor fills with wonder future story, / Whilst virtue crowns him with immortal glory” (elemental edition, lines 3-4). To eulogize Charles I, Pulter picks up the thread (the poem’s theme or storyline), which is connected to the thread of grace or divine favor.</p>
                <p>Sandys assigns the job of settling the controversy not to the sword but to justice: “By Equitie let us our Judgements guide: / And this long controverted Cause decide” (<title rend="italic">A Paraphrase Upon Job</title>, p. 44). In and through verses that plead for justice and the righteous restoration of kingship, Pulter implies that Truth, penned by the poet and identified as the poet, will restore order, and thus reverse the confusion of tongues and the babble. The term “truth” appears twice in the poem directly, once associated with the king’s movements and then with divine truth that envelops the king’s people who live, move, and have their being in him. But it is also inferred by the reference to Time’s Daughter who uses verses to forge the identifications between truths.</p></note></seg> pen his story,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="22">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Whils’t Grace conduct’s him to Eternall Glory</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Whilst Grace conducts him to eternal glory;</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Whilst <seg>Grace<note type="gloss">God-given grace immortalizes the righteous king.</note></seg> conducts him to eternal glory;</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="23">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">And then when totall Nature is <seg>deſolve’d<note type="physical">second “e” may be scribbled out</note></seg></rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">And then, when total nature is dissolved,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">And then, when total nature is dissolved,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="24">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Lett Him and His in Glory bee involv’d</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Let him and <seg>his<note type="gloss">those to whom he is closely related, his family or kindred; figuratively, the king’s followers</note></seg> in glory be involved;</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Let him and his in glory be <seg>involved<note type="critical"><p>involve means to enfold, envelop, entangle, include (“involve, v.” OED, 1).</p> 
                Dissolve[d]/involve[d] is perhaps Pulter’s most frequently used rhymed couplet. Select examples of poems in which the couplet appears include <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="8">On that Unparalleled Prince Charles the First, His Horrid Murder</ref>; <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="27">On the King’s Most Excellent Majesty</ref>; <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="30">The Center</ref>; <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="32">Aletheia’s Pearl</ref>; <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="41">The Invocation of the Elements</ref>; and <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="56">A Dialogue Between Two Sisters</ref>. Most often, the couplet is used in distiches that describe the destruction of the world as a consequence of the eclipsed king: “But if the sun in darkness be involved, / Old nature’s fabric would be soon dissolved” (stanza 2, <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="8">On that Unparalleled Prince Charles the First, His Horrid Murder</ref>).</note></seg>;</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="25">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">And on all thoſe that doe thy Isarell love</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">And on all those that do <seg>thy Israel<note type="gloss">literally, those descended from Israel or Jacob, so the Jewish or Hebrew nation; figuratively, here, God’s chosen, applied by Christians to Christians</note></seg> love,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">And on all those that do <seg>thy Israel<note type="critical">England (the monarch and his people—new Israel). This is a poem about “this church and nation” (6).</note></seg> love,</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="26">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Lett peace, and truth, flow on them from <seg>above<note type="physical">reverse of page blank</note></seg></rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Let peace, and truth, flow on them from above.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>Let peace, and truth, flow<note type="critical">Echoes line 6 of <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="27">On the King’s Most Excellent Majesty</ref>. The line is a variation on Psalm 85:10. The alignment of peace with truth is a commonplace. John Milton’s <title rend="italic">Poems of Mr. John Milton both English and Latin</title> (London, 1645), a copy of which Pulter likely owned, thanks to her younger sister Margaret Ley Hobson, connects “Truth, and Peace, and Love,” which, unlike Time, “shall ever shine / About the supreme Throne” (“On Time,” 20). Milton’s “On the morning of Christs Nativity. Compos’d 1629” allegorizes Peace, Truth, Justice, and Mercy, who prepare the way for the Second Coming (<title rend="italic">Poems</title>, pp. 4, 7-8).</note></seg> on them from <seg>above<note type="critical">This second occurrence of the love/above rhymed couplet in the poem—the first being 9 and 10 lines earlier—reinforces the effectiveness of the poem’s work in binding king, nation, and God. The anaphora (“Let …. Let”) marking the last eight lines links the actions and connects the movements described in the poem. The concluding lines of Poem 64 are also reminiscent of Bradstreet’s prophetic benediction (with its anaphora) that constitutes the final speech in “A Dialogue” and envisions an elect, unified England. Refer to <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="#ctxs">Pulter Reads Bradstreet’s <title rend="italic">Tenth Muse</title></ref></note></seg>.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
