<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../src/vmachine.xsl"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
  schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI [

  <!ENTITY ff "<!-- ff ligature, representing capital modern day capital F, here represented as 'ff' -->ff">

  ]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mads.pp.115">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
          <title>Phalaris and the Brazen Bull (Emblem 50)</title>
        <title type="sub">Poem #115</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Created by</resp>
          <persName>Leah Knight</persName>
          <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoded by</resp>
          <persName>Katherine Poland</persName>
          <persName>Matthew Taylor</persName>
          <persName>Betsy Chou</persName>
          <persName>Emily Andrey</persName>
          <persName>Mallen Clifton</persName>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>IT-project consultation by</resp>
          <persName>Josh Honn</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
          <orgName>Brock University</orgName>
          <orgName>University of Leeds</orgName>
        </sponsor>
        <principal>
          <persName/>
        </principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="1"/>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Transcription, transformations, and notes</resp>
          <persName>Leah Knight</persName>
          <orgName>Brock University</orgName>
          <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>
          <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
        </respStmt>
      </editionStmt>
      <extent/>
      <publicationStmt>
        <ab/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listBibl>
          <msDesc>
            <msIdentifier>
              <repository>See witness list.</repository>
            </msIdentifier>
          </msDesc>
        </listBibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p/>
      </projectDesc>
      <p>Transcriptions are encoded in TEI(P5)-conformant XML.</p>
      <samplingDecl>
        <p/>
      </samplingDecl>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction>
          <p>Apparent errors are preserved and editorial corrections provided using SIC and CORR tags, but only where the editor conjectures that the original scribe or compositor would have recognized the instance as an error. For example, what according to modern usage is incorrect subject/verb agreement might have been deemed acceptable to a seventeenth-century scribe or compositor. All such instances are treated instead using the ORIG and REG tags. (See below.)</p>
          <p>Corrections and annotations made within the scope of the original document either by its original authors, owners, and/or transcribers are noted using ADD tags. These annotations and may be further explained within NOTE tags, as added by the editors of this digital edition, for display within the apparatus.</p>
        </correction>
        <normalization>
          <p>Original spellings, abbreviations, and orthography are preserved. Where in the manuscripts a character’s status as majuscule or minuscule is ambiguous, the editor has silently chosen one or the other based on context and judgment (i.e., does not register such ambiguity in either the markup or the notes).</p>
        </normalization>
        <quotation>
          <p>Original quotation marks, if any, are preserved.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation>
          <p>Original hyphenation is preserved.</p>
        </hyphenation>
      </editorialDecl>
      <charDecl>
        <!-- Ligature combinations for which there are currently no corresponding Unicode codepoints. -->
        <glyph xml:id="ffllig">
          <glyphName>Handwritten 'ff' ligature, used in handwriting to represent modern F</glyphName>
        </glyph>
      </charDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="DDC22">
          <bibl>
            <title>Dewey Decimal Classification</title>
            <edition/>
            <publisher/>
            <pubPlace/>
          </bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en-GB">British English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <!-- dewey decimal system class code 821: English Poetry -->
        <classCode scheme="DDC22">821</classCode>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
    <!-- List of all images associated with this document -->
    <graphic url="./document_images/7610_255.jpg" xml:id="f7610_255"/>
  </facsimile>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="ft">Transcription of manuscript: By <persName xml:id="lknight">Leah Knight</persName> and <persName xml:id="wwall">Wendy Wall</persName>.</witness>
          <witness xml:id="ee">Elemental edition: By <persName>Leah Knight</persName> and <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>.</witness>
         <witness xml:id="ae">Amplified edition: By <persName>Jonathan Koch</persName>.</witness>
        </listWit>
      </div>
    </front>

    <body>

      <!-- Each page break should be represented with a block like this with the correct facs reference-->
      <app>
        <rdg wit="#ft">
          <pb ed="#ft" facs="#f7610_255" n="126r"/>
        </rdg>
        <rdg wit="#ee">
          <pb ed="#ee" facs="#f7610_255"/>
        </rdg>
        <rdg wit="#ae">
          <pb ed="#ae" facs="#f7610_255"/>
        </rdg>
      </app>

      <head>
        <app type="title">
          <rdg wit="#ft"><fw facs="#f7610_069" type="pageNum" place="margin-topright">PG#</fw>[Emblem 50]</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Phalaris and the Brazen Bull<lb/>(Emblem 50)</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>Phalaris and the Brazen Bull<lb/>(Emblem 50)<note type="critical">The title supplied by Leah Knight and Wendy Wall in the Elemental Edition draws out the figure of Phalaris from within the story of the brass bull’s construction and use in sixth century (BCE) Sicily. Such focus is consistent with Phalaris’s presence in the archive of early modern English print (see <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="#ctxs">Phalaris and Perillus in Early Modern Print</ref>). But the poem’s conceit turns on the figure of Perillus, who is punished for his prideful cunning, just as, Pulter hopes, the accursed regicides will be. Perhaps, then, the title of the emblem might as aptly read: “Perillus and Brazen Bull.”</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
        <app type="editorialnote">
          <rdg wit="#ft">
            <note type="editorialnote">In these transcriptions we preserve as many details of the original material, textual, and graphic properties of Hester Pulter’s manuscript verse as we have found practical. Whenever possible, for instance, original spelling, punctuation, capitalization, lineation, insertions, deletions, alterations, spacing between words and lines, and indentation are all maintained; abbreviations and brevigraphs are not expanded; and superscript and subscript representations are retained. <ref target="//pulterproject.northwestern.edu/about-project-conventions.html#top" type="new-window-url">See full conventions for the transcriptions here.</ref></note>
          </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ee">
            <note type="editorialnote">The aim of the elemental edition is to make the poems accessible to the largest variety of readers, which involves modernizing spelling and punctuation as well as adding basic glosses. Spelling and punctuation reflect current standard American usage; punctuation highlights syntax which might otherwise be obscure. Outmoded but still familiar word forms (“thou,” “‘tis,” “hold’st”) are not modernized, and we do not modernize grammar when the sense remains legible. After a brief headnote aimed at offering a “way in” to the poem’s unique qualities and connections with other verse by Pulter or her contemporaries, the edition features a minimum of notes and interpretative framing to allow more immediate engagement with the poem. Glosses clarify synonyms or showcase various possible meanings in Pulter’s time. Other notes identify named people and places or clarify obscure material. We rely (without citation) primarily on the Oxford English Dictionary (OED), the Oxford Reference database, and the King James Version (KJV) of the Bible. When we rely on Alice Eardley’s edition of Pulter’s work, we cite her text generally (“Eardley”); other sources are cited in full. The result is an edition we consider a springboard for further work on Pulter’s poetry. <ref target="//pulterproject.northwestern.edu/about-project-conventions.html#elemental-edition" type="new-window-url">See full conventions for this edition here.</ref></note></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">
            <note type="editorialnote">Since Pulter uses the formal features of this emblem to reproduce the acts of violence and torture depicted in the poem, I have employed a semi-diplomatic editorial principle in an effort to preserve and highlight these features. Another benefit of this approach is that it retains the original spelling of words, like “stag” (line 16), which had contemporary resonance that is lost when the spelling is modernized. At line 15, I have corrected “Newburg” to “Newbury,” providing a note explaining my reasoning, and I have incorporated the additions to lines 18 and 22 (“our” and “those”) without drawing typographic attention to their inserted status in the original manuscript. The difference between majuscule and minuscule letters is sometimes difficult to discern in the scribal hand of the manuscript (especially for initial k’s and s’s), but every effort has been taken to transcribe those letters uniformly.</note>
          </rdg>
        </app>
        <app type="headnote">
          <rdg wit="#ee">
              <note type="headnote">How terribly just to die in the very torture device one invented! Pulter canvasses classical history and myth for tales of lawless, tyrannical figures known for having baked, stretched, chopped, drowned, bashed, and torn their unsuspecting victims to death—only to suffer the same fate themselves. She both wishes for, and finally prophesies, the extension of this pattern of comeuppance to those she condemns as the lawless tyrants of her own day: primarily, the Civil War “regicides” who killed Charles I. Pulter’s fantasy of vengeance escalates from one of racial and national boundary-crossings (the punitive transformation of British Parliamentarians into West Indian slaves) into her enemies’ full descent into Hell. In the conclusion of this revenge fantasy, Pulter imagines their roars of eternal pain echoing the poem’s opening cries, such that, formally, the poem simulates the cycle of justice it describes.</note>
          </rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">
            <note type="headnote">
              <p>Emblem 50 is one of Pulter’s most explicitly political poems. Here, as elsewhere in her work, revolutions and repetitions of form, language, and image support an argument that for Pulter the civil wars, and particularly the execution of Charles I, were an affront to natural order (e.g., <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="8">On that Unparalleled Prince Charles the First, His Horrid Murder</ref>). In much of her other political verse, Pulter laments the death of Charles and other royalist leaders in an elegiac mode, expressing personal and political lament in sighs and tears.<seg>1<note type="gloss"><bibl>Sarah C. E. Ross, <title rend="italic">Women, Poetry, and Politics in Seventeenth-Century Britain</title> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2015), 138–69,</bibl> and <bibl>“Tears, Bezoars and Blazing Comets: Gender and Politics in Hester Pulter’s Civil War Lyrics,” <title rend="italic">Literature Compass</title> 2, no. 1 (2005): 1–14;</bibl> and <bibl>Kate Chedgzoy, <title rend="italic">Women’s Writing in the British Atlantic World: Memory, Place and History, 1550–1700</title> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2007), 144–53.</bibl></note></seg> “Phalaris” works rather differently. As an emblem poem, “Phalaris” might draw from its natural and historical images to offer a moral lesson, but under Pulter’s hand that lesson is strikingly specific to contemporary politics.<seg>2<note type="gloss">On the uniqueness of Pulter’s emblems within the larger tradition, see <bibl>Margaret J. M. Ezell, “The Laughing Tortoise: Speculations on Manuscript Sources and Women’s Book History,” <title rend="italic">English Literary Renaissance</title> 38, no. 2 (2008): 346–9</bibl>; <bibl>Alice Eardley, “Hester Pulter’s ‘Indivisibles’ and the Challenges of Annotating Early Modern Women’s Poetry,” <title rend="italic">Studies in English Literature, 1500–1900</title> 52, no. 1 (2012): 130–2</bibl>, and <bibl>“Introduction” to <title rend="italic">Poems, Emblems, and the Unfortunate Florinda</title>, ed. Alice Eardley (Chicago: Iter Press, 2014), 27–9</bibl>; <bibl>Ross, Women, Poetry, 157–69; Helena Kaznowska, “Women Are from Venus: Addressing Female Agency with Classical Allegory,” in <title rend="italic">Audience and Reception in the Early Modern Period</title>, ed. John R. Decker and Mitzi Kirkland-Ives (New York: Routledge, 2021), 287–90</bibl>; and <bibl>Victoria E. Burke, “Gendering the Emblem: Hester Pulter’s Formal Experimentation,” in <title rend="italic">Feminist Formalism and Early Modern Women’s Writing</title>, ed. Lara Dodds and Michelle M. Dowd (Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 2022), 92–109</bibl>.</note></seg> With boldness and perhaps a touch of delight, Pulter links the story of the cruel Sicilian tyrant Phalaris and the brass bull constructed by his court artisan Perillus to the agonizing conditions for royalists living in Cromwellian England. She also explores in a rich counterfactual vein how the regicides suffer the effects of their own instruments of violence. The result is not one of the many Pulterian emblems that critics have described as “grasp[ing] at a belief in a fading ordered world” or as culminating in a lyrical address to God.<seg>3<note type="gloss"><bibl>Gary Waller, <title rend="italic">The Female Baroque in Early Modern English Literary Culture: From Mary Sidney to Aphra Behn</title> (Amsterdam: Amsterdam University Press, 2020), 194–5;</bibl> and <bibl>Rachel Dunn, “Breaking a Tradition: Hester Pulter and the English emblem book,” <title rend="italic">The Seventeenth Century</title> 30, no. 1 (2015): 55–73, especially 63.</bibl></note></seg> Yes, the verse ends with a picture of “conscience” gnawing at the hearts of so-called Christians, but this is no psalmic hymn or communal lament.<seg>4<note type="gloss">On the Scriptural forms of Pulter’s verse, see <bibl>Nikolina Hatton, “Hester Pulter’s Psalmic Poems,” <title rend="italic">Renaissance Studies</title> 37, no. 3 (2023): 364–83;</bibl> and <bibl>Sarah C. E. Ross, “Hester Pulter’s Devotional Complaints: ‘Then will I hallelujahs ever sing’,” <title rend="italic">Journal for Early Modern Cultural Studies</title> 20, no. 2 (2020): 99–119.</bibl></note></seg> This is a powerful and vengeful prophecy against what Pulter would argue as the destructive innovations of those who fought Stuart monarchy.</p>
              <p>Formally, “Phalaris” works as a double sonnet, constructed, as are many of Pulter’s sonnets, from rhymed couplets.<seg>5<note type="gloss">On reading Pulter within the early modern sonnet tradition and her use of rhymed couplets, see <bibl>Elizabeth Scott-Baumann, “Hester Pulter’s Well-Wrought Urns: Early Modern Women, Sonnets, and New Criticism,” <title rend="italic">Journal for Early Modern Cultural Studies</title> 20, no. 2 (2020): 120–43, especially 123–5.</bibl> Scott-Baumann is responding, in part, to the lament of Diana E. Henderson over the silencing of female sonneteers after Mary Wroth; <bibl>“Where Had All the Flowers Gone? The Missing Space of Female Sonneteers in Seventeenth-Century England,” <title rend="italic">Renaissance and Reformation / Renaissance et Réforme</title> 35, no. 1 (2012): 139–65.</bibl> On Pulter’s use of couplets, see also <bibl>Lara Dodds and Michelle M. Dowd, “Happy Accidents: Critical Belatedness, Feminist Formalism, and Early Modern Women’s Writing,” <title rend="italic">Criticism</title> 62, no. 2 (2020): 184–6.</bibl></note></seg> The first fourteen lines recount classical examples of violent actors (Perillus, Procrustes, Sciron, Termerus, Sinis) punished by symmetrical acts of violence. The second fourteen lines imagine the same for political actors of Pulter’s day (the earl of Essex, Charles I’s executioners, Oliver Cromwell). The turn of the first sonnet arrives at line 13, where Pulter’s speaker exclaims, “Oh that all those that Flatter Tiranny / Might first their own accursed projects trie.” Punctuated by its spondaic words (“Oh that”), this couplet ends the first sonnet with a strong thesis, the conditions of which will be tested and explored in the poem’s second half. If only, the speaker imagines (or perhaps prays), all political flatterers might suffer the same fate as Perillus. This thesis is further elaborated by a rhyme scheme that intensifies the four lines leading to the center of the poem. The rest of the poem bounds along in rhymed couplets, yet here, at the middle, Pulter employs either an ABAB structure – the trisyllabic “Cruelly” rhyming more closely with the trisyllable “Tiranny”; “Die” with “trie” – or, more simply, an accretive AAAA structure, in which all four words share the same final sound. Either way, the rhymes link the central parts of the poem – ancient and modern, myth and counterfactual – into a single argument: those who try cruel tyranny ought to die. Working from this premise, the second half of Pulter’s poem proceeds, in four-line segments, to conjure up the deaths of those who set the stage for Charles I’s execution, of those who performed the execution, and of those who followed the execution with the sequestration of royalist estates and the deportation of royalist families. The second sonnet ends with a couplet that returns the verse to its emblematic opening: “That Worm will gnaw though for A time ’tis hid / And make them Roar wors then Perillus did.”<seg>6<note type="gloss">On this return, see the Headnote to the Elemental Edition of <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="115">Phalaris and the Brazen Bull [Emblem 50]</ref>. On the ways that the endings of Pulter’s poems “resolve,” “dissolve,” or “involve,” see <bibl>Liza Blake, “Hester Pulter’s Particle Physics and the Poetics of Involution,” <title rend="italic">Journal for Early Modern Cultural Studies</title> 20, no. 2 (2020): 72, 88–9.</bibl></note></seg></p>
              <p>To craft her prophetic emblem, Pulter drew from ancient images and stories which had gained new life and purpose in civil war England. Though we know little of Pulter’s education or what books she read, we do know that she met with friends and relatives in Hertfordshire and in London and that she was almost certainly receiving news and books from the metropole.<seg>7<note type="gloss">On Pulter’s probable use of newsbooks as well as first-hand news from London, see <bibl>Eardley, “Introduction,” 18–9 and 28–9</bibl>; <bibl>Elizabeth Zeman Kolkovich, “In Defense of Indulgence: Hester Pulter’s Maternal Elegies,” <title rend="italic">Journal for Early Modern Cultural Studies</title> 20, no. 2 (2020): 48–53</bibl>; <bibl>Karen Britland, “The Queer Poetics of Hester Pulter’s Poem, ‘Of a Young Lady at Oxford, 1646’,” <title rend="italic">Women’s Writing</title> 29, no. 3 (2022): 382–401</bibl>; and <bibl>Andrea Brady, “Dying with Honour: Literary Propaganda and the Second English Civil War,” <title rend="italic">The Journal of Military History</title> 70, no. 1 (2006): 9–30</bibl>. On the work being done to discover Pulter’s sources, see <bibl>Leah Knight and Wendy Wall, “Poet in the Making: How Hester Pulter Read the Digital Age,” <title rend="italic">Journal for Early Modern Cultural Studies</title> 20, no. 2 (2020): 2–3</bibl>. For new connections and associations that have been discovered through corpus-based analysis and social history, see <bibl>Karen Britland, “Conspiring with ‘friends’: Hester Pulter’s Poetry and the Stanley Family at Cumberlow Green,” <title rend="italic">The Review of English Studies</title> 69, no. 292 (2018): 832–54</bibl>. For the political diversity of Pulter’s family, see <bibl>Eardley, “Introduction,” 9–19</bibl>.</note></seg> She refashioned these raw materials, adapting and adopting them to her own voice, her own ends.<seg>8<note type="gloss">Frances E. Dolan has suggested that Pulter’s poetry “absorb[s] and break[s] down its components—as a dunghill does—so that one does not necessarily recognize the components” (<bibl>“Hester Pulter’s Dunghill Poetics,” <title rend="italic">Journal for Early Modern Cultural Studies</title> 20, no. 2 [2020]: 32</bibl>).</note></seg> The figure of Phalaris, for instance, was widely used by contemporary writers as an example of tyranny, but it was his artisan Perillus who received the harsher treatment in these texts, where he was excoriated for his cunning and flattery (see <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="#ctxs">Phalaris and Perillus in Early Modern Print</ref>). In one striking example from 1621, the minister Thomas Granger compares Perillus to Haman from the book of Esther: “So <foreign rend="italic">Haman</foreign> was hanged vpon the same gallowes, that he had prepared for <foreign rend="italic">Mordecai</foreign>, <foreign rend="italic">Hest</foreign> 7. and <foreign rend="italic">Perillus</foreign> was first broyled in the brasen Bull that hee made for the tyrant <foreign rend="italic">Phalaris</foreign> to torment others in. <foreign rend="italic">Iob</foreign> sayth, The Lord taketh the wise in their craftinesse.”<seg>9<note type="gloss"><bibl>Thomas Granger, <title rend="italic">A Familiar Exposition or Commentarie on Ecclesiastes</title> (London, 1621), 259.</bibl></note></seg> In drawing out the cruelty and arrogance of Perillus over that of Phalaris, Pulter selected a contemporary interpretation of the story that was at once personal and pragmatic. Working from a moment when accusations of tyranny often flowed in the direction of Stuart monarchy, Pulter chose to avoid that element and focus instead on other agents – on those lower figures, who, like Perillus, were as much to blame for the downfall of the state and were themselves perhaps more cruel.<seg>10<note type="gloss">Pulter’s Independent contemporary, John Goodwin, had used a similar strategy to defend his accusation against England’s ministers for corrupting the state, writing that “if the Land had a Phalaris King over it, there would be found more then one Perillus to make him brazen Bulls for the tormenting of such Christians, who are either too weak, or too wise, to swim down the stream of a State Religion, or to call men, Rabbi” (<bibl><title rend="italic">The Apologist Condemned</title> [London, 1653], 34</bibl>).</note></seg> With such a focus, Pulter was also free to imagine herself (as she does throughout her collection) as Queen Esther, transferring Mordecai’s death sentence to his courtly antagonist, Haman.</p>
              <p>Pulter may have seen herself as an agent of earthly justice meted out against the Perilluses of her world, but the other myths that she invokes in her poem point to a different agent: Theseus. After finishing with Phalaris, Pulter moves to a catalog of criminals and robbers whom Theseus punished, using their own modes of violence against them, on his journey from his hometown of Troezen to Athens, where he would become king: Procrustes, the innkeeper, who “stretcht or Cutt” his visitors to fit his iron-bed; Sciron, a bandit who forced passersby to wash his feet and “kickd [them] down … to the seas”; Termerus, a robber who bashed his head against the heads of his victims; and Sinis, another robber, who tied his victims to bent trees and then released the trees and so split them in two (see <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="#ctxs">Procrustes, Sciron, Termerus, and Sinis in Early Modern Print</ref>). Though the poem ends with a vision of conscience doing the work of self-torture, Pulter’s verse cannot shake the figure of Theseus, whose presence behind the stories of the poem’s first half haunts the punishments in the poem’s second half.<seg>11<note type="gloss">Pulter imagines Theseus as avenger of a young royalist suicide in <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="43">Of a Young Lady at Oxford, 1646</ref>.</note></seg> Who will chain the earl of Essex, “that Fell Tyrant that in Newbury Raignd,” “unto the Fatall stag[e]”? Who will submit “those that made the Engine to pull Down” Charles’s “sacred Head” to a similar fate? Who will prompt “Oliver that Pulley [to] trie”? Pulter suggests that the crimes are so obvious that “Were some Condemnd the Ax would moue alone,” and perhaps she sees the agent of punishment as something vaguer, a Rhamnusia or a Nemesis, the figure of revenge. But in order for the executioner’s axe to move alone, “some” must first be “Condemnd.” How, the poem seems to ask, and by whom?</p>
              <p>The confidence and vehemence with which Pulter imagines the torture of regicides suggests firm answers to these questions.<seg>12<note type="gloss">The emblem that follows “Phalaris” in the manuscript—<ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="116">British Brennus [Emblem 51]</ref>—is similarly virulent, but compare this confident vehemence to the self-restrained ending of <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="102">The Ugly Spider [Emblem 37]</ref>. On Pulter’s attack on Cromwell, see <bibl>Alice Eardley, “‘Shut up in a Countrey Grange’: The Provenance of Lady Hester Pulter’s Poetry and Prose and Women’s Literary History,” <title rend="italic">Huntington Library Quarterly</title> 80, no. 2 (2017): 352–3.</bibl></note></seg> She writes, near the end of the poem, in a prophetic mode: the should’s and would’s become sure’s and will’s. Perhaps this boldness comes from Pulter’s awareness that her verse was not going to circulate,<seg>13<note type="gloss"><bibl>Eardley, “Shut up,” 355–9.</bibl></note></seg> but the details of the counterfactuals offer a different explanation. Take the picture of the earl of Essex, who was the general in charge of parliamentary forces at the decisive battle at Newbury on 20 September 1643. Pulter could well have been remembering Essex’s role in that battle, but he had died in 1646, at least eight years before Pulter wrote her poem. What is more likely is that Pulter’s memory of Essex was filtered through a Restoration event: Charles II’s order that Essex’s funeral monument be destroyed. Pulter, who wrote another poem entirely about this event (<ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="62">On the Fall of That Grand Rebel the Earl of Essex's Effigies in Harry the 7th's Chapel in Westminster Abbey</ref>), could have also encountered Essex’s name in the popular press where he was, in 1661, being remembered as “the first disturber of our peace” and compared to “<foreign rend="italic">Dionysius</foreign>, King of <foreign rend="italic">Sicily</foreign> … a Tyrant, begot of Tyrants.”<seg>14<note type="gloss"><bibl>Gryffith Williams, “The Declaration of the Just Judgments of God,” in <title rend="italic">Seven Treatises, Very necessary to be observed in these very bad Days</title> (London, 1661), 43.</bibl></note></seg></p>
              <p>If the picture of Essex is informed by Restoration contexts, so too are the poem’s images of the other regicides, including Cromwell, being hung on pulleys or chained to the “Fatall stag[e]” where Charles laid his head, “Lamb like on that Alter.” Pulter’s description of Charles’s execution is entirely consistent with contemporary civil war reports and images, as well as with poems like Andrew Marvell’s “An Horatian Ode.”<seg>15<note type="gloss"><bibl>Dunn, “Breaking a Tradition,” 61.</bibl></note></seg> But the language of pulleys and chains moves us from the scene of Charles’s death to the scene of the regicides, tried and punished at the Restoration. Though there are anecdotal reports of chains or ropes being at hand to restrain Charles in 1649, none of the contemporary visual representations of the scene show a system of restraint. Instead, it is at the public execution site “Tyburn,” which groans for “those Regicides,” that chains and pulleys are most appropriate. In January 1661, Charles II ordered the bodies of Cromwell, Henry Ireton, and John Bradshaw to be exhumed, hanged, and beheaded—the exact sequence that Pulter imagines for Oliver and the other regicides in her poem. In looking for the Theseus behind the acts of revenge in the poem’s second half, we need look no further than Charles II.<seg>16<note type="gloss">The younger Charles also appears in Pulter’s <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="8">On that Unparalleled Prince Charles the First, His Horrid Murder</ref>, <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="15">Let None Sigh More for Lucas or for Lisle [On the Same (2)]</ref>, <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="27">On the King’s Most Excellent Majesty</ref>, <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="64">And Must the Sword this Controverse Decide </ref>, and <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="70">Virtue’s Duel [Emblem 4]</ref>.</note></seg></p>
              <p>“Phalaris” ends with a final punishment that stands out in a poem otherwise concerned with domestic affairs: after judgment has been meted out against Cromwell and the regicides, then “should their Children to Jameca goe / Their staits sequstred Widdow Eyes or’eflow.” As with the other details she imagines, this detail points to a Restoration context for the poem. Since the end of the civil wars, England had been pursuing a more active imperial program, beginning with wars to conquer Ireland and Scotland and continuing with the Dutch before finally settling for peace in 1654. The wars in Ireland were particularly brutal, and it is surprising that Pulter, who had Irish roots, chose to include Jamaica and not Ireland in her poem, as she had done in <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="93">Vain Herostratus [Emblem 28]</ref>.<seg>17<note type="gloss">On Pulter’s Irish connections, see <bibl>Eardley, “Introduction,” 13–4</bibl>; <bibl>Dunn, “Breaking a Tradition,” 62</bibl>.</note></seg> But Pulter would have been privy also to the Protectorate’s activities in the Caribbean. Her nephew, James Ley, third earl of Marlborough (1618–1665), had participated in military and economic ventures to the region throughout the 1640s and 1650s. In 1660, Ley began petitioning parliament for support to settle Jamaica, and in 1664 he was nominated governor of the colony.<seg>18<note type="gloss"><bibl>G. G. Harris, <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1093/ref:odnb/16620" type="new-window-url">“Ley, James, Third Earl of Marlborough (1618/19–1665), Naval Officer,”</ref> <title rend="italic"> Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</title>. 3 Jan. 2008; Accessed 26 July 2023.</bibl> My thanks to Tom Cogswell for pointing out this family connection.</note></seg> This personal chronology aligns, as well, with the place that Jamaica occupied in England’s public imagination. In 1655, Cromwell’s forces had invaded Jamaica after failing to make headway in Hispaniola—the intended target of his 1654 Western Design to balance power in the Caribbean—but it was not until after the Restoration that accounts of royalists shipped off to Jamaica proliferated (see <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="#ctxs">Pulter and Jamaica</ref>).<seg>19<note type="gloss"><bibl>Carla Gardina Pestana, <title rend="italic">The English Conquest of Jamaica: Oliver Cromwell’s Bid for Empire</title> (Cambridge, MA: The Belknap Press of Harvard University Press, 2017).</bibl></note></seg> Pulter’s counterfactual reversal of these accounts in her “Phalaris” points, once again, to a composition date after the Restoration.</p>
              <p>When Pulter writes of the “accursed projects” of those who flatter tyranny, she is working in the idiom of late Stuart empire-building. And within this idiom, indeed within Pulter’s poem, we can see the paradox of the Restoration: the way that it is premised on forgetting past violence, on acts of indemnity and oblivion, and at the same time on remembering that past, on framing the new projects of monarchy and empire against the emblems of past projects—the emblem of the heads of those who compassed and imagined the death of the king now skewered on London Bridge, the emblem of Jamaica as Cromwell’s failed Western Design, the emblem of Perillus roaring in his bull.<seg>20<note type="gloss">In arguing for “Phalaris” as Pulter’s missing poem of the Restoration (see <bibl>Eardley, “Introduction,” 21</bibl>), I depart from Peter C. Herman’s claim that Pulter changed her political allegiances after seeing the licentious court of Charles II (<bibl>“Lady Hester Pulter’s The Unfortunate Florinda: Race, Religion, and the Politics of Rape,” <title rend="italic">Renaissance Quarterly</title> 63, no. 4 [2010]: 1208–46</bibl>).</note></seg></p>
            </note>
          </rdg>
        </app>
      </head>

      <l n="1">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft"><fw type="seqNum" place="inline">50</fw>When Phalaris for Tiranny Soe &ff;am’d</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">When <seg>Phalaris<note type="gloss">Phalaris of Acragas (ca. 570–549 BCE) was a Sicilian tyrant famed for his cruelty generally, and especially for roasting enemies alive by enclosing them in a bronze bull with a fire burning underneath; victims’ screams sounded like the bull roaring.</note></seg>, for tyranny so famed,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">When <seg>Phalaris<note type="gloss">The story of Phalaris (d. <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.554 BCE), the tyrant ruler of Acragas, Sicily, came to the early modern world through Cicero, Ovid, Seneca, Plutarch, Pliny, and Lucian, and appears across the print record, from Dante’s <title rend="italic">Inferno</title> XXVII to Sir Philip Sidney’s <title rend="italic">Defence of Poesie</title> to John Donne’s sermons (see <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="#ctxs">Phalaris and Perillus in Early Modern Print</ref>).</note></seg> <seg>for Tiranny soe Fam’d<note type="gloss">Early modern references to Phalaris focus on his authoritarian rule, often listing him alongside tyrants like Nero, Herod, Nimrod, Pharaoh, Caligula, and Dionysius, as a standard of evil against which to compare contemporary leaders (see <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="#ctxs">Phalaris and Perillus in Early Modern Print</ref>).</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="2">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Had Seen the Braſen Bul <seg>Pirillus<note type="physical">second “i” possibly corrected from “e”</note></seg> &ff;ram’d</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Had seen <seg>the brazen bull Perillus framed<note type="gloss">The bull was invented (“framed”) by Perillus of Athens as a device for executing criminals; Phalaris admired the device and made Perillus its first victim.</note></seg>,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Had seen the <seg>Brasen Bul Pirillus Fram’d<note type="gloss">Phalaris’s court artisan, Perillus, cast a bull in brass and presented it to the king as a torture device. The victim would be placed inside the bull and a fire lit underneath so that the cries of the afflicted would seem to come from the bull’s mouth.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="3">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Hee made him &ff;irst the Horrid pain Explore</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">He made him first the horrid pain <seg>explore<note type="gloss">discover; examine; test</note></seg>,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Hee made him First the Horrid pain explore</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="4">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">And with his life his cunning out to Roar</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">And with his life his cunning <seg>out to roar<note type="gloss">figuratively, breathing out his life (and losing his cleverness) with a loud cry</note></seg>.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">And with his life <seg>his cunning<note type="gloss">Perillus’s cunning, arrogant, greedy, and bloodthirsty behavior captured the imaginations of early modern writers, many of whom approved his punishment by Phalaris and some of whom went as far as to say that Perillus was crueler than Phalaris (see <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="#ctxs">Phalaris and Perillus in Early Modern Print</ref>).</note></seg> out <seg>to roar<note type="gloss">Perillus’s roar was a common idiom in the early modern world, as in Andrew Marvell’s “Flecknoe, an English Priest at Rome,” where the titular poet “swell[s], with anger full, / And roare[s] out, like Perillus in’s own bull” (see <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="#ctxs">Phalaris and Perillus in Early Modern Print</ref>).</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="5">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Thus as Pirillus in the Bull was put</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Thus, as Perillus in the bull was put,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Thus as Pirillus in the Bull was put</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="6">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Procrustus to his Bed was Stretcht or Cutt</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee"><seg>Procrustes to his bed was stretched or cut<note type="gloss">In Greek myth, the innkeeper and robber Procrustes forced travelers onto a bed and made them fit it either by stretching or cutting off their limbs; he was finally killed by Theseus with his own invention.</note></seg>;</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>Procrustus<note type="gloss">An innkeeper who kept an iron bed to which he fit his guests by chopping or stretching their bodies. In Greek myth, Procrustes was subjected to his own device by Theseus on the last stop of his journey from Troezen to Athens, where he would become king. The story of Procrustes was used in the early modern world as an analogy for the manipulation of another’s words to fit one’s own purposes (see <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="#ctxs">Procrustes, Sciron, Termerus, and Sinis in Early Modern Print</ref>).</note></seg> to his Bed was stretcht or <seg>Cutt<note type="critical">A possible slant rhyme of the couplet (“put/cut”) would, if true for Pulter’s English as in our own, perfectly enact Procrustes’s violent method.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="7">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">And hee that Kickd down People to the Seas</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">And <seg>he that kicked down people to the seas<note type="gloss">In Greek myth, the robber Sciron forced passersby to wash his feet, then kicked them into the sea to be eaten by a sea monster. He was killed when Theseus threw him into the sea.</note></seg></rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">And <seg>hee that kickd down People<note type="gloss">Sciron, one of the bandits whom Theseus defeats on his journey to Athens; Sciron’s tactic for robbery was to force passersby to wash his feet and then to kick them into the sea below. For the myth’s sources, see Eardley, <title rend="italic">Poems</title>, 257.</note></seg> to the seas</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="8">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Receiv’d the like Ramnuſa to apeas</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Received the like, <seg>Rhamnusia<note type="gloss">Greek goddess of vengeance (also called Nemesis)</note></seg> to appease.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Receiv’d the like <seg>Ramnusa<note type="gloss">Rhamnusia or Nemesis, the figure of revenge in Greek myth. Pulter also uses the figure in <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="13">Upon the Imprisonment of his Sacred Majesty, That Unparalleled Prince, King Charles the First</ref> and <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="91">Ambitious Apes [Emblem 26]</ref>.</note></seg> to apeas</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="9">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Soe hee that with his &ff;orhead daſh’d out Brains</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">So <seg>he that with his forehead dashed out brains<note type="gloss">Termerus was a bandit in Greek myth who murdered passersby by ramming his head against theirs; he was murdered when Theseus smashed his skull (Eardley).</note></seg></rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Soe <seg>hee that with his Forehead dash’d out Brains<note type="gloss">Termerus, a robber who bashed his head against the heads of his victims. Unlike the other Greek villains mentioned in the poem, Termerus was killed by Heracles (whose head proved harder than the robber’s) and not by Theseus (as in Eardley, <title rend="italic">Poems</title>, 257).</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="10">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Had like for like, What alſoe was his gains</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Had like for like. What also was <seg>his<note type="gloss">In Greek mythology, Sinis robbed and dismembered travelers by fastening their limbs to pine branches, bending down the trees, and then suddenly letting them go (Eardley); Theseus kills Sinis in similar fashion (as the speaker suggests two lines later).</note></seg> gains</rdg>
           <rdg wit="#ae">Had like for <seg>like, What<note type="critical">This comma is the only sentence punctuation in the original manuscript before the terminal period. With it, Pulter signals a caesura in the line, which, significantly, comes just as she introduces Sinis, the splitter of bodies and poetic lines. On the significance of punctation, absent and present, see <bibl>Alice Eardley, “‘I haue not time to point yr booke … which I desire you yourselfe to doe’: Editing the Form of Early Modern Manuscript Verse,” in <title rend="italic">The Work of Form: Poetics and Materiality in Early Modern Culture</title>, ed. Elizabeth Scott-Baumann and Ben Burton (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2014), 169–71.</bibl></note></seg> alsoe was his gains</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="11">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">That tween two Trees did Kill men Cruelly</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">That ’tween two trees did kill men cruelly?</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">That tween two Trees did kill men Cruelly</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="12">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Did hee not by the Self Same Tortour Die</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Did he not by the self-same torture die?</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Did <seg>hee<note type="gloss">Sinis, another of the bandits whom Theseus defeats on his journey to Athens; Sinis assaulted his victims by tying them to bent trees and then releasing the trees and so splitting them in two. For the myth’s sources, see Eardley, <title rend="italic">Poems</title>, 257.</note></seg> not by the self same Tortour Die</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="13">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Oh that all thoſe that &ff;latter Tiranny</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">O, that all those that flatter tyranny</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae"><seg>Oh<note type="gloss">One of Pulter’s favorite interjections, used over 100 times across her poems.</note></seg> that all those that Flatter Tiranny</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="14">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Might first their own accursed projects trie</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Might first their own accurséd projects try!</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Might first their own accursed <seg>projects<note type="gloss">A scheme or proposal. “Project,” used both as a noun and as a verb, developed significant economic and imperialist meanings in the seventeenth century, so much so that “projectors” became a term of abuse for a promoter of bad ventures (<bibl><title rend="italic">Oxford English Dictionary</title>, s.v. “projector, n., sense 1.b”</bibl>).</note></seg> trie</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="15">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Then that &ff;ell Tyrant that in Newburg Raignd</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Then <seg>that fell tyrant that in Newbury reigned<note type="critical">Eardley suggests the manuscript’s “Newburg” might be Newbury, where in 1643 Robert Devereux, third Earl of Essex, led the army against the king; we have read “Newburg” in the manuscript as a transcription error for “Newbury” (pronounced, here, “Newb’ry,” to fit the meter).</note></seg></rdg>
          <rdg wit="#ae">Then that <seg>Fell Tyrant<note type="critical">Eardley suggests Robert Devereux, the third earl of Essex (1591–1646), who was the general in charge of parliamentary forces at the decisive battle at Newbury on 20 September 1643 (<title rend="italic">Poems</title>, 258). Pulter may have been reminded of the general and his role in that battle by renewed attention to Essex at the Restoration, when he was remembered as a chief architect of the civil wars and when his funeral moment was destroyed on the order of Charles II.</note></seg> that in <seg>Newbury<note type="critical">The manuscript reads “Newburg,” but the reference is almost certainly to the first Battle of Newbury (see above and Eardley, <title rend="italic">Poems</title>, 258). Nearly all references to “Newburg” in the corpus of early modern English print are to “Nuremburg” in Germany. Although an earl of “Newburg” was created among the Scottish peers in 1660s, neither this title nor the German city presents a convincing alternative to Eardley’s correction.</note></seg> Raignd</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="16">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Should first unto the &ff;at’all Stag bin Chaind</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Should first unto the <seg>fatal stage been chained<note type="gloss">This seems to be a Royalist wish that a Parliamentarian leader would have been subject to the fate that awaited Charles I, who was chained and executed on a platform in a venue used sometimes as a theatrical stage. The manuscript has “stag” instead of “stage.”</note></seg>;</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Should first unto the Fatall <seg>stag<note type="critical">The manuscript reads “stag,” a suggestively Royalist word (see Elizabeth Kolkovich, <ref type="pp-curation-ref" target="/poems/ae/upon-the-death-of-my-dear-and-lovely-daughter/#the-hunted-deer">The Hunted Dear</ref>), but the word is almost certainly “stage,” a reference to the platform on which Charles I was executed outside the Banqueting House of Whitehall. Contemporary accounts, like Andrew Marvell’s “An Horatian Ode,” drew attention to theatricality of the scene: “That thence the royal actor born / The tragic scaffold might adorn, / While round the armèd bands / Did clap their bloody hands” (<bibl><title rend="italic">The Poems of Andrew Marvell</title>, ed. Nigel Smith, Rev. ed, [New York: Pearson Longman, 2007], ll. 53–6</bibl>).</note></seg> bin <seg>Chaind<note type="critical">Eardley notes that “Chains were attached to the platform to restrain the king,” but no system of restraint appears in the contemporary visual representations of the execution (<title rend="italic">Poems</title>, 258). Perhaps Pulter was superimposing the grizzlier scenes of the execution of the regicides at the Restoration onto the original event.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="17">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Then thoſe that made the Engine to pull Down</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Then those that made the <seg>engine<note type="gloss">tricky; contrivance; plot or snare; machine, especially of war but also in theater instrument of torture</note></seg> to pull down</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Then those that made the <seg>Engine to pull Down<note type="critical">A machine or instrument, often of torture; can also refer to theatrical machinery (i.e. deus ex machina) (<bibl><title rend="italic">Oxford English Dictionary</title>, s.v. “engine, n., senses II.4.b and II.7</bibl>). This last sense builds on the line’s theatrical imagery and anticipates the downward motion of Charles’s “sacred Head” onto the famously low execution block—a motion enacted by the line break and the enjambment that follows.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="18">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">His Sacred Head which wore <add place="below">^</add><add place="above"><seg>o:r<note type="physical">"r" in double superscript</note></seg></add> Brittiſh Crown</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee"><seg>His sacred head<note type="gloss">that of Charles I, who was beheaded in 1649</note></seg> which wore our British crown.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">His sacred Head which wore <seg>our<note type="critica">This word, which is necessary to fill the line’s meter, was added later in the composition process. The first-person plural pronoun, along with the demonym “Brittish,” aspire to a collective national identity that aligns more closely with a Restoration sensibility, when the “Brittish Crown” was once again “ours,” than with a republican one.</note></seg> Brittish Crown</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="19">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">When Lamb like on that Alter hee did lie</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">When lamb-like on that altar he did lie,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">When <seg>Lamb like on that Alter hee did lie<note type="critical">The language again resembles contemporary reports of the regicide, including Marvell’s “Horatian Ode”: “He nothing common did, or mean, / Upon that memorable scene; / But with his keener eye / The axe’s edge did try. / Nor called the Gods with vulgar spite / To vindicate his helpless right; / But bowed his comely head / Down, as upon a bed” (<bibl><title rend="italic">Poems</title>, ed. Smith, ll. 57–64</bibl>).</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="20">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Why did not Oliver that Pulley trie</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Why did not <seg>Oliver<note type="gloss">Oliver Cromwell, who led the Parliamentarians in defeating and executing Charles I during the English Civil War</note></seg> that <seg>pulley<note type="gloss">part of a gallows for hanging; “pulley” could allude to the use of such a device in torture</note></seg> try?</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Why did not <seg>Oliver<note type="gloss">Oliver Cromwell (1599–1658), commander of the New Model Army that overthrew the Stuart monarchy and later Lord Protector of the commonwealth which replaced that monarchy.</note></seg> that Pulley trie</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="21">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Were Some Condemnd the Ax would moue alone</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee"><seg>Were some condemned, the axe would move alone<note type="gloss">Some are so villainous that no executioner would be needed, since the axe would be moved to act of its own accord.</note></seg>,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Were some Condemnd the Ax would moue alone</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="22">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">As Tyburn for <add place="above"><seg>thoſe<note type="physical">in darker ink than surrounding words</note></seg></add> Regicides doe groan</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">As <seg>Tyburn<note type="gloss">a place of public execution in London</note></seg> for those <seg>regicides<note type="gloss">the king’s killers</note></seg> do groan.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">As <seg>Tyburn<note type="critical">London’s principal public execution site, featuring gallows for executions by hanging. The poem’s earlier references to “chains,” “engines,” and “pulleys” seem to point toward this method of execution rather than the decapitation by axe performed at Charles I’s execution and re-imagined in line 21.</note></seg> for <seg>those Regicides<note type="critical">Like “our” in line 18, the word “those” was added later in the composition process. The addition is again a metrical necessity, but the pronoun suggests a finite group of regicides, perhaps the list of those regicides excluded from Charles II’s Act of Indemnity and Oblivion at the Restoration. The word “regicide” had flourished in print discourse around 1649, but then fallen out of the print record for most of the 1650s before returning to public use in 1660 (<bibl><ref target="//earlyprint.wustl.edu/url/1701805560" type="new-window-url">“N-gram Browser,” s.v., “regicide,”</ref> <title rend="italic"> Early Print</title></bibl>).</note></seg> doe groan</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="23">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Then Should their Children to Jame’ca goe</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Then should their children to <seg>Jamaica<note type="gloss">Jamaica, captured by the British in 1655, was among the islands in the West Indies used to exile Royalists during the interregnum.</note></seg> go;</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Then should their <seg>Children to Jameca goe<note type="gloss">A reference to the supposed deportation of royalist widows and children to Jamaica, which had come under English rule in 1655 as part of the Western Design pursued by Oliver Cromwell. Accounts of forced emigration circulated primarily after the Restoration and may have been fabricated to signal loyalty to the Stuart cause (see Pestana, <title rend="italic">English Conquest</title>, and <ref type="pp-curations-ref" target="#ctxs">Pulter and Jamaica</ref>). Pulter’s nephew, James Ley, third earl of Marlborough, was involved in England’s Caribbean ventures and would be named governor of Jamaica in 1664.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="24">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Their <seg>Staits<note type="physical">blot after “i”</note></seg> Sequstred Widdow Eyes o’reflow</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee"><seg>Their ’states sequestered<note type="gloss">regicides’ estates (properties) should be confiscated (or “sequestered”), as the Royalists’ goods were during and after the civil wars.</note></seg>, <seg>widow eyes o’erflow<note type="gloss">regicides’ widows’ eyes should be overflowing with grief over their husbands’ deaths.</note></seg>.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Their <seg>staits sequstred<note type="critical">A reference to the seizure and sale of royalist estates to fund the commonwealth government. As elsewhere in the poem, Pulter employs poetic forms that replicate the punishment: the elision of “estates” to “staits” and “sequestered” to “sequstred” enacts a syllabic theft as well as describing a material one.</note></seg> Widdow Eyes or’eflow</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="25">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Sure thoſe that doe their ffellow Chriſtians Sell</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Sure <seg>those that do their fellow Christians sell<note type="gloss">the Parliamentarians who sold Royalists into slavery, as the lines above indicate (“to Jamaica go”), by sending them to the West Indies</note></seg></rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Sure those that doe their <seg>Fellow Christians sell<note type=
            "critical">A provocative choice of phrase and argument at a moment when England was forcibly sending thousands of convicted criminals and Irish people to Atlantic colonies and increasingly participating in the traffic of enslaved Africans.</note></seg></rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="26">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">Will in their Conſcience feel the flames of Hell</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">Will in their conscience feel the flames of Hell.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">Will in their <seg>Conscience<note type="critical">One of only two times (cf. <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="102">The Ugly Spider [Emblem 37]</ref>, line 20) that Pulter uses this theologically and politically charged word in her corpus.</note></seg> feel the flames of Hell</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="27">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">That Worm will graw though for A time ’tis hid</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">That <seg>worm will gnaw<note type="gloss">proverbial for something eating away at one’s conscience; also figuratively, the pains of Hell</note></seg>, though for a time ’tis hid,</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">That <seg>Worm<note type="gloss">A common idiom for the work of a guilty conscience, deriving from Mark 9:44–48 (Eardley, <title rend="italic">Poems</title>, 258).</note></seg> will gnaw though for A time ’tis hid</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
      <l n="28">
        <app>
            <rdg wit="#ft">And make them Roar worſ then <seg>Pirillus<note type="physical">first “i” is written over an “e”</note></seg> did.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ee">And make them roar worse than Perillus did.</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#ae">And make them Roar wors then Perillus did.</rdg>
        </app>
      </l>
        <app>
            <rdg type="milestone" wit="#ft">
                <milestone unit="poem" rend="straight-horline"/>
            </rdg>
        </app>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
