<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../src/vmachine.xsl"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI [

<!ENTITY ff "<!-- ff ligature, representing capital modern day capital F, here represented as 'ff' -->ff">

]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mads.pp.25">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Circle [3]</title>
                 <title type="sub">Poem 25</title>
                <respStmt><resp>Created by</resp>
                    <persName>Leah Knight</persName>
                    <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoded by</resp>
                    <persName>Katherine Poland</persName>
                    <persName>Matthew Taylor</persName>
			<persName>Betsy Chou</persName>
                        <persName>Emily Andrey</persName>
                    <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
                </respStmt>
		<respStmt>
                     <resp>IT-project consultation by</resp>
                     <persName>Josh Honn</persName>
                 </respStmt>
                <sponsor>
                    <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
                    <orgName>Brock University</orgName>
                    <orgName>University of Leeds</orgName>
                </sponsor>
                <principal>
                    <persName/>
                </principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1"/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription, transformations, and notes</resp>
                    <persName>Leah Knight</persName>
                    <orgName>Brock University</orgName>
                    <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>
                    <orgName>Northwestern University</orgName>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent/>
            <publicationStmt>
                <ab/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl>
                    <msDesc>
                        <msIdentifier>
                            <repository>See witness list.</repository>
                        </msIdentifier>
                    </msDesc>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <p>Transcriptions are encoded in TEI(P5)-conformant XML.</p>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p>Apparent errors are preserved and editorial corrections provided using SIC
                        and CORR tags, but only where the editor conjectures that the original
                        scribe or compositor would have recognized the instance as an error. For
                        example, what according to modern usage is incorrect subject/verb agreement
                        might have been deemed acceptable to a seventeenth-century scribe or
                        compositor. All such instances are treated instead using the ORIG and REG
                        tags. (See below.) </p>
                    <p>Corrections and annotations made within the scope of the original document
                        either by its original authors, owners, and/or transcribers are noted using
                        ADD tags. These annotations and may be further explained within NOTE tags, as
                        added by the editors of this digital edition, for display within the
                        apparatus.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p>Original spellings, abbreviations, and orthography are preserved. Where in
                        the manuscripts a character’s status as majuscule or minuscule is ambiguous,
                        the editor has silently chosen one or the other based on context and
                        judgment (i.e., does not register such ambiguity in either the markup or the
                        notes).</p>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p>Original quotation marks, if any, are preserved.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p>Original hyphenation is preserved.</p>
                </hyphenation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <charDecl>
                <!-- Ligature combinations for which there are currently no corresponding Unicode codepoints. -->
                <glyph xml:id="ffllig">
                    <glyphName>Handwritten 'ff' ligature, used in handwriting to represent modern
                        F</glyphName>
                </glyph>
            </charDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="DDC22">
                    <bibl>
                        <title>Dewey Decimal Classification</title>
                        <edition/>
                        <publisher/>
                        <pubPlace/>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en-GB">British English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <!-- dewey decimal system class code 821: English Poetry -->
                <classCode scheme="DDC22">821</classCode>
		<keywords>
		    <term>death</term>
		    <term>fear</term>
		    <term>revolution</term>
		    <term>dissolution</term>
        	</keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic url="./document_images/7610_088.jpg" xml:id="f7610_088"/>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div>
                <listWit>
                    <witness xml:id="ft">Transcription of manuscript: By <persName xml:id="lknight">Leah Knight</persName> and <persName xml:id="wwall">Wendy Wall</persName>.</witness>
                    <witness xml:id="ee">Elemental edition: By <persName>Leah Knight</persName> and <persName>Wendy Wall</persName>.</witness>
                    <witness xml:id="ae">Amplified edition: By <persName>Elizabeth Scott-Baumann</persName>.</witness>
                </listWit>
            </div>
        </front>

        <body>
            <app>
                <rdg wit="#ft"><pb ed="#ft" facs="#f7610_088" n="42v"/></rdg>
                <rdg wit="#ee"><pb ed="#ee" facs="#f7610_088"/></rdg>
                <rdg wit="#ae"><pb ed="#ae" facs="#f7610_088"/></rdg>
            </app>

            <head>
                <app type="title">
                    <rdg wit="#ft"><fw facs="#f7610_069" type="pageNum" place="margin-topright">PG#</fw><seg>The Circle<note type="physical">The previous poem concludes at the top of this page.</note></seg> [3]</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">The Circle [3]</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">The Circle [3]</rdg>
                </app>
                <app type="editorialnote">
                    <rdg wit="#ft"><note type="editorialnote">In these transcriptions we preserve as many details of
                        the original material, textual, and graphic properties of Hester Pulter’s manuscript verse
                        as we have found practical. Whenever possible, for instance, original spelling, punctuation,
                        capitalization, lineation, insertions, deletions, alterations, spacing between words and lines,
                        and indentation are all maintained; abbreviations and brevigraphs are not expanded; and
                        superscript and subscript representations are retained.
                        <ref target="http://pulterproject.northwestern.edu/l/transcript-conventions">See full
                            conventions for the transcriptions here.</ref></note></rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee"><note type="editorialnote">
                        The aim of the elemental edition is to make the poems accessible to the largest variety of readers,
                        which involves modernizing spelling and punctuation as well as adding basic glosses. Spelling and
                        punctuation reflect current standard American usage; punctuation highlights syntax which might
                        otherwise be obscure. Outmoded but still familiar word forms (“thou,” “‘tis,” “hold’st”) are not
                        modernized, and we do not modernize grammar when the sense remains legible. After a brief headnote
                        aimed at offering a “way in” to the poem’s unique qualities and connections with other verse by
                        Pulter or her contemporaries, the edition features a minimum of notes and interpretative framing to
                        allow more immediate engagement with the poem. Glosses clarify synonyms or showcase various
                        possible meanings in Pulter’s time. Other notes identify named people and places or clarify obscure
                        material. We rely (without citation) primarily on the Oxford English Dictionary (OED), the Oxford
                        Reference database, and the King James Version (KJV) of the Bible. When we rely on Alice Eardley’s
                        edition of Pulter’s work, we cite her text generally (“Eardley”); other sources are cited in full. The
                        result is an edition we consider a springboard for further work on Pulter’s poetry.
                        <ref target="http://pulterproject.northwestern.edu/l/elemental-conventions">See full conventions
                            for this edition here.</ref></note>
                    </rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae"><note type="editorialnote">With an undergraduate and graduate student audience in mind, this poem has been modernised in spelling and punctuation. Where modernisation would affect form, priority has been given to the integrity of the poem’s formal features (so, for instance, verb endings -est and -eth have been retained unmodernised; where the meter requires it, the verb ending -ed is accented, e.g., “Then shall thy blessèd influence”). Nouns have been capitalized only when there is clear personification. The notes provide information essential to understanding the poem, while the Headnote aims to stimulate readers’ own interpretations through suggesting literary or historical contexts, possible influences, comparable poems (by Pulter and by her predecessors and peers) and relevant critical arguments.</note></rdg>
                </app>
            <app type="headnote">
                <rdg wit="#ee"><note type="headnote">In the third of four poems by the same name, Pulter cites the earth’s eternal circling as a model for those who resist death. Such resistance is castigated as “impatiency”; since the word derives from the Latin <foreign rend="italic">passio</foreign>, or suffering, refusing death is refusing suffering, and thus it is a kind of impatience (or anti-patience). In another condensed formulation that may at first be hard to parse, Pulter advises attention to things that “revolve,” which seem at first—not least through internal rhyme—to contrast with the addressee, who must “dissolve.” But the phrase “it is no more” signals not that a person’s dissolution or death is their destruction (that they are no more); rather, it suggests that death is nothing but another revolution, a mere turn of the circle. The same issue is summed up in <ref type="pp-poem-ref" corresp="47">Why Art Thou Sad at the Approach of Night</ref>: “revolution / Is the preserving of the universe / From dissolution.” Pulter’s turn to her most usual poetic form, the couplet, is delayed in Poem 25 by an initial triplet; by prolonging the first rhyme, it seems to command the extraordinary patience that the poem recommends.</note></rdg>
                <rdg wit="#ae"><note type="headnote">This poem suggests wittily that unwillingness to die is a kind of impatience with life, because death actually brings life again. When earthly things (including humans) die, Pulter suggests, they are dissolved and “revolve” or return because all matter is recycled or regenerated just as the earth rotates. Pulter’s speaker downplays death by counselling that it comes to all (“In the whole world’s society”, i.e., in the company of everyone in the world) and also that death is only a kind of revolution. The phrase “when thou dost dissolve it is no more” briefly allows the possibility that the world dissolves when we do, but pulls back to the sense of “it [death] is no more” than the revolution of “many things”. This poem is the third in the manuscript to be titled ‘The Circle’ and it plays with religious, philosophical and materialist ideas of circularity, combining Christian-stoical advice not to fear death with a materialist belief in the recycling of matter. The image of the “mound” is potent here, combining the sense of the circular earth, the globe, with a pile of dirt, which rotates and also orbits the sun, and is in a constant process of regeneration.</note></rdg>
            </app>
            </head>

            <l n="1">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">To bee unwilling or afraid to die</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">To be unwilling or afraid to die</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">To be unwilling or afraid to die</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="2">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">In the whole Worlds Society,</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">In the whole world’s society</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">In the whole world’s <seg>society<note type="gloss">fellowship; company</note></seg>,</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="3">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">Is a Sign of Huge impatiencie</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">Is a sign of huge impatiency.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">Is a sign of huge <seg>impatiency<note type="gloss">lack of patience; more broadly, failure to endure suffering</note></seg>.</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="4">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">That many things Revolve thou mayest explore</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">That many things <seg>revolve<note type="gloss">turn on an axis; return to a state or place</note></seg>, thou may’st <seg>explore<note type="gloss">examine, survey, discover</note></seg>;</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">That many things <seg>revolve<note type="gloss">turn; return, regress or restore; turn over in one’s mind, ponder</note></seg> thou mayest explore</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="5">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">And when thou dost diſſolve it is noe more</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">And when thou dost <seg>dissolve<note type="gloss">die; disintegrate</note></seg>, it is no more.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">And when thou dost <seg>dissolve<note type="gloss">disintegrate; more unusually, to die or depart</note></seg> it is no more,</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="6">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">&ff;or Soe this earthly tranſcitory Mound</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">For so this earthly <seg>transitory<note type="gloss">fleeting, transient</note></seg> mound</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">For so this earthly <seg>transitory<note type="gloss">not lasting, transient</note></seg> <seg>mound<note type="gloss">pile of dirt; the earth</note></seg></rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <l n="7">
                <app>
                    <rdg wit="#ft">In An eternall motion Still runs Round.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ee">In an eternal motion still runs round.</rdg>
                    <rdg wit="#ae">In an eternal motion still runs round.</rdg>
                </app>
            </l>
            <app>
                <rdg type="milestone" wit="#ft">
                    <milestone unit="poem" rend="curline-right"/>
                </rdg>
            </app>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
